DEV-MUC3-0001 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 JAN 90 -- [REPORT] [ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE, COPREFA] [TEXT] THE ARCE BATTALION COMMAND HAS REPORTED THAT ABOUT 50 PEASANTS OF VARIOUS AGES HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED BY TERRORISTS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] IN SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT. ACCORDING TO THAT GARRISON, THE MASS KIDNAPPING TOOK PLACE ON 30 DECEMBER IN SAN LUIS DE LA REINA. THE SOURCE ADDED THAT THE TERRORISTS FORCED THE INDIVIDUALS, WHO WERE TAKEN TO AN UNKNOWN LOCATION, OUT OF THEIR RESIDENCES, PRESUMABLY TO INCORPORATE THEM AGAINST THEIR WILL INTO CLANDESTINE GROUPS.

MEANWHILE, THREE SUBVERSIVES WERE KILLED AND SEVEN OTHERS WERE WOUNDED DURING CLASHES YESTERDAY IN USULUTAN AND MORAZAN DEPARTMENTS. THE ATONAL BATTALION REPORTED THAT ONE EXTREMIST WAS KILLED AND FIVE OTHERS WERE WOUNDED DURING A CLASH YESTERDAY AFTERNOON NEAR LA ESPERANZA FARM, SANTA ELENA JURISDICTION, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT.

IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT A SOLDIER WAS WOUNDED AND TAKEN TO THE MILITARY HOSPITAL IN THIS CAPITAL.

THE SAME MILITARY UNIT REPORTED THAT THERE WAS ANOTHER CLASH THAT RESULTED IN ONE DEAD TERRORIST AND THE SEIZURE OF VARIOUS KINDS OF WAR MATERIEL NEAR SAN RAFAEL FARM IN THE SAME TOWN.

IN THE COUNTRY'S EASTERN REGION, MILITARY DETACHMENT NO.4 REPORTED THAT A TERRORIST WAS KILLED AND TWO OTHERS WERE WOUNDED DURING A CLASH IN LA RANERA STREAM, SAN CARLOS, MORAZAN DEPARTMENT. AN M-16 RIFLE, CARTRIDGE CLIPS, AND AMMUNITION WERE SEIZED THERE.

MEANWHILE, THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE REPORTED THAT PONCE BATTALION UNITS FOUND THE DECOMPOSED BODY OF A SUBVERSIVE IN LA FINCA HILL, SAN MIGUEL. AN M-16 RIFLE, FIVE GRENADES, AND MATERIAL FOR THE PRODUCTION OF EXPLOSIVES WERE FOUND IN THE SAME PLACE. THE BRIGADE, WHICH IS HEADQUARTERED IN SAN MIGUEL, ADDED THAT THE SEIZURE WAS MADE YESTERDAY MORNING.

NATIONAL GUARD UNITS GUARDING THE LAS CANAS BRIDGE, WHICH IS ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK HIGHWAY IN APOPA, THIS MORNING REPELLED A TERRORIST ATTACK THAT RESULTED IN NO CASUALTIES. THE ARMED CLASH INVOLVED MORTAR AND RIFLE FIRE AND LASTED 30 MINUTES. MEMBERS OF THAT SECURITY GROUP ARE COMBING THE AREA TO DETERMINE THE FINAL OUTCOME OF THE FIGHTING.

DEV-MUC3-0002 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 4 JAN 90 -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO STATEMENTS MADE BY A SALVADORAN OFFICER TODAY, DESPITE THE CHANGE IN THE LEADERSHIP OF THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE, THE AIR FORCE WILL CONTINUE ITS NORMAL ACTIVITIES.

THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE MAINTAINS THE SAME OPERATIONAL LEVEL IT HAS HAD FOR THE LAST 10 YEARS, DESPITE THE REMOVAL OF ITS TOP COMMANDER, JAUN RAFAEL BUSTILLOS, THIS WEEK.

PARATROOPER BATTALION COMMANDER MAJOR RENE RODRIGUEZ HURTADO SAID TODAY THAT THE AIR FORCE WILL CONTINUE TO OBEY THE ORDERS OF THE GENERAL STAFF AND TO MAINTAIN A SIMILAR OPERATIONAL LEVEL.

[RODRIGUEZ] "WE KNOW GENERAL VILLAMARIONA [NEW AIR FORCE COMMANDER] ENOUGH TO KNOW THAT WE WILL CONTINUE WITH OUR BATTALION'S ATTACKS ON ALL THE TERRORIST CRIMINALS' REDOUBTS. WE DEPEND DIRECTLY ON THE GENERAL STAFF, SINCE IT IS THE STRATEGIC HEAD OF THE ENTIRE ARMY. THE GENERAL STAFF GIVES US OUR ORDERS TO LAUNCH OUR OPERATIONS."

MAJOR RODRIGUEZ HURTADO TODAY DENIED THAT SALVADORAN AIR FORCE PLANES HAD ENTERED NICARAGUAN TERRITORY AS THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT SAID LAST WEEK. MAJ RODRIGUEZ HURTADO SAID THAT SALVADORAN AIR FORCE PLANES HAVE NEVER ENTERED THE NEIGHBORING TERITORY OF NICARAGUA.

[RODRIGUEZ] "I CAN TELL YOU THAT THOSE WERE NEITHER SALVADORAN NOR HONDURAN PLANES. IN MY OPINION, THE SANDINISTS WANT TO INVENT AN EXCUSE TO CONTINUE HELPING THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. OURS AND THE HONDURAN PLANES ARE SMALL PLANES. I DO NOT THINK THAT HONDURAN PLANES ENTERED NICARAGUAN TERRITORY. THOSE COMMUNISTS ARE TRYING TO INVENT AN EXCUSE TO CONTINUE HELPING THE FMLN TERRORIST CRIMINALS."

MAJ. RODRIGUEZ MADE THESE STATEMENTS DURING THE PRESENTATION OF A NUMBER OF WEAPONS CONFISCATED BY THE PARATROOPERS BATTALION ON 4 JANUARY.

[RODRIGUEZ] "HERE WE HAVE 12 RIFLES, 11 AR-15 RIFLES AND 1 AK-47 RIFLE; 4,000 CARTRIDGES, OF WHICH 2,000 ARE FOR M-16 MACHINE GUNS AND 2,000 FOR AK-47 RIFLES; 36 CARTRIDGES OF AN UNKNOWN CALIBER-- MILITARY INTELLIGENCE HAS ALREADY BEEN INFORMED OF THIS DISCOVERY; AND I (ICON) RADIO OF THE TYPE USED BY THE LEADERS OF THE TERRORIST GROUPS."

THE WEAPONS WERE FOUND AT EL NISPERO CREEK NEAR THE SACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. AMONG THE CONFISCATED WEAPONS WERE CARTRIDGES OF UNKNOWN MAKE. THIS IS APPPARENTLY THE FIRST TIME THE ARMY HAS FOUND THAT TYPE OF CARTRIDGE. MAJ RODRIGUEZ HURTADO SAID THAT MILITARY INTELLIGENCE WILL PROCEED TO ESTABLISH THE ORIGIN OF THESE CARTRIDGES AND THE WEAPONS FOR WHICH THEY ARE INTENDED.

DEV-MUC3-0003 (NOSC)

SANTIAGO, 5 JAN 90 -- [EXCERPTS] THE GOVERNMENT JUNTA YESTERDAY APPROVED A DRAFT BILL TO "MODIFY LAW 18314, WHICH DEFINES TERRORIST ACTIVITIES AND ESTABLISHES PENALTIES." THE BILL WILL RESTRICT THE APPLICATION OF THE LAW TO THE MOST SERIOUS CASES AND WILL LEAVE OTHER CRIMES, THAT WERE FORMERLY CONSIDERED TERRORIST ACTIVITY, FOR TRIAL UNDER COMMON LAW.

THE NEW BILL ACCEPTS THE POSSIBILITY IN SOME CASES OF A PRISONER BEING RELEASED ON BAIL OR RECEIVING A PARDON OR AMNESTY. THE BILL ALSO ESTABLISHES OTHER BENEFITS NOT CONTEMPLATED BY LAW 18314, INCLUDING A NEW PROCEEDINGS FOR SPEEDIER TRIALS. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

ACCORDING TO RETIRED GENERAL FERNANDO TORRES SILVA, WHO IS THE ARMY JUDGE ADVOCATE GENERAL, THE MODIFICATIONS ESTABLISH LIGHTER SENTENCES, FREEDOM ON BAIL, AND POSSIBLE PARDONS OR AMNESTIES. THESE BENEFITS WERE NOT CONTEMPLATED UNDER THE FORMER ANTITERRORIST LAW.

AS AN EXAMPLE TORRES CITED THAT "SENTENCES OF INDIVIDUALS TRIED AS ACCOMPLICES WILL BE LOWER. THEY WILL RECEIVE LOWER SENTENCES THAN THAT PREVIOUSLY CONTEMPLATED."

THE NEW BILL WILL ALSO ALLOW A GREAT NUMBER OF PEOPLE WHO ARE BEING TRIED BY THE INTERIOR MINISTRY TO GO OUT ON BAIL.

ACCORDING THE GENERAL ATTORNEY'S OFFICE, MORE THAN 1,000 PRISONERS MIGHT BENEFIT FROM THE MODIFICATIONS.

DEV-MUC3-0004 (NOSC)

CLANDESTINE, 8 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATION COMMENTARY] [TEXT] GOODBYE [AIR FORCE COMMANDER] GENERAL RAFAEL BUSTILLO, FALSE HOPE FOR MASS KILLERS. GEN. BUSTILLO RESIGNS OR IS MADE TO RESIGN AS THE AIR FORCE CHIEF. BECAUSE OF THIS, THE GENERAL IS ADMITTING THAT WITHOUT THE BOMBING ON SAN SALVADOR'S NEIGHBORHOODS THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WOULD HAVE DEFEATED THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES. BUSTILLO'S RESIGNATION IS YET ANOTHER SIGN OF THE FAILURE OF 10 YEARS OF THE U.S. COUNTERINSURGENCY POLICY IN EL SALVADOR, AS BECAME CLEAR WITH THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED ON 10 NOVEMBER.

FOR 10 YEARS THE MILITARY AND THEIR U.S. SPONSORS BASED THEIR TRUST IN THE AIR POWER TO DROWN IN BLOOD THE ASPIRATION OF THE NATION TO ACHIEVE DEMOCRACY AND SOCIAL JUSTICE. THIS FIRST HAPPENED IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY, WITH THE DESTRUCTION OF DOZENS OF TOWNS LIKE TENANCINGO, BERLIN, TOROLA, SAN FERNANDO, AND SO MANY OTHERS THAT TOOK PLACE ALONG WITH THE GENOCIDE CARRIED OUT BY THE INFANTRY WITH THE MASS MURDERS OF CIVILIANS IN EL MOSOTO, SUNPUL, AND OCOTAPAYO. BUSTILLO IS LEAVING AS SO MANY GENERALS AND U.S. AMBASSADORS HAVE. AND LIKE ALL OF THEM HIS DEPARTURE REVEALS THE IMPERIALIST POWER'S FAILURE TO CONSOLIDATE ITS COUNTERINSURGENCY PROGRAM IN EL SALVADOR.

AS ALL THE OTHERS WHO HAVE LEFT, BUSTILLO ALSO SEEKS EXCUSES IN THE FACE OF HIS FAILURE, BY ACCUSING OTHERS. HE ACCUSES [FORMER DEFENSE MINISTER EUGENIO] VIDES CASANOVA OF BEING SOFT IN FIGHTING THE PEOPLE'S PLAN. ONE WOULD HAVE TO ASK BUSTILLO IF THE AIR FORCE, OF WHICH HE REPRESENTED ITS MOST ENCOURAGING PILLAR, WAS SOFT WHEN IT MURDERED 70,000 SALVADORANS, MONSIGNOR ARNULFO ROMERO AND THE JESUIT PRIESTS INCLUDED, AND EVEN WHEN IT MURDERED PATRIOT OFFICERS OF THAT SAME ARMY. WAS THE U.S. PENTAGON SOFT WHEN IT GAVE $3 BILLION, WEAPONS, AND BOMBS FOR THE MOST COWARDLY ACT OF GENOCIDE LATIN AMERICA CAN RECALL THIS CENTURY?

THE U.S. STRATEGY, IMPLEMENTED THROUGH THE TOP MILITARY COMMAND IN THE PAST 10 YEARS WITH ALL ITS MIGHT DID ALL IT COULD SO THAT THE PERMANENT REBELLION IN THE RURAL AREAS REACHED THE COUNTRY'S VITAL CENTERS, AS INDEED HAPPENED AS OF THE 10 NOVEMBER OFFENSIVE. BUSTILLO STATES IT CLEARLY.

THE BOMBING TEMPORARILY HALTED THE DEFEAT OF THE TOP COMMAND. THROUGH AN ACT OF GENOCIDE, IT MANAGED TO REMOVE THE DISGRUNTLED PEOPLE FROM THE NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE THE GUERRILLA FORCES WERE. BUSTILLO ACKNOWLEDGES GENOCIDE IS THE SOLE WAY THE ARMED FORCES CAN SURVIVE. BUSTILLO ACKNOWLEDGES THE FMLN'S STRENGTH AND THEREFORE URGES THE ARMED FORCES TO BE TOUGHER AND INFLEXIBLE AND REJECTS A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT. A POLITICAL SOLUTION WOULD EXPRESS THE CONSENSUS AMONG THE COUNTRY'S MAJOR SECTORS. OBVIOUSLY THE TOP COMMAND REPRESENTS A DECADENT MINORITY. BUSTILLO SUPPORTS LAUNCHING A FASCIST CRUSADE AGAINST THE PEOPLE'S WISH FOR DEMOCRACY. IN THIS EFFORT, HE LASHES OUT AT THE CATHOLIC CHURCH, ALL OPPOSITION SECTORS THAT REPORT HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS, AND ALL SECTORS THAT SUPPORT DEMOCRATIZING THE COUNTRY. IN CONCLUSION, WE SAY THAT BUSTILLO IS NOT RESIGNING OF HIS OWN VOLITION. THE FMLN ACTION ELIMINATED BUSTILLO AS IT ELIMINATED GARCIA, VIDES, AND SO MANY OTHER MILITARY CHIEFS WHO LEFT THEIR POSTS WITHOUT FULFILLING THE TASK COMMISSIONED BY THE UNITED STATES: TO STOP THE FMLN.

THE FMLN OFFENSIVE BARED THE GENOCIDAL, ANTIPOPULAR, AND FASCIST NATURE OF THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI REGIME TO SUCH AN EXTENT THAT IT PROMPTED A STRONG DEBATE IN THE UNITED STATES ON CUTTING MILITARY AID. THE JESUITS' MURDERS AND THE BOMBINGS SO SHOOK THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY THAT IT IS PRESSURING FOR PUNISHMENT OF THE OFFICERS INVOLVED IN THESE INCIDENTS. HOWEVER, THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION ACCEPTED THIS, SINCE COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE [CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINTS CHIEFS OF STAFF] AND HIS CLIQUE, EVEN CRISTIANI, MUST SHOULDER THIS RESPONSIBILITY. WE MUST NOT FORGET THAT IN COSTA RICA THE SALVADORAN DEFENSE MINISTER DISCLOSED CRISTIANI AUTHORIZED THE BOMBINGS.

BUSH NEEDED A SCAPEGOAT TO PLACE IT ON THE ALTAR OF THE DEBATES WHICH WILL BEGIN IN THE U.S. CONGRESS ON THE FATE OF MILITARY AID. BUSTILLO IS BUSH'S SCAPEGOAT. HOWEVER, BUSTILLO WAS ALREADY A USELESS ELEMENT OF THE MURDEROUS MACHINERY THAT REMAINS ACTIVE. WILL THE U.S. PUBLIC AND CONGRESS BE APPEASED WITH THIS FOUL TASTING CANDY? TIME AND THE SPIRIT OF THE TIMES ARE OBVIOUSLY RUNNING AGAINST THE FASCIST PROGRAM IN EL SALVADOR. WHILE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD TEAR DOWN DOGMAS, DICTATORSHIPS, AND WALLS, BUSTILLO, WHO LEAVES THROUGH THE DOOR OF DEFEAT, ASKS THE ARMED FORCES TO BE TOUGHER, COMMIT MORE GENOCIDE, AND BUILD MORE WALLS OF REPRESSION AGAINST THE CHURCH, THE PEOPLE, AND THE NATION AS A WHOLE. GOODBYE, GEN. BUSTILLO. WE CONTINUE WRITING HISTORY WITHOUT YOU. THE DECADE WE BEGIN IS OF DEMOCRACY, INDEPENDENCE, AND SELF-DETERMINATION. THAT IS WHY FOREIGN INTERVENTION AND THE WALLS OF INTOLERANCE HAVE A SHORT LIFE SPAN IN THIS COUNTRY, WHERE THE PEOPLE GROW IN HEROISM AND THE STRUGGLE FOR SOCIAL CHANGE IS NOT DETERRED BY BOMBINGS.

DEV-MUC3-0006 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 JAN 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMY TODAY PREVENTED THE OCCUPATION OF CITIES IN THE EASTERN PART OF EL SALVADOR, WAGING STRONG CLASHES BETWEEN MIDNIGHT AND DAWN, ACCORDING TO REPORTS BY MILITARY SOURCES.

THE ATTACKS, ACCORDING TO THE REPORTS, TOOK PLACE IN USULUTAN, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, 110 KM EAST OF THE CAPITAL, AND IN SANTA ELENA WHERE AS OF 0700 CLASHES WERE STILL UNDER WAY. SANTA ELENA IS LOCATED 119 KM EAST OF THE CAPITAL, AND BOTH CITIES ARE COFFEE REGIONS.

IN USULUTAN, 6TH BRIGADE TROOPS AND RAPID DEPLOYMENT BATTALIONS REPELLED THE INCURSION WITH ARTILLERY FIRE. DURING THE 2D WEEK OF DECEMBER, THERE HAD BEEN STRONG CLASHES ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF USULUTAN, IN WHAT THE GUERRILLAS CALLED THE "BATTLE OF EL NISPERAL," IN THE CANTON THAT BEARS THE SAME NAME, WHICH COST THE ARMY 29 DEAD, ALTHOUGH IT HAS ONLY ADMITTED TO 21 DEATHS.

IN SANTA ELENA THE CLASHES WERE ALSO STRONG, BUT SO FAR THERE HAVE BEEN NO REPORTS OF CASUALTIES ON EITHER SIDE.

FROM SAN VICENTE, IN THE CENTRAL PART OF THE COUNTRY, WHERE THE CHICHONTEPEC VOLCANO IS LOCATED, STRONG CLASHES WERE REPORTED, AND THE 5TH BRIGADE BOMBED REBEL POSITIONS ON THE COLCANO, WHERE THE FMLN HAS STRONG BASTIONS.

THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE IS CARRYING OUT OPERATIONS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR. AND ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF THE CAPITAL THIS MORNING POWERFUL EXPLOSIONS, CHARACTERIZED AS MILITARY ACTIONS TO PREVENT REBELS FROM GATHERING, COULD BE HEARD. THE NIGHT BEFORE LAST, THERE WERE ATTEMPTS TO ENTER THE CAPITAL FROM THAT DIRECTION.

THE ARMY HAS INCREASED ITS SURVEILLANCE TO PREVENT MOBILIZATIONS, AND THROUGH CAREFUL SEARCHES VEHICLES ARE BEING CONTROLLED AT THE CAPITAL CITY'S ENTRANCES AND EXITS.

IN OTHER ACTIONS, THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE REPORTED AT LEAST SIX FMLN DEATHS IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

LAST NIGHT THERE WERE FEWER ATTACKS ON STORES AND ELECTRIC TOWERS IN THE CAPITAL. THERE WERE ALSO THREATS OF POWER RATIONING IF THESE ACTIONS CONTINUED.

DEV-MUC3-0007 (NOSC)

SANTIAGO, 9 JAN 90 -- [COMMENTARY] [OLGA KLIVADENKO] [TEXT] THE DEPLOYMENT OF U.S. SHIPS, INCLUDING THE AIRCRAFT CARRIER "JOHN F. KENNEDY" AND THE CORVETTE "VIRGINIA" ALONG THE COLOMBIAN COAST YESTERDAY, SEEKING TO INTERCEPT DRUG TRAFFICKING ROUTES, COULD BE THE RESULT OF THREE POLICIES:

FIRST, THAT THE UNITED STATES NEEDS TO JUSTIFY THE INVASION OF PANAMA UNDER THE EXCUSE OF ITS FIGHT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

SECOND, THAT BOTH THE DEPLOYMENT OF SHIPS AND THE INVASION OF PANAMA ARE PART OF A SERIOUS MILITARY PLAN TO END THE DRUG PLAGUE.

THIRD, THAT THE UNITED STATES MUST SOMEHOW JUSTIFY THE INVASION OF PANAMA AND THE NEED TO RECOVER ITS INTERNATIONAL IMAGE HAS PROVIDED A REAL OPPORTUNITY TO PUT AN END TO DRUG TRAFFICKING.

IF THE OBJECTIVE REALLY IS TO ELIMINATE DRUGS, THEN THE BATTLE IS PRAISEWORTHY, BUT--LIKE IN PANAMA--THE PROCEDURE IS PAINFUL, OVERBEARING, IMPERIALISTIC, AND HUMILIATING. INSTEAD OF WINNING THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES' APPRECIATION AND SOLIDARITY WITH THIS LAUDABLE CAUSE, THE UNITED STATES IS AGAIN PROVOKING ANGRY REACTIONS AND DEEP DISTRUST. THE SIDE EFFECTS OF THIS ACTION COULD BE VERY NEGATIVE FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, IN WHICH ALL THE COUNTRIES OF THIS CONTINENT SHOULD BE COOPERATING. ALTERNATIVELY, WOULD IT BE BETTER IF THEY DID NOT COOPERATE IN THIS PHASE?

COULD IT BE THAT WHAT WE HAVE CALLED IMPERIALISTIC CLUMSINESS, INSENSIBILITY, AND ABUSE, IS SIMPLY A DELIBERATE STRATEGY WITH WHICH, PERHAPS FOR WELL FOUNDED REASONS AND EVEN AT THE RISK OF DIPLOMATIC CONFLICTS, THE UNITED STATES SEEKS TO ISOLATE LATIN AMERICA ON PURPOSE AND THUS ENSURE THE SUCCESS OF ITS OPERATION? IF THIS WERE THE CASE THEN WE MUST ASK, WHY?

FROM ITS OPERATIONS IN PANAMA AND COLOMBIA, THE UNITED STATES IS TELLING US THAT IT IS NOT CONCERNED WITH THE DIPLOMATIC ASPECT FOR THE TIME BEING. THE UNITED STATES WANTS ACTION AND EFFICIENCY. THE UNITED STATES IS LOSING ITS PATIENCE, AND PERHAPS ITS CONFIDENCE IN THE SERIOUSNESS AND CAPABILITY OF LATIN AMERICA TO FACE THIS WAR.

IF THE ACTION IN COLOMBIA GOES FURTHER THAN A MERE SURVEILLANCE, THE UNITED STATES WILL BE ESTABLISHING A PRECEDENT IN THIS BATTLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. THIS MEANS THAT DURING A FIRST PHASE THE UNITED STATES WILL CARRY OUT A MILITARY OPERATION BY ITSELF. DURING A SECOND PHASE IT WILL DISCUSS SECONDARY SUBJECTS BUT WITH LESS URGENCY IN THE WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

NEXT 15 FEBRUARY, BUSH WILL MEET IN CARTAGENA DE INDIAS, COLOMBIA, WITH HIS COLOMBIAN, PERUVIAN, AND BOLIVIAN COUNTERPARTS. PERHAPS ON THAT OCCASION THEY WILL TALK ABOUT THE OTHER ASPECTS OF THIS WAR: THE REORGANIZATION OF THE LOCAL ECONOMIES TO END THE DEPENDENCY ON COCA PLANTATIONS, THE RECOVERY OF DRUG ADDICTS, AND THE CONSOLIDATION OF GOVERNMENTS, ETC.

DURING THIS CURRENT PHASE, HOWEVER, THE UNITED STATES WISHES TO ACT ALONE. WHO KNOWS IF IT IS BECAUSE OF LATIN AMERICA'S LACK OF UNDERSTANDING? AS WE SAID A FEW DAYS AGO, THE DRUG TRAFFICKING PROBLEM IS CREATING NEW SITUATIONS IN INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS. THE U.S. PROPOSAL IS PROBABLY SOMETHING LIKE: COULD A WORLD POWER LIKE THE UNITED STATES CONTINUE TO IGNORE A SERIOUS PROBLEM LIKE THE PRODUCTION, DISTRIBUTION, AND CONSUMPTION OF DRUGS, MERELY TO AVOID HARMING LATIN AMERICAN SENSIBILITIES, SENSIBILITIES OF COUNTRIES WHOSE GOVERNMENTS ARE ALWAYS MUDDLED UP IN USELESS DIPLOMATIC AND BUREAUCRATIC PROCEDURES AND FRUITLESS NEGOTIATIONS? AND ALL THIS WHILE A LARGE PART OF THE DEVELOPED WORLD'S POPULATION IS BECOMING ADDICTED TO A DEADLY PRODUCT?

THE UNITED STATES COULD ALSO BE ASKING ITSELF: HAVE THE LATIN AMERICAN GOVERNMENTS BEEN ABLE TO SOLVE THIS SERIOUS PROBLEM BY THEMSELVES? CAN THOSE GOVERNMENTS STOP DRUG TRAFFICKING WHEN IT IS KNOWN THAT DRUGS AND CORRUPTION GO HAND IN HAND; WHEN IN THE PAST AND PERHAPS IN THE PRESENT, HIGH RANKING GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS HAVE BEEN LINKED WITH THIS ILLEGAL TRADE AND PROTECTING THE MEDELLIN CARTEL CHIEFS? WHY, FOR EXAMPLE, AFTER ALL THIS HASN'T THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT MANAGED TO EXTRADITE THE MAIN CHIEFS OF THAT CARTEL TO THE UNITED STATES?

LET US RECALL THE HORRIBLE EXPLOSION OF THE COLOMBIAN AIRLINER, IN WHICH MORE THAN 100 PEOPLE DIED; THE BOMB EXPLOSION IN THE SECRET POLICE HEADQUARTERS IN BOGOTA; THE MURDER OF MANY JOURNALISTS WHO WERE ENGAGED IN AN HEROIC WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING; AND MAINLY, LET US RECALL THE EVER-PRESENT DIFFICULTIES THAT MUST BE FACED WHEN THE MEDELLIN CARTEL CHIEFS MUST BE PUNISHED AND EXTRADITED.

DEV-MUC3-0008 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 9 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] RICARDO ALFONSO CASTELLAR, MAYOR OF ACHI, IN THE NORTHERN DEPARTMENT OF BOLIVAR, WHO WAS KIDNAPPED ON 5 JANUARY, APPARENTLY BY ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) GUERRILLAS, WAS FOUND DEAD TODAY, ACCORDING TO AUTHORITIES.

CASTELLAR WAS KIDNAPPED ON 5 JANUARY ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF ACHI, ABOUT 850 KM NORTH OF BOGOTA, BY A GROUP OF ARMED MEN, WHO FORCED HIM TO ACCOMPANY THEM TO AN UNDISCLOSED LOCATION.

POLICE SOURCES IN CARTAGENA REPORTED THAT CASTELLAR'S BODY SHOWED SIGNS OF TORTURE AND SEVERAL BULLET WOUNDS.

CASTELLAR WAS KIDNAPPED BY ELN GUERRILLAS WHILE HE WAS TRAVELING IN A BOAT DOWN THE CAUCA RIVER TO THE TENCHE AREA, A REGION WITHIN HIS JURISDICTION.

IN CARTAGENA IT WAS REPORTED THAT CASTELLAR FACED A "REVOLUTIONARY TRIAL" BY THE ELN AND THAT HE WAS FOUND GUILTY AND EXECUTED.

CASTELLAR IS THE SECOND MAYOR THAT HAS BEEN MURDERED IN COLOMBIA IN THE LAST 3 DAYS.

ON 5 JANUARY, CARLOS JULIO TORRADO, MAYOR OF ABREGO IN THE NORTHEASTERN DEPARTMENT OF SANTANDER, WAS KILLED APPARENTLY BY ANOTHER GUERILLA COLUMN, ALSO BELONGING TO THE ELN.

TORRADO'S SON, WILLIAM; GUSTAVO JACOME QUINTERO, THE DEPARTMENTAL GOVERNMENT SECRETARY; AND BODYGUARD JAIRO ORTEGA, WERE ALSO KILLED.

THE GROUP WAS TRAVELING IN A 4-WHEEL DRIVE VEHICLE BETWEEN CUCUTA AND THE RURAL AREA KNOWN AS CAMPANARIO WHEN THEIR VEHICLE WAS BLOWN UP BY FOUR EXPLOSIVE CHARGES THAT DETONATED ON THE HIGHWAY.

DEV-MUC3-0010 (NOSC)

LIMA, 9 JAN 90 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA HAS CONFIRMED THAT THE U.S. TROOPS THAT SURROUNDED OUR DIPLOMATIC MISSION IN PANAMA WERE WITHDRAWN AFTER A FORMER MINISTER SURNAMED CORDOVA LEFT THE EMBASSY. THE MILITARY MAN, WHO IS INVOLVED IN A MURDER TRIAL, LEFT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY AS SOON AS HE LEARNED THAT THE EMBASSY CONSIDERED HIM PERSONA NON GRATA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GARCIA] I THINK JOURNALISTS HAVE MAGNIFIED THE ISSUE A BIT. AS FAR AS WE KNOW, PEOPLE SOUGHT PROTECTION....[CHANGES THOUGHT] SOMEONE ARRIVES AT THE DOOR OF THE EMBASSY AND ASKS FOR REFUGE IN VIEW OF A SITUATION OF FORCE. THE SITUATION IN PANAMA IS ABNORMAL; IT HAS BEEN TOTALLY INVADED BY 30,000 SOLDIERS.

SOME PERSONS ENTERED THE EMBASSY. AT LEAST ONE OF THEM HAD BEEN ALLEGEDLY LINKED WITH THE DEATH OF A PANAMANIAN MINISTER, A MR SPADAFORA, WHO WAS MURDERED. THE AUTHORITIES OF THE EMBASSY AND OF THE FOREIGN MINISTRY STATED THAT THIS PERSON'S PRESENCE WAS UNDESIRABLE. WE DO NOT REFUSE TO GRANT REFUGE--A CONDITION THAT IS GRANTED BEFORE GRANTING POLITICAL ASYLUM--TO WHOMEVER FEELS HARASSED OR MISTREATED. IN A CASE LIKE THIS, HOWEVER, IN WHICH THERE WAS AN ALLEGED INVOLVEMENT IN A MURDER WHICH WAS COMMITTED YEARS AGO, THIS PERSON--I BELIEVE HE IS A MAN SURNAMED CORDOVA, APPARENTLY A HIGHRANKING PANAMANIAN GUARD OFFICER--WAS TOLD THAT HIS PRESENCE WAS NOT WANTED. HE LEFT THE EMBASSY OF HIS OWN WILL.

THERE ARE OTHER PANAMANIAN DEFENSE FORCES OFFICERS AT THE EMBASSY, INCLUDING MR NORIEGA'S SECRETARY, BUT THEIR STATUS SHOULD BE ESTABLISHED BY PERU.

AN INCIDENT WAS REPORTED YESTERDAY, AS THE U.S. TROOPS SURROUNDED THE EMBASSY, DEPLOYING BARRIERS AND BARBED WIRE.

THERE WAS AN ATTEMPT TO DEPICT A DRAMATIC AND SPECTACULAR PICTURE OF A SIEGE OR PERHAPS OF AN INVASION OF THE EMBASSY.

FORTUNATELY, THE FOREIGN MINISTRY RESORTED TO DIPLOMATIC CHANNELS AND THE TROOPS WERE SOON WITHDRAWN. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0013 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 JAN 90 -- [TEXT] THE CATHOLIC CHURCH HAS EXPRESSED SATISFACTION WITH THE INVESTIGATIONS IN THE CASE OF THE MURDERED JESUITS AND IS ENCOURAGING THE GOVERNMENT TO CONTINUE TO SEARCH FOR THE PERPETRATORS OF THIS CRIME.

MONSIGNOR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ TODAY STATED THAT THE CATHOLIC CHURCH IS PLEASED WITH THE PROGRESS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS REGARDING THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS. HE SAID THAT IF THE SOLDIERS INVOLVED IN THE KILLING ARE PUNISHED, THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT ONLY EARN INTERNATIONAL PRESTIGE, BUT WILL LAY THE GROUNDWORK TO CONSOLIDATE THE ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE IN EL SALVADOR.

ROSA CHAVEZ SAID THAT IF THE KILLING IS SOLVED, THE PERIOD OF IMPUNITY THAT HAS TARNISHED THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM AND COVERED UP A NUMBER OF CRIMES TO WHICH JUSTICE HAS NOT BEEN APPLIED WILL END.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ROSA CHAVEZ] IT SEEMS THAT THE PRESIDENT SHOULD BE RECOGNIZED FOR HAVING HAD THE COURAGE TO KEEP HIS PROMISE TO CONDUCT A THOROUGH INVESTIGATION. WE UNDERSTAND THAT HE HAS NOT YET REVEALED THE DETAILS OF THIS CRIME BUT THAT HE WILL DO SO SOON.

HOWEVER, I WANT TO SAY SOMETHING THAT HAS NOT BEEN SAID: THE CHURCH IS NOT INTERESTED IN LEARNING WHO THE MURDERERS ARE JUST FOR THE TRUTH TO COME OUT. THE CHURCH WANTS THIS PUNISHMENT TO MEAN THAT IMPUNITY HAS ENDED IN EL SALVADOR; THAT THE POOR WILL FEEL CERTAIN THAT JUSTICE WILL PREVAIL FOR THEM; THAT SO MANY CRIMES THAT HAVE BEEN FORGOTTEN WILL BE SOLVED LITTLE BY LITTLE; BUT MAINLY, THAT FROM NOW ON, CRIMES WILL NO LONGER GO UNSOLVED. [END RECORDING]

MSGR ROSA CHAVEZ ADDED THAT THE TONE OF VERBAL VIOLENCE MUST BE LOWERED SINCE THIS ONLY RESULTS IN A USELESS CONFRONTATION AND PROMOTES A POLARIZATION OF THE CONFLICT, AS WELL AS HINDERS ANY EFFORT TO APPLY JUSTICE. HE SAID THAT THE VERBAL WAR IS AS HARMFUL AS IRRATIONAL VIOLENCE. HE SAID THAT IRRESPONSIBLE CHARGES AND ACCUSATIONS CONTINUE IN THE COUNTRY, AND THEY DO NOT HELP STRENGTHEN THE PEACE PROCESS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ROSA CHAVEZ] IT IS IMPORTANT TO OVERCOME VERBAL VIOLENCE. THIS MEANS THAT A CALM CLIMATE, A CLIMATE THAT IS AS IMPARTIAL AS POSSIBLE, MUST BE SOUGHT TO DISCUSS ISSUES. WE RECALL THAT LAST YEAR, MANY VIOLENT STATEMENTS WERE MADE. MANY HARSH EXPRESSIONS WERE UTTERED. [WORDS INDISTINCT] TOO MANY HEATED STATEMENTS PRINTED IN SOME NEWSPAPERS. THE LANGUAGE USED IS TOO HARSH. I THINK THAT TO OBTAIN JUSTICE, WE NEED A CALMER CLIMATE. [END RECORDING]

HE ADDED THAT A CLIMATE OF SERENITY AND RESPECT WOULD FACILITATE THE RIGHT CONDITIONS FOR A DIALOGUE THAT WOULD GUARANTEE MECHANISMS TO RECONCILE OUR SOCIETY. HE URGED THE GOVERNMENT AND THE JUDICIAL AUTHORITIES TO CONTINUE MAKING PROGRESS IN THE REVIEW OF THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM TO REORGANIZE IT IN A WAY THAT WILL ALLOW THE HONEST ADMINSTRATION OF JUSTICE TO DO AWAY WITH IMPUNITY.

DEV-MUC3-0020 (NOSC)

CLANDESTINE, 11 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] REGARDING THE JESUITS' CASE, THE FMLN STATES THAT:

1. THE FMLN AND SEVERAL SECTORS, INCLUDING YOUNG ARMED FORCES OFFICERS, WERE RIGHT IN POINTING TO THE ARMY AS BEING RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS HORRIBLE CRIME. THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE ARMED INSTITUTION FOR THIS CASE AND THE CASES INVOLVING FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION], MONSIGNOR ROMERO, THE NUNS, AND THE U.S. AGRARIAN EXPERTS, AS WELL AS FOR THE BOMBINGS IN THE CITIES AND MASSACRES IN THE RURAL SECTOR, SHOW THAT WE WERE RIGHT WHEN WE MENTIONED IN OUR LAST PEACE PROPOSAL THE NEED TO CLEAN UP THE ARMY AND REFORM THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM.

2. TO ADVANCE IN THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIZATION, IT IS NOT ENOUGH TO SOLVE THIS CASE. THE OTHER CASES NEED TO BE SOLVED AND THOSE GUILTY FOR THEM SHOULD BE PUNISHED. THE ESTABLISHMENT OF RESPONSIBILITIES CANNOT REMAIN AT THE LEVEL OF OFFICERS AND TROOPS WHO ONLY CARRIED OUT ORDERS. MOST IMPORTANT IS TO ESTABLISH RESPONSIBILITY AMONG HIGHER-RANKING OFFICERS BECAUSE A DECISION OF THIS SORT COULD NOT BE BEYOND THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE TOP COMMAND.

3. IT IS ALSO NECESSARY TO COMPLY WITH THE ESQUIPULAS II AGREEMENTS CONCERNING DEMOCRATIZATION; REFORMING THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM; LIFTING THE STATE OF EMERGENCY; REESTABLISHING FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION, MOBILIZATION, AND ORGANIZATION; RELEASING THE MORE THAN 3,000 POLITICAL PRISONERS; AND STOPPING THE REPRESSION AGAINST THE CHURCH AND OTHER SECTORS.

4. THE ANNOUNCEMENT BY CRISTIANI IS AN EFFORT TO RESOLVE COMPLICATED DISCUSSIONS ON U.S. AID FOR EL SALVADOR AND TO CONTINUE TO BENEFIT FROM THIS AID TO MAINTAIN THE WAR. IT WOULD BE A MISTAKE TO INCREASE AID TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY BECAUSE OF THIS ANNOUNCEMENT OR BECAUSE THE CASE MAY BE RESOLVED. SUCH AID WOULD LEAVE OPEN THE POSSIBILITY OF SEEING A CASE LIKE THAT OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS HAPPENING AGAIN. THE BEST WAY TO CONTRIBUTE TO A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION IS TO CEASE AID. WE APPEAL TO THE U.S. CONGRESS TO MAKE THIS DECISION. IF THIS IS DONE, THE FMLN WOULD COMMIT ITSELF TO MAKING EFFORTS TO REACH AN IMMEDIATE CEASEFIRE.

5. FAVORABLE CONDITIONS FOR NEGOTIATIONS DEPEND ON JUSTICE-MAKING PROGRESS. IF THE ARMY IS THOROUGHLY PURGED BECAUSE OF THIS CASE, PEACE COULD BE REACHED EARLIER.

6. TO CONTRIBUTE TOWARD A PROMPT PEACE, WE WILL ASK THE OFFICE OF THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL TO MEDIATE. WE URGE THE GOVERNMENT TO JOINTLY MEET WITH US AND WITH MR JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR WITHIN THE NEXT 30 DAYS TO RENEW THE DIALOGUE-NEGOTIATION PROCESS.

7. THE FMLN WILL BE WATCHING HOW THE SITUATION DEVELOPS. IT URGES NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL FORCES TO EXERT PRESSURE SO THAT THE INVESTIGATION PROCESS DOES NOT END WITH A DECLARATION OF INTENTION OR WITH STATEMENTS BLAMING LOW-RANKING SOLDIERS TO PROTECT THOSE WHO ARE MOST RESPONSIBLE. THIS WOULD PUSH AWAY THE POSSIBILTIY OF A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND: COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ, SHAFICK JORGE HANDAL, EDUARDO SANCHO, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, AND FRANCISCO JOVEL.

DEV-MUC3-0022 (NOSC)

ROME (ITALY), 11 JAN 90 -- [INTERVIEW WITH DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE LEADER RUBEN ZAMORA BY ALESSANDRO OPPES] [EXCERPT] [PASSAGE OMITTED] [OPPES] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAS DESCRIBED THE ARREST OF FIVE SOLDIERS ACCUSED OF COMMITTING THE MASSACRE [OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS] AS "A MANIPULATED COVER OPERATION." BASICALLY, CRISTIANI IS ALLEGED TO HAVE DECIDED TO PUNISH A NUMBER OF LOW-RANKING OFFICERS TO CLOSE THE CASE AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE AND TO END INTERNATIONAL PRESSURES. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION IN THIS REGARD?

[ZAMORA] THE FACT THAT PRESIDENT CRISTIANI ACKNOWLEDGES THAT MEMBERS OF THE ARMY WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MASSACRE IS A FIRST STEP AND DEFINITELY A GOOD THING, BUT IT IS ENTIRELY INSUFFICIENT UNLESS THE SUBSEQUENT STEPS ARE ALSO TAKEN. FIRST, TO IDENTIFY WHO THE RESPONSIBLE PARTIES WERE: THIS IS THE FIRST IMPORTANT POINT, BECAUSE NOBODY CAN FEEL SATISFIED IF ONLY LOW-RANKING OFFICERS ARE IDENTIFIED. SUCH AN ACT CAN ONLY HAVE BEEN ORDERED BY HIGH-RANKING OFFICERS. WE MUST NOT FORGET THE MURDER OF MONSIGNOR ROMERO, FOR WHICH THERE WERE NO SENTENCES AND NO TRIALS.

[OPPES] HOWEVER, THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND IMMEDIATELY DENIED INVOLVEMENT IN THE OPERATION, STATING THAT IT WAS AN ISOLATED ACTION "DIVORCED FROM ANY INSTITUTIONAL POLICY."

[ZAMORA] I BELIEVE THIS IS ENTIRELY WRONG: THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT FATHERS CANNOT BE CONSIDERED AN ISOLATED ACTION. OVER 7,000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED IN EL SALVADOR DURING 10 YEARS OF CIVIL WAR, AND 90 PERCENT OF THEM WERE CIVILIANS. POLITICAL ASSASSINATION BY THE GOVERNMENT FORCES IS A CONSTANT PRACTICE. FURTHERMORE, TORTURE IS REGULARLY PRACTISED IN EL SALVADOR. THE ARMY HIGH COMMAND CANNOT FAIL TO KNOW THIS. THEY CANNOT CLAIM TO BE INNOCENT, BECAUSE THEY HAVE THE GREATEST RESPONSIBILITIES FOR HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS.

[OPPES] YET LAST MONTH THE SUMMIT OF CENTRAL AMERICAN HEADS OF STATE IN SAN JOSE ENDED WITH A SUCCESS FOR PRESIDENT CRISTIANI, WHO SECURED AN EXPLICIT CONDEMNATION OF THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE GUERRILLAS IN NOVEMBER, WHEREAS NO SPECIFIC CHARGES WERE LEVELED AT THE GOVERNMENT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS.

[ZAMORA] THERE IS A POSITIVE FACTOR THAT SHOULD BE BORNE IN MIND, NAMELY, THE CALL FROM THE FIVE PRESIDENTS FOR A RESUMPTION OF THE DIALOGUE IN EL SALVADOR AND THE APPEAL TO THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL TO CARRY OUT MEDIATION TO THIS END. BUT IN THE SUMMIT'S FINAL DOCUMENT, IT IS THE FMLN AND THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS WHO PAY THE PRICE FOR THE AGREEMENT AMONG THE PRESIDENTS: THESE ARE DIPLOMATIC GAMES THAT DO NOT FACILITATE THE RESTORATION OF PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA.

[OPPES] WHAT PATHS CAN BE TAKEN NOW TO ADVANCE THE NEGOTIATIONS?

[ZAMORA] NEGOTIATIONS ARE BECOMING INCREASINGLY NECESSARY. THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE SHOWS THAT THE FMLN IS A STRONG MILITARY FORCE, BUT ALSO THAT A REVOLUTIONARY ATTITUDE DOES NOT EXIST AMONG THE MASSES. IT ALSO SHOWS THAT THE GOVERNMENT ARMY, AFTER 10 YEARS OF U.S. TRAINING, IS AN ARMY WHOSE MILITARY STANCE IS DEFENSIVE, NOT OFFENSIVE (WHICH IS THE KEY TO U.S. MILITARY STRATEGY.) WHILE THIS ALL SHOWS THAT THERE CAN ONLY BE A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS, IT IS ALSO TRUE THAT PRECISELY FOLLOWING THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE (AND THIS IS THE PARADOX) THE ARMY STIFFENED ITS STANCE AGAINST NEGOTIATIONS. I BELIEVE THAT SOONER OR LATER COMMON SENSE WILL PREVAIL AND IT WILL SIT DOWN AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLE. AT THE END OF NOVEMBER THE U.S. SECRETARY OF STATE'S ASSISTANT FOR LATIN AMERICA SPOKE OFFICIALLY FOR THE FIRST TIME ABOUT THE NEED FOR NEGOTIATIONS TO RESOLVE THE CRISIS IN EL SALVADOR: THIS IS AN IMPORTANT SIGN OF A CHANGING SITUATION.

DEV-MUC3-0023 (NOSC)

LIMA, 11 JAN 90 -- [TEXT] THE MRTA [TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT] TODAY DISTRIBUTED LEAFLETS CLAIMING RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER OF FORMER DEFENSE MINISTER ENRIQUE LOPEZ ALBUJAR.

GENERAL OSVALDO DIAZ SALVADOR, CHIEF OF THE 7TH SUBREGION OF THE NATIONAL POLICE, HAS CONFIRMED THE EXISTENCE OF THE LEAFLETS, AND ADDED THAT THE MURDER CASE IS STILL BEING INVESTIGATED. HE SAID THAT AMONG THE THOUSANDS OF DETAINEES THERE ARE 16 SUSPECTS WHO ARE BELIEVED TO HAVE PARTICIPATED IN THE MURDER OF THE OUTSTANDING GENERAL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DIAZ SALVADOR] WELL, THERE ARE TWO OPERATIONS. FIRST, THE DRAGNET OPERATION, IN WHICH PEOPLE WITH THE CHARACTERISTICS ESTABLISHED BY WITNESSES ARE ARRESTED, AND SECOND, THERE IS A MORE SPECIFIC OPERATION BEING CONDUCTED BY THE SPECIALIZED UNITS.

[REPORTER] IS THERE ANY INFORMATION YET REGARDING THE CAPTURE OF THE MURDERERS OF THE FORMER DEFENSE MINISTER?

[DIAZ SALVADOR] THESE OPERATIONS SEEK TO CLEAR UP BOTH A CRIME THAT HAS SHOCKED THE NATION AND ALSO THE KILLING OF TWO PATROLMEN WHO WERE MURDERED IN COLD BLOOD THE DAY BEFORE THE GENERAL WAS MURDERED.

[REPORTER] DO THE POLICE HAVE IDENTIKITS OF THE MURDERERS?

[DIAZ SALVADOR] WE HAVE RECEIVED SOME IDENTIKITS OF PEOPLE WHO COULD HAVE PARTICIPATED IN THE ATTACK FROM THE SPECIALIZED UNITS OF THE TECHNICAL POLICE. BASED ON THESE IDENTIKITS THE POLICE WILL BE MORE SPECIFIC AND SELECTIVE.

[REPORTER] HOW MANY IDENTIKITS DO YOU HAVE SO FAR?

[DIAZ SALVADOR] SO FAR WE HAVE RECEIVED THREE IDENTIKITS.

[REPORTER] THE MURDER IS ATTRIBUTED TO MRTA AND NOT TO THE SHINING PATH. WHAT NEWS DO THE HAVE ON THIS?

[DIAZ SALVADOR] I BELIEVE THE INTELLIGENCE SERVICES WILL HAVE THE FINAL WORD ON THIS.

[REPORTER] IS IT TRUE THAT THE MRTA HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER?

[DIAZ SALVADOR] WELL, WE ALL KNOW THAT SOME LEAFLETS HAVE APPEARED TODAY INSIDE A NEWSPAPER THAT CLAIMS TO BE THE MOUTHPIECE ON THIS MATTER, BUT I DO NOT THINK THIS IS FINAL. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0024 (NOSC)

LA PAZ, 12 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [EXCERPT] TWO BOMB ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT IN LA PAZ LAST NIGHT, ONE IN FRONT OF GOVERNMENT HOUSE FOLLOWING THE MESSAGE TO THE NATION OVER A RADIO AND TELEVISION NETWORK BY PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA.

THE EXPLOSIONS DID NOT CAUSE ANY SERIOUS DAMAGE BUT THE POLICE WERE MOBILIZED, FEARING A WAVE OF ATTACKS.

THE SELF-STYLED "ZARATE WILLKA LIBERATION ARMED FORCES" SENT SIMULTANEOUS WRITTEN MESSAGES TO THE MEDIA, CALLING ON THE PEOPLE TO OPPOSE THE GOVERNMENT, WHICH IT SAYS IS "AT THE SERVICE OF THE WEALTHY AND THE EXPLOITERS." IT ALSO CALLS FOR FREE EDUCATION, THE ESTABLISHMENT OF PERMANENT JOBS, THE DEFENSE OF COCA-LEAF FARMING, AND THE DEFENSE AGAINST U.S. INTERVENTION AND BIG LAND OWNERS.

THE FIRST BOMB ATTACK OCCURRED AT 2230 [0230 GMT ON 12 JANUARY] IN FRONT OF THE PLANNING AND ECONOMIC COORDINATION MINISTRY, JUST BEFORE PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA CONCLUDED HIS MESSAGE TO THE NATION IN WHICH HE EXPLAINED THE GUIDELINES OF THE GENERAL ECONOMIC PROGRAM THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL IMPLEMENT BETWEEN 1990 AND 1993.

ROBERTO BARBERY, INTERIOR MINISTRY INTELLIGENCE DEPARTMENT DIRECTOR, HAS REPORTED THAT DYNAMITE STICKS WERE HURLED FROM A CAR.

THE SECOND ATTACK OCCURRED AT 2335 [0335 GMT ON 12 JANUARY], JUST AFTER THE CABINET MEMBERS HAD LEFT GOVERNMENT HOUSE WHERE THEY HAD LISTENED TO THE PRESIDENTIAL MESSAGE.

A BOMB WAS PLACED OUTSIDE GOVERNMENT HOUSE IN THE PARKING LOT THAT IS USED BY CABINET MINISTERS. THE POLICE PLACED THE BOMB IN A NEARBY FLOWER BED, WHERE IT WENT OFF. THE SHOCK WAVE SHATTERED SOME WINDOWS IN GOVERNMENT HOUSE AND STREET LAMPS IN THE PLAZA MURILLO.

AS OF 0500 GMT TODAY, THE POLICE HAD RECEIVED REPORTS OF TWO OTHER EXPLOSIONS IN TWO LA PAZ NEIGHBORHOODS, BUT THESE HAVE NOT YET BEEN CONFIRMED. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0027 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 JAN 90 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [NANCY PERLA] [TEXT] SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT FRANCISCO MERINO HAS DESCRIBED THE POSSIBLE RESUMPTION OF DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS AS POSITIVE.

MERINO SAID THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] SHOULD NOT CLAIM CREDIT FOR THE RESUMPTION OF A DIALOGUE BECAUSE IT WAS PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI WHO TOOK THE INITIATIVE IN RESUMING THE TALKS. MERINO ADDED THAT THE REBELS SHOULD ABANDON THE DELAYING AND IRRESPONSIBLE TACTICS REGARDING THE DIALOGUE BECAUSE THE FMLN HAS LOST CREDIBILITY BOTH IN THE MILITARY SENSE AND IN INTERNATIONAL POLITICS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] THE FMLN HAS LOST CREDIBILITY IN ALL OF ITS ACTIVITIES, INCLUDING MILITARY ACTIONS. THE ONLY VALID ALTERNATIVE TO PACIFY THE COUNTRY IS FOR THE REBELS TO STOP HOSTILITIES, VIOLENCE, AND TERRORISM. WE SHOULD JOINTLY EXPLORE THE POSSIBILITIES OF THEIR JOINING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS. [END RECORDING]

HE ALSO SAID ONE OF THE ALTERNATIVES READILY AVAILABLE TO THE FMLN IS TO PARTICIPATE IN THE ELECTIONS FOR DELEGATES TO THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PARLIAMENT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] EL SALVADOR HAS PROPOSED AT THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY TO RATIFY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PARLIAMENT PROTOCOL. THIS WOULD OPEN THE DOOR FOR THE SPECIAL ELECTION OF THE SALVADORAN DELEGATES TO THE PARLIAMENT. IF A TRULY DEMOCRATIC WILLINGNESS BY THE FMLN EXISTS, THIS COULD BE THEIR FIRST OPPORTUNITY TO PARTICIPATE. IT HAS NOT YET BEEN DECIDED WHETHER THIS ELECTION WILL BE HELD BEFORE THE 1991 OFFICIAL ELECTIONS FOR MAYORS AND DEPUTIES. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN COULD JOINTLY CONSIDER THE ADVANTAGES OF A SPECIAL ELECTION THIS YEAR. THEN WE COULD MAKE PREPARATIONS FOR THE 1991 CONSTITUTIONAL ELECTIONS. [END RECORDING]

REGARDING THE FMLN MILITARY ACTIONS, MERINO SAID THE GOVERNMENT IS FAMILIAR WITH THE REBELS' TACTICS, PARTICULARLY WHEN TALKS ARE BEING CONSIDERED. HE ALSO SAID THE REBELS OPERATE IN CYCLES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] THE GOVERNMENT HAS NEVER REACTED NAIVELY TO THE FMLN TERRORISTS' STATEMENTS OR THEIR PARTICIPATION IN THE DIALOGUE. WE ARE FULLY AWARE OF THEIR PLANS AND STRATEGIES. THE GOVERNMENT, HOWEVER, BEARS THE PRIMARY RESPONSIBILITY OF SEEKING HARMONY AND THE CITIZENS'S SECURITY. [END RECORDING]

AFTER THE REBELS' COUNTEROFFENSIVE IN NOVEMBER, WHICH WAS REGARDED AS THE LARGEST MILITARY OPERATION IN THE PAST 10 YEARS, THE POSSIBILITY FOR A NEW DIALOGUE HAS APPEARED IN EL SALVADOR ONCE MORE, CREATING EXPECTATIONS, BOTH HERE AND ABROAD. THE COMING MEETING OF PRESIDENT CRISTIANI WITH UNITED NATION'S REPRESENTATIVES, SCHEDULED FOR NEXT WEEK, AND THE MEETING ON 12 JANUARY OF A REBEL DELEGATION WITH A UNITED NATIONS OFFICIAL SEEM TO INDICATE THAT TALKS WILL BE HELD SHORTLY.

DEV-MUC3-0029 (NOSC)

CLANDESTINE, 12 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] THE U.S. CONGRESSMEN'S WORKTABLES ARE FILLED WITH SURPRISES. THEY ARE TO RENEW THEIR SESSIONS IN 2 WEEKS' TIME, AND IMPORTANT MATTERS ARE WAITING TO BE DISCUSSED.

AFTER THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] STARTED ITS 11 NOVEMBER OFFENSIVE WHICH BURIED THE ARMY'S PROPAGANDISTIC CLAIMS THAT IT HAD FINISHED OFF THE GUERRILLAS, ALONG CAME THE GREAT SURPRISES IN THE EAST EUROPEAN COUNTRIES, WHEN THEY BROUGHT DOWN WALLS WITHOUT HAVING TO RESORT TO MILITARY INVASIONS AND ATTAINED A DEMOCRATIC OPENING. ENDING THE YEAR, THE WORLD WAS SURPRISED WITH THE BRUTAL U.S. INVASION OF PANAMA.

NOW, WHEN THE LAST DECADE OF THE CENTURY IS ABOUT TO BEGIN, EL SALVADOR ADDS ANOTHER PAGE TO THE BOOK OF LAST-MINUTE SURPRISES. ALFREDO CRISTIANI HIMSELF--WHO, TOGETHER WITH ARMED FORCES OFFICERS, SAID HOURS AFTER THE JESUITS AND THEIR MAIDS HAD BEEN MURDERED THAT THERE WERE SUSPICIONS THAT THE FMLN COULD BE INVOLVED IN THE MASSACRE--HAS JUST ACCEPTED, ESPECIALLY FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE U.S. CONGRESS, THAT ARMED FORCES PERSONNEL WERE THE ONES WHO MURDERED THE TOP BRAINS, THE BEST INTELLECTUALS OF EL SALVADOR. THE MURDERERS WERE MILITARY PERSONNEL, AND, AT LEAST ON THE NATIONAL TELEVISON NETWORK, CRISTIANI PROMISED TO DISLOSE THEIR NAMES. [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]...THE JESUITS' MURDERS OR THE CANCELLATION OF AID.

IF IT IS TRUE THAT THE ARMY--WHICH MURDERED MONSIGNO OSCAR ROMERO, 1,000 PEASANTS IN EL MOZOTE, 70 INDIANS IN LAS HOJAS, HUNDREDS OF SALVADORANS IN ZUNPU, AND UNIONISTS AT THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] OFFICES, ALONG WITH THE REST OF THE ARMED FORCES' WELL-KNOWN CRIMES--IS GOING TO BE PURGED AT LAST, IF THIS IS REALLY TRUE, THEN WE WOULD HAVE TO SAY THAT A TRUE NEGOTIATION WILL START. IN THE PAST, THE FMLN HAS MADE PROPOSALS FOR NEGOTIATIONS TO END THE WAR.

ONE OF OUR DEMANDS, A REALISTIC DEMAND TO PROPITIATE PEACE IN EL SALVADOR, IS UNDOUBTEDLY THE PURGE OF THE ARMY. IN MEXCIO AND IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, WE SAID THAT IF THE GOVERNMENT DID NOT ACCEPT THE FMLN'S PROPOSAL, THE NATION WOULD DO SO. AND THAT IS WHAT HAS HAPPENED. THE NATION DEMANDS THAT THE ARMED FORCES BE PURGED.

THE MOST IMPORTANT U.S. NEWSPAPERS AND NEWSCASTS HAVE NOTED THE IRREFUTABLE FACT THAT 10 YEARS OF U.S. ADVICE AND AN INVESTMENT OF MORE THAN $3 BILLION--VERY CLOSE TO $4 BILLION--TO CREATE A HUGE BUILDUP IN THEIR ARMAMENTS HAVE NOT SERVED TO CHANGE THE MENTALITY OF AN ARMY THAT MURDERED MONSIGNOR ROMERO AND THOUSANDS OF CIVILIANS, INCLUDING NUNS AND U.S. ADVISERS. WE BELIEVE DEMOCRATIC SENATOR CHRISTOPHER DODD WAS MISTAKEN WHEN HE SAID THAT U.S. AID IN ITSELF WAS NOT BEING DISCUSSED. THE 10 YEARS OF AID, ADVICE, AND U.S. STRATEGY IN EL SALVADOR HAVE PROVEN TO BE A FAILURE. IF THE UNITED STATES HAS ANY INTENTIONS OF CONTRIBUTING TO PEACE, NOW IS THE TIME TO CHANGE ITS POLICY TOWARD EL SALVADOR.

EVENTS HAVE PLACED THE ISSUE OF THE CONTINUATION OF AID TO EL SALVADOR ON THE CONGRESSMEN'S WORKTABLES. THE AID WAS MADE CONDITIONAL ON PUNISHMENT FOR THE JESUITS' MURDERS. BUT WHAT IS THE ORDER OF THE DAY? IT IS A DECISION THAT GOES BEYOND A BASIC DEMAND FOR JUSTICE. IT WILL DETERMINE THE CONTINUATION OF U.S. AID. IT ENTAILS THE DECISION TO TURN THEIR POLICY AROUND TO CONTRIBUTE TO A POLITICAL SOLUTION IN EL SALVADOR. THEY ARE TO DISCUSS WHETHER CONGRESS' POSITION IS TO BE: ONE, WE APPROVE THE PURGE OF THE ARMY AND THUS WE WILL GIVE THEM MORE AID, OR, TWO, WE APPROVE THE PURGE AS A CONCRETE STEP TO DEMOCRATIZATION AND WILL SUSPEND MILITARY AID SO THAT THESE CONDITIONS CAN BE USED TO REACH A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION.

WILL U.S. CONGRESSMEN BE CAPABLE OF SURPRISING THE WORLD BY HELPING THE SALVADORANS TO TOPPLE THE FASCIST WALL, THE WALL OF WAR? WILL THEY DO THIS BY STOPPING MILITARY AID? THE FMLN HAS SAID CLEARLY THAT IF THE UNITED STATES STOPS AID TO THE ARMY IT WILL CORRESPOND WITH ACTIONS TO REACH A COMPLETE HALT IN HOSTILITIES. WE HOPE THE U.S. CONGRESS DOES NOT MAKE A MISTAKE. IF IT STOPS AID, IF IT CUTS IT, IF IT ENDS IT, WE WILL STAND BEFORE A CLEAR AND HOPEFUL SIGN FOR PEACE. HOWEVER, IF NOT, WE WILL STAND BEFORE YET ANOTHER SIGN OF WAR, AND THE SURPRISE WILL NOT BE A GOOD ONE.

DEV-MUC3-0032 (NOSC)

CLANDESTINE, 13 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] REGARDING THE ASSASSINATION OF HECTOR OQUELI COLINDRES, LEADER OF THE NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT AND THE DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE AND SECRETARY FOR LATIN AMERICA OF THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL, IN GUATEMALA ON 12 JANUARY, WE STATE:

1. WE BLAME ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE], THE REGIME OF [PRESIDENT ALFREDO] CRISTIANI AND [ARENA LEADER ROBERTO] D'AUBUISSON, AND ITS ARMED FORCES FOR THIS DETESTABLE ASSASSINATION. THE LINKS BETWEEN D'AUBUISSON'S ARENA PARTY AND THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL LIBERATION MOVEMENT OF MARIO SANDOVAL ARE WELL KNOWN. BOTH OPPOSE EVERY EFFORT TO BRING PEACE TO THE REGION.

2. THIS NEW CRIME AND THE RECENT EVENTS CONCERNING THE CASE OF THE JESUITS, WHICH SHOW THAT THE MASTERMINDS WILL NOT BE PUNISHED, FORCES US TO REVIEW OUR DIALOGUE OFFER BECAUSE WE ARE NOT INTERESTED IN HELPING THE FASCIST REGIME WASH ITS FACE TO OBTAIN U.S. MILITARY AID AND TO PROCEED WITH ITS PLAN TO ANNIHILATE EVERY TYPE OF OPPOSITION.

3. THE ASSASSINATION OF DR OQUELI AND HIS COMPANION, GILDA FLORES, THE EXTENSION OF THE STATE OF THE SIEGE, AND THE FACT THAT NOTHING INDICATES THAT THERE WILL BE PUNISHMENT FOR THE MASTERMINDS OF THE MASSACRE OF 16 NOVEMBER SHOW THAT CRISTIANI'S ANNOUNCEMENT TO GET TO THE BOTTOM OF THE LATTER CASE IS ONLY A FARCE TO OBTAIN U.S. AID AND TO PROCEED WITH THE SLAUGHTER OF OPPOSITION MEMBERS.

4. AS THOSE EVENTS SHOW, THE POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFICT REQUIRES A PURGE OF THE ARMED FORCES, DEMOCRATIZATION, AND SELF-DETERMINATION. THERE CAN BE NO DIALOGUE AMID STATE TERRORISM, A STATE OF SIEGE, AND GENERAL TRAMPLING ON HUMAN RIGHTS. UNDER THE STATE OF SIEGE, THE REGIME GIVES ITSELF THE RIGHT TO CARRY OUT A GENERAL REPRESSION. THEREFORE, WE CALL ON ALL POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES TO STRUGGLE FOR ITS ABROGATION.

5. THE 15 DECEMBER 1989 UN GENERAL ASSEMBLY RESOLUTION DEMANDING RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS AND DEMOCRATIC FREEDOMS MUST BE UNCONDITIONALLY IMPLEMENTED IN OUR COUNTRY TO CREATE AN ATMOSPHERE AND CONDITIONS FAVORABLE TO A POLITICAL SOLUTION.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[DATED] EL SALVADOR, 13 JANUARY 1990

DEV-MUC3-0033 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 JAN 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN OPPOSITION NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MNR) TODAY DEMANDED THAT GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO "THOROUGHLY" INVESTIGATE THE ASSASSINATION OF MNR LEADER HECTOR OQUELI AND OF GUATEMALAN ATTORNEY GILDA FLORES.

DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE, THE MNR EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE CONDEMNED THE "ABOMINABLE" CRIME PERPETRATED ON 12 JANUARY IN GUATEMALA BY ARMED MEN WEARING CIVILIAN CLOTHES. THE MNR ALSO DEMANDED THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT GUARANTEE THE SECURITY OF MNR SECRETARY GENERAL GUILLERMO UNGO, WHO WILL ARRIVE IN EL SALVADOR WITHIN THE NEXT FEW HOURS TO ATTEND OQUELI'S FUNERAL, WHICH IS SCHEDULED FOR 15 JANUARY.

OQUELI, 45, AND GILDA FLORES, A MEMBER OF THE DEMOCRATIC SOCIALIST PARTY (PSD) OF GUATEMALA, WERE KIDNAPPED WHILE THEY WERE ON THEIR WAY TO LA AURORA AIRPORT IN GUATEMALA CITY. THEIR BODIES WERE FOUND LATER AT A PLACE NEAR THE SALVADORAN BORDER.

"THE PEOPLE RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS UNJUSTIFIABLE ASSASSINATION ARE THE ETERNAL ENEMIES OF LIBERTY, PEACE, AND DEMOCRACY," THE MNR STATES. THE MNR, ALONG WITH THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC PARTY AND THE SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT [MPSC], MAKE UP THE DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE COALITION.

THE MPSC ALSO ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE DEPLORING THE ASSASSINATION OF OQUELI AND URGING THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO CONDEMN THIS ACTION.

DEV-MUC3-0034 (NOSC)

CLANDESTINE, 13 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATION COMMENTARY] [TEXT] WHAT WE HAD PREDICTED HAS OCCURRED. CRISTIANI ANNOUNCED THIS AFTERNOON THAT A COLONEL, TWO LIEUTENANTS, ONE SECOND LIEUTENANT, TWO SECOND SERGEANTS, AND TWO SOLDIERS WERE INVOLVED IN THE MASSACRE OF THE JESUITS.

THE ACCUSATION AGAINST COLONEL BENAVIDES IS THE FOLLOWING: THAT THE MULTIPLE CRIME WAS COMMITTED IN THE SECTOR UNDER HIS COMMAND. FROM THE LIEUTENANT ON DOWN, THE ACCUSATION IS THAT THEY DIRECTLY PARTICIPATED IN THE CRIME. [WORDS INDISTINCT], AS CRISTIANI SAID, THAT IT WAS COL BENAVIDES, BUT IT WAS NOT COL BENAVIDES WHO ISSUED THE ORDER. SO, THE QUESTION IS: WHO GAVE THE ORDER TO KILL THE JESUITS AND THEIR TWO MAIDS. IN OUR VIEW, COL BENAVIDES WAS IMPLICATED SOLELY AS A MEANS OF PROPAGANDA AIMED AT THE U.S. CONGRESS. IT IS CLEAR THAT COL BENAVIDES DID NOT GIVE THE ORDER. HE PROBABLY DID NOT EVEN KNOW ABOUT THE ACTION. THIS IS CONSISTENT WITH WHAT WE KNOW ABOUT HIS BACKGROUND. FIRST, HE IS NOT KNOWN TO HAVE CARRIED OUT ACTS OF REPRESSION OR CORRUPTION. OUR REPORT INDICATES THAT BENAVIDES HAS MAINTAINED A POSITION IN FAVOR OF INSTITUTIONS AND OPEN TO DISCUSSIONS. HE WAS DESCRIBED AS AN ACTIVE, STUDIOUS AND NOT REPRESSIVE CADET, ONE OF THE FEW EXCEPTIONS IN LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1977 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPTAIN GENERAL GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY]. IN OTHER WORDS, FOR THE LA TANDONA, A GANG OF ASSASSINS, HE IS A PERFECT SCAPEGOAT.

THE MASSACRE OF THE JESUITS WAS NOT A PERSONAL DECISION. IT WAS PART OF THE ARMED FORCES' COUNTEROFFENSIVE ACTIONS DURING THE NOVEMBER BATTLES. IT WAS A COLD-BLOODED, PREMEDITATED PLAN EXECUTED TO DECAPITATE THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT AND THE DEMOCRATIC OPPOSITION. LET US REMEMBER THE THREATS AGAINST FATHER ELLACURIA OVER THE NATIONAL RADIO NETWORK PRIOR TO THE ASSASSINATION. LET US REMEMBER THAT BETWEEN THE NIGHT OF 15 NOVEMBER AND EARLY MORNING OF 16 NOVEMBER, SEVERAL OFFICES OF LABOR UNIONS AND HOUSES OF OPPOSITION MEMBERS WERE ATTACKED. LET US REMEMBER THAT AFTER THE MASSSACRE OF THE JESUITS, THE OFFICERS SHOUTED OVER LOUDSPEAKERS THAT THEY HAD KILLED ELLACURIA AND THAT THEY WERE GOING TO CONTINUE KILLING COMMUNISTS. THE BISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR WAS A WITNESS TO THIS.

IN OUR VIEW, THE ASSASSINS OF THE JESUITS WERE THOSE WHO APPEARED ON THE RADIO AND TELEVISION NETWORK MAKING KNOWN THE RESULTS OF THE SO-CALLED HONOR COMMISSION. COL BENAVIDES WILL PROBABLY BE FREED IN A SHORT TIME AND BE APPOINTED TO SOME POST ABROAD, OR HE MIGHT EXPERIENCE THE SAME FATE AS THAT OF CAPTAIN EDUARDO ALFONSO AVILA, WHO WENT IN AND OUT OF JAIL EACH TIME THAT MILITARY AID FOR EL SALVADOR WAS DISCUSSED IN THE U.S. CONGRESS.

HOWEVER, IN ANY CASE AND AS HAS ALWAYS OCCURRED, IT WILL BE THE LIEUTENANTS, THE NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICERS, AND THE SOLDIERS WHO CARRIED OUT AN ORDER WHO WILL PAY THE CONSEQUENCES. WE HAVE ALREADY SEEN THIS HAPPEN IN THE CASES OF THE NUNS WHEN [WORDS INDISTINCT] A FEW SOLDIERS, THE MASSACRE OF SAN FRANCISCO, AND THE ASSASSINATION OF THE U.S. ADVISERS AND RODOLFO VIERA. [WORDS INDISTINCT] ONCE AGAIN THE PEOPLE'S HOPES ARE FRUSTRATED, AS HAS HAPPENED IN SO MANY OTHER CASES.

THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUITS AGAIN CONFIRMS THAT TO, AS CRISTIANI SAID, GET TO THE BOTTOM OF THIS, WE HAVE TO OBTAIN DEMOCRACY, JUSTICE, AND SELF-DETERMINATION.

DEV-MUC3-0035 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 JAN 90 -- [TEXT] THE NEW FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] PROPOSAL TO STOP FIGHTING PROVIDED THE U.S. CONGRESS SUSPENDS AID TO EL SALVADOR IS BLACKMAIL. WITH THIS, HE SAID, THE FMLN IS SHOWING TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY THAT ITS MEMBERS ARE PLAIN TERRORISTS.

THIS WAS SAID ON 12 JANUARY BY THE RULING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE PRESIDENT DR ARMANDO CALDERON SOL, WHO MAINTAINED THAT ASPIRATIONS OF THE SUBSERSIVES ARE "DETESTABLE," AND, THEREFORE, CANNOT BE ACCEPTED.

THE PROMINENT POLITICAL LEADER SAID THAT WHILE IN EAST EUROPE THERE IS A TRUE DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTION, THE FMLN MAINTAINS ITS POSITION OF TRYING TO SUBDUE THE PEOPLE WITH A TOTALITARIAN PLAN THROUGH VIOLENT MEANS. "HISTORY HAS LEFT THEM BEHIND AND THEY (THE TERRORISTS) HAVE NOT NOTICED IT," HE ADDED.

CALDERON SOL EMPHASIZED THAT FMLN LEADERS SHOULD RECONSIDER THE POSITION THEY HAVE MAINTAINED AND SHOULD RESPECT THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM BECAUSE WITHOUT IT, NO NATION CAN ACHIEVE HARMONY AND DEVELOPMENT.

THE SEDITIOUS "SHOULD UNDERSTAND THAT THEY ARE ALONE AND THAT NO ONE SUPPORTS THEIR ANARCHIC PLAN," THE ARENA PRESIDENT ADDED. HE RECALLED THAT DURING THE TERRORIST AGGRESSION, THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY SUPORTED THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN NEVER RECEIVED ANY SUPPORT.

CALDERON SOL STRESSED THAT THE FMLN MUST PROVIDE REAL PROOF THAT IT WANTS TO REACH PEACE THROUGH NEGOTIATED MEANS, BECAUSE PRESIDENT CRISTIANI HAS GOOD INTENTIONS AND WANTS TO SOLVE THE CONFLICT AS SOON AS POSSIBLE THROUGH TALKS.

THE SUBVERSIVES MUST SUSPEND THE AGGRESSION AGAINST THE PEOPLE AND THE DESTRUCTION OF THE NATIONAL ECONOMY, BECAUSE ONE CANNOT BE AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLE WHILE THE FMLN AT THE SAME TIME IS PREPARING AN OFFENSIVE.

DEV-MUC3-0036 (NOSC)

GUATEMALA CITY, 13 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE GUATEMALAN FOREIGN MINISTRY CONDEMNED TODAY THE ASSASSINATION OF LEFTIST SALVADORAN LEADER HECTOR OQUELI AND GUATEMALAN POLITICAL LEADER GILDA FLORES.

BOTH BODIES WERE FOUND TODAY IN AN AREA NEAR GUATEMALA AND EL SALVADOR BORDER AFTER THE VICTIMS WERE KIDNAPPED IN GUATEMALA CITY YESTERDAY.

A FOREIGN MINISTRY COMMUNIQUE "REGRETS AND CONDEMNS" THE ASSASSINATION OF OQUELI, ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL FOR LATIN AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN, AND DEPUTY SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MNR), A LEFTIST MOVEMENT IN EL SALVADOR.

"WE DEEPLY REGRET THE DEATHS OF TWO VALUABLE PERSONS, AND WE CONDEMN THIS ACT OF VIOLENCE," THE NOTE ADDS.

THE DOCUMENT IS THE FIRST OFFICIAL REACTION TO THE KIDNAPPING AND ASSASSINATION OF BOTH LEADERS.

GILDA FLORES WAS AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE DEMOCRATIC SOCIALIST PARTY (PSD) OF GUATEMALA, WHOSE SECRETARY GENERAL MARIO SOLORZANO REPORTED THAT "SALVADORAN PARAMILITARY GROUPS" ARE CARRYING OUT ACTIONS IN THIS COUNTRY.

ACCORDING TO SOLORZANO, THE INCIDENT "SHOWS THERE IS COOPERATION BETWEEN PARAMILITARY GROUPS OF BOTH COUNTRIES," BECAUSE THE PERPETRATORS KNEW OF OQUELI'S ARRIVAL "AND THEY STAGED AN ENTIRE OPERATION TO KIDNAP HIM."

THE BODIES OF THE POLITICAL LEADERS WERE FOUND EARLY THIS MORNING WITH SHOTS THROUGH THE TEMPLE IN THE GUATEMALAN TOWN OF JALPATAGUA, NEAR THE BORDER WITH EL SALVADOR, OQUELI'S RELATIVES TOLD EFE IN EL SALVADOR.

OQUELI ARRIVED IN GUATEMALA LAST THURSDAY. ON FRIDAY MORNING, WHILE ON HIS WAY TO LA AURORA AIRPORT TO CATCH A PLANE TO NICARAGUA, HE WAS KIDNAPPED BY "HEAVILY ARMED MEN," ACCORDING TO THE MNR.

DEV-MUC3-0039 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 15 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TODAY POSTPONED HIS TRIP TO THE UNITED STATES, WHICH WAS SCHEDULED FOR 16-23 JANUARY, UNTIL LATER THIS MONTH, ACCORDING TO AN ANNOUNCEMENT TODAY BY INFORMATION SECRETARY MAURICIO SANDOVAL.

THE PRESIDENTIAL SPOKESMAN EXPLAINED THAT THE POSTPONEMENT OF CRISTIANI'S TRIP IS DUE TO THE PRESIDENT'S INTEREST IN MEETING WITH UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR TO REQUEST THAT PEREZ DE CUELLAR ACT AS MEDIATOR TO ACHIEVE THE RESUMPTION OF DIALOGUE WITH THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS.

"WE HAVE RECEIVED INFORMATION FROM NEW YORK TO THE EFFECT THAT PEREZ DE CUELLAR WILL NOT BE AVAILABLE ON THE DATES INITIALLY SET FOR THE TRIP, THUS, CRISTIANI'S VISIT HAS BEEN POSTPONED, SANDOVAL SAID.

ACCORDING TO SANDOVAL, CRISTIANI WILL MEET WITH PEREZ DE CUELLAR ON 31 JANUARY, AFTER WHICH HE WILL GO TO WASHINGTON IN EARLY FEBRUARY TO MEET WITH U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH.

SANDOVAL DENIED THAT THE POSTPONEMENT OF CRISTIANI'S TRIP IS RELATED TO POSSIBLE REACTION TO THE ARREST OF EIGHT MEMBERS OF THE ARMY, INCLUDING FOUR OFFICERS, ON CHARGES OF BEING IMPLICATED IN THE MURDER OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO EMPLOYEES.

"THERE IS NO RELATION, BECAUSE THE CASE OF THE JESUITS IS BEING RESOLVED," THE SPOKESMAN SAID.

SANDOVAL ALSO DENIED THAT POSTPONEMENT OF THE TRIP IS LINKED TO THE ASSASSINATION OF HECTOR OQUELI, A SALVADORAN LEADER OF THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL, 3 DAYS AGO IN GUATEMALA.

AFTER LEARNING OF OQUELI'S ASSASSINATION, THE GUERRILLAS ANNOUNCED THAT THEY WILL "REVISE" THEIR OFFER TO RESUME THE DIALOGUE WITH THE GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, THE PRESIDENTIAL SPOKESMAN INDICATED THAT THE GUERRILLAS HAVE SENT NO OFFICIAL NOTE EXPLAINING THE REVISION.

DEV-MUC3-0043 (NOSC)

MADRID (SPAIN), 26 JAN 89 (RNE) -- [TEXT] NAPOLEON DUARTE, PRESIDENT OF EL SALVADOR, HAS REJECTED THE PROPOSAL FROM THE GUERRILLAS, WHO ACCEPTED THE ELECTIONS IF THEY WERE POSTPONED FOR 6 MONTHS AND HELD WITH DEMOCRATIC GUARANTEES. TODAY A DELEGATION OF THE SALVADORAN INSURGENTS WILL HOLD TALKS IN MADRID WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE SPANISH FOREIGN MINISTRY. THE SPANISH OFFICIALS' INTERLOCUTOR IS MIGUEL SAENZ, MEMBER OF THE POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] AND THIS IS HIS FIRST REACTION, IN EXCLUSIVE STATEMENTS TO RNE [SPANISH NATIONAL RADIO], TO NAPOLEON DUARTE'S REJECTION OF THE INSURGENTS' PROPOSAL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SAENZ] THE ONLY WAY LEFT IS TO CONTINUE THE STRUGGLE, AND THUS WE WOULD HAVE TO INTENSIFY THIS STRUGGLE IN THE POLITICAL AND MILITARY FIELD. THEN, UNFAILINGLY, IF THERE IS NO POLITICAL SOLUTION, THERE WILL BE A SOCIAL EXPLOSION IN THE COUNTRY. IT IS UNSTOPPABLE. WE BELIEVE THAT SPAIN IN PARTICULAR, AS PRESIDENT OF THE EEC, WITH THE TRADITIONAL, CULTURAL TIES UNITING US, CAN PLAY QUITE A PROMINENT ROLE. SPECIFICALLY, WE BELIEVE THAT THE EEC CAN INTERCEDE WITH ITS OFFICES BETWEEN THE PARTIES IN CONFLICT IN ORDER TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE RESOLUTION OF THE CONFLICT. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0045 (NOSC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 26 JAN 89 -- [INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA BY JULIO ARMANDO VALDES] [EXCERPT] [AZCONA] ...WHICH HAS DISMAYED ALL HONDURAN PEOPLE. THE GOVERNMENT STRONGLY CONDEMNS THIS KIND OF ACTION--THE MURDER OF [RETIRED] GENERAL GUSTAVO ALVAREZ MARTINEZ--WHICH WAS POLITICALLY MOTIVATED AND PERPETRATED BY PROFESSIONALS, AND WHICH, I BELIEVE, DESERVES THE DENUNCIATION OF ALL HONDURANS.

[VALDES] MR PRESIDENT, WILL THE THREE BRANCHES OF GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES ADOPT ADDITIONAL SECURITY MEASURES?

[AZCONA] YES, WE WILL BE DISCUSSING THAT SOON. I HAVE A MEETING SCHEDULED WITH THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL, WHICH WILL ALSO BE ATTENDED BY THE THREE PRESIDENTS OF THE STATE BRANCHES. I MEAN, THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] WILL CHAIR THE MEETING, AND NATIONAL CONGRESS PRESIDENT CARLOS ARBIN MONTOYA AND SUPREME COURT PRESIDENT SALOMON JIMENEZ CASTRO WILL ALSO ATTEND. WE HAVE ALSO INVITED THE CANDIDATES OF THE TWO [NUMBER AS HEARD] PARTIES TO THIS MEETING SINCE ONE OF THEM IS GOING TO BE THE NEXT HONDURAN PRESIDENT. WE PLAN TO ESTABLISH SOME GUIDELINE--SOME RULES TO BE FOLLOWED--NOT JUST FOR THE REMAINDER OF OUR TERM BUT IN THE FUTURE AS WELL, BECAUSE WE SHOULD BE FARSIGHTED AND NOT JUST CONCENTRATE ON THE SHORT TERM, WHICH HAS BEEN VERY COMMON IN HONDURAS, WHERE WE LOOK AND FIND SOLUTIONS ONLY FOR THE PRESENT. WE SHOULD FIND SOLUTIONS JOINTLY [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN THE LONG RUN, WHICH INCLUDES THE ISSUE OF VIOLENCE. WE BELIEVE IN A DEMOCRACY LIKE OURS, WHICH IS A VERY COMPLETE DEMOCRACY. IN OTHER WORDS, THERE ARE INTERNAL ELECTIONS FOR SELECTING CANDIDATES, WHERE CITIZENS ENJOY FULL RIGHTS, WHERE PARTIES AND PARTY LEADERS CONSULT WITH THE PEOPLE, WHERE WE HAVE TRUE, CLEAN, AND HONEST ELECTIONS, WHERE WE HAVE A NATIONAL ELECTORAL COMMISSION THAT IS NOT INFLUENCED BY NOR CAN IT BE INFLUENCED BY THE GOVERNMENT, AND WHERE THE STATE BRANCHES ARE TOTALLY INDEPENDENT.

ALL OF THESE CHARACTERISTICS MAKE HONDURAS A DEMOCRACY, AND EVERY SECTOR OF HONDURAN SOCIETY SHOULD STRIVE TO STRENGTHEN THEM BY AVOIDING VIOLENCE AT ALL COSTS, OBEYING THE LAW, AND CONDEMNING AND ATTACKING EXTREME TERRORIST GROUPS REGARDLESS OF THEIR AFFILIATION, THUS ENABLING US TO CONSOLIDATE OUR DEMOCRACY AND REACH THE LEVEL OF POLITICAL DEVELOPMENT ATTAINED BY OTHER DEMOCRATIC COUNTRIES.

IT HAS BEEN DEMONSTRATED WORLDWIDE THAT PROGRESS AND DEVELOPMENT CAN ONLY BE ACHIEVED THROUGH DEMOCRACY. THE FRG, THE MEDITERRANEAN COUNTRIES--ITALY, FRANCE, AND SPAIN--ARE EXAMPLES OF THIS, AND THERE IS THE CASE OF JAPAN, WHICH HAS A LIBERAL DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM AND HAS ACHIEVED EXTRAORDINARY LEVELS OF DEVELOPMENT. TAIWAN IS YET ANOTHER EXAMPLE. AT THIS STAGE...

[VALDES, INTERRUPTING] YES, BUT THIS TAKES TIME.

[AZCONA] YES. AT THIS STAGE I BELIEVE THERE IS SUFFICIENT PROOF THAT THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM IS THE BEST MEANS OF ATTAINING HIGHER LEVELS OF DEVELOPMENT. THERE IS NO DOUBT IN ANYONE'S MIND ABOUT THAT, BUT THE FACT THAT WE HAVE THIS SYSTEM IS NOT ENOUGH. EACH ONE OF US, EACH SECTOR, MUST DO HIS PART TO MAKE IT WORK.

WHEN I MENTION SECTORS, I AM REFERRING TO PRIVATE ENTERPRISE, WHICH MUST BE GENEROUS, EXHIBIT CONFIDENCE IN THE COUNTRY, AND SHOW MUCH INITIATIVE; TO ORGANIZED LABOR GROUPS, WHICH MUST FIGHT FOR THEIR RIGHTS WITHOUT FOMENTING STRIKES AND OTHER DISORDERS, WHICH ARE SOMETIMES BROUGHT ABOUT ILLEGALLY INSTEAD OF FOLLOWING THE NORMAL LEGAL PROCEDURES; TO PROFESSIONAL ASSOCIATIONS, WHICH ALSO HAVE AN ENORMOUS RESPONSIBILITY, BECAUSE THEIR MEMBERS MUST COMPLY WITH THEIR DUTIES; AND THE SAME GOES FOR GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES AND OTHERS.

IN OTHER WORDS, THIS WILL NOT BE ACCOMPLISHED BY THIS OR THE NEXT GOVERNMENT ALONE. OUR GOVERNMENTS ARE TRANSITORY AND THEIR POWER IS RELATIVE. I HAVE SAID THIS MANY TIMES. THERE IS NO POINT IN LASHING OUT AT THE PRESIDENT, BECAUSE POWER IN HONDURAS IS RELATIVE AND CONDITIONAL. WHAT IS ESSENTIAL IS TO CONTRIBUTE POSITIVELY TOWARD HONDURAS' DEVELOPMENT. THIS SHOULD BE A RESPONSIBILITY NOT ONLY OF PUBLIC EMPLOYEES, BUSINESSMEN, WORKERS, AND ORGANIZED PEASANTS, BUT ALL HONDURANS SHOULD CONTRIBUTE. THAT IS WHAT COUNTS.

[VALDES] MR PRESIDENT, WHEN WILL THIS MEETING BE HELD AND WHAT IMMEDIATE MEASURES WILL YOU PROPOSE?

[AZCONA] THE APPROPRIATE AUTHORITIES ARE DOING EVERYTHING POSSIBLE TO INVESTIGATE THE LATEST CRIME, WHICH WAS NOT AN EVERYDAY OCCURRENCE LIKE A ROBBERY OR SOMETHING OF THAT NATURE. THIS CRIME WAS CAREFULLY PLANNED. IT WAS A TERRORIST ACT PERPETRATED BY PROFESSIONALS.

[VALDES] MR PRESIDENT, SOME PEOPLE HAVE BEEN SAYING THAT THE DEATH PENALTY MIGHT BE A WAY TO COPE WITH THE SITUATION. WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THIS?

[AZCONA] I RECENTLY READ SOMETHING ABOUT THE DEATH PENALTY IN A MEXICAN MAGAZINE. THE DEATH PENALTY IS OPPOSED BY A MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE AND HAS BEEN ABOLISHED IN HONDURAS. I DO NOT THINK THIS IS THE SOLUTION HERE BECAUSE THE DEATH PENALTY HAS NOT SOLVED THE CRIME PROBLEM ANYWHERE ELSE IN THE WORLD. FOR INSTANCE, THIS PENALTY EXISTS IN MANY U.S. STATES, BUT THIS HAS NOT DETERRED CRIMINALS FROM COMMITTING TERRIBLE CRIMES. PEOPLE HAVE LOST CONTROL. WHEN CRIMINALS HAVE NO RESPECT FOR THEIR FELLOW MAN, NOT EVEN THE DEATH PENALTY CAN STOP THEM. HOWEVER, THERE ARE CRIMES, SUCH AS DRUG TRAFFICKING, FOR WHICH NO BAIL SHOULD BE PERMITTED. I THINK A BILL THAT HAS BEEN PROPOSED BY THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE SHOULD BE PASSED BY THE CONGRESS. OF COURSE, IT WILL BE APPROVED BY THE PRESIDENT SO THOSE FOUND GUILTY OF THIS CRIME CANNOT BE BAILED OUT. IT IS NOT RIGHT FOR THE AUTHORITIES TO ARREST A DRUG TRAFFICKER ONLY TO SEE HIM RELEASED ON BAIL BY A JUDGE WHO HAS NO OTHER CHOICE THAN TO ABIDE BY THE LAW.

[VALDES] MR PRESIDENT, THE FAR RIGHTIST GROUP AAA [ANTICOMMUNIST ACTION ALLIANCE], THROUGH A LOCAL RADIO STATION, WARNED THAT THEY WILL TAKE REVENGE ON MAJOR COMMUNIST LEADERS, SUCH AS JORGE ARTURO REINA, RAMON CUSTODIO, AND OTHERS. WHAT DO YOU HAVE TO SAY ABOUT THIS?

[AZCONA] I AM ADAMANTLY OPPOSED TO THIS TYPE OF REVENGE BECAUSE IT WOULD ONLY LEAD TO ESCALATED CONFRONTATIONS BETWEEN GROUPS. I CONDEMN THIS ATTITUDE IN VIEW OF THE REGRETTABLE MURDER OF GENERAL GUSTAVO ALVAREZ MARTINEZ. AS FAR AS THE DEATH PENALTY GOES, IT WILL NOT BE A SOLUTION TO THE CRIME PROBLEM.

[VALDES] MR PRESIDENT, CIVIC COMMITTEES HAVE TO BE ORGANIZED IN THE COUNTRY.

[AZCONA] I AGREE, BUT THESE COMMITTEES SHOULD BE CONTROLLED BY THE AUTHORITIES. A CIVIC COMMITTEE TO PROTECT COMMUNITIES IS ONE THING, BUT IT IS QUITE ANOTHER THING TO SUE THESE COMMITTEES TO PERFORM DUTIES THAT ARE ALREADY THE RESPONSIBILITY OF STATE AGENCIES, SUCH AS THE ARMED FORCES.

[VALDES] WHEN WILL THE GOVERNMENT BRANCHES MEET?

[AZCONA] THEY WILL MEET WHEN I RETURN FROM CARACAS.

DEV-MUC3-0049 (NOSC)

LA PAZ, 24 DEC 88 -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO A CLAIM MADE BY THE MINISTER OF INTERIOR, MIGRATION, AND JUSTICE, JUAN CARLOS DURAN, 1988 WAS A "POSITIVE YEAR," BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT MANAGED TO SCORE ACHIEVEMENTS IN THE ECONOMIC AREA AS WELL AS IN DEFENSE OF THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM EXISTING IN BOLIVIA.

THE MINISTER REMARKED: "I BELIEVE THAT IT WAS A YEAR OF FULL ACCOMPLISHMENT, A VERY POSITIVE AND VERY GOOD YEAR"; HE ADDED THAT THE MONTHS OF THE CURRENT FISCAL YEAR REPRESENTED PROGRESS FOR THE GOVERNMENT IN STATE ADMINISTRATION TASKS.

HE EXPLAINED THAT GREATER CONSOLIDATION WAS ACHIEVED IN THE ECONOMIC AREA, MAKING IT POSSIBLE FOR THE EFFORTS INTENDED TO REINFORCE BOLIVIA'S POLITICAL SYSTEM TO BE WELL AIMED.

HE CLAIMED THAT A SYSTEM SUCH AS THE ONE IN FORCE IN OUR NATION HAS ENABLED THE CITIZENS TO ENJOY "ABSOLUTE FREEDOM," SOMETHING THAT HAS BEEN UNDERSCORED NOT ONLY IN OUR COUNTRY, BUT IN THE NATIONS OF THE ENTIRE WORLD AS WELL.

HE NOTED THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT HAD TO RESORT TO ANY UNUSUAL ACTION TO DEFEND DEMOCRACY. HE RECALLED MARTIAL LAW HAD NOT BEEN ORDERED, ATTESTING TO PROGRESS IN THE NATIONAL CONSCIOUSNESS.

HE COMMENTED: "BOLIVIA IS AN EXEMPLARY COUNTRY IN TERMS OF FREEDOM," STRESSING THE BENEFITS THIS NATION HAS EXPERIENCED BY HAVING A DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM IN WHICH EVERYONE HAS AN OPPORTUNITY TO DISAGREE EVEN WITH THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH.

HE SAID THAT THE CITIZENS AS A WHOLE HAVE FOUND IT NECESSARY FOR RIGHTS TO BE RECOGNIZED AND OBLIGATIONS ACCEPTED. FOR THIS REASON, HE CLAIMED, THE PRESENT GOVERNMENT HAS MADE IT POSSIBLE TO ACHIEVE STABILITY IN THE VARIOUS FIELDS OF ACTIVITY, SOMETHING THAT WILL HAVE FAR MORE VISIBLE EFFECTS IN THE NEAR FUTURE.

DRUG TRAFFICKING

WITH REGARD TO THE BATTLE AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFIC, HE CITED THE WORK PERFORMED BY THE SPECIAL FORCES TO BATTLE DRUG TRAFFICKING WHICH, ACCORDING TO HIS ACCOUNT, DESTROYED HUNDRED OF COCAINE FACTORIES AND PROCESSING PITS, IN ADDITION TO CONFISCATING DRUGS AND ARRESTING PERSONS LINKED WITH THEIR PRODUCTION OR ILLICIT TRAFFICKING.

HE DECLARED THAT, DESPITE ITS ECONOMIC AND TECHNICAL LIMITATIONS, BOLIVIA HAS MANAGED TO RESPOND TO THE INTERNATIONAL CONFIDENCE AND TO FOSTER A CONSCIOUSNESS AIMED AT IMPROVING THE METHODS FOR COMBATING DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

ROBBERY

THE MINISTER ANNOUNCED THAT THE SANTA CRUZ POLICE HAD MOBILIZED IN A "COMBING OPERATION," TO FIND THE PERPETRATORS OF THE ROBBERY OF A CAR ON THE TRACK OF THE EASTERN RAILROAD SYSTEM FROM WHICH 130,000 BOLIVIANOS, INTENDED TO PAY CHRISTMAS BONUSES, WAS STOLEN.

HE SAID THAT THE ARMED FORCES AND POLICE WERE STILL COMPLYING WITH INSTRUCTIONS TO ERADICATE THE CRIME THAT HAS BEEN OCCURRING ON A LARGE SCALE DURING RECENT MONTHS IN THE CITY OF SANTA CRUZ, AND TO BENEFIT THE EASTERN POPULATION WITH PROTECTION.

HE EXPLAINED THAT THE POLICE HAVE BEEN TAKING STATEMENTS FROM INDIVIDUALS WHO MAY HAVE SEEN THE HOLDUP MEN AT CLOSE RANGE, SO AS TO CAPTURE THEM PROMPTLY.

DEV-MUC3-0050 (NOSC)

SANTIAGO, 24 JAN 89 -- [TEXT] THE CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTRY HAS CATEGORICALLY REJECTED THE U.S. DECISION TO CITE A TREATY SIGNED WITH CHILE IN 1914, TO TURN THE MURDER CASE OF FORMER CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTER ORLANDO LETELIER OVER TO AN INTERNATIONAL COMMITTEE OF JURISTS.

THIS STATEMENT WAS MADE BY FOREIGN MINISTER HERNAN FELIPE ERRAZURIZ, WHO ADDED THAT THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT IS HANDLING THE SITUATION IN A SERIOUS AND PROFESSIONAL MANNER.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ERRAZURIZ] YES, ON 12 JANUARY WE RECEIVED A DIPLOMATIC NOTE WHICH WE ARE NOW STUDYING. WE CATEGORICALLY REJECT THE IMPLICIT PRESSURE ON SOMETHING WE ARE HANDLING IN A SERIOUS AND PROFESSIONAL MANNER. WE HAVE GRANTED ALL POSSIBLE COOPERATION IN ACCORDANCE WITH OUR RIGHTS AND INTERNATIONAL LAW. [END RECORDING]

IN VIEW OF THIS SITUATION, THE FOREIGN MINISTRY ISSUED AN OFFICIAL STATEMENT WHICH SAYS THAT THE 1914 TREATY IS BEING STUDIED TO SEE WHETHER OR NOT IT IS APPLICABLE.

THE STATEMENT ADDS THAT THE TERMS USED BY THE U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT SPOKESMAN LAST MONDAY IN REFERRING TO THIS MATTER REPRESENT A DISTORTED AND PARTIAL VIEW, REFLECTING THE DESIRE TO IMPOSE A POSITION DISREGARDING INTERNATIONAL LAW AND THE DOMESTIC LAWS OF OTHER COUNTRIES.

THE FOREIGN MINISTRY STATEMENT CONCLUDES BY SAYING THAT THE CHILEAN COURTS ARE PROCESSING A ROGATORY LETTER SUBMITTED THROUGH NORMAL DIPLOMATIC CHANNELS, HAVING TO DO WITH THE PROCEEDINGS BEING CARRIED OUT IN THE UNITED STATES ON THIS CRIMINAL CASE.

DEV-MUC3-0053 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 23 JAN 89 -- [TEXT] PATRIOTIC UNION [UP] PRESIDENT BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA TODAY REVEALED THAT THE GOVERNMENT WARNED HIM OF A PLOT TO MURDER HIM AT EL DORADO AIRPORT UPON HIS RETURN FROM CUBA.

AFTER RETURNING HOME FROM THE AIRPORT ON SATURDAY NIGHT, BERNARDO JARAMILLO RECEIVED ANOTHER DEATH THREAT OVER THE TELEPHONE. TODAY, FOLLOWING ADDITIONAL EVIDENCE TO SUBSTANTIATE THE THREAT, THE AUTHORITIES STEPPED UP SECURITY MEASURES FOR JARAMILLO. AN ARMORED VEHICLE, 2 STATION WAGONS, 2 MOTORCYCLES, AND 15 MEN, ARMED TO THE TEETH AND NOT MORE THAN 30 YEARS OLD, HAVE BECOME JARAMILLO'S GUARDIAN ANGELS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GUTIERREZ] ARE YOU AFRAID?

[JARAMILLO] I HAVE ALWAYS SAID THAT ONLY BAD PEOPLE ARE AFRAID. HOWEVER, I WILL TELL YOU QUITE HONESTLY THAT I WOULD BE MORE AFRAID IF I HAD DECIDED TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY. I AM DETERMINED TO REMAIN IN COLOMBIA AND TO CONTINUE WORKING FOR DEMOCRACY AND PEACE.

[GUTIERREZ] DO YOU FEEL THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS GIVING YOU ENOUGH PROTECTION?

[JARAMILLO] ONE THING IS THE DIRECT PROTECTION EFFICIENTLY PROVIDED BY THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY, AND ANOTHER THING IS THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY FOR ELIMINATING THESE PROBLEMS. I DO NOT BELIEVE THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY FOR DISMANTLING THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS IS APPROPRIATE.

[GUTIERREZ] WHEN YOU LEAVE YOUR HOME, DO YOU FEEL IT IS YOUR LAST DAY?

[JARAMILLO] I HAVE ALWAYS BEEN AN OPTIMIST; I ALSO BELIEVE THAT YOU WILL DIE WHEN YOU LEAST EXPECT IT. WHEN I WALK OUT OF MY HOME, I TAKE ALL THE NECESSARY PRECAUTIONS. [END RECORDING]

JARAMILLO SAID HIS TWO SONS, WHO DO NOT LIVE IN BOGOTA, CALLED TO SAY THEY WANTED TO SEE HIM. JARAMILLO TOLD THEM TO STAY AWAY; HE FEARS THAT A SURPRISE ATTACK CAN HAPPEN AT ANY TIME AND THAT HIS FAMILY AND FRIENDS MAY BECOME THE VICTIMS OF THIS NEVER-ENDING WAR.

DEV-MUC3-0054 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 21 JAN 89 -- [TEXT] FOUR OFFICIALS WHO HAD STARTED TO INVESTIGATE THE KILLING OF 12 JUDICIAL OFFICIALS NEAR LA ROCHELA, IN SANTANDER DEPARTMENT HAVE RESIGNED BECAUSE OF THREATS. HOWEVER, VARIOUS ENTITIES CONTINUE TO INVESTIGATE THE CRIME.

DEATH HANGS OVER BARRANCABERMEJA. THE JUDGE APPOINTED TO INVESTIGATE THE KILLINGS OF THE 12 JUDICIAL OFFICIALS WAS THREATENED TODAY. YESTERDAY, TWO INDIVIDUALS RIDING A RED MOTORCYCLE THREATENED TWO INVESTIGATORS DURING THE FUNERAL OF [WORDS INDISTINCT] HELD IN BARRANCABERMEJA OIL PORT. IN SPITE OF THESE INCIDENTS, A 15-MEMBER TEAM, INCLUDING TWO JUDGES AND THREE MEMBERS OF THE JUDICIAL POLICE, ARE EXAMINING EVIDENCE FOUND IN LA ROCHELA, WHERE THE CRIME WAS COMMITTED.

THE NATIONAL DIRECTOR OF THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS DEPARTMENT FLEW IN A HELICOPTER TO INSPECT THE SITE AND LOOKED ON AS EVIDENCE WAS GATHERED. A POSTER OF ALVARO GOMEZ HURTADO AND SEVERAL EMPTY AR-15 AND 9-MM CARTRIDGES WERE FOUND ON A HIGHWAY, AS WELL AS A CARD WITH A NAME ON IT. IT HAS NOT BEEN DETERMINED YET IF THESE OBJECTS BELONGED TO THE VICTIMS OR TO THE CRIMINALS.

COLLEAGUES OF THE 12 WHO WERE MURDERED CAREFULLY SIFTED THROUGH THE SOIL, LOOKING FOR MORE EVIDENCE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED OFFICIAL] WE MUST INVESTIGATE THIS SCIENTIFICALLY; IN OTHER WORDS, WE MUST APPLY SCIENCE TO THIS. THE EVIDENCE WILL TELL US WHAT HAPPENED. [END RECORDING]

RELATIVES OF THE MURDER VICTIMS WENT TO THE JUDICIAL POLICE OFFICE IN BARRANCABERMEJA TO DEMAND THE VICTIMS' CLOTHING, IDENTIFICATION CARDS, AND EVEN A TYPEWRITER THEY WERE PLANNING TO USE TO REPORT ON THE INVESTIGATIONS OF THE 56 KILLINGS THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN THIS PART OF THE MIDDLE MAGDALENA AREA.

IT HAS BEEN 4 DAYS SINCE THE KILLING AND NO ONE HAS BEEN ARRESTED. HOWEVER, THE JUDGES AND THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS DEPARTMENT OFFICIALS ARE HERE, TRYING TO GATHER EVIDENCE THAT WILL CLEAR UP THIS CRIME.

DEV-MUC3-0058 (NOSC)

LIMA, 20 MAY 88 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THREE WOMEN SURVIVORS HAVE REPORTED TO THE COURTS IN THE PERUVIAN CITY OF AYACUCHO REGARDING THE MASSACRE--FOR WHICH THEY HOLD THE ARMY RESPONSIBLE--OF NEARLY 80 PEOPLE, INCLUDING MISSING PEOPLE, IN THE TOWN OF CAYARA.

ACCORDING TO THE REPORT, SOLDIERS WITH THEIR FACES PAINTED BLACK ARRIVED IN CAYARA LAST SATURDAY AND "BROKE DOWN DOORS, LOOTED STORES, AND BURNED SEVERAL HOUSES."

THE MEN OF CAYARA WERE ROUNDED UP AT THE TOWN CHURCH. THE REPORT ADDED: "THERE WAS NOTHING WE COULD DO. WE HEARD HORRIBLE GROANS OF PAIN AND DESPERATION. THUS, IT CAN BE DEDUCED THAT THEY WERE KILLED AFTER BEING MERCILESSLY TORTURED."

LATER, THE SOLDIERS ROUNDED UP PEASANTS FROM THE CAYARA AREA "AND, AFTER FORCING THE MEN AND WOMEN TO LIE PRONE IN SEPARATE ROWS, KILLED THE MEN ONE BY ONE."

THE SOLDIERS USED MACHETES, AXES, AND FIREARMS FOR THE KILLINGS.

THE THREE WOMEN SUPPLIED A LIST OF 57 PEOPLE WHO WERE KILLED IN THE MASSACRE AND 18 WHO ARE MISSING, INCLUDING A 20-YEAR-OLD NURSE.

A PICTURE OF THIS NURSE, MARTHA CRISOSTOMO GARCIA, APPEARS ON THE FRONT PAGE OF TODAY'S LA REPUBLICA, WITH A REQUEST FOR "SOMEONE TO PROVIDE INFORMATION ON HER."

CAYARA IS A TOWN IN AYACUCHO DEPARTMENT, IN SOUTHERN PERU. IT WAS THE BIRTHPLACE OF THE ARMED ACTIVITIES OF THE MAOIST SHINING PATH GUERRILLAS IN 1980. CAYARA IS 80 KM FROM ACCOMARCA, WHERE AN ARMY PATROL REPORTEDLY KILLED 69 PEASANTS, INCLUDING MEN, WOMEN, AND CHILDREN, AND BURNED THEIR HOMES IN 1985.

LAST FRIDAY, THE SHINING PATH AMBUSHED AN ARMY PATROL, KILLING 1 OFFICER AND 3 NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICERS AND INJURING 15 SOLDIERS, 4 OF THEM SERIOUSLY. SIX SHINING PATH TERRORISTS WERE ALSO KILLED.

AN OFFICIAL ARMY COMMUNIQUE REPORTED THAT THE SHINING PATH TERRORISTS ESCAPED TOWARD CAYARA, WHICH, ACCORDING TO THIS COMMUNIQUE, HAD BEEN ABANDONED, THAT ONLY SOME OLD PEOPLE AND CHILDREN LIVED IN CAYARA, AND THAT FOUR BODIES WERE FOUND IN THE CHURCH.

JAVIER DIEZ CANSECO, A LEFTIST SENATOR, SAID THE MASSACRE WAS IN REPRISAL FOR LAST FRIDAY'S AMBUSH.

THE OPPOSITION HAS ASKED THAT AN INVESTIGATING COMMISSION BE FORMED. ALTHOUGH THIS ISSUE HAS BEEN DISCUSSED IN CONGRESS, DEBATE HAS BEEN POSTPONED UNTIL NEXT MONDAY.

THE GOVERNMENT SAID IT DOES NOT OPPOSE THE APPOINTMENT OF A COMMISSION. "HOWEVER, WE CANNOT YIELD TO AN OPPOSITION WHIM," GOVERNMENT-PAY CONGRESSMEN SAID.

EL NACIONAL HAS PUBLISHED A LIST OF 47 PEOPLE KILLED AND 50 PEOPLE MISSING. THE NEWSPAPER CLAIMS THAT AT LEAST 100 SOLDIERS "SEPARATED THE MEN AND WOMEN AND KILLED THE MEN INSIDE THE CHURCH."

DEV-MUC3-0060 (NOSC)

LIMA, 25 JAN 89 (TELAM-ANSA) -- [TEXT] THE PRO-MAOIST SHINING PATH TERRORIST ORGANIZATION PERPETRATED ONE OF ITS MOST SERIOUS ATTACKS IN RECENT MEMORY IN THE TOWN OF ANDAHUA, LOCATED IN THE SOUTHERN AREQUIPA DEPARTMENT. DURING THIS ATTACK, THE TERRORISTS SET MOST OF THE CITY'S PUBLIC BUILDINGS ON FIRE. THEY FAILED, HOWEVER, TO BRING LOCAL GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS BEFORE THEIR "KANGAROO COURT" BECAUSE THE OFFICIALS WERE ALERTED AND FLED BEFORE THE TERRORISTS ARRIVED.

POLICE AUTHORITIES REPORTED TODAY IN LIMA THAT YESTERDAY HEAVILY-ARMED SHINING PATH TERRORISTS OVERPOWERED ANDAHUA RESIDENTS AND BURNED THE OFFICES OF THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ENTERPRISE, THE AGRARIAN BANK, THE NATIONAL BANK, AND HEALTH MINISTRY OFFICES. ALTHOUGH THE BUILDINGS WERE BURNED TO THE GROUND, NO ONE WAS INJURED.

THE TERRORISTS ATTEMPTED TO BRING THE LOCAL AUTHORITIES BEFORE A KANGAROO COURT TO IMPLEMENT WHAT THEY CALL "PEOPLE'S JUSTICE," THE PUBLIC EXECUTION OF THESE AUTHORITIES IN THE PRESENCE OF THE PEOPLE. THE LOCAL AUTHORITIES, HOWEVER, HAD ALREADY FLED.

BEFORE LEAVING THE CITY, THE TERRORISTS BLOCKED AND DESTROYED SEVERAL SEGMENTS OF THE ROAD LINKING ANDAHUA WITH AREQUIPA AND OTHER ADJACENT TOWNS IN ORDER TO PREVENT LOCAL RESIDENTS FROM FOLLOWING THEM.

DEV-MUC3-0061 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 FEB 89 -- [REPORT] [MARCO ANTONIO GUEVARA] [TEXT] ON A NATIONAL RADIO AND TELEVISION NETWORK LAST NIGHT, THE GOVERNMENT REVEALED THE RESULTS OF A NUMBER OF INVESTIGATIONS ON THE MURDER OF MSGR ARNULFO ROMERO; HOWEVER, THE ATTORNEY GENERAL SAID AT NOON TODAY ONLY THE FOURTH CRIMINAL COURT JUDGE CAN DETERMINE WHETHER THE EVIDENCE AGAINST ANY PERSON IS LEGAL:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIAL ALVARADO] SINCE I DO NOT KNOW THEIR CONTENT, I CANNOT GIVE AN OPINION ON THE MATTER. HOWEVER, IF FROM THOSE RECORDS OR THE VIDEO ONE CAN DETERMINE THERE IS SUFFICIENT EVIDENCE TO SOLVE THE CRIME COMMITTED AGAINST MSGR ROMERO, I WILL UNQUESTIONABLY REQUEST THAT EVIDENCE AND SUBMIT IT IMMEDIATELY TO THE FOURTH CRIMINAL COURT. I BELIEVE EVIDENCE SHOULD NOT BE USED TO SPECULATE OR SHOULD NOT BE PUBLICLY PROMOTED. IF PERTINENT EVIDENCE EXISTS, IT MUST BE SUBMITTED TO THE CORRESPONDING JUDGE, WHO IS THE EXCLUSIVE LEGAL AUTHORITY TO DEAL WITH IT AND, AFTER AN EXHAUSTIVE ANALYSIS, DETERMINE THE VALIDITY OF THE EVIDENCE. [END RECORDING]

NEVERTHELESS, MSGR ROMERO'S CASE HAS BEGUN TO HAVE THE ELEMENTS IT HAD LACKED FOR MORE THAN 8 YEARS. THE LEGAL EVIDENCE MUST CONTAIN A SERIES OF CONDITIONS, AND ONLY THE JUDGE CAN DETERMINE WHETHER THEY HAVE VALUE OR NOT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIAL ALVARADO] THE VIDEO FOR EXAMPLE IS NOT EVIDENCE. THE CONTENTS OF THE VIDEO MUST BE REAFFIRMED BY THE PERSONS WHO IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER PARTICIPATED IN THE PREPARATION, AND THE ACCURACY OF THE CONTENTS NARRATED IN THAT VIDEO MUST BE LEGALLY DETERMINED. [END RECORDING]

GARCIA ALVARADO ADDED THAT THE FOURTH CRIMINAL COURT JUDGE DECIDED A FEW HOURS AGO TO SUMMON FORMER ATTORNEY ROBERTO GIRON FLORES AND THE OFFICIALS JULIO ALFREDO SAMAYOA AND GERARDO LE CHEVALIER TO GIVE THE EVIDENCE THEY CLAIM TO HAVE ON THE CASE. BECAUSE THEY ARE OFFICIALS, THE LATTER TWO MUST MAKE SWORN STATEMENTS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIAL ALVARADO] THE JUDGE IN CHARGE OF THE CASE HAS ISSUED RESOLUTIONS ORDERING THE SUMMONS OF IVON FLORES AND SWORN STATEMENTS FROM THE TWO OFFICIALS MENTIONED. [END RECORDING]

THESE NEW RESOLUTIONS OF THE FOURTH CRIMINAL COURT JUDGE ON MSGR ROMERO'S CASE WERE ISSUED AT THE REQUEST OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE, WHICH DEMONSTRATES, THE ATTORNEY GENERAL SAID, THAT HE IS NOT AN UNDERTAKER OF TRIALS, MUCH LESS OF PEOPLE.

VICE PRESIDENT ANTONIO CASTILLO CLARAMOUNT SAID THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE HAS THE MORAL OBLIGATION TO PUNISH THE MURDERERS OF MSGR ROMERO, INCLUDING MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON. THE VICE PRESIDENT ALSO INSISTED THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY HAS A RESPONSIBILITY TO SEE THAT THOSE GUILTY OF THE MURDER OF MSGR ROMERO BE PUNISHED. HOWEVER, HE STRESSED THE SUPREME COURT MUST ACT. HE SAID THE INVESTIGATION MUST CONTINUE AND GATHER ALL THE EVIDENCE TO SOLVE THIS CASE, WHICH OCCURRED IN MARCH 1980.

DEV-MUC3-0062 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] JUSTICE MINISTER JULIO ALFREDO SAMAYOA SAID TODAY ALL THE EVIDENCE GATHERED BY THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS COMMISSION DEMONSTRATES THAT DR ANTONIO REGALADO WAS THE PERPETRATOR OF THE MURDER OF MSGR ROMERO.

IN HIS CAPACITY AS CHAIRMAN OF THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS COMMISSION, DR JULIO ALFREDO SAMAYOA REPORTED TODAY IN DETAIL ON THE MURDER OF MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO. DR SAMAYOA SAID TO CLARIFY THE CASE, THE COMMISSION HAS CONDUCTED 238 MEETINGS, OVER 100 INQUIRIES, AND 21 DEPOSITIONS. HE ADDED THAT THE INVESTIGATION WAS CARRIED OUT UNDER THE NAME OF "OPERATION PINEAPPLE" AND THAT IT WAS CONCLUDED THAT MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON WAS THE MASTERMIND AND DR ANTONIO REGALADO WAS THE PERPETRATOR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SAMAYOA] THERE IS NO DOUBT. ALL THE INVESTIGATIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE COMMISSION POINT TO MAJ ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON AS THE MASTERMIND. THIS HAS TO BE PROVEN IN COURT. HOWEVER, HE HAS PARLIAMENTARY IMMUNITY; HE CANNOT BE BROUGHT TO COURT. THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA] HAS THE MAJORITY IN THE NATIONAL ASSEMBLY, AND ARENA IS NOT GOING TO PERMIT A DECLARATION THAT WILL BRING HIS CASE TO COURT. [END RECORDING]

DR SAMAYOA ALSO SAID HE IS WILLING TO PRESENT ALL THE EVIDENCE HE HAS ON THE CASE. HOWEVER, HE SAID HE DID NOT TRUST THE BEHAVIOR OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL OF THE REPUBLIC:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SAMAYOA] WE WILL PRESENT THE EVIDENCE. I THINK THEY ARE GOING TO BE SORRY THEY MADE THAT REQUEST, BECAUSE MANY PERSONS ARE INVOLVED. SINCE THEIR PARTICIPATION HAS NOT YET BEEN PROVEN, THESE NAMES HAVE NOT YET BEEN RELEASED. HOWEVER, WHEN WE PRESENT THE ENTIRE DOSSIER TO THE COURTS, THESE NAMES ARE GOING TO COME UP. THEN SOME WILL JUDGE AND DECIDE IF THEY PARTICIPATED OR NOT. BUT THEIR NAMES ARE THERE, AS ARE THEIR ACTIVITIES AND THEIR RELATIONSHIPS TO THE DEATH SQUADS. MANY PERSONS WHO ARE MENTIONED ARE APPARENTLY RESPECTABLE, AND I MEAN RESPECTABLE IN QUOTES. [END RECORDING]

THE ASSASSINATION OF MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO TOOK PLACE ON 24 MARCH 1980; ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL, THE INVESTIGATIONS HAVE TAKEN 9 YEARS BECAUSE MANY PERSONS CONSIDERED KEY WITNESSES HAVE DIED SINCE THE TIME OF THE MURDER. HOWEVER, HE ADDED, WITH THE COOPERATION OF THE FBI AS WELL AS SOME CENTRAL AMERICAN INVESTIGATION ORGANIZATIONS, THE CASE HAS BEEN CLARIFIED, WHICH MIGHT LEAD TO THE IMPRISONMENT OF MAJ D'AUBUISSON ONCE HE LOSES HIS PARLIAMENTARY IMMUNITY.

DEV-MUC3-0063 (NOSC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 6 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] THE PUBLIC SECURITY FORCES (FUSEP) HAVE DECLARED A STATE OF MAXIMUM ALERT THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY IN VIEW OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUBVERSIVE ATTACKS ON POLICE STATIONS, A SPOKESMAN FOR THAT INSTITUTION HAS REPORTED.

THE ALERT STATUS HAS BEEN IN EFFECT SINCE LAST THURSDAY, WHEN FUSEP STAFF COMMANDER COLONEL CRISTOBAL SIMON ROMERRO SENT NOTICE TO COMMANDERS AND REGIONAL AND SUBREGIONAL POSTS ALERTING THEM ABOUT THE DANGER OF LEFTIST ATTACKS.

A POLICE SPOKESMAN HAS SAID THE FUSEP HAS INTELLIGENCE INFORMATION ON LEFTIST PLANS TO ATTACK POLICE STATIONS.

THE SOURCE REPORTED THAT A STATE OF MAXIMUM ALERT WILL BE IN EFFECT UNTIL FURTHER NOTICE, ADDING THAT THE POLICE HAVE STRATEGIC PLANS TO RESPOND TO ANY ATTACKS.

THERE IS NO REPORT ON WHETHER OR NOT THE ARMY IS ALSO ON A STATE OF ALERT. YESTERDAY, PEOPLE WERE ABLE TO MOVE ABOUT AS USUAL IN SOUTHERN TEGUCIGALPA, WHERE SOME ARMY COMBAT UNITS ARE HEADQUARTERED.

THE POLICE DEPARTMENT DECLARED THE STATE OF ALERT AS A RESULT OF A WAVE OF VIOLENCE THAT BEGAN WITH THE KILLING OF THREE PEOPLE IN JANUARY.

NICARAGUAN CONTRA COMMANDER MANUEL ADAN RUGAMA, ALIAS AURELIANO, WAS SHOT TO DEATH IN NORTHERN TEGUCIGALPA ON 7 JANUARY, AND ATTORNEY CARLOS LORENZANA, WHO DEFENDED JUAN RAMON MATTA IN HONDURAS, WAS SHOT TO DEATH NEAR HIS RESIDENCE IN THE MODELO NEIGHBORHOOD BY UNIDENTIFIED ASSAILANTS. NONE OF THESE CRIMES HAS BEEN SOLVED BY THE POLICE.

ON 25 JANUARY, ALLEGED COMMANDOS OF THE "CINCHONERO" PEOPLE'S LIBERATION FRONT MACHINEGUNNED RETIRED GENERAL GUSTAVO ALVAREZ MARTINEZ, A FORMER ARMED FORCES COMMANDER. ALVAREZ MARTINEZ WAS KILLED NEAR HIS RESIDENCE IN TEGUCIGALPA'S FLORENCIA DEL ESTE NEIGHBORHOOD. THE FOLLOWING SUNDAY THE RESIDENCE OF THE NICARAGUAN AMBASSADOR IN THIS CAPITAL WAS ATTACKED.

THIS PAST WEDNESDAY UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE FIRED ON A U.S. MILITARY CONVOY IN YORO DEPARTMENT. MILITARY SOURCES HAVE REPORTED THAT SPECIAL TROOPS ARE COMBING THE AREA.

DEV-MUC3-0069 (NOSC)

LIMA, 2 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] INTERIOR MINISTER JUAN SORIA DIAZ HAS DENIED THAT TWO DEA [DRUG ENFORCEMENT AGENCY] HELICOPTERS HAVE BEEN DOWNED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN TINGO MARIA.

THE INTERIOR MINISTER ALSO SAID THAT SATISFACTORY PROGRESS IS BEING MADE IN FORMING A CIVILIAN FRONT TO FIGHT SUBVERSION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SORIA] A FAIRLY LARGE ACTIVITY HAS BEEN REPORTED IN THE HUALLAGA AREA. DRUG TRAFFICKING HAS BEEN REPRESSED. I HAVE BEEN INFORMED THAT SOME ARRESTS HAVE REPORTEDLY BEEN MADE. A LARGE QUANTITY OF DRUGS HAS BEEN SEIZED, AND SOME PEOPLE HAVE REPORTEDLY BEEN INJURED IN THE AREA. I AM AWAITING A FINAL REPORT.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE TWO HELICOPTERS THAT HAVE REPORTEDLY BEEN DOWNED BY TERRORISTS IN THE ALTO HUALLAGAS AREA, SIR?

[SORIA] WELL, I DO NOT KNOW WHERE THIS REPORT ORIGINATED. I CAN ASSURE YOU THAT THE DEA HELICOPTERS THAT ARE COOPERATING WITH THE POLICE FORCES HAVE NOT SUFFERED ANY DAMAGE.

[REPORTER] HAVE THE HELICOPTERS BEEN DOWNED?

[SORIA] THEY HAVE NOT BEEN DOWNED. NO HELICOPTER HAS BEEN DOWNED. THE HELICOPTERS HAVE NOT BEEN INVOLVED IN ANY TYPE OF INCIDENT. I DO NOT KNOW WHERE YOU GOT THAT REPORT.

[REPORTER] IS IT TRUE THAT SOME POLICEMEN ARE DESERTING IN SOME AREAS OF CONFLICT IN THE COUNTRY, MINISTER?

[SORIA] NOT THAT I KNOW OF. I DO NOT KNOW WHERE YOU GOT THAT REPORT.

[REPORTER] MINISTER, IN THE PAST FEW DAYS IT HAS BEEN ANNOUNCED THAT THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY COULD BE IN JEOPARDY. HAVE ANY PRECAUTIONARY MEASURES BEEN TAKEN?

[SORIA] PRECAUTIONARY MEASURES HAVE BEEN TAKEN. THE ENTIRE ELECTORAL TIMETABLE IS BEING IMPLEMENTED THROUGH THE EFFORTS OF THE ARMED FORCES, WHICH ARE CONSTITUTIONALLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ELECTIONS.

[REPORTER] WOULD THE VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY PROMPT THE STATE OF SIEGE AT A NATIONAL LEVEL?

[SORIA] NO. I BELIEVE THAT THE VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY REMAINS UNDER CONTROL AT A NATIONAL LEVEL. IT HAS NOT CHANGED MUCH SINCE LAST YEAR. WE ARE CONTINUING TO IMPLEMENT ALL THE APPROPRIATE MEASURES TO GUARANTEE PUBLIC SECURITY.

[REPORTER] MINISTER, THE FORMATION OF A CIVILIAN FRONT TO FIGHT SUBVERSION HAS BEEN MENTIONED. IT HAS BEEN SAID THAT AN ATTEMPT IS ALREADY BEING MADE IN THIS REGARD. WHAT PROGRESS HAS BEEN MADE?

[SORIA] WELL, THE PRIME MINISTER HAS MADE SEVERAL CALLS IN THE NAME OF THE GOVERNMENT, STATING THAT WE MUST UNITE TO FIGHT SUBVERSION. NO ONE CAN REMAIN NEUTRAL CONCERNING SUBVERSION BECAUSE SOONER OR LATER ALL OF US WILL BE AFFECTED.

THE PERUVIAN COMMUNITIES ARE BECOMING INCREASINGLY AWARE OF THIS FACT. THEY ARE ALREADY DEFENDING THEMSELVES, AND WE ARE HELPING THEM TO DEFEND THEMSELVES.

[REPORTER, INTERRUPTING] IS EVERY MINISTRY WORKING TO THIS EFFECT?

[SORIA] EVERY MINISTRY IS WORKING TO THIS EFFECT, AND WE ARE SUPLYING ALL THE COMMUNITIES THAT WANT TO COOPERATE IN DEFENDING THEMSELVES FROM SUBVERSION WITH THE APPROPRIATE MEANS AND ORGANIZATIONS. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0070 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 MAR 89 (AFP) -- [REPORT] [AFP SPECIAL CORRESPONDENT ARTURO GUDINO] [TEXT] ALFREDO CRISTIANI, PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF THE SALVADORAN NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA), WARNED TODAY THAT HE IS NOT WILLING TO NEGOTIATE WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) IF HE WINS THE UPCOMING 19 MARCH PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS.

CRISTIANI SAID: "WE ARE WILLING TO TALK BUT NOT TO NEGOTIATE ANY PLATFORM." CRISTIANI WARNED THAT IF THE REBELS DO NOT LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND JOIN THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL LIFE, "THE BEST THING FOR THEM TO DO IS TO LEAVE FOR NICARAGUA OR CUBA."

AS SOMEONE WHO IS CONSIDERED CERTAIN TO BECOME THE NEXT SALVADORAN PRESIDENT, CRISTIANI RECEIVED AN OVATION FROM A CHEERING CROWD THAT GATHERED AT LA LIBERTAD SQUARE IN SAN SALVADOR, WHERE ARENA HELD ITS LAST MAJOR DEMONSTRATION IN SAN SALVADOR.

CRISTIANI ADDED: "WE WILL NEVER LET THEM ATTAIN POWER BY MEANS OF RIFLES."

THE ARENA CANDIDATE, WHO IS FAVORED TO WIN THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS, ASSERTED THAT ONCE HE ATTAINS POWER, HE WILL GIVE FULL SUPPORT TO THE ARMY AND THE SECURITY FORCES "SO THEY CAN PUT AN END TO THE VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY."

CRISTIANI, A WEALTHY BUSINESSMAN, ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT IF HE WINS THE ELECTIONS HE WILL PUT AN END TO THE NATIONALIZATION OF THE BANKING SECTOR AND FOREIGN TRADE ACTIVITIES, THE MAIN PILLARS OF A PLAN WHOSE IMPLEMENTATION BEGAN AFTER THE COUNTRY'S 1979 COUP D'ETAT. PRESIDENT DUARTE KEPT THIS PLAN ALIVE AND THE AGRARIAN REFORM PROGRAM INTACT DURING HIS PRESIDENTIAL TERM.

"WE WILL DO AWAY WITH INCAFE (NATIONAL COFFEE INSTITUTE), WHICH HAS STOLEN JOBS FROM HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF SALVADORAN PRODUCERS," THE ARENA LEADER SAID, ADDING: "WE DO NOT WANT A BANKING OR A BUSINESS GOVERNMENT."

CRISTIANI, HOWEVER, DID NOT MENTION THE CURRENT AGRARIAN REFORM, THROUGH WHICH YOUNG MILITARY MEN WHO LED THE 1979 COUP D'ETAT INTENDED TO BREAK THE BACK OF THE OLIGARCHY.

THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS, MOSTLY FROM THE UPPER AND MIDDLE CLASSES, MARCHED ALONG THE MAIN SAN SALVADOR STREETS TODAY TO LA LIBERTAD SQUARE, WHICH WAS FILLED WITH ARENA POSTERS AND RED, WHITE, AND BLUE ARENA FLAGS.

ARENA'S CRISTIANI SAID: "WE WILL ELIMINATE THE UNEMPLOYMENT PROBLEM. WE WILL BUILD ROADS AND INCREASE PRODUCTION. WE WILL PROVIDE THE MOST NEEDY WITH HEALTH, EDUCATION, AND ALL OTHER SERVICES."

MEANWHILE, THOUSANDS OF YOUTHS CHEERED FOR CRISTIANI AND DANCED IN LA LIBERTAD SQUARE TO SONGS RIDICULING ARENA'S MAIN OPPOSITION IN THE ELECTIONS, THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC], WHICH IS CURRENTLY IN POWER.

ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON, ARENA FOUNDER AND FORMER PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, DENOUNCED THE UNITED STATES, WHICH HE ACCUSED OF SPONSORING THE PDC.

D'AUBUISSON, WHOM THE PDC HAS ACCUSED OF BEING THE "BRAINS BEHIND" THE MARCH 1980 ASSASSINATION OF MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO, SAID: "WHETHER THE WHITE BLONDS [CHELES] LIKE IT OR NOT, WE WILL WIN THE ELECTIONS 10 YEARS AFTER THE 1979 FATAL COUP D'ETAT."

D'AUBUISSON HARSHLY ATTACKED PRESIDENT DUARTE, WHO IS SUFFERING FROM TERMINAL CANCER, AND REFERRED TO HIM AS "THE CRAZY AND WORN OUT DUARTE."

CRISTIANI IS WILLING TO TALK WITH THE FMLN, BUT ONLY WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE CONSTITUTION AND THE LAW. D'AUBUISSON SAID: "WE WILL GIVE THEM TIME TO JOIN THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC LIFE, LITTLE BY LITTLE."

ARENA'S MEETING, WHICH ACCORDING TO ITS ORGANIZERS DREW A CROWD OF 40,000 SUPPORTERS, ENDED WITHOUT INCIDENT TONIGHT.

DEV-MUC3-0071 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 MAR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS TODAY THREATENED TO MURDER INDIVIDUALS INVOLVED IN THE 19 MARCH PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS IF THEY DO NOT RESIGN FROM THEIR POSTS.

"ALL INDIVIDUALS AND INSTITUTIONS INVOLVED IN THE 19 MARCH ELECTORAL FARCE WILL BE MERCILESSLY PUNISHED BY THE PEOPLE'S JUSTICE FOR CONTRIBUTING TO THE CONTINUATION OF THE WAR," THE GUERRILLAS WARNED TODAY IN A MESSAGE BROADCAST BY RADIO VENCEREMOS, THEIR OFFICIAL RADIO STATION.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) IS OPPOSED TO THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS AND HAS ASKED THE PEOPLE NOT TO VOTE OR TO DESTROY THEIR BALLOTS.

THE GUERRILLA THREAT IS AIMED AT MEMBERS OF THE DEPARTMENTAL AND MUNICIPAL BALLOT-RECEIVING BOARDS, MAYORS, JUDGES, PARTY DIRECTORATES, AND ELECTORAL COLLEGE OFFICIALS.

THE WARNING ALSO APPLIES TO THE OWNERS OF VEHICLES THAT OPERATE DURING AN IDEFINITE TRANSPORTATION STRIKE THE FMLN IS SCHEDULED TO INITIATE ON 16 MARCH AT 0000.

SWEARING IN APPROXIMATELY 20 BALLOT-RECEIVING BOARDS IN SAN SALVADOR, RICARDO PERDOMO, PRESIDENT OF THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL, SAID THE ARMED FORCES AND THE COUNCIL ARE PREPARED TO GUARANTEE NORMAL ELECTIONS.

"WE WERE EXPECTING THIS. WE KNOW THE GUERRILLAS WILL IMPLEMENT ALL TYPES OF BOYCOTTS TO HINDER THE ELECTIONS. NEVERTHELESS, WE ARE IN A POSITION TO GUARANTEE THE ELECTIONS," PERDOMO REITERATED.

MILITARY UNITS HAVE BEEN DEPLOYED SINCE YESTERDAY IN CITIES IN THE EASTERN DEPARTMENTS OF MORAZAN, SAN MIGUEL, USULUTAN, AND LA UNION, WHERE THE REBELS PERSISTENTLY SABOTAGE THE ELECTRICAL SYSTEM.

THE FMLN HAS ANNOUNCED IT WILL INTENSIFY ITS "INSURRECTIONAL ACTIONS" THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, WHICH COULD AFFECT THE NATION'S ELECTRICAL AND TELEPHONE SYSTEMS ON ELECTION DAY.

THE GUERRILLAS ARE OPPOSED TO THE ELECTIONS BECAUSE THEY FEEL THEY ARE "PART OF THE COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN AND A MEANS OF LEGITIMIZING THE CONTINUATION OF WAR, HUNGER, AND POVERTY."

"THOSE WHO COOPERATE WITH THE ELECTORAL FARCE WILL BE THROWN OUT OF THEIR HOMES, EXECUTED, AND THEIR PROPERTIES WILL BE SABOTAGED BEFORE, DURING, AND AFTER THE ELECTIONS," THE REBELS SAID.

THE GUERRILLAS SENT MESSAGES ON SATURDAY NIGHT TO THE MAYORS AND MUNICIPAL COUNCILS OF EIGHT TOWNS IN LA UNION DEPARTMENT, DEMANDING THAT THEY RESIGN OR THE FMLN WILL "BRING TO BEAR" AGAINST THEM "THE ENTIRE WEIGHT OF POPULAR JUSTICE."

DEV-MUC3-0072 (NOSC)

SAN SALVADOR, 7 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON YESTERDAY STATED: "I HAVE WITHSTOOD THE LOWEST SLANDER FOR 8 YEARS. GOD ALMIGHTY AND MY CONSCIENCE KNOW I HAD NOTHING TO DO WITH THAT REPUDIATED MURDER.

"EVERY TIME THERE ARE ELECTIONS, WE HEAR THE SAME RUMORS THAT THERE IS EVIDENCE ABOUT MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO'S CASE AND THAT IT WILL BE PRESENTED. THUS, A GREAT SHOW IS PRESENTED, BUT ONCE THE ELECTIONS ARE OVER NO ONE REMEMBERS THAT MARTYR OF THE CHURCH.

"DUARTE'S GOVERNMENT, SUPPORTED BY THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY, PDC, RESORTS TO VILE DEFAMATION, SLANDER, AND LIES AGAINST ITS POLITICAL OPPONENTS BECAUSE IT CANNOT HIDE ITS CORRUPTION."

THIS STATEMENT WAS ISSUED BY THE NATIONAL REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE, ARENA, DEPUTY TO REJECT THE ANNOUNCEMENT ISSUED BY THE GOVERNMENT, "IN A NATIONAL RADIO AND TELEVISION NETWORK," THAT IMPLICATED D'AUBUISSON "IN MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO'S DEATH."

"I AM SORRY I DID NOT SEE THE BROADCAST, BUT OTHERS HAVE COMMENTED ON IT. I CAN VERY WELL IMAGINE ALL THE DESPICABLE THINGS THAT WERE IRRESPONSIBLY SAID TO TWIST THE TRUTH SO THE PDC COULD AGAIN USE MSGR ROMERO'S DEATH AS AN ELECTION ISSUE. IT IS ALL PART OF THE PDC'S PROPAGANDA, BUT THE TRUTH WILL ALWAYS PREVAIL," D'AUBUISSON SAID.

"THE MOST REPREHENSIBLE THING IS THAT THE DUARTE ADMINISTRATION USES RADIO AND TELEVISION STATIONS, OPENLY ABUSING ITS AUTHORITY, TO SLANDER ME--SIMPLY BECAUSE I AM THE PDC'S POLITICAL ADVERSARY, AND BECAUSE THE PDC HAS NO EXCUSE TO JUSTIFY THE CRISIS THAT HAS BEEN CAUSED BY ITS CORRUPTION."

D'AUBUISSON ADDED: THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATS' "LIE" IS AIMED AT DECEIVING SALVADORAN CATHOLICS. THAT IS DESPICABLE AND UNSPEAKABLE, BECAUSE THEY ARE INSULTING MSGR ROMERO'S MEMORY.

THE PDC HAS GOVERNED THE COUNTRY FOR 8 YEARS. THE PDC CONTROLLED THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE WHEN MSGR ROMERO WAS KILLED. THE CRUCIAL QUESTION IS: WHY WEREN'T THE NECESSARY MEASURES TAKEN TO CLARIFY THE CASE AT THE TIME? WHY DOES THE GOVERNMENT CLAIM IT HAS THE EVIDENCE YET FAILS TO PRESENT IT? AH, BECAUSE THIS WOULD END THE GOVERNMENT'S POLITICAL GAME OF SAYING THAT IT IS INVESTIGATING MSGR ROMERO'S DEATH! THIS ENTIRE ATTITUDE IS REPREHENSIBLE, D'AUBUISSON STATED.

HE ASSERTED: I AM AWARE OF THE PDC'S INCREDIBLE PLOT TO SLANDER ME, BUT THE PDC ONLY SAYS WHAT IS CONVENIENT. IT IS A DIRTY GAME BUT GOD IS MY WITNESS; MY CONSCIENCE IS CLEAR. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE KNOW MY GREAT CRIME HAS BEEN TO STRUGGLE AGAINST THE MARXIST-LENINISTS. THE PDC CANNOT FORGIVE ME FOR THIS BECAUSE THEY ARE CLOSELY LINKED WITH THOSE WHO "ARE GREEN ON THE OUTSIDE [REFERENCE TO THE PDC'S PARTY COLORS] BUT RED ON THE INSIDE." HOWEVER, I WILL CONTINUE STRUGGLING LIKE A GOOD SALVADORAN SO THE "TURNCOATS" DO NOT BETRAY US, AS WAS THE CASE IN NICARAGUA, MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON ARRIETA EMPHASIZED.

DEV-MUC3-0074 (NOSC)

CLANDESTINE, 13 MAR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, MUCH ATTENTION: THE FOLLOWING IS A CALL TO THOSE WHO ARE HELPING TO ORGANIZE THE ELECTIONS. MUCH ATTENTION:

WE CALL ON ALL THOSE PEOPLE WHO ARE HELPING TO ORGANIZE THE ELECTIONS. WE DEMAND THAT THEY PUBLICLY RESIGN FROM THEIR POSTS. WE REPEAT: WE CALL ON ALL THOSE PEOPLE WHO ARE HELPING TO ORGANIZE THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS AND DEMAND THAT THEY PUBLICLY RESIGN. THE 19 MARCH ELECTION BEING ORGANIZED BY THE PDC AND ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] IS PART OF THE MILITARY COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN AIMED AT LEGITIMIZING REPRESSION, THE BOMBING OF CIVILIANS, AND THE HUNGER AND POVERTY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. IN LIGHT OF THE ABOVE, THESE PEOPLE MUST IMMEDIATELY RESIGN. AFTER THEY HAVE DONE THIS, THEY WILL NO LONGER BE CONSIDERED BY OUR PEOPLE AS BEING PART OF THE MILITARY COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN AND THEY WILL BE ABLE TO LIVE IN THEIR HOMES WITHOUT ANY PROBLEMS.

ARENA AND THE PDC REFUSED TO ACCEPT OUR PEACE PROPOSAL TO MAKE THE ELECTIONS A TOOL FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE WAR. THEREFORE, THE FEELING OF THE MAJORITY OF OUR PEOPLE IS ONE OF REJECTION OF THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS. THIS FEELING REQUIRES THAT EVERYONE INVOLVED IN ORGANIZING THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS PUBLICLY RESIGN AND JOIN THE PEOPLE IN THEIR SEARCH FOR PEACE THROUGH DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION AND IN DEFEATING THE ELECTORAL FARCE AIMED AT PERPETUATING THE WAR.

DEV-MUC3-0075 (NOSC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 7 FEB 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] A BOMB BLAST DAMAGED A TELEPHONE OFFICE TODAY IN THE NORTHERN CITY OF SAN PEDRO SULA. A LEFTIST GROUP, WHICH CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR AN ATTACK ON A U.S. MILITARY CONVOY LAST WEEK CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS ATTACK.

THE BOMB, MADE UP OF DYNAMITE AND A FUSE, EXPLODED JUST BEFORE DAWN IN THE HONDUTEL [HONDURAN TELECOMMUNICATIONS ENTERPRISE] OFFICE IN SAN PEDRO SULA, 190 KM NORTH OF THIS CAPITAL.

THE EXPLOSION DAMAGED FURNITURE, FOUR TELEPHONES, AND SHATTERED WINDOWS, BUT NOBODY WAS INJURED.

LEAFLETS FOUND IN THE RUBBLE STATED THAT A LEFTIST GROUP WAS RESPONSIBLE BOTH FOR THE BOMB AS WELL AS THE ATTACK ON A U.S. MILITARY CONVOY LAST WEEK IN THE HONDURAN NORTHERN MOUNTAIN REGION.

ALTHOUGH NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED, ONE OF THE VEHICLES IN THE U.S. CONVOY WAS HIT BY TWO BULLETS. UNTIL TODAY NOBODY HAD CLAIMED CREDIT FOR THAT ATTACK.

"THE JACOBO CARCOMO COMMAND OF THE MORAZANIST PATRIOTIC FRONT [FPM] ATTACKED A U.S. CONVOY WITH M-16 RIFLE-FIRE," THE LEAFLETS READ. CARCOMO WAS A HONDURAN LEFT-WING AUTHOR AT THE BEGINNING OF THE 20TH CENTURY.

THE FPM, NAMED AFTER A CENTRAL AMERICAN LEADER OF THE LAST CENTURY, HAS CLAIMED CREDIT FOR SEVERAL GUERRILLA ATTACKS IN THE PAST.

HONDURAS HAS BEEN GRIPPED BY A WAVE OF VIOLENCE THIS YEAR, INCLUDING THE ASSASSINATIONS OF A FORMER ARMED FORCES COMMANDER, A COMMANDER OF THE ANTI-SANDINIST REBELS (SUPPORTED BY THE UNITED STATES), AND A LAWYER OF AN ALLEGED DRUG TRAFFICKING TSAR.

PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA HAS CALLED FOR NATIONAL DIALOGUE STARTING THIS WEEK WITH THE GOVERNMENT, THE OPPOSITION PARTIES, LABOR UNIONS, BUSINESSMEN, AND OTHER GROUPS TO TRY TO CURB THE SUDDEN SURGE OF VIOLENCE.

HONDURAS, A CLOSE U.S. ALLY, HAS TRADITIONALLY BEEN A PEACEFUL COUNTRY IN A REGION STRICKEN BY INTERNAL CONFLICTS.

DEV-MUC3-0077 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 7 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN INDUSTRIALIST NORMAL ECHEVARRIA AND U.S. BUSINESSMAN MICHAEL REYFF, KIDNAPPED 11 DAYS AGO IN MEDELLIN, WERE RESCUED TODAY. THE POLICE OPERATION TOOK PLACE ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT'S CAPITAL. NO RANSOM WAS PAID. TWO OF THE KIDNAPPERS WERE KILLED, BUT THE OTHERS MANAGED TO ESCAPE. NEVERTHELESS, THERE IS EVIDENCE THAT COULD LEAD TO THEIR ARREST.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] COLONEL OTALORA, ASSISTANT COMMANDER OF THE MEDELLIN METROPOLITAN POLICE, HOW WERE NORMAL ECHEVARRIA AND U.S. CITIZEN MICHAEL REYFF RESCUED?

[OTALORA] AT 1700, MEDELLIN METROPOLITAN POLICE MEMBERS WERE ABLE TO RESCUE NORMAL ECHEVARRIA AND MICHAEL REYFF; THEY ARE SAFE AND SOUND. ONCE AGAIN WE THANK THE PEOPLE FOR THEIR TIMELY COOPERATION. [WORDS INDISTINCT] LOCAL BUSINESSMEN LENT US THEIR HELICOPTERS TO SEARCH FOR AND ARREST THE KIDNAPPERS. UNFORTUNATELY IT QUICKLY BECAME DARK AND WE COULD NOT LOCATE THE KIDNAPPERS. HOWEVER, WE HAVE IDENTIFIED THEM AND HOPE TO ARREST THEM IN A FEW HOURS.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE CONDITION OF THE TWO HOSTAGES?

[OTALRA] NORMAL ECHEVARRIA IS PERFECTLY ALL RIGHT. HE WILL PROBABLY MEET WITH YOU IN A FEW MINUTES. HE IS VERY HAPPY TO SEE HIS FAMILY. WE ARE PLEASED WITH THE POSITIVE RESULTS OF THIS OPERATION, AND THE NATIONAL POLICE FEEL PROUD. THE PEOPLE OF ANTIOQUIA HAVE BEEN BROUGHT CLOSER TO THEIR POLICE.

[REPORTER] WAS IT NECESSARY TO PAY A RANSOM? HAD THE FAMILY BEEN ASKED TO PAY A RANSOM?

[OTALORA] NO, NO RANSOM WAS PAID. MR ECHEVARRIA WILL TELL YOU THAT LATER. THEY ARE PERFECTLY SAFE AND SOUND.

[REPORTER] WHERE WERE THEY KEPT? CAN YOU DESCRIBE IT?

[OTALORA] NO, I CANNOT GIVE YOU DETAILS RIGHT NOW. WE WILL PROBABLY ISSUE THAT INFORMATION LATER. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0081 (NOSC)

SANTIAGO, 8 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] THE BODY OF LIEUTENANT JOSE LUIS CANALES WAS REMOVED SHORTLY AFTER 1400 THIS AFTERNOON. HE WAS MURDERED BY FOUR UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE ON A SOCCER FIELD AT CARAMPANGUE AND ALBORADA STREETS, IN THE SANTIAGO NEIGHBORHOOD OF QUILCURA. THE MURDERERS ARE STILL AT LARGE.

THE PROSECUTOR OF THE 5TH MILITARY COURT, RODRIGO SANDOVAL, WAS AT THE SCENE. HE WILL INVESTIGATE THIS ATTACK, IN WHICH A 2D CORPORAL OF THE CARABINEROS WAS ALSO KILLED.

CARABINEROS HAVE REPORTED THAT THE VEHICLE USED BY THE MURDERERS TO ESCAPE WAS FOUND AT 82 OR 81 BARROS LUCO STREET, IN LA CISTERNA NEIGHBORHOOD.

EYEWITNESSES REPORTED THAT THREE MEN AND A DARK-HAIRED GIRL, WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE ATTACK GOT OUT OF THE CAR, A WHITE HONDA ACCORD. THE UNIFORMED POLICE REPORTED THAT AFTER FINDING THE CAR, THEY RAIDED A HOUSE THAT TURNED OUT TO BE A HIDEOUT OF THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT. THE HOUSE IS AT 9224 BENAVENTE STREET, IN THE LA BANDERA NEIGHBORHOOD.

ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, MANY SUBVERSIVE DOCUMENTS WERE FOUND IN THE HOUSE.

DEV-MUC3-0082 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 8 FEB 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO RESHUFFLED HIS CABINET TODAY, APPOINTING FIVE NEW MINISTERS AND RECONFIRMING EIGHT FOR THE FINAL PHASE OF HIS TERM, ACCORDING TO AN OFFICIAL DECREE.

THE REORGANIZATION OCCURRED AFTER THE MINISTERS PRESENTED A PROTOCOL RESIGNATION TO ALLOW THE PRESIDENT TO APPOINT NEW MINISTERS; SOME OF THEM DID NOT WANT TO BE POLITICALLY DISQUALIFIED FROM RUNNING FOR A SEAT IN CONGRESS IN THE 1990 ELECTIONS.

THIS HAS BEEN THE THIRD IMPORTANT CABINET RESHUFFLE SINCE BARCO TOOK OFFICE IN AUGUST 1986.

THE FIVE NEW CABINET MINISTERS INCLUDE TWO WOMEN WHO WILL HOLD THE POSTS OF PUBLIC WORKS AND LABOR MINISTERS. THE OTHERS WHO WILL JOIN THE CABINET WERE APPOINTED TO THE GOVERNMENT, COMMUNICATIONS, AND HEALTH MINISTRIES.

THE OUTGOING MINISTERS STATED IN THEIR PROTOCOL LETTER OF RESIGNATION THAT A CABINET RESHUFFLE IS FUNDAMENTAL TO ALLOW THE GOVERNMENT TO ACHIEVE ITS GOALS IN THE FINAL STAGE OF PRESIDENT BARCO'S ADMINISTRATION.

"WE HAVE SERVED IN A A PARTICULARLY DIFFICULT PERIOD OF NATIONAL LIFE, CHARACTERIZED BY SITUATIONS OF CRIMINALITY AND TERRORISM," THE RESIGNATION LETTER STATED.

THE LETTER ADDED THAT THE RESIGNATION RESULTED FROM SOME OF THE MINISTERS' NOT WANTING TO BE POLITICALLY DISQUALIFIED FROM RUNNING FOR PUBLIC POSTS. COLOMBIAN LAW DEMANDS THAT THOSE ASPIRING TO PUBLIC POSTS MUST NOT HAVE SERVED AS GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS WITHIN THE LAST 12 MONTHS.

DEV-MUC3-0083 (NOSC)

LIMA, 6 FEB 89 -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS BY PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA] [EXCERPT] [REPORTER] ...TO AN ARRESTED LEADER OF THE TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT MEAN THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS ENGAGED IN A DIALOGUE WITH THAT GROUP?

[GARCIA] THINGS SHOULD BE PROPERLY CLARIFIED BECAUSE ONE SHOULD NOT BE INFLUENCED BY REPORTS OR ANECDOTES. THERE IS AN ESSENTIAL FACT: A HARD BLOW HAS BEEN DEALT TO SUBVERSION WITH THE ARREST OF ONE OF ITS PRINCIPAL CHIEFTAINS--NOT A LEADER BUT A CHIEFTAIN. PERU HAS BEEN THE TARGET OF BLOODY TERRORIST ATTACKS. THERE CAN BE NO CONCESSIONS FOR TERRORISTS OTHER THAN THOSE GRANTED BY THE LAW. THIS FACT CANNOT BE DISPELLED BY AN ANECDOTE LIKE THE ONE I READ IN THE NEWSPAPERS TODAY. THE ESSENTIAL FACT IS THAT THIS ARREST [OF VICTOR POLAY CAMPOS] IS A MAJOR BLOW TO SUBVERSION. IT WAS NOT MERELY GOOD LUCK, BUT IT WAS THE RESULT OF WORK AND FOLLOW-UP BY THE INTELLIGENCE SERVICES OF THE ARMED FORCES AND THE POLICE. I BELIEVE THIS IS THE KEY POINT. I HAVE SEEN THAT ATTENTION HAS BEEN GIVEN TO A VISIT [PAID BY PRIME MINISTER ARMANDO VILLANUEVA TO POLAY CAMPOS IN PRISON] WHICH WAS NEITHER A COURTESY VISIT NOR AN EXPRESSION OF SUPPORT, BUT JUST A SUPERVISORY ACT, GIVEN THE IMPORTANCE OF THE FACTS. ANOTHER OBJECTIVE OF THE VISIT, WHICH FOR SURE HAS ALREADY BEEN COMMENTED ON BY SOME COMMUNIST POLITICIANS, WAS TO OBSERVE THE CONDITION OF THE DETAINEE. THE VISIT DID NOT MEAN THAT THE DETAINEE WAS GRANTED SPECIAL STATUS. WE DO NOT GRANT SPECIAL STATUS TO ANYONE, MUCH LESS TO THESE MURDERERS WHO HAVE STAINED THE NATION WITH BLOOD. THE FULL WEIGHT OF THE LAW MUST BE STRICTLY ENFORCED ON THESE INDIVIDUALS. CONSEQUENTLY, THE VISIT BY PRIME MINISTER ARMANDO VILLANUEVA TO THE ANTITERRORIST DIRECTORATE DOES NOT MEAN THAT A DIALOGUE HAS BEGUN OR THAT SOMEONE IS BEING PRAISED, AS SOME ILL-INTENTIONED MASS MEDIA WILL PROBABLY SAY. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0085 (NOSC)

LIMA, 3 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] A SPECTACULAR OPERATION WAS CONDUCTED YESTERDAY NOON WHEN A 39-MAN POLICE PATROL OF THE SANTA LUCIA DETACHMENT, REINFORCED BY ANTI-NARCOTICS POLICE, SURROUNDED THE UCHIZA AIRPORT AND WAITED FOR THE ARRIVAL OF TWO COLOMBIAN LIGHT AIRPLANES THAT WERE SUPPOSEDLY CARRYING DRUGS. A TIP HAD BEEN RECEIVED BY THE POLICE.

THE LANDING STRIP WAS SUBJECTED TO CONTINUOUS SURVEILLANCE. A 60-MAN ARMED GROUP OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS APPEARED AT 1620. APPARENTLY, THIS GROUP WAS GOING TO PROTECT THE COLOMBIAN LIGHT AIRPLANES.

THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS ARRIVED ABOARD SEVERAL VEHICLES. THEY DID NOT KNOW THEY WERE BEING WATCHED BY THE POLICE, WHOM THEY OUTNUMBERED.

UNDER THESE CIRCUMSTANCES, AND IMPLEMENTING A MASTERLY PLAN, THE POLICE FORCES APPEARED AND A SPECTACULAR SHOOT-OUT ENSUED.

SURPRISED BY THE UNEXPECTED ATTACK, THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS RETURNED THE FIRE, WHICH LASTED FOR 1/2 AN HOUR.

AS A RESULT OF THE CLASH, TWO DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE KILLED AND FOUR WERE INJURED AND TRANSPORTED TO THE CENTRAL HOSPITAL IN TINGO MARIA. MEANWHILE, 15 DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE ARRESTED; THE REST FLED.

AFTER THE INITIAL INVESTIGATIONS, THE CAPTURED DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE FULLY IDENTIFIED. THE FOLLOWING COLOMBIAN CITIZENS WERE INVOLVED: FLORIAN CARVAJAL TELLO, MARIO MONTES MURILLO, AND ROLAND ARAMAYO DIAZ. THE FOLLOWING PERUVIAN CITIZENS WERE INVOLVED: JAIME LEMOS VERA, GUILLERMO ARO MENDIETA, ARMANDO SANCHEZ FLORES, ROMULO ROJAS FARFAN, PERCY ROJAS RODRIGUEZ, RUAL MORETTI CORDOVA, WILLIAM GUAJAN LOSA, CARLOS ROSAS RODRIGUEZ, FERNANDO GARCES ALVARADO, RAUL BEATINO BARDALES, ALCIDES ANGULO DIAZ, AND LUIS RODRIGUEZ CASTILLO.

THE NAMES OF THE INJURED DRUG TRAFFICKERS ARE: JOSE HERNANDEZ VELA, CESAR VEGA VILCA, PEDRO ARROYO ELIAS, AND GRACIAN MARTINEZ SAVICH.

IN ADDITION, CIVIL GUARDSMEN FOUND NEAR THE UCHIZA LANDING STRIP A TOTAL OF 700 KG OF COCAINE PASTE READY FOR SHIPMENT.

TWO NISSAN PICK-UP TRUCKS, ONE TOYOTA PICK-UP TRUCK, SIX REVOLVERS, TWO PISTOLS, AND EIGHT SHOTGUNS OF VARIOUS BRANDS WERE ALSO SEIZED.

DEV-MUC3-0086 (NOSC)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 22 MAR 89 -- [EXCERPT] THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND WILL SOON PRESENT A NEW PEACE PROPOSAL TO ARENA AND THEREFORE CALLS FOR THE FORMATION OF A BROAD COALITION TO FACE THE NEW GOVERNMENT, A COALITION TO INCLUDE THE PDC, WHICH IS NOW AN OPPOSITION PARTY AFTER HAVING LOST THE ELECTIONS.

FMLN COMMANDERS ANA GUADUALUPE MARTINEZ, SALVADOR SAMAYOA, AND JOSE MARIA LOPEZ READ THE FMLN COMMUNIQUE AND SAID THAT ARENA'S REACHING POWER DEFINITELY "MEANS THAT THE OLIGARCHY WILL REJOIN THE MILITARY DICTATORSHIP."

THE COMMANDERS ALSO EVALUATED THE LAST 5 YEARS OF THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DUARTE GOVERNMENT IN EL SALVADOR:

SALVADOR SAMAYOA SAID: "THE LAST 5 YEARS HAVE BEEN THE MOST DIFFICULT. THE ONLY GOOD THING IS THAT AFTER THE ELECTIONS, WE ARE CLOSER TO DEFINING THE CONFLICT IN EL SALVADOR.

"IT HAS BEEN A LONG AND DIFFICULT WAR. THE ENEMY WAS ILL-DEFINED, ENJOYING CERTAIN POPULARITY AMONG THE PEOPLE, MAKING IT EASIER FOR THEM TO TRY AND PERSUADE THEM THAT OUR REVOLUTIONARY STRUGGLE WAS A TERRORIST WAR WHEN THIS WAS NOT THE CASE."

ANA GUADALUPE MARTINEZ SAID:

"I BELIEVE THAT THE EVENTS THAT BEGAN IN 1981 ARE COMING FULL CIRCLE NOW, BUT NOW THERE ARE MANY ADVANTAGES.

"THE PDC EMERGED FROM A POPULAR STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DICTATORSHIP. NOW THEY ARE IN OPPOSITION AND CAN DEAL WITH THE REST OF THE OPPOSITION AS EQUALS, AND THAT IS AN ADVANTAGE FOR US.

"THE SPLIT WITHIN THE DEMOCRATIC SIDE IS FOR THE BETTER. I BELIEVE WE ARE NOW IN THE FINAL STAGES."

WHEN MARTINEZ WAS ASKED HOW SHE WOULD DESCRIBE THE PDC'S ROLE IN EL SALVADOR DURING THE LAST 5 YEARS, SHE REPLIED:

"THE PDC PLAYED A VERY NEGATIVE ROLE. IT PROLONGED THE WAR THAT WOULD HAVE OTHERWISE BEEN VERY MUCH SHORTER, BUT IT IS POSSIBLE THAT THE PDC MAY DEVIATE FROM THEIR PAST BEHAVIOR AND PLAY A DIFFERENT ROLE THAN THE OPPOSITION, FAVORING A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT."

THE FMLN COMMANDERS BELIEVED THAT ARENA'S VICTORY WILL BRING BACK THE DEATH SQUADS. THE FMLN COMMANDERS BELIEVE THAT NOW THE POSSIBILITY OF A MILITARY COUP IS GREATER.

CONTRARY TO WHAT MIGHT BE BELIEVED, THE FMLN COMANDERS SAID: "WE DO NOT SEE A STRONG RIGHT WING. WE SEE THEM MORE TRAPPED POLITICALLY AND ECONOMICALLY." THE COMMANDERS ALSO ARGUED THAT THEY ARE NOT GOING TO FACE THE SAME OLIGARCHY AND ARMY THEY FACED IN 1979.

THE MESSAGE THEY HAVE FOR ARENA STATES: "SEE WHAT HAS HAPPENED? IS IT NOT ENOUGH TO HAVE LAUNCHED A MILITARY OFFENSIVE?"

THE COMMANDERS SAID THAT, NEVERTHELESS, THE FMLN IS READY FOR A GREAT MILITARY EFFORT AND REITERATED THAT IF ANYTHING CLEARLY EMERGED DURING THE LAST 2 MONTHS, IT IS THAT "WE ARE A POLITICAL MAJORITY IN EL SALVADOR." [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0088 (NOSC)

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 28 MAR 89 (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] RADIO VENCEREMOS IN SPANISH TO EL SALVADOR AT 0000 GMT ON ON 29 MARCH BROADCASTS APPROXIMATELY 6 MINUTES OF WAR REPORTS.

THE FIRST OF THE REPORTS, ALL OF WHICH ARE READ BY THE STATION ANNOUNCER, DESCRIBES EVENTS IN CHALATENANGO. THE REPORT STATES THAT ON 27 MARCH AT 2100, FMLN UNITS BEGAN ATTACKING ATLACATL BATTALION POSITIONS IN PLAN DEL PICACHO, LA CEIBITA, AMATILLO, LA CEIBA AREA, TEMPISQUE HILL, AND EL COPINOL, ALL OF WHICH ARE WITHIN LAS VUELTAS JURISDICTION, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT. THE ATTACK LASTED FOR 4 HOURS, AND WHEN IT CONCLUDED THE ARMY'S TROOPS HAD BEEN DISLODGED FROM THEIR POSITIONS IN LA CEIBITA AND PLAN DEL PICACHO. THE "ENEMY" SENT REINFORCEMENTS TO TEMPISQUE HILL AND EL COPINOL 1 HOUR LATER, BUT "THIS EFFORT PROVED USELESS" AND AIR SUPPORT HAD TO BE CALLED IN. THE CLASH LASTED UNTIL 0400 ON 28 MARCH, RESULTING IN NINE CASUALTIES.

THE STATION ANNOUNCER GOES ON TO REPORT THAT ON 28 MARCH AT 1000, SNIPER UNITS ENTERED PLAN DEL PICACHO AND INFLICTED THREE CASUALTIES ON THE ATLACATL BATTALION. ANOTHER REPORT FROM THE SAME AREA INDICATES THAT ON 27 MARCH AN ATLACATL BATTALION UNIT ENTERED A MINE FIELD SET UP BY THE FMLN IN PLAN DEL PICACHO, RESULTING IN THREE ARMY CASUALTIES. ALL IN ALL, OVER 2 DAYS THE FMLN CLAIMS TO HAVE INFLICTED 15 CASUALTIES ON THE ATLACATL BATTALION.

THE STATION ANNOUNCER GOES ON TO REPORT THAT ON 27 MARCH FMLN UNITS WITH RIFLES, RIFLE GRENADES, AND HOMEMADE ARTILLERY ATTACKED ARMY POSITIONS AT THE 5 NOVEMBER DAM. NO CASUALTY FIGURE WAS GIVEN FOR THIS ATTACK.

MEANWHILE, THE STATION ANNOUNCER SAYS, THE FELICIANO AMA FRONT STATIONED IN SANTA ANA REPORTS THAT ON 26 MARCH FMLN UNITS AMBUSHED A SIX-VEHICLE MILITARY CONVOY TRANSPORTING TROOPS FROM THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE'S EL PIPIL BATTALION FROM METAPAN TO SANTA ANA. THE AMBUSH TOOK PLACE IN CASITAS, TEXISTEPEQUE JURISDICTION, WHEN TWO POWERFUL FELICIANO AMA MINES EXPLODED, INFLICTING EIGHT CASUALTIES ON THE ARMY AND TOTALLY DESTROYING A MILITARY VEHICLE.

DEV-MUC3-0090 (NOSC)

FRIJANES, 29 MAR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] ELITE UNITS OF THE GUATEMALAN ARMY THIS AFTERNOON BEGAN TO SURROUND PAVON PRISON, WHICH SINCE 26 MARCH HAS BEEN IN THE HANDS OF SOME 200 PRISONERS WHO ARE HOLDING MORE THAN 500 PEOPLE HOSTAGE.

THE UNITS WERE DEPLOYED TO PAVON, 30 KM SOUTHEAST OF THE GUATEMALAN CAPITAL, TO APPLY PRESSURE ON THE PRISONERS, WHO TODAY REFUSED TO SIGN A DOCUMENT CONTAINING GUARANTEES DRAFTED BY THE MEDIATION COMMISSION.

INSTEAD, THE PRISONERS PRESENTED A COUNTERPROPOSAL TO THE MEDIATION COMMISSION--WHICH WAS ESTABLISHED BY PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO HIMSELF TO "PREVENT BLOODSHED"--SEVERAL COMMISSION MEMBERS SAID AS THEY LEFT THE PENAL CENTER.

A POSSIBLE PEACEFUL SOLUTION THAT WAS HOPED FOR YESTERDAY IS AGAIN "ON HOLD" TODAY BECAUSE OF THE REBELS' REFUSAL TO SIGN THE DOCUMENT.

HUMAN RIGHTS ATTORNEY GENERAL GONZALO MENENDEZ SAID THAT "THE SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEM IS AGAIN AT AN IMPASSE, BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER MUST ANALYZE THE PRISONERS' PROPOSAL."

THE UPRISING, WHICH BEGAN AT 1100 (1700 GMT) ON 26 MARCH AND WHICH INCLUDES DEMANDS FOR BETTER JAIL CONDITIONS, HAS LEFT AT LEAST 12 DEAD AND SOME 20 INJURED, ACCORDING TO POLICE SPOKESMEN.

SOME 150 HONOR GUARD MEMBERS, "ALL EXPERTS IN DISORDERS AND UPRISINGS," HAVE BEEN POSITIONED NEAR THE PRISON UNDER THE COMMAND OF A LIEUTENANT COLONEL AND FIVE OTHER OFFICERS, ACCORDING TO STATEMENTS MADE TO ACAN-EFE BY A TOP MILITARY OFFICER, WHO ASKED TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS.

THE ASSAULT TROOPS ARE ARMED WITH BATONS, TEAR GAS, GAS MASKS, AND MACHINEGUNS.

"MY MEN ARE CAPABLE OF DEALING WITH DISORDERS AND HAVE BEEN PREPARED FOR CASES SUCH AS THIS ONE," THE MILITARY CHIEF SAID.

THE REBELLIOUS PRISONERS, WHO HAVE CONTROL OF 65 PERCENT OF THE PRISON INSTALLATIONS, REMAIN INFLEXIBLE AND REFUSE TO RELEASE THE HOSTAGES AND LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS.

DESPITE THE MEDIATING COMMISSION'S OPTIMISM, AFTER 72 HOURS THE REBELLIOUS PRISONERS PRESENTED A NEW PROPOSAL TODAY AT NOON, HUMAN RIGHTS ATTORNEY GENERAL GONZALO MENENDEZ SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0091 (NOSC)

LA PAZ, 29 MAR 89 -- [TEXT] INTERIOR MINISTRY UNDER SECRETARY WALTER COSTAS BADANI HAS STATED THAT BOLIVIAN INTELLIGENCE AND SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS HAVE YET TO DETECT THE PRESENCE OF SHINING PATH TERRORISTS IN BOLIVIA.

COSTAS BADANI TOLD PANAMERICANA THAT THE PERUVIAN PRESS ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS HAS TRIED TO IMPLICATE BOLIVIAN TIES IN THIS TERRORIST ORGANIZATION'S ACTIVITIES.

COSTAS BADANI POINTED OUT THAT THE SHINING PATH GUERRILLAS HAVE CONDUCTED THEIR TERRORIST OPERATIONS EXCLUSIVELY IN PERUVIAN TERRITORY AND THAT BOLIVIA HAS NO CONNECTION WHATSOEVER WITH THIS GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [COSTAS BADANI] THE REPORTS ABOUT THESE TIES ARE ALARMING AND GROUNDLESS. THE INTERNATIONAL PRESS, AND ESPECIALLY THE PERUVIAN MEDIA, HAVE OFTEN TRIED TO INVOLVE BOLIVIA IN THE TERRORIST PROBLEMS, WHICH I DO NOT THINK HAVE GONE BEYOND PERU'S BORDERS. WE HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH THEM, AND ANY RUMOR IN THIS REGARD IS GROUNDLESS SPECULATION. [END RECORDING]

COSTAS BADANI ALSO SAID THAT, IF NECESSARY, THE APPROPRIATE GOVERNMENT SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS WILL CARRY OUT THEIR SPECIFIC DUTIES IN A COORDINATED MANNER. THIS MEANS THAT THEY WILL EXCHANGE INFORMATION WITH SIMILAR ORGANIZATIONS OF THE ARMED FORCES.

DEV-MUC3-0093 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 27 MAR 89 -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, THE HOLY WEEK TRUCE WAS APPARENTLY BROKEN OVER THE WEEKEND BY SEVERAL REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC) FRONTS IN ANTIOQUIA, META, AND HUILA DEPARTMENTS. ONE ARMY LIEUTENANT, FOUR SOLDIERS, AND THREE CIVILIANS WERE KILLED DURING THE ATTACKS.

THE DEFENSE MINISTRY REPORTED THE FIRST INCIDENT TOOK PLACE AT LA LINEA, A CORREGIMIENTO LOCATED IN ALGECIRAS MUNICIPALITY, HUILA DEPARTMENT, WHERE A FARC FRONT AMBUSHED AN 11TH BRIGADE ARMY PATROL. SEVERAL MINES PLACED IN THE AREA WENT OFF WHEN THE SOLDIERS PASSED THROUGH LA LINEA CORREGIMIENTO. LIEUTENANT JAIME QUINTERO CARDONA AND SOLDIERS NELSON SANCHEZ MOLINA, MAXIMILIANO SERRATO CUELLAR, AND DAIRO SUAREZ SUAREZ WERE KILLED IN THIS ACTION.

IN ADDITION, THE FERVOR OF THE SATURDAY PROCESSION AND PRAYERS WERE INTERRUPTED IN SANTA RITA CORREGIMIENTO, ITUANGO MUNICIPALITY, ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, AT 1800 BY 200 GUERRILLAS WHO ENTERED THE TOWN SHOOTING AT ARMY TROOPS--APPROXIMATELY 72 SOLDIERS--WHO WERE RETURNING TO THE TOWN AFTER THEIR PATROL OPERATIONS.

GIRARDO BATTALION OFFICERS, WHO ASKED US NOT TO REVEAL THEIR NAMES, STATED THAT THE REBELS, WHO WERE MEMBERS OF THE FARC 28TH FRONT, ATTACKED TWO TRUCKS FILLED WITH SOLDIERS.

THE SANTA RITA POLICE CHIEF FOUND THE BODIES OF A SOLDIER AND A REBEL ON THE ROAD LEADING TO SANTA RITA. THE SOLDIER WAS IDENTIFIED AS EDISON ESTRADA BOLIVAR. SOLDIER RAUL DURANGO HERRERA WAS WOUNDED AND TAKEN TO THE PABLO TOBON URIBE HOSPITAL IN MEDELLIN.

THE DEAD REBEL, WHO HAS NOT YET BEEN IDENTIFIED, HAD A SUBMACHINEGUN, 3 CLIPS, AND 30 9-MM CARTRIDGES ON HIM.

ITUANGO MUNICIPALITY, 195 KM NORTH OF MEDELLIN, IS NEAR LOWER CAUCA, WHERE THE ARMY DISMANTLED DURING HOLY WEEK A FARC 37TH FRONT PLAN DESIGNED TO COMMIT AND CARRY OUT AMBUSHES AND ASSAULTS.

MEANWHILE, AT LEAST 50 FARC REBELS BLEW UP A JEEP NEAR SAN JUAN DE URAMA MUNICIPALITY NEAR ROAD NO 32 IN META DEPARTMENT.

ACCORDING TO POLICE COMMANDER COLONEL JOSE WILLIAM BERMUDEZ ZAPATA, WHO COMMANDS ANTIGUERRILLA OPERATIONS WITH THE SUPPORT OF 7TH BRIGADE TROOPS, THE REBELS KILLED THREE PEOPLE AND TOOK THE FOURTH PASSENGER OF THE JEEP WITH THEM.

THE VICTIMS--WHO WERE INVOLVED IN COCAINE TRAFFICKING--ARE: ALFONSO OLIVARES, ALIAS PICO FRESCO; AN N.N. [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] KNOWN AS EL MOCHO; AND ROMAN OLIVARES GUTIERREZ. JAIME MONTEALEGRE IS THE NAME OF THE PERSON TAKEN BY THE REBELS.

MEANWHILE, WE HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO OBTAIN INFORMATION ABOUT THE RESULTS OF THE OPERATIONS CONDUCTED BY 5TH BRIGADE TROOPS COMMANDED BY GENERAL ALFONSO VACA PERILLA IN THE AREAS OF EL CARMEN AND SAN VICENTE DE CHUCURRI, SANTANDER DEPARTMENT.

COL JORGE ERNESTO FERRERO ECHEVERRI, SANTANDER DEPARTMENT POLICE COMMANDER, SAID THE SPECIAL SECURITY COUNCIL WILL MEET TODAY (MONDAY) TO ASSESS THE SITUATION.

COL FERRERO EXPLAINED THAT "IN PRINCIPLE, WE HAVE REPORTS SAYING MANY PEOPLE WERE KILLED, BUT WE DO NOT KNOW EXACTLY HOW MANY. WE KNOW SEVEN PEASANTS WERE MURDERED BY FARC 12TH FRONT MEMBERS."

HELICOPTERS CONTINUE OVERFLYING THE BATTLE ZONE. AIRBORNE TROOPS REPLACED THE TROOPS WHO WERE FIGHTING AGAINST THE MEN UP IN ARMS.

PEASANTS WHO ARRIVED AT SAN VICENTE CHUCURRI SAID POWERFUL EXPLOSIONS HAVE BEEN CONTINUOUSLY HEARD SINCE THE MILITARY ACTIONS BEGAN ON 22 MARCH.

ARMY OFFICERS BELIEVE THE REBEL COLUMN IS SURROUNDED IN A MOUNTAINOUS STRIP LOCATED BETWEEN EL CARMEN AND SAN VICENTE CHUCURRI MUNICIPALITIES.

GEN VACA PERILLA RETURNED TO THE AREA YESTERDAY, BUT HE DID NOT MAKE ANY STATEMENTS. HE HAS BEEN COMMANDING OPERATIONS IN THE AREA FOR THE LAST 5 DAYS.

AN UNOFFICIAL REPORT INDICATED TWO HELICOPTERS WERE HIT BY FARC REBELS' RIFLE FIRE.

SAN VICENTE CHUCURRI PARISH PRIEST JUVENAL MARTINEZ SAID THE AREA RESIDENTS AND THE COMMON FRONT ARE TRYING TO FORM A COMMISSION TO VERIFY WHAT IS GOING ON IN THE AREA.

DEV-MUC3-0098 (NOSC)

BOGOTA, 29 MAR 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] DIEGO MONTANA, ACTING PRESIDENT OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION [UP], TOLD EFE TODAY THAT ONLY THE PARTICIPATION OF THE SIMON BOLIVAR NATIONAL GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD (CNG) IN THE PEACE TALKS COULD GUARANTEE A POLITICAL SOLUTION IN COLOMBIA.

THE CNG GROUPS THE SIX MAIN LEFTIST GUERRILLA ORGANIZATIONS THAT OPERATE IN COLOMBIA. THERE ARE 20,000 GUERRILLAS IN 100 FRONTS THROUGHOUT COLOMBIA.

THE GROUPS COMPRISING THE CNG ARE THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC, COMMUNIST); AND ; THE POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY (EPL, MAOIST); AND ; CAMILISTA UNION-ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (UC-ELN, PRO-CASTROITE); AND ; THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19, NATIONALIST LEFT); QUINTIN LAME MOVEMENT (INDIGENIST); AND THE REVOLUTIONARY WORKERS PARTY (PRT, TROTSKYIST); AND .

TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT, THE M-19, AND THE TRADITIONAL POLITICAL PARTIES WILL BEGIN IN BOGOTA ON 3 APRIL AS PART OF THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, WHICH THE GOVERNMENT AND GUERRILLA MOVEMENTS BEGAN LAST JANUARY TO ACHIEVE PEACE.

THE UP ANNOUNCED IN EARLY MARCH THAT IT WOULD NOT PARTICIPATE IN THE ROUNDTABLES, THE NAME GIVEN TO THE TALKS THAT WILL BEGIN NEXT MONDAY AND IN WHICH THE PARTICIPANTS WILL DISCUSS THE LARGE NUMBER OF POLITICAL CRIMES THAT HAVE BEEN PERPETRATED BY RIGHTIST PARAMILITARY GROUPS.

SINCE THE UP WAS FOUNDED, NEARLY 1,000 OF ITS MEMBERS AND LEADERS HAVE BEEN MURDERED.

THE "DIRTY WAR" AGAINST THE LEFT, PROGRESSIVE POLITICIANS, AND HUMAN RIGHTS ACTIVISTS HAS RESULTED IN 700 POLITICAL ASSASSINATIONS SO FAR THIS YEAR.

THERE WERE 2,978 POLITICAL ASSASSINATIONS IN 1988; 1,200 IN 1987; AND 1,000 IN 1986.

IN ADDITION, NEARLY 1,500 PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN CLASHES BETWEEN THE ARMED FORCES AND GUERRILLAS IN 1988. SO FAR THIS YEAR, ABOUT 100 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED IN CLASHES.

DIEGO MONTANA TOLD EFE THAT HE WAS PLEASED TO SEE THAT THE M-19 HAD INITIATED PEACE TALKS WITH THE GOVERNMENT, BUT HE NOTED THAT THE REST OF THE CNG ACCOUNTS FOR 84 PERCENT OF THE REBELS.

"I AM PLEASED TO SEE THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS HOLDING TALKS WITH 16 PERCENT OF THE GUERRILLAS," MONTANA SAID, "BUT THE PEACE PROCESS WILL NOT BE SUCCESSFUL IF THE OTHER 84 PERCENT OF THE GUERRILLA GROUPS KEEP ON FIGHTING."

MONTANA ALSO PRAISED THE LATEST COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE CNG, WHICH WAS SIGNED BY THE FARC, THE EPL, AND THE UC-ELN, WHICH ANNOUNCED THEIR DECISION TO BEGIN TALKS WITH THE GOVERNMENT, BUT WHICH LINKED THEIR PARTICIPATION TO THE DISMANTLING OF RIGHTIST PARAMILITARY GROUPS.

MOREOVER, JACOBO ARENAS, COMMANDER OF THE FARC AND MEMBER OF THE CNG STAFF, TOLD BOGOTA EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK THAT "ANYTHING LEADING TO THE OPENING OF ROADS, THE BUILDING OF BRIDGES, AND THE OPENING OF LOCKS IS BENEFICIAL," AND HE PRAISED THE TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE M-19 IN THAT REGARD.

ARENAS, HOWEVER, SAID THE M-19 HAD PULLED ITSELF OUT OF THE CNG BY REACHING A PEACE AGREEMENT ON ITS OWN AND THAT IN THE NEXT PLENARY MEETING THE POSSIBLE EXPULSION OF THE M-19 FROM THE CNG WOULD BE STUDIED.

DEV-MUC3-0101 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 OCT 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI SAID POSITIVE RESULTS WERE OBTAINED DURING THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT IN COSTA RICA. ONE OF THE ACCOMPLISHMENTS, CRISTIANI SAID, IS THAT THERE WAS AN OPPORTUNITY TO HOLD BILATERAL TALKS WITH SOUTH AMERICAN PRESIDENTS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] WE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO HOLD BILATERAL TALKS WITH SOUTH AMERICAN PRESIDENTS AND TO BRIEF THEM ON THE PEACE PROCESS, THE GOVERNMENT EFFORTS TO ATTAIN PEACE, AND THE OBJECTIVES OF THE PEACE PROCESS. THE PRESIDENTS RECEIVED FIRSTHAND INFORMATION ON THE PEACE PLAN AND ON THE RESULTS THE GOVERNMENT EXPECTS FROM THIS PROCESS [WORDS INDISTINCT]. I BELIEVE WE HAVE RECEIVED GREAT SUPPORT FOR THE PEACE PROCESS. AS A COUNTRY, EL SALVADOR HAS RECEIVED THE LATIN AMERICAN PRESIDENTS' SUPPORT FOR THE PEACE PROCESS, ESPECIALLY THE SUPPORT OF THE SOUTH AMERICAN PRESIDENTS WITH WHOM WE HAD NOT HAD AN OPPORTUNITY TO HOLD BILATERAL TALKS. [END RECORDING]

REGARDING THE COFFEE PROBLEM, CRISTIANI SAID THE PRESIDENTS NOTED THE NEED FOR REACHING AGREEMENTS ON THE COFFEE PACT AND THE PRICE OF COFFEE. HE ADDED THAT DURING THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT HE CONDEMNED, IN THE PRESENCE OF ALL PRESIDENTS, THE AID NICARAGUA GIVES TO THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. HOWEVER, THERE WAS NO RESPONSE FROM THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT, CRISTIANI STATED.

CONCERNING THE RECENT ATTACKS BLAMED ON THE GUERRILLAS, PARTICULARLY THE 30 OCTOBER ATTACK ON THE ARMY'S HIGH COMMAND, CRISTIANI SAID THIS IS REGRETTABLE BECAUSE CIVILIANS ARE MORE AFFECTED BY SUCH ATTACKS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] THIS INCIDENT TAKES PLACE AT A TIME WHEN THE FMLN IS TRYING TO SHOW ITS STRENGTH. THE FMLN IS ALSO TRYING TO PROVOKE SOME REACTION FROM THE ARMED FORCES SO THAT THE ARMY, IN A GIVEN MOMENT, EXERTS PRESSURE TO SUSPEND THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. I THINK THIS IS THE REASON FOR THEIR ATTITUDE. [END RECORDING]

CRISTIANI ADDED THAT SUCH ATTITUDES WILL NOT HINDER THE DIALOGUE PROCESS IN VENEZUELA. HE ADDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT PROPOSAL WILL BE THE SAME PROPOSAL PRESENTED IN COSTA RICA AND IT WILL BE FULLY DISCUSSED. HOWEVER, THE PRIORITY WILL ALWAYS BE THE CESSATION OF HOSTILITIES.

DEV-MUC3-0104 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 2 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT COMMANDER EDUARDO SANCHO, ALIAS FERMAN CIENFUEGOS, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] COMRADE SANCHO, WHY HAS THE FMLN DECIDED NOT TO ATTEND THE CARACAS MEETING?

[SANCHO] THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND INSTRUCTED ME THIS AFTERNOON TO ANNOUNCE TO THE NATION A COMMUNIQUE IN WHICH WE DECIDED NOT TO ATTEND THE CARACAS MEETING AND DIALOGUE. THE REASON FOR THIS IS THE RECENT FENASTRAS MASSACRE, WHICH WE BELIEVE CANNOT BE IGNORED. THIS IS NOT JUST ANOTHER ATTACK, LIKE THE ONES WE ARE USED TO, BUT AN ATTACK THAT SIGNALS A NEW POLITICAL ERA SIMILAR TO THOSE WHEN AN ELECTORAL MASSACRE OCCURRED, WHEN MSGR ARNULFO ROMERO WAS MURDERED, WHEN OTHER CRIMES MARKED NEW STEPS IN THE NEW FASCIST ESCALATION OF THE DICTATORSHIP NOW LED BY ALFREDO CRISTIANI, COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, AND THE GREAT EXECUTIONER AND PERPETRATOR OF MASSACRES, ELENA FUENTES. THE MAIN THING IS THAT THE FASCIST MILITARY DICTATORSHIP, HEADED BY A SMALL ARMED FORCES GROUP, HAS BEEN EXPOSED. WE DO NOT THINK THIS CAN BE IGNORED. THE STATE AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] HAVE TO PAY A POLITICAL PRICE. THIS PRICE IS COL PONCE'S RESIGNATION, WHICH IS NOW DEMANDED BY THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT.

[REPORTER] AFTER THE ATTACK, INSTEAD OF SEEKING A DETENTE, THE ARMY, ON THE CONTRARY, CONTINUED ITS PROVOCATIONS. FOR INSTANCE, SEVERAL PLAINCLOTHES MEMBERS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE [WORDS INDISTINCT] FENASTRAS AND THE POPULAR MOVEMENT TOOK THEM PRISONER. MORE THAN 30 OF THEM WERE DETAINED. WE LEARNED THIS AFTERNOON THAT THE POLICE RELEASED A COMMUNIQUE SAYING THEY WOULD STATION ANTIRIOT POLICEMEN AT THE NATIONAL CEMETERY. WE ALSO HEARD COL MAURICIO VARGAS SAYING THAT, IF THE DIALOGUE DOOR IS CLOSED, IT HAS TO BE KICKED OPEN. WHAT DO YOU THINK OF THE SITUATION AFTER THE COWARDLY ATTACK ON FENASTRAS?

WE THINK ALL THESE ACTIVITIES OF THE DEATH SQUADS, THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, THE POLICE, AND THE NATIONAL GUARD ARE ONLY THE OPEN EXPRESSION OF THE ARMED FORCES' POSITION, WHICH IS TO PLAN A FULL-SCALE CONFRONTATION WITH THE POPULAR MOVEMENT. WE THINK THIS INDICATES [WORDS INDISTINCT] BEHIND THE BACKS OF THE MAJORITY OF ARMED FORCES MEMBERS. IT IS A MINORITY WHO HAVE DECIDED ON THESE PROVOCATIONS AGAINST THE POPULAR MOVEMENT. THIS MOVEMENT, HOWEVER, IS SUFFICIENTLY STRONG TO DISARM THESE PROVOCATEURS, PRESENT THEM TO THE PRESS, AND HAND THEM OVER TO SHOW THAT THE PEOPLE EXPRESS THEIR TREMENDOUS POWER WHENEVER THEY WANT.

[REPORTER] WITH LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO 1966 GRADUATES OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] IN POWER, AND WITH THE SITUATION THE ARENA [NATIONAL REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] ERA HAS USHERED IN, IS THERE NO POSSIBLE SOLUTION THROUGH DIALOGUE? WHAT OTHER ALTERNATIVE DO YOU HAVE?

[SANCHO] I BELIEVE THAT IT IS QUITE CLEAR THAT PRESIDENT CRISTIANI AND THE HIGH COMMAND ARE PRACTICALLY DOING AWAY WITH POLITICAL OPPORTUNITIES, AS OUR EARLIER COMMUNIQUE ISSUED AFTER THE FENASTRAS ATTACK INDICATES. THE END RESULT IS THAT SINCE THERE IS NO POLITICAL FRAMEWORK WITHIN WHICH TO ESTABLISH A POLITICAL GAME WITH CERTAIN POLITICAL RULES FOR THE OPPOSITION AND STATE FORCES, OUR ONLY OTHER ALTERNATIVE IS TO IMMEDIATELY TAKE UP OUR WEAPONS, BECAUSE THERE IS NO OTHER WAY OF GUARANTEEING THE SURVIVAL OF THE POPULAR MOVEMENT AND THE NATION. THE PEOPLE'S LEGITIMATE RIGHT TO DEFENSE IS BECOMING INCREASINGLY LEGITIMATE, AND IT IS GAINING GREATER NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL RECOGNITION.

[REPORTER] THE POPULAR MOVEMENT IS ONCE AGAIN FACING A DECISIVE MOMENT IN THE COUNTRY'S HISTORY, AND THE WORKERS ARE GIVING THEIR SHARE OF BLOOD IN THIS STRUGGLE. WHAT MESSAGE WOULD YOU SEND TO THE POPULAR MOVEMENT, ESPECIALLY TO THE COMRADE WORKERS AT FENASTRAS?

[SANCHO] ON THIS OCCASION, I WISH TO SEND A SPECIAL MESSAGE TO FENASTRAS. I MUST TELL THEM TO CONTINUE TO BE INSPIRED BY THE PUREST CONCEPTS OF THE POPULAR STRUGGLE, TO KEEP THEIR INSPIRATION, TO BE CREATIVE AND COOL, AND THAT WHEN PEOPLE BEGIN TO CREATE THEIR OWN HISTORY, THEY ARE TRULY INVINCIBLE.

I BELIEVE THAT FENASTRAS HAS THE PEOPLE'S FULL SUPPORT AND THAT IT WILL GRADUALLY GAIN EVEN MORE SUPPORT. FENASTRAS MUST CONTINUE--AS ITS LEADERS SAY--ON THE WARPATH. IN REALITY, THE COST IN LIVES OF LEADERS SUCH AS FEBE ELIZABETH AND ALL THE OTHERS WHO WERE KILLED, AS WELL AS THOSE KILLED IN THE PAST, IS QUITE HIGH. THE COST IS POLITICAL. IT HAS TAKEN LIVES BUT THIS, IN REALITY, STRENGTHENS THE ORGANIZATION. THE PEOPLE'S RESPONSE HAS BEEN ONE OF ANGER AND DISCONTENT, AND THIS DISCONTENT WILL EVENTUALLY TURN INTO A CLAMOR FOR ARMED STRUGGLE BY SECTORS THAT REALLY [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND TO ACHIEVE OUR PEOPLE'S FREEDOM. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0108 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 NOV 89 -- [TEXT] COLONEL MAURICIO ERNESTO VARGAS, COMMANDER OF THE 3RD INFANTRY BRIGADE, REPORTED ON 31 OCTOBER THAT BETWEEN JANUARY AND SEPTEMBER, THE ARMY HAD INFLICTED 800 CASUALTIES ON THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AND SEIZED 300 WEAPONS IN THE EASTERN AREA OF THE COUNTRY. COL VARGAS ADDED THAT THE ARMY SUFFERED 443 CASUALTIES DURING THE SAME PERIOD. THE MILITARY COMMANDER OF THE AREA ADDED THAT 393 GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED AND 310 WOUNDED IN MORE THAN 600 CLASHES AND THAT 143 SOLDIERS WERE KILLED AND 300 WOUNDED.

"QUALITATIVE CHANGES HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN THE 3RD INFANTRY BRIGADE SINCE 1984, WHEN THE FMLN CHANGED ITS OVERALL STRATEGY FROM SEIZING POWER BY MILITARY MEANS TO THE EXTENDED PEOPLE'S WAR WHOSE BASIC ELEMENT IS THE UPRISING OF THE MASSES," COL VARGAS SAID.

VARGAS ADDED THAT DESPITE REBEL ACTIONS, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE CARRIED OUT THE GOVERNMENT'S PLANS AND ARE PROMOTING THE "EASTERN 89" PLAN IN 18 MUNICIPALITIES WITH 40 MILLION COLONS TO COVER THE COLLECTIVE AND INDIVIDUAL NEEDS OF THE PEOPLE. THEY ARE PREPARING A SECOND PHASE OF THE PLAN, WHICH WILL INCLUDE THE OTHER THREE DEPARTMENTS.

VARGAS ALSO REPORTED THAT, BECAUSE 30 PERCENT OF THE COUNTRY'S COFFEE IS GROWN IN THE EASTERN SECTOR OF THE COUNTRY, THE ARMY IS CARRYING OUT COMBING OPERATIONS TO PROTECT THE PEOPLE OF THE AREA DURING THE COFFEE HARVEST.

REGARDING THE GOVERNMENT - FMLN DIALOGUE HELD IN COSTA RICA, WHICH HE ATTENDED AS ADVISOR FOR THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION, VARGAS SAID THE ARMED FORCES CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THE GOVERNMENT'S DEMOCRATIC NATURE. "THERE IS SOMEONE WHO IS TRYING TO HINDER THE DIALOGUE AND PEACE. WE REJECT ALL CHARGES OF INVOLVEMENT IN THE RECENT ACTS OF VIOLENCE AND ATTACKS AND PUBLICLY REITERATE OUR TOTAL SUPPORT FOR THE COUNTRY'S PEACE PROCESS," VARGAS ADDED.

DEV-MUC3-0110 (BELLCORE)

LIMA, 9 MAR 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE ATTENDED BY FOREIGN CORRESPONDENTS, PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA SAID HERE TODAY THAT HE SUPPORTS THE CONSTRUCTION "OF NOT ONE BUT FIVE" INTERNATIONAL HIGHWAYS IN THE AMAZONIAN REGION.

ACCORDING TO PRESS REPORTS, THE UNITED STATES PRESSURED JAPAN NOT TO PROVIDE FINANCING FOR THE BRAZILIAN-PERUVIAN PROJECT.

GARCIA SAID HE WAS NOT AWARE THAT U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH HAD HELD TALKS WITH THE JAPANESE GOVERNMENT AT HIROHITO'S FUNERAL TO PREVENT THE FINANCING OF THE HIGHWAY.

SOME REPORTS SAID THAT BUSH HAD HELD TALKS WITH JAPANESE PRIME MINISTER NOBORU TAKESHITA ON THE NEED TO PRESERVE THE NATURAL ENVIRONMENT, ESPECIALLY THE AMAZON REGION, WHICH IS CONSIDERED THE "WORLD'S LUNGS."

THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT SAID: "PRESIDENT BUSH IS A POLITICIAN WITH WIDE EXPERIENCE. I DO NOT BELIEVE HE SAID SUCH A THING. IF HE DID SAY IT, IT WOULD BE VERY SERIOUS, BECAUSE HE WOULD BE INTERVENING IN OUR DOMESTIC AFFAIRS."

BRAZILIAN PRESIDENT JOSE SARNEY RECENTLY SAID THAT THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE INTERNATIONAL HIGHWAY IS "A MATTER OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY."

BRAZIL AND PERU ARE SPONSORING A PROJECT TO BUILD A HIGHWAY THROUGH THE AMAZON REGION TO JOIN THE BRAZILIAN NORTHWESTERN STATE OF ACRE AND THE PACIFIC OCEAN. BOTH COUNTRIES HAVE ASKED FOR JAPAN'S FINANCIAL SUPPORT FOR THE PROJECT.

IN PRACTICE, THE OBJECTIVE IS TO ESTABLISH A LAND CORRIDOR BETWEEN THE ATLANTIC AND PACIFIC OCEANS--AN OLD PROJECT OF THE BRAZILIAN MILITARY GEOSTRATEGISTS.

THE BRAZILIAN MILITARY MINISTERS SUPPORTED SARNEY'S POSITION BY ANNOUNCING THAT THEY WILL NOT ACCEPT "ANY TYPE OF FOREIGN FOREIGN INTERFERENCE IN THE AMAZON REGION" AND THAT THEY REJECTED AS "UNACCEPTABLE" THE ATTEMPTS TO LINK THE FOREIGN DEBT WITH INVESTMENTS TO PRESERVE THE AMAZON FOREST.

GARCIA INDICATED THAT IF THE UNITED STATES WANTS TO HELP PRESERVE THE ECOLOGICAL BALANCE, IT SHOULD "SPEED UP DISARMAMENT TALKS WITH THE SOVIET UNION." HE ADDED THAT "THE BEST WAY TO PROTECT THE AMAZON REGION IS TO ELIMINATE DEADLY WEAPONS AND NUCLEAR BOMBS."

GARCIA THEN REITERATED: "I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT PRESIDENT BUSH HAS SAID THAT, BUT IF HE SAID IT, I BELIEVE THAT IT IS A SERIOUS MATTER AND HE SHOULD GIVE US A CONCRETE OPINION."

GARCIA DEFENDED RELATIONS WITH BRAZIL BY SAYING: "I BELIEVE FORTIFYING ECONOMIC, SOCIAL, AND GEOGRAPHIC RELATIONS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES IS A NATIONAL OBJECTIVE." THEN HE ADDED: "BRAZIL IS ONE OF THE WORLD'S MOST IMPORTANT COUNTRIES, AND PERU HAS WRONGLY LIVED IN FEAR OF BRAZIL. LET US HOPE THAT NOT ONE BUT FIVE HIGHWAYS ARE BUILT THROUGH THE AMAZON REGION."

SIXTY PERCENT OF PERU'S 1.3 MILLION SQUARE KILOMETERS LIE IN THE AMAZON REGION. THAT MAKES UP NEARLY ONE-FIFTH OF THE ENTIRE AMAZON BASIN.

DEV-MUC3-0113 (BELLCORE)

BOGOTA, 26 OCT 89 -- [TEXT] DRUG TRAFFICKER JOSE GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, AKA "THE MEXICAN," HAS DENIED HE REQUESTED, THROUGH A LETTER, AN ALLIANCE WITH THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC).

THIS WAS STATED IN A LETTER ADDRESSED TO LA PRENSA DIRECTOR JUAN CARLOS PASTRANA. RODRIGUEZ GACHA SENT COPIES OF THIS LETTER TO ALL MEDIA.

THE TEXT OF THE LETTER FOLLOWS:

MR PASTRANA:

AN ARTICLE ON PAGE 1 OF YOUR 19 OCTOBER NEWSPAPER MAINTAINS THAT VERY RELIABLE SOURCES HAD DISCLOSED THAT JOSE GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA SENT A MESSAGE TO THE FARC LEADERS LAST WEEK PROPOSING AN ALLIANCE WITH THAT SUBVERSIVE GROUP.

THE TRUTH IS THAT SUCH A LETTER DOES NOT EXIST AND THAT I HAVE SENT NO MESSAGE TO ANY OF THE PEOPLE MENTIONED IN YOUR NEWSPAPER.

HOWEVER, THE WORST PART OF THIS IS THAT THE EVIL INTENTION OF THE ALLEGED WRITERS OF THE LETTER REACHES THE LIMIT BECAUSE THEY PORTRAY ME AS THE SELF-CONFESSED CULPRIT OF ALL CRIMES PERPETRATED AGAINST UP [PATRIOTIC UNION] LEADERS. IT IS TRUE I WAS ACCUSED OF THE [FORMER UP LEADER JAIME] PARDO LEAL ASSASSINATION. HOWEVER, THE COURTS HAVE ALREADY ISSUED A VERDICT OF NOT GUILTY. NO MAN HAS EVER BEEN PURSUED IN COLOMBIA WITH SUCH MALICE. IT SEEMS THAT THE ENTIRE PENAL CODE HAS FALLEN UPON ME, WHILE MY OPPONENTS ARE COMPLETELY IGNORED.

REGARDING THE REST OF THE LETTER, IT DOES NOT EVEN DESERVE MENTIONING BECAUSE SUCH A LETTER DOES NOT EXIST. THEREFORE, EVERYTHING IS FALSE. MOREOVER, ALL SECTORS ARE FULLY AWARE OF MY PRINCIPLES AND MY STRUGGLE TOWARD THE SO-CALLED FARC GROUPS.

I CLEARLY WANT TO STRESS MY AGREEMENT WITH THE PROPOSALS MADE BY THE M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT], ESPECIALLY THOSE DEALING WITH CEASING OFFENSIVE OPERATIONS AGAINST THE ARMED FORCES AND THE DEFINITE LAYING DOWN OF WEAPONS. THESE ARE THE FIRST STEPS TOWARD MAKING COLOMBIA SIT AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLE, WITH NO EXCLUSIONS.

THIS IS MY POSITION, AND THIS IS THE TRUTH. I AM AWARE THAT THE MISSION OF EACH ONE OF YOU, AS COLOMBIANS, IS TO BRING PEACE BACK TO COLOMBIA.

YOURS FAITHFULLY,

JOSE GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA

DEV-MUC3-0117 (BELLCORE)

SANTA FE (ARGENTINA), 4 MAY 88 (NA) -- [EXCERPT] TWO MEDIUM-SIZED BOMBS EXPLODED EARLY THIS MORNING AT THE HOUSE OF JUDGE GUILLERMO TORRE ALDAY AND AT THE OFFICES OF LAWYER LUIS ROSSMAN, A FORMER DIRECTOR OF THE SANTA FE PROVINCIAL BANK. THE EXPLOSIONS CAUSED SOME DAMAGE, BUT NO CASUALTIES.

JUDGE RAMIRO PUYOL IS CARRYING OUT THE INVESTIGATION INTO THE TWO CASES, BUT SO FAR THERE HAVE BEEN NO POSITIVE RESULTS.

THE TWO BOMBS EXPLODED ONLY MINUTES APART AND CAUSED MINOR DAMAGE TO THE WALLS OF THE TWO PREMISES. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES.

ACCORDING TO SEVERAL MEMBERS OF THE BOMB SQUAD OF THE LOCAL POLICE, THE TWO BOMBS WERE PLANTED WITH THE EXCLUSIVE PURPOSE OF INTIMIDATING THE OWNERS OF THE PREMISES.

THIS AFTERNOON SOURCES CLOSE TO THE INVESTIGATION ANNOUNCED THAT BOTH ATTACKS HAD THE INTENTION OF "FRIGHTENING" TORRE ALDAY AND ROSSMAN, WHO WAS DIRECTOR OF THE PROVINCIAL BANK OF SANTA FE DURING GOVERNOR JOSE VERNET'S TENURE.

IT HAS BEEN LEARNED THAT BOTH TORRE ALDAY AND ROSSMAN ARE LINKED TO THE BANKRUPTCY CASES OF SOME LOCAL ENTERPRISES. THEREFORE, IT IS THOUGHT THAT THE ATTACKS HAD THE INTENTION OF INTIMIDATING BOTH MEN.

JUDGE PUYOL IMMEDIATELY BEGAN HIS INVESTIGATION INTO THE TWO CASES, WHICH, ACCORDING TO SOME MEMBERS OF THE BOMB SQUAD, "DO NOT HAVE ANY POLITICAL IMPLICATIONS." [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0118 (BELLCORE)

GUATEMALA CITY, 20 MAY 88 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALA'S CLANDESTINE ORGANIZATION "SECRET ANTICOMMUNIST ARMY" (ESA) HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR WEDNESDAY'S TERRORIST ATTACK AGAINST THE RESIDENCE AND OFFICE OF ALEKSANDR TRUSHIN, TASS CORRESPONDENT IN GUATEMALA.

AN ESA BULLETIN DISTRIBUTED TO THE NEWS MEDIA STATES THAT THE ATTACK AGAINST THE SOVIET NEWS AGENCY "WAS TO EXPRESS REJECTION OF THE SOCIALIST-LEANING MEASURES" ADOPTED BY THE VINICIO CEREZO AREVALO GOVERNMENT.

THE DOCUMENT EXPLAINS THAT "THIS IS A WARNING," BECAUSE IF ARREST WARRANTS ARE ISSUED FOR THE FIVE CIVILIANS INVOLVED IN THE ABORTIVE 11 MAY COUP, "ACTIONS WILL BE UNDERTAKEN AGAINST MEMBERS OF THE GUATEMALAN CHRISTIAN DEMOCRACY," WHICH IS THE RULING PARTY.

THE ATTACK, CARRIED OUT WITH TWO BOMBS, WAS PERPETRATED AGAINST THE SOVIET NEWSMAN'S HOME, LOCATED IN A RESIDENTIAL AREA SOUTH OF THIS CITY. THIS OCCURRED ON 18 MAY.

THE EXPLOSIVE DEVICES WERE HURLED FROM AN AUTOMOBILE. IT DESTROYED AN ENTRANCE AND WINDOWS OF THE HOME AS WELL AS TRUSHIN'S CAR. HOWEVER, NEITHER TRUSHIN NOR HIS WIFE WERE INJURED.

THE COMMUNIQUE BY ESA, A PARAMILITARY ORGANIZATION THAT EMERGED IN THE 1960'S, ADDS THAT IT "WILL NOT REST UNTIL THE COMMUNIST AGGRESSION HAS BEEN STOPPED AND ITS DEFEAT ACHIEVED."

IT ALSO SAYS THAT "THE CURRENT GOVERNMENT IS PROMOTING REVOLUTION. IF IT WANTS WAR, IT WILL HAVE WAR BECAUSE WE ARE READY TO DIE AND TO FIGHT AGAINST COMMUNISM ANY TIME."

THE DOCUMENT, SIGNED BY COMMANDERS "UBICO TOROKZIK" AND "RAFAEL NETANAGIUHI," SAYS THAT DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL HECTOR GRAMEJO, FOREIGN MINISTER ALFONSO CABRERA, AND PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO AREVALO PLANNED THE COUP.

ACCORDING TO THIS COMMUNIQUE, IN THE RECENT TRIP TO CUBA BY RAQUEL BLANDON, WIFE OF PRESIDENT CEREZO AREVALO, SHE MET WITH LIBYAN AHMAD MUSTAFA [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] "TO ASK HIM FOR ECONOMIC SUPPORT FOR THE NEXT GENERAL ELECTIONS IN 1990."

ESA IS OPPOSED TO THE ISSUANCE OF ARREST WARRANTS AGAINST MARIO DAVID GARCIA, DANILO ROCA, NICOLAS BUONAFINA, GUSTAVO ANZUETO VIELMAN, AND MARIO CASTEJON. THESE ARE THE CIVILIANS WHOM THE CEREZO AREVALO GOVERNMENT HAS ACCUSED OF INVOLVEMENT IN THE COUP ATTEMPT.

THIS GROUP STRESSES THAT THE ATTEMPT WAS A "PLOY PROMOTED BY GEN HECTOR GRAMEJO. THAT IS THE BASEST THING THAT THE DEFENSE MINISTER COULD HAVE DONE: TO SELL HIMSELF AND HIS MILITARY COLLEAGUES."

ESA MEMBERS DESCRIBE THEMSELVES AS "GUATEMALA'S PROGRESSIVE PATRIOTS," AND THEY REAFFIRM THAT THE ATTACK ON THE TASS MISSION "WAS A WARNING."

DEV-MUC3-0120 (BELLCORE)

LIMA, 19 MAY 88 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [TEXT] TODAY THE NATIONAL CENTER SECURITY ZONE COMMAND DENIED THE KILLING OF PEASANTS IN CAYARA, AYACUCHO. THE COMMAND ISSUED THE FOLLOWING OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE:

1. AT 2300 ON 23 [AS HEARD] MAY, NEAR CAYARA, VICTOR FAJARDO PROVINCE, AYACUCHO DEPARTMENT, A GROUP OF APPROXIMATELY 100 SUBVERSIVES AMBUSHED A TWO-VEHICLE ARMY PATROL ON A RELIEF OPERATION BETWEEN THE TOWNS OF SAN PEDRO DE GUAILLAS AND HUANCAPI.

2. THE FOLLOWING MEMBERS OF THE PERUVIAN ARMY DIED AS A RESULT OF THIS CRIMINAL ATTACK: CAPTAIN JOSE URBULU SIMO, SECOND SERGEANT ANGEL VARGAS SAMARA, AND CORPORALS FAVIAN ROLDAN ORTIZ AND CARLOS ESPINOZA DE LA CRUZ. FIFTEEN ARMY PERSONNEL WERE ALSO WOUNDED DURING THE ATTACK, FOUR OF THEM SERIOUSLY. THE CAPTAIN AND OTHER PERSONNEL KILLED DURING THE OPERATION WERE BURIED ON 16 MAY IN LIMA AND HUARAS, RESPECTIVELY.

THE ARMY PERSONNEL KILLED SIX UNIDENTIFIED SUBVERSIVES WHILE REPELLING THE ATTACK. THE EVIDENCE INDICATES THAT AN UNSPECIFIED NUMBER OF SUBVERSIVES WERE ALSO WOUNDED.

3. PERUVIAN ARMY REINFORCEMENT PATROLS PURSUED THE SUBVERSIVE COLUMN, WHICH TOOK FLIGHT IN THE DIRECTION OF CAYARA. THE PATROL FOUND THE TOWN COMPLETELY EMPTY AND ABANDONED WITH THE EXCEPTION OF SOME CHILDREN AND OLD PEOPLE WHO REPORTED THAT FOUR DEAD BODIES WERE LEFT IN THE TOWN'S CHURCH.

4. DURING THE SEARCH OPERATION AROUND CAYARA, THE PATROLS CLASHED WITH SUBVERSIVES AND KILLED AN UNSPECIFIED NUMBER.

5. ON 16 MAY THE POLITICAL-MILITARY COMMAND REPORTED THE ATTACK TO THE PROSECUTOR'S OFFICE IN AYACUCHO AND ASKED THE COURT TO INTERVENE. THE PERUVIAN ARMY HAS ALSO BEGUN AN INQUIRY INTO THE MATTER.

6. THE FALSE REPORT BY LOCAL AUTHORITIES OF THE KILLING OF A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE FROM CAYARA IS COMPLETELY GROUNDLESS. THE REPORT OF AN ALLEGED BOMBARDMENT IS ALSO FALSE. ALL THIS HAS THE SOLE PURPOSE OF HINDERING THE ACTION OF THE FORCES OF ORDER WHO ARE TRYING TO CAPTURE THE CRIMINAL SUBVERSIVES WHO AMBUSHED THE ARMY PATROL.

7. THE SEARCH OPERATION CONTINUES AND THE RESULTS WILL BE REPORTED AS SOON AS THEY BECOME KNOWN.

LIMA, 18 MAY 1988

[SIGNED] PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICE, NATIONAL CENTER SECURITY ZONE COMMAND

DEV-MUC3-0121 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 15 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] WE INFORM THE WORKING CLASS, STUDENTS, AND SALVADORAN PEOPLE IN GENERAL: AS OF 16 MARCH, THE DATE SET BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] TO BEGIN ITS NATIONAL TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE, ALL OUR MILITIA UNITS WILL BE IN FIGHTING SPIRITS AND WILL ATTACK TRANSPORTATION VEHICLES SUCH AS TAXIS, MINIBUSES, PICKUP TRUCKS, GOVERNMENT VEHICLES, BUSES, [WORDS INDISTINCT], AND ALL VEHICLES THAT DO NOT ABIDE BY THE STOPPAGE. WE WILL BURN AND BLOW UP VEHICLES.

WE WARN THE POPULATION NOT TO RIDE MILITARY VEHICLES, BECAUSE THEY WILL BE AMBUSHED. IN EMERGENCY CASES AT NIGHT OR EARLY IN THE MORNING, PEOPLE SHOULD RIDE PRIVATE OR FIRST-AID VEHICLES AND SHOULD DISPLAY A WHITE FLAG. WE ALSO URGE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE NOT TO VOTE, BECAUSE THAT VOTE WILL CONTRIBUTE TO WORSEN THE WAR AND WILL SUPPORT THE COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN OF THE YANKEE IMPERIALISTS' AND THEIR SERVILE LOCAL AUTHORITIES.

IT HAS BEEN PROVED THAT NEITHER THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY NOR THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE WANT A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE WAR. IN RESPONSE TO THEIR REFUSAL, LET US NOT VOTE IN THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS; LET US VOTE IN THE 15 SEPTEMBER ELECTIONS.

THAT MUST BE THE PEOPLE'S RESPONSE TO THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS. THE BALLOT BOXES AND THEIR RESPECTIVE [WORD INDISTINCT] WILL BE SABOTAGED, AND PERSONNEL PARTICIPATING IN THAT ELECTION GAME WILL BE SUBSEQUENTLY ANNIHILATED, BECAUSE THEIR PARTICIPATION MEANS THEY AGREE WITH THE ELECTIONS AND SUPPORT THE WORSENING OF THE WAR.

NO TO THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS, BECAUSE THEY ARE A DEMAGOGIC AND FRAUDULENT MANEUVER AND BECAUSE THEY ARE A DENIAL OF PEACE.

DEV-MUC3-0123 (BELLCORE)

SANTIAGO, 14 MAR 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] AGRICULTURE MINISTER JAIME DE LA SOTTA AND FOREIGN MINISTER HERNAN FELIPE ERRAZURIZ WILL LEAVE TONIGHT FOR THE UNITED STATES IN AN ATTEMPT TO ACHIEVE THE LIFTING OF THE BAN ON IMPORTED CHILEAN FRUITS. THEY WILL TAKE LAN-CHILE FLIGHT 141 THAT DEPARTS AT APPROXIMATELY 2100 FROM SANTIAGO AND GOES DIRECTLY TO NEW YORK.

IN NEW YORK, THE TWO MINISTERS WILL TAKE ANOTHER PLANE TO WASHINGTON AND WILL ARRIVE AT APPROXIMATELY NOON TOMORROW. IN THE U.S. CAPITAL THEY WILL MEET WITH OFFICIALS OF THE FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION.

THE MAIN OBJECTIVE OF THE TRIP IS TO ACHIEVE THE LIFTING OF THE BAN ON IMPORTED CHILEAN FRUITS. U.S. OFFICIALS ANNOUNCED THE BAN OVER AN UNUSUAL TELEVISION NETWORK FOLLOWING THE DISCOVERY THAT SOME CHILEAN GRAPES WERE LACED CYANIDE. DE LA SOTTA STATED THAT THIS IS AN EXAMPLE OF THE DAMAGE THAT TERRORISM CAN CAUSE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DE LA SOTTA] YOU CAN SEE AND MEASURE THE SCOPE OF A TERRORIST ACT SUCH AS THE ONE WE HAVE JUST EXPERIENCED, THE SOLE OBJECTIVE OF WHICH IS TO CAUSE HARM. THIS CAN BE DEMONSTRATED BY THE ADVERTISEMENT, NOT A CLEAR AND CONCRETE ADVERTISEMENT, BUT AN ANONYMOUS TELEPHONE CALL BY WHICH THEY WARNED US, THAT IS, THEY WARNED THE EMBASSIES THEY CALLED, THAT THEY WOULD CARRY OUT SUCH AN ACT. THIS CALL WAS MADE 3 DAYS AFTER THE DEPARTURE OF THE FRUIT SHIPMENT. WE ATTEMPTED TO CONTROL THE SITUATION TO THE EXTENT POSSIBLE, FOLLOWING TECHNICAL PROCEDURES CONCERNING THE AMOUNT OF SAMPLES TAKEN. THEN WE ANNOUNCED THAT THE SITUATION WAS UNDER CONTROL, THAT IT WAS AN ANOMYOUS CALL AND AS SUCH COULD NOT BE TAKEN SERIOUSLY. LATER, IN THE SHIPMENTS THAT ARRIVED IN THE UNITED STATES LAST WEEKEND, THE PRESENCE OF CYANIDE WAS DETECTED IN TWO GRAPES. [END RECORDING]

DE LA SOTTA ADDED THAT ALL POSSIBLE EFFORTS WILL BE MADE TO OVERCOME THE IMPASSE. THE MAJOR PROBLEM NOW INVOLVES THE 17 MILLION BOXES THAT ARRIVED AT THEIR PORTS OF DESTINATION READY FOR DISTRIBUTION. NOW NO ONE KNOWS WHAT TO DO WITH THEM. THERE ARE 7 OR 8 MILLION BOXES MORE BEING SHIPPED TO THE SAME PORTS, AND 3 MILLION BOXES REMAIN IN THE COUNTRY, READY TO BE SHIPPED. DE LA SOTTA SAID THAT THE CYANIDE WAS FOUND IN TWO SINGLE GRAPES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DE LA SOTTA] THE ESSENTIAL THING, I BELIEVE, IS [WORDS INDISTINCT] THAT THE UNITED STATES CAN ADOPT MEASURES. WE WILL TALK WITH THE HEALTH OFFICIALS TO GIVE THEM THE NECESSARY ASSURANCES SO THEY CAN LIFT THE BAN AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. [END RECORDING]

IN ORDER TO FACE THE PROBLEM, THE GOVERNMENT HAS CREATED THREE COMISSIONS TO STUDY THE DIFFERENT ASPECTS OF THE PROBLEM, THE AGRICULTURE MINISTER STATED.

DEV-MUC3-0124 (BELLCORE)

SANTIAGO, 14 MAR 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] MANUEL FELIU, CHAIRMAN OF THE INDUSTRY AND TRADE CONFEDERATION, HAS ESTIMATED THAT THE LOSSES CAUSED BY THE ACT OF ECONOMIC TERRORISM AGAINST OUR COUNTRY WILL BE MORE THAN $880 MILLION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [FELIU] IT IS THE RESULT OF A TERRORIST BOYCOTT. IT IS THE BEGINNING OF A BOYCOTT. ALL CHILEANS MUST UNITE AGAINST THIS PROBLEM BECAUSE IT AFFECTS ALL OF US, NOT ONLY THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT.

[REPORTER] WHAT ECONOMIC DAMAGE CAN THIS BOYCOTT CAUSE THE CHILEAN FRUIT INDUSTRY?

[FELIU] THE DAMAGE IS ENORMOUS. IT CAN AMOUNT TO MORE THAN $800 [AS HEARD] MILLION IN EXPENSES BEFORE THE END OF THIS EXPORTING SEASON. THIS HUGE LOSS WILL CREATE ALL TYPES OF PROBLEMS, NOT ONLY FOR THE FARMERS, EXPORTERS, AND FINANCIAL SECTOR, BUT ALSO FOR THE SEA AND AIR TRANSPORTATION INDUSTRY, THE INSURANCE INDUSTRY, AND ALL SECTORS OF THE NATIONAL ECONOMY RELATED TO FRUIT EXPORT ACTIVITIES.

IN SHORT, IT CAUSES A SERIES OF HUGE PROBLEMS FOR THE WORKERS, THE BUSINESSMEN, AND ALL PEOPLE INVOLVED IN THOSE EXPORTS IN ONE WAY OR THE OTHER. [END RECORDING]

FELIU MADE THESE COMMENTS AT THE END OF A VISIT HE MADE TO THE PRODUCTION, TRADE, AND AGRICULTURAL UNIONS TO OFFER HIS SOLIDARITY TO MEMBERS OF THE AGRICULTURAL SECTOR.

DEV-MUC3-0125 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 MAR 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] URBAN COMMANDOS DESTROYED A TRUCK OWNED BY TROPICAL SODA COMPANY AT APPROXIMATELY 0730 TODAY ON THE MAIN ROAD OF DOLORES NEIGHBORHOOD.

THE STRONG EXPLOSION, WHICH DESTROYED THE FRONT PART OF THE TRUCK, CAUSED MINOR PROPERTY DAMAGE TO NEARBY HOUSES AND TO VEHICLES PARKED IN THE AREA. THE INFORMATION RELEASED INDICATES THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION AND ADDS THAT THREE YOUNG MEN PLACED THE DYNAMITE CHARGE AND WARNED THE DRIVER TO LEAVE THE AREA.

ACCORDING TO RESIDENTS OF THE AREA, A BEER TRUCK WAS ALSO BLOWN UP 3 DAYS AGO IN THAT SAME PLACE. THAT TRUCK WAS OWNED BY LA CONSTANCIA BEER COMPANY.

IN ADDITION, AN AGRICULTURE MINISTRY VEHICLE WAS PARTIALLY DESTROYED BY A DYNAMITE CHARGE. THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE AT THE CORNER OF ROOSEVELT AVE AND 53TH AVENUE SOUTH NEAR THE AGRICULTURE MINISTRY AT APPROXIMATELY 0900.

ACCORDING TO A WITNESS, THE DYNAMITE CHARGE WAS PLACED BY A YOUNG MAN WHO LEFT IN A WHITE PICKUP TRUCK THAT WAS WAITING FOR HIM ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THE STREET. THE DESTROYED VEHICLE BELONGED TO THE AGRICULTURE MINISTRY PROJECT DEPARTMENT.

ALTHOUGH WE COULD NOT CONFIRM THIS REPORT, AGRICULTURE MINISTRY EMPLOYEES ASSERTED THAT A VENDOR WALKING ON THE AREA WAS WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION. WINDOWS OF NEARBY BUILDINGS AND THE WINDSHIELD OF ANOTHER MINISTRY VEHICLE WERE ALSO BROKEN AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION. NO ORGANIZATION CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS ATTACK, ALTHOUGH IT WAS SAID THAT THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY HAS BEEN USING THOSE VEHICLES FOR ITS POLITICAL CAMPAIGN.

ANOTHER REPORT STATED TWO GAS STATIONS WERE SABOTAGED BY FMLN URBAN COMMANDOS IN SEVERAL PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR, WITHOUT INFLICTING ANY CASUALTIES. ONE OF THE GAS STATIONS IS LOCATED ON THE ROAD LEADING TO SAN ANTONIO ABAD. A FOUR-PERSON REBEL GROUP PLACED A POWERFUL BOMB INSIDE THE GAS STATION OFFICE AT APPROXIMATELY 1600, CAUSING SERIOUS PROPERTY DAMAGE.

THE OFFICE AND EQUIPMENT OF THE SECOND GAS STATION, KNOWN AS TEXACO - LOS CONGOS, WAS ALSO SERIOUSLY DAMAGED AS A RESULT OF TWO EXPLOSIONS.

IN ADDITION, A PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION BUS WAS STOPPED ON THE ROAD TO MONTSERRAT. THE INCIDENT DID NOT CAUSE ANY PROPERTY DAMAGE BUT DID CAUSE FEAR AMONG AREA RESIDENTS.

OFFICIAL SOURCES ADDED THAT TWO PARAMILITARY MEN WERE MURDERED BY FMLN UNITS EARLY THIS MORNING IN THE NORTHERN END OF SAN SALVADOR.

THE REPORT INDICATES ANGEL MARROQUIN HERNANDEZ AND JOSE ANGEL FLORES, MEMBERS OF THE SANTO DOMINGO CANTON CIVIL DEFENSE, WERE ABDUCTED AND SUBSEQUENTLY MURDERED BY THE REBELS NEAR [NAME INDISTINCT] BRIDGE, GUAZAPA JURISDICTION. IN ADDITION, THREE TREASURY POLICE MEMBERS WERE WOUNDED DURING A REBEL ATTACK LAST NIGHT. THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE ON ARMY BOULEVARD. FINALLY, A MINOR WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED THIS MORNING AFTER URBAN COMMANDOS DETONATED A BOMB NEAR A POWER TOWER IN SOYAPANGO CITY.

DEV-MUC3-0129 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 15 MAR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE PEACE PROPOSAL PRESENTED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] GENERAL COMMAND SPARKED A DEBATE OF UNPRECEDENTED BROADNESS AND DURATION TO ATTAIN A NATIONAL AGREEMENT TO SOLVE THE CONFLICT. THE PROGRESS ACHIEVED MUST BE INCREASED, STRENGTHENING THE UNITY AND BROAD SUPPORT OF SECTORS THAT ADVOCATE PEACE WITH SOCIAL JUSTICE AND NATIONAL INDEPENDENCE.

IN THIS PROCESS, WE HAVE SHOWN FLEXIBILITY TOWARD PROPOSALS PRESENTED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE POLITICAL PARTIES. NEVERTHELESS, THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY (PDC), ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE], AND THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND HAVE CLOSED THE DOOR TO THE POSSIBILITY OF HOLDING ELECTIONS WITHOUT WAR, IN CONDITIONS OF CLEANLINESS AND EQUALITY THAT WOULD TURN THEM INTO AN OPPORTUNITY TO SOLVE THE CONFLICT. THEY INSISTED ON HOLDING THE ELECTIONS AS PART OF MILITARY PLAN THAT TRIES TO APPEAR TO BE DEMOCRATIC TO JUSTIFY TO THE U.S. CONGRESS WHY THERE SHOULD BE CONTINUED SHIPMENTS OF WEAPONS AND MORE MILLIONS IN AID.

THERE WILL BE NEW ELECTION FRAUD AND DISPUTES BETWEEN THOSE WHO MURDERED MONSIGNOR [OSCAR ARNULFO] ROMERO AND MASSACRED 70,000 SALVADORANS, AND THE VORACIOUS CORRUPT DEVOURERS OF MILLIONS WHO HAVE MORTGAGED THE COUNTRY'S SOVEREIGNTY. A FRAUD WILL TAKE PLACE IN A MILITARIZED COUNTRY, WHERE MORE THAN HALF OF THE MUNICIPAL OFFICES ARE NOT FUNCTIONING, AND WHERE THE MILITARY MANIPULATES THE BALLOT BOXES, VOTES, AND RESULTS -- AND THEY WILL DO IT AGAIN, AS THEY HAVE ALWAYS DONE.

WITHIN THIS FRAMEWORK, WE HAVE THE LEGITIMATE RIGHT TO SUPPORT THE PEOPLE'S FEELINGS AND REJECT THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS, URGING THEM TO FIGHT AND REJECT THE ATTEMPTS TO TURN THE ELECTIONS INTO AN INSTRUMENT TO CONTINUE THE WAR, URGING THEM NOT TO VOTE OR TO VOID THEIR BALLOT. THE ELECTIONS WILL ATTEMPT TO LEGITIMIZE THE WAR, AND THEY WILL BE HELD IN THE MIDST OF A WAR. THE ARMED FORCES WILL BE BOMBING CIVILIANS; THE POLICE WILL BE CAPTURING, TORTURING, AND ASSASSINATING; THE JAILS WILL AGAIN BE FILLED WITH POLITICAL PRISONERS. PSYCHOLOGICAL WARFARE WILL BE LAUNCHED BY THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND BY WAVING THE SPECTER OF GENOCIDE OVER THE POPULATION; THIS AMID THE DRAMATIC POVERTY OF THE DEPRIVED MASSES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0130 (BELLCORE)

SANTIAGO, 16 MAR 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] IN THE PRESENCE OF SOME 50 MEMBERS OF THE PARTIES THAT COMPRISE IT, THE CENTER-RIGHT POLITICAL COALITION COALICION POLITICA DE CENTRO DERECHA HAS BEEN OFFICIALLY FORMED. THE CEREMONY, HELD AT THE NATIONAL PARTY HEADQUARTERS IN THE OLD AND VENERABLE FERNANDEZ CONCHA CLUB, WAS PRESIDED OVER BY SERGIO ONOFRE JARPA, PATRICIO PHILLIPS, AND JAIME TORMO.

DURING THE CEREMONY, RADICAL DEMOCRATIC PARTY HEAD JAIME TORMO SAID THAT THE THREE PARTIES WILL NOW START ANALYZING THEIR COMMON POSITIONS, UNDER THE EFFECTIVE COORDINATION OF NATIONAL RENEWAL SECRETARY ANDRES ALLAMAND.

JORGE MARTINEZ, OF THE NATIONAL PARTY THEN READ A JOINT DECLARATION. THE THREE PARTIES REPORTED THAT ONE OF THEIR GOALS IS TO RESTORE THE MIDDLE CLASS'S DIGNITY AND ITS OPPORTUNITIES FOR JOBS, BECAUSE THIS CLASS HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE GREATEST SPONSOR OF NATIONAL INTELLECTUAL, MATERIAL, AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT.

ANOTHER GOAL IS TO PREVENT THE COALITION FROM BECOMING A SUPER PARTY OR MERGING WITH OTHER PARTIES. THIS COALITION WILL CONTINUE TO EXIST AS SUCH, AND ITS OBJECTIVE IS TO PROMOTE COOPERATION, BOTH AMONG MEMBER PARTIES AND WITH PARTIES THAT MAY WANT TO JOIN THEM IN THE FUTURE.

THE FIRST OFFICIAL ACT OF THE CENTER-RIGHT POLITICAL COALITION WAS TO SEND A CABLE TO U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH TO POINT OUT THE SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES OF THE MEASURES THE UNITED STATES HAS ADOPTED AGAINST CHILEAN FRUITS.

THE CABLE, WHICH WAS READ BY ANDRES ALLAMAND, STATED:

[BEGIN RECORDING] IN VIEW OF THE GROUNDLESS AND EXAGGERATED MEASURES TAKEN BY SOME MEMBERS OF YOUR ADMINISTRATION AGAINST CHILEAN FRUIT EXPORTS, WE CALL YOUR ATTENTION TO THE FACT THAT THESE MEASURES WILL RUIN A LARGE SECTOR OF CHILEAN PRIVATE ENTEPRISE, WILL LEAVE HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF WORKERS JOBLESS, AND WILL CAUSE A SERIOUS IMBALANCE IN OUR BALANCE OF PAYMENTS. THESE MEASURES WILL SERIOUSLY AFFECT THE GOOD RELATIONS THE CHILEAN PEOPLE HAVE ALWAYS HAD WITH THE U.S. PEOPLE, AND THEY WILL DEEPLY INJURE THOSE WHO, LIKE US, DEFEND FREE ECONOMY AND FREE TRADE.

MOST SERIOUS, HOWEVER, IS THE FACT THAT THESE MEASURES APPARENTLY REWARD THE TERRORIST ACTIVITIES AGAINST CHILE, BECAUSE THEY HELP THE TERRORISTS ACHIEVE THEIR GOALS. [END RECORDING]

THE CABLE ADDS THAT CHILE HAS EARNED JUSTIFIED PRESTIGE AS A SERIOUS AND EFFECTIVE EXPORTER; THAT IT HAS BEEN HONORING ITS FOREIGN DEBT AT A SACRIFICE; AND THAT IT HAS COOPERATED IN SEVERAL PUBLIC WELFARE PROJECTS SPONSORED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT. IN VIEW OF ALL THAT, THE COALITION REQUESTS AN URGENT SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEM.

DEV-MUC3-0131 (BELLCORE)

TEGUCIGALPA, 13 MAR 89 (LA TRIBUNA) -- [REPORT] [ROSE MARY TORRES DE GONZALEZ] [TEXT] A GUERRILLA UNIT THAT OPERATED IN THE MERENDON MOUNTAIN RANGE, IN THE OMOA HILLS AREA, 100 KM NORTHWEST OF SAN PEDRO SULA ON THE GUATEMALAN BORDER, WAS DISMANTLED OVER THE WEEKEND BY COMBINED NATIONAL ARMY UNITS.

MEMBERS OF THE II ARTILLERY BATTALION, SPECIAL TACTICAL BATTALION, II INFANTRY BATTALION, AND III INFANTRY BATTALION PARTICIPATED IN THE OPERATION. ACCORDING TO LOCAL RESIDENTS, THE ARMY CAPTURED EIGHT ALLEGED SUBVERSIVES AND SEIZED SUPPLIES, MILITARY UNIFORMS, AND MARXIST LITERATURE.

LA TRIBUNA VISITED CUYAMEL, RIO CHIQUITO, TEGUCIGALPITA, COMAYAGUA, CUYAMELITO, POTRERILLOS, SAN CARLOS, CORINTO, AND QUEBRADA SECA IN CORTES DEPARTMENT, WHERE THE PEOPLE WERE OBVIOUSLY WORRIED BECAUSE THEY COULD NOT EXPLAIN THE MILITARY MOVEMENTS.

THE VILLAGES WERE MILITARIZED ON TUESDAY LAST WEEK WHILE SPECIALISTS IN ANTIGUERRILLA TACTICS WERE DEPLOYED TO "COMB" THE LOCAL MOUNTAINS.

ACCORDING TO LOCAL RESIDENTS, THE EIGHT ALLEGED GUERRILLA MEMBERS -- WHO WERE CAPTURED AND LATER TAKEN BY HELICOPTER TO THE 105TH INFANTRY BRIGADE HEADQUARTERS IN SAN PEDRO SULA -- REPORTEDLY INCLUDED AN OLD MAN AND A MINOR. THE PEOPLE ADDED THAT STRANGE PEOPLE COME DOWN FROM THE MOUNTAINS AT SUNDOWN, REPORTEDLY IN SEARCH OF FOOD.

THE PEOPLE STATED THAT SOMEONE TIPPED OFF THE POLICE TO THE ACTIVITIES OF THE SUSPICIOUS LOOKING PERSONS WHO CAME FROM THE MOUNTAINS. CONSEQUENTLY, THE ARMY SET UP AN AIR LIFT. THE LANDING STRIP WAS LOCATED IN A CLEARING NEAR THE TOWN OF PUEBLO NUEVO.

MILITARY VEHICLES WERE FREQUENTLY SEEN WITH SOLDIERS COMING OR GOING TO THE MOUNTAINS. "PAINTED - FACE" SOLDIERS WERE SEEN GOING TO THE MOUNTAINS, WHICH THEY "COMBED" UNTIL THEY REACHED PINALEJO, SANTA BARBARA.

"THE SILENCE IN THESE MOUNTAINS WAS SOMETIMES DISRUPTED BY SHOTS AND WE WERE AFRAID. WE HAD NO OTHER CHOICE BUT TO COVER OURSELVES FROM HEAD TO TOE," AN OLD MAN, WHO WAS TOO AFRAID TO REVEAL HIS NAME, STATED.

DURING THE DAY, THE PEOPLE MINGLE WITH THE MEN IN UNIFORM, WHO SOMETIMES STOP PEOPLE TO ASK WHERE THEY COME FROM AND CAREFULLY SEARCH VEHICLES -- PARTICULARLY WHEN TRAVELING TO AND FROM THE MILITARIZED COMMUNITIES.

COLONEL ERICK O'CONNOR, COMMANDER OF THE 105TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, ARRIVED ON SATURDAY TO INSPECT THE AREA WHERE THE OPERATION HAS BEEN CARRIED OUT. HE REFUSED TO ISSUE A STATEMENT WHEN APPROACHED BY LA TRIBUNA'S REPORTERS, BUT ANNOUNCED THAT THE COMMAND POST WOULD ISSUE AN OFFICIAL REPORT TODAY.

DEV-MUC3-0133 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 17 MAR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAS DECIDED TO COMBINE THE PEOPLE'S REJECTION OF THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS WITH AN INTENSIFICATION OF ACTIONS THROUGHOUT THE NATION. THIS INCLUDES THE NATIONWIDE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE, WHICH WE NOW DECLARE TO BE INDEFINITE.

THE REJECTION OF THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS BY OUR PEOPLE AND THE IMPACT OF OUR ACTIONS HAVE LED THE REGIME TO LAUNCH A CAMPAIGN OF DISINFORMATION, AGGRESSION, AND THREATS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN A BID TO CONFUSE THE POPULATION AND, IN ADDITION, TO SET THE STAGE FOR AN ELECTORAL FRAUD.

IN ORDER TO MAKE MATTERS CLEAR TO OUR PEOPLE AS WELL AS TO THE LOCAL AND INTERNATIONAL PRESS, WE REPORT THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE GAGGING OF THE NATIONAL PRESS IS PART OF THE PLAN TO COVER UP THE FRAUD THAT WILL BE COMMITTED ON 19 MARCH. IN ADDITION, THE CONTROL OVER THE MEDIA IS INTENDED TO ATTRIBUTE TERRORIST ACTIONS TO THE FMLN.

2. THE REGIME HAS TRIED TO BLAME US FOR A NUMBER OF ACTIONS, SUCH AS THE ATTACK ON A RED CROSS AMBULANCE, AMONG OTHERS, FOR THE SAME PURPOSE. THE FMLN HAS A DEFINITE POLICY OF NOT HARMING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THE HURLING OF GRENADES AT BUS STOPS IS A COMMON PRACTICE OF ARMY PERSONNEL AND IT IS THEREFORE PREPOSTEROUS TO BLAME THE FMLN.

3. A NUMBER OF FALSE COMMUNIQUES WITH AN OBVIOUS TERRORIST TONE HAVE APPEARED. THEY CLUMSILY GLORIFY VIOLENCE AND THREATEN THE PRESS IN TERMS THAT ARE QUITE UNLIKE THOSE APPEARING IN DOCUMENTS IN WHICH WE OUTLINE OUR OFFICIAL POSITION. WE EMPHATICALLY STATE THAT THE FMLN HAS IN NO WAY OR AT ANY TIME THREATENED THE PRESS OR THE CITIZENS. WE RECALL THE FACT THAT OUR OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUES ARE SIGNED BY OUR GENERAL COMMAND AND BROADCAST THROUGH OUR STATIONS.

WE REITERATE THAT THE FUNDAMENTAL THING AT THIS TIME IS TO REINFORCE AND EXPAND UNITY IN THE SEARCH FOR PEACE THROUGH EVERY POSSIBLE MEANS. THE STRUGGLE WHICH WE ARE WAGING WITH WEAPONS IN HAND IS AIMED AT AN ARMY THAT HAS ONCE MORE DENIED TO OUR NATION THE POSSIBILITY OF FINDING A FORMULA FOR A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION AT AN IMPORTANT CROSSROADS IN THE NATION'S HISTORY.

WE MADE A PROPOSAL TO HOLD FREE ELECTIONS, IN PEACE AND FOR PEACE, BUT THE ARMY STUBBORNLY INSISTS ON HOLDING FRAUDULENT ELECTIONS, AT WAR AND FOR WAR. CONSEQUENTLY, THE ELECTIONS WILL BE HELD DURING WAR.

DEV-MUC3-0134 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [TEXT] WE ARE GOING TO GIVE YOU A REPORT ON SOMETHING THAT HAPPENED A FEW MINUTES AGO IN THE CENTER OF SAN SALVADOR. WE HAVE ON THE TELEPHONE A LISTENER WHO IS GOING TO TELL US ABOUT TWO EXPLOSIONS JUST BEFORE NOON THAT LEFT AT LEAST FIVE PERSONS WOUNDED. PLEASE GO AHEAD WITH THE REPORT.

[LISTENER] SONORA LISTENERS, THIS IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT. JUST A FEW MINUTES AGO, AT 1130, TWO BOMBS EXPLODED HERE AT THE EASTERN END OF THE CENTRAL MARKET. FIVE PERSONS WERE SERIOUSLY WOUNDED IN THIS TERRORIST ATTACK. THEY WERE JUST TAKEN TO THE ROSALES HOSPITAL. THE WOUNDED INCLUDE A CHILD AND A WOMAN. WE DID NOT GET THEIR NAMES BECAUSE THE AUTHORITIES DID NOT LET US DO SO. RED CROSS PERSONNEL TOOK THE WOUNDED TO ROSALES HOSPITAL.

THE PEOPLE AROUND HERE ARE VERY FRIGHTENED AND ARE RUNNING AROUND. THE PEOPLE WERE BUYING FOOD WHEN THE EXPLOSIONS OCCURRED. THEY ARE NERVOUS AND ARE TRYING TO QUICKLY FIND TRANSPORTATION. THE EXPLOSIONS WERE HEARD FAR FROM HERE. AT THE MARKET'S EASTERN GATE, WHERE THE FRUIT STANDS ARE LOCATED, WE WERE TOLD BY PASSERSBY THAT A MAN WORKING THERE WAS THE MOST SERIOUSLY WOUNDED BY THE BOMBS. ALL THE WOUNDED WERE TAKEN TO THE HOSPITAL.

THE TERRORISTS LEFT A COMMUNIQUE THAT WAS IMMEDIATELY PICKED UP BY THE NATIONAL POLICE.

THE PEOPLE ARE FLEEING THE MARKET. THEY CANNOT CONTINUE SHOPPING BECAUSE IT IS ASSUMED THIS WAS A WARNING TO KEEP THE PEOPLE FROM GOING OUT OR GOING TO VOTE.

DEV-MUC3-0135 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [TEXT] ON THE EVE OF PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS, MORE THAN 80 PERCENT OF PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION IN SAN SALVADOR IS PARALYZED WHILE A MAJORITY OF THE RESIDENTS ARE NOT RECEIVING POTABLE WATER OR ELECTRIC POWER.

REPORTS ARRIVING THIS MORNING FROM THE OUTSKIRTS OF THE CAPITAL, STATE THAT CITIES SUCH AS MEJICANOS, SAN MARCOS, APOPA, ISUSTEPEQUE, AND DELGADO, AMONG OTHERS, HAVE NOT RECEIVED BASIC PUBLIC SERVICES FOR THE PAST 3 DAYS.

THE NATIONAL POLICE THIS MORNING REPORTED THAT PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION IN SAN SALVADOR HAS BEEN MORE THAN 80 PERCENT HALTED FOR THE 3D DAY IN A ROW AND ONLY CERTAIN MINIBUSES AND LIGHT CARGO VEHICLES ARE SERVING CERTAIN ROUTES.

WORKERS AT THE EASTERN AND WESTERN BUS TERMINALS OF THIS CAPITAL REPORT THAT THE TRANSPORTATION SITUATION IS SIMILAR TO YESTERDAY'S. NO BUSES HAVE ARRIVED OR DEPARTED SAN SALVADOR FOR THE COUNTRY'S 13 DEPARTMENTS.

MUCH CENTRAL AMERICAN COMMERCIAL TRANSPORTATION IS ALSO PARALYZED BY THE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE IN EL SALVADOR SINCE MANY RAILROAD BOXCARS ARE BEING HELD UP AT THE SALVADORAN BORDERS UNABLE TO ENTER THE NATIONAL TERRITORY.

MEANWHILE, AT LEAST TWO BOMBS PLACED NEAR ELECTRIC POWER POLES WERE DETONATED THIS MORNING IN SAN SALVADOR. ONE WAS PLACED AT 16 WEST STREET IN THE IVU NEIGHBORHOOD, IN THE SOUTHERN AREA OF THE CAPITAL, AND A FRAGMENTATION GRENADE EXPLODED NEAR THE SANTA ISABEL NEIGHBORHOOD. A TELEPHONE JUNCTION BOX, THE EXACT LOCATION OF WHICH HAS NOT YET BEEN DETERMINED, WAS ALSO DESTROYED.

MILITARY SECURITY HAS BEEN STEPPED UP THROUGHOUT THIS CAPITAL AND ITS OUTSKIRTS ONLY 24 HOURS BEFORE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS. OFFICIAL SOURCES THIS MORNING REPORTED THAT ARMED FORCES TROOPS ARE MAINLY PATROLING SAN SALVADOR GAS STATIONS, SINCE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] URBAN COMMANDS HAVE THREATENED TO DESTROY THEM.

IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS ARE OVERFLYING THE CAPITAL TO PROTECT VEHICLES THAT ARE TRANSITTING THE MAIN STREETS OF SAN SALVADOR, DESPITE THE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE DECREED BY THE INSURGENCY 3 DAYS AGO. REPORTS ALSO STATE THAT THE NATIONAL AND TREASURY POLICE ARE OFFERING FREE TRANSPORTATION TO PEOPLE HEADING FOR THEIR RESPECTIVE WORK PLACES.

THE ARMY IS USING LOUDSPEAKERS ON MILITARY VEHICLES TO URGE THE PEOPLE TO VOTE IN PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS TOMORROW. FOR SUNDAY'S ELECTIONS, THE ARMY WILL DEPLOY A LARGE NUMBER OF UNITS TO TRANSPORT VOTERS, WHO WILL BE GOING TO THEIR RESPECTIVE POLLING PLACES THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

IN THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL, POLICE-MILITARY SECURITY HAS BEEN STEPPED UP LESS THAN 24 BEFORE THE 1989 PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS. WE HAVE NOTICED A LARGER NUMBER OF SECURITY PERSONNEL NEAR THE SEVEN VOTING CENTERS THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL HAS SET UP IN SAN SALVADOR MUNICIPALITY.

IN THE OUTLYING CITIES OF NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR, SUCH AS MEXICANOS, CUSCATANCINGO, AND APOPA, TRANSPORTATION IS STILL COMPLETELY PARALYZED IN THE WAKE OF THE GROUND TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE DECREED BY THE FMLN, WHICH IS IN ITS 3D DAY TODAY.

MEANWHILE, REPORTS FROM CHALATENANGO, 72 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, STATE THAT THE ENTIRE DEPARTMENT IS WITHOUT ELECTRICITY DUE TO RATIONING THAT THE CEL [LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION] HAS IMPOSED ON THE ENTIRE COUNTRY AFTER FMLN GUERRILLAS CARRIED OUT LARGE-SCALE SABOTAGE OPERATIONS AGAINST THE ELECTRICITY NETWORK EARLY THIS WEEK.

MILITARY SOURCES CONSULTED THIS MORNING IN CHALATENANGO SAID THAT THERE HAVE BEEN NO CLASHES BETWEEN MILITARY FORCES AND GUERRILLAS IN THAT AREA FOR THE PAST FEW HOURS. THESE SOURCES SAID THAT THE VOTING BOOTHS THAT WILL BE INSTALLED IN 33 MUNICIPALITIES OF THAT NORTHERN DEPARTMENT ARE READY. THEY ADDED THAT THE NUMBER OF MILITARY UNITS IN THAT AREA OF THE COUNTRY HAS BEEN INCREASED.

DEV-MUC3-0136 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [RENE HURTADO] [TEXT] ONLY HOURS BEFORE TOMORROW'S ELECTIONS BEGIN AT 0700, BEFORE THE PEOPLE BEGIN CASTING THEIR VOTES TO ELECT A NEW PRESIDENT AND VICE PRESIDENT, THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] CONTINUES WITH ITS TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE AND ITS ATTACKS ON MILITARY GARRISONS.

TODAY AT APPROXIMATELY 2130 [0330 GMT], A GROUP OF REBELS LAUNCHED A SURPRISE ATTACK ON THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE. SOME SHOTS WERE FIRED, SOME BAZOOKAS WERE ALSO FIRED, BUT IT IS NOT KNOWN IF THEY ACTUALLY HIT A TARGET INSIDE THE BASE. HOWEVER, AIR FORCE SPOKESMEN HAVE SAID THAT THE ATTACK WAS LAUNCHED FROM SANTA LUCIA COLONIA. NO DAMAGE OR CASUALTIES RESULTED FROM THIS ATTACK ON THE AIR FORCE HEADQUARTERS BY FMLN REBELS. THE SOLDIERS GUARDING THE AREA REPELLED THE REBEL ATTACK.

A SEARCH OPERATION IS UNDER WAY IN THE AREA TO FIND THE REBELS WHO ATTACKED THE AIR FORCE BASE THIS EVENING. NO CASUALTIES OR DAMAGE RESULTED FROM THIS ATTACK.

DEV-MUC3-0139 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 19 MAR 89 (RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI) -- [TEXT] THE DICTATORSHIP HAS CARRIED OUT ANOTHER COWARDLY ACTION. PAY CLOSE ATTENTION: ON THE NIGHT OF 18 MARCH, TWO REPORTERS WERE COWARDLY SHOT IN SOYAPANGO. LAST NIGHT, REPORTER ROBERTO NAVAS AND LUIS GALDAMEZ WERE SHOT BY TROOPS OF THE DICTATORSHIP.

THE THREATS BY ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIA AND VIDES CASANOVA THREATS FELL UPON REPORTERS LUIS GALDAMEZ AND ROBERTO NAVAS LAST NIGHT. WE ARE VIGOROUSLY CONDEMNING THIS NEW COWARDLY ACTION CARRIED OUT BY VIDES CASANOVA'S TROOPS AND COMMANDING OFFICERS.

IN THE AREA OF SOYAPANGO AT APPROXIMATELY 2200 LAST NIGHT, REPORTERS ROBERTO NAVAS AND LUIS GALDAMEZ WERE COWARDLY STRAFED BY TROOPS OF THE DICTATORSHIP.

REPORTS GIVEN BY SOYAPANGO RESIDENTS INDICATE THAT [AIR FORCE COMMANDER] JUAN RAFAEL BUSTILLO'S TROOPS ARE PATROLLING AND CONTINUOUSLY SOWING TERROR IN THAT DENSELY POPULATED AREA.

REPORTERS ROBERTO NAVAS AND LUIS GALDAMEZ WERE RIDING A MOTORCYCLE AT APPROXIMATELY 2200 WHEN THEY WERE VICTIMS OF INDISCRIMINATE SHOOTING. WE SUPPORT THE CONDEMNATION PRESENTED BY OUR COMRADE REPORTERS WE GIVE... [9-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION].

WE HAVE LEARNED THAT JOURNALIST ROBERTO NAVAS DIED INSTANTANEOUSLY AS A RESULT OF THE SHOOTING BY JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE'S TROOPS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] SERIOUSLY WOUNDED. LUIS GALDAMEZ IS CRITICALLY ILL WHILE ROBERTO NAVAS DIED INSTANTANEOUSLY. THE TWO REPORTERS WERE MEMBERS OF THE TEAM OF REPORTERS [WORDS INDISTINCT] REUTER.

WHILE CONDEMNING AND VIGOROUSLY SUPPORTING THE JOURNALISTS' PROTEST [WORD INDISTINCT] WE URGE YOU TO REPUDIATE THIS KIND OF ACTION, WHICH [WORDS INDISTINCT].

DURING TODAY'S TRANSMISSION 6-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION AND OF VIDES CASANOVA. THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] CIVILIANS AND THE INDISCRIMINATE SHOOTING OF PRIVATE VEHICLES, RED CROSS VEHICLES, AND REPORTERS [WORDS INDISTINCT] COWARDLY ACTIONS [WORD INDISTINCT] GENERALIZED [WORDS INDISTINCT] VIDES CASANOVA'S TROOPS ARE CARRYING OUT WITHIN THE REPRESSIVE FRAMEWORK OF THE 19 MARCH ELECTION FARCE.

DEV-MUC3-0140 (BELLCORE)

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 19 MAR 89 (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] (CLANDESTINE) RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI IN SPANISH TO EL SALVADOR AT 1311 GMT ON 19 MARCH BROADCASTS APPROXIMATELY 35 MINUTES OF MILITARY REPORTS, INCLUDING CLASHES BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS THAT TOOK PLACE ON THE EVE OF THE SALVADORAN ELECTIONS AND ARE TAKING PLACE ON ELECTION DAY ITSELF, AND DETAILS ON THE EFFECTS OF THE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE ON THE ELECTION PROCESS.

A NUMBER OF REPORTS INDICATE THAT EXPLOSIONS AND SHOOTOUTS ARE HEARD IN SAN RAMON, SAN ANTONIO ABAD, CIUDAD SATELITE, AND OTHER AREAS LOCATED ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR AND IN SAN SALVADOR ITSELF, WHERE OVER 20 EXPLOSIONS HAVE LEFT THE ENTIRE CAPITAL WITHOUT ELECTRICITY. ONE REPORT ADDS: "NO ONE IS VOTING TODAY, 19 MARCH; TRANSPORTATION IS NONEXISTENT, AND NO ONE IS VOTING IN SAN SALVADOR OR IN ANY OTHER PART OF THE COUNTRY. THE 19 MARCH ELECTION FARCE IS A COMPLETE FAILURE."

ANOTHER REPORT STATES THAT FMLN GUERRILLA UNITS CLASHED WITH MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 1 TROOPS IN SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, AT 2200 ON 18 MARCH, INFLICTING FIVE CASUALTIES. THE REPORT ADDS THAT GUERRILLA UNITS ATTACKED ARMY FORCES IN TEJUTLA, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, INFLICTING OVER 20 CASUALTIES: "AFTER OUR ATTACK, THE ENEMY BEGAN SHOOTING AT TEJUTLA CHURCH, CLAIMING FMLN GUERRILLAS WERE HIDING INSIDE."

A REPORT FROM MORAZAN DEPARTMENT SAYS THE FMLN DAMAGED AN AIR FORCE HELICOPTER, SEIZED ONE M-60 MACHINEGUN AND A PRC-77 COMMUNICATION RADIO, AND INFLICTED FOUR CASUALTIES ON MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 4 TROOPS.

A SANTA ANA DEPARTMENT REPORT ADVISES THAT "HEAVY" CLASHES TOOK PLACE IN METAPAN, TEJUTEPEQUE, AND ILOBASCO. ANOTHER REPORT INDICATES FMLN FORCES ATTACKED THE AIR FORCE HEADQUARTERS AT APPROXIMATELY 2100 ON 18 MARCH.

ANOTHER REPORT STATES THAT "HEAVY" CLASHES TOOK PLACE IN CHINAMECA AND SAN VICENTE CITY; FMLN UNITS ATTACKED ARMY POSITIONS IN BERLIN, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT; AND THE CLASHES STILL CONTINUE IN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT.

THE NEXT REPORT STATES THAT FMLN UNITS CLASHED WITH LENCA BATTALION TROOPS FOR SEVERAL HOURS IN SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, INFLICTING A TOTAL OF 15 CASUALTIES. IN ADDITION, "WE RECOVERED ONE M-60 MACHINEGUN, ONE M-79 GRENADE LAUNCHER, AND ONE PRC-77 COMMUNICATION RADIO."

THE LAST REPORT STATES: "WE HAVE INFLICTED MANY CASUALTIES IN SAN RAMON, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, AND THROUGHOUT THE REST OF THE COUNTRY, WHERE HEAVY CLASHES ARE PRESENTLY TAKING PLACE. VEHICLES ARE NOT CIRCULATING IN SAN SALVADOR, AND CIVILIANS HAVE NOT GONE OUT OF THEIR HOMES."

DEV-MUC3-0141 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 MAR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMY ACCEPTED RESPONSIBILITY THIS MORNING FOR THE DEATH OF TWO REPORTERS WHO WERE SHOT BY SOLDIERS IN THE PAST FEW HOURS IN THE CAPITAL AND IN THE EASTERN SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT.

ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL REPORT, IN BOTH CASES, THE SOLDIERS FIRED WHEN THE REPORTERS, BOTH SALVADORANS, IGNORED ORDERS TO HALT. HOWEVER, FRIENDS OF THE VICTIMS MAINTAIN THIS IS NOT TRUE.

A SPOKESMAN FOR THE ARMY PRESS COMMITTEE SAID THAT LAST NIGHT, AN AIR FORCE MEMBER FIRED AT PHOTOGRAPHERS ROBERTO NAVAS AND LUIS GALDAMEZ, SALVADORANS WHO WORK FOR THE BRITISH REUTER NEWS AGENCY, "WHEN THEY FAILED TO STOP AT A MILITARY CHECKPOINT" AT A CAPITAL CITY AVENUE.

NAVAS DIED AND GALDAMEZ WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED. GALDAMEZ WAS LEFT LYING IN THE STREET UNTIL HE WAS PICKED UP "SEVERAL HOURS LATER," BY HIS OWN ACCOUNT, AND TAKEN TO A HOSPITAL, WHERE HE UNDERWENT SURGERY.

ACCORDING TO HOSPITAL SOURCES AND REUTER, GALDAMEZ IS NOW "OUT OF DANGER;" IT WILL NOT BE NECESSARY TO AMPUTATE HIS RIGHT ARM, AS WAS ORIGINALLY FEARED.

ANOTHER REPORTER, MAURICIO PINEDA, A SOUND TECHNICIAN FOR CANAL DOCE TELEVISION OF SAN SALVADOR, DIED THIS MORNING IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY AT A CROSSROADS, WHEN A SOLDIER FIRED AT PINEDA'S VEHICLE WHILE HE WAS ON HIS WAY TO COVER TODAY'S ELECTIONS.

THE ARMY SPOKESMAN EMPHASIZED THAT IN BOTH CASES, "THE SOLDIERS FIRED ON SUSPICIOUS-LOOKING PEOPLE WHO DID NOT RESPECT THE STOP SIGN AT A MILITARY CHECKPOINT."

HOWEVER, GALDAMEZ SAID HE AND NAVAS, WHO WERE ON A MOTOCYCLE, DID STOP AT THE CHECKPOINT AND THAT THE SOLDIERS FIRED ON THEM WITHOUT JUSTIFICATION.

RAUL BELTRAN, ONE OF MAURICIO PINEDA'S COWORKERS, SAID THE CANAL DOCE TEAM WAS TRAVELING IN A STATION WAGON WITH WHITE FLAGS AND SIGNS INDICATING THEY WERE REPORTERS AND THAT THE SOLDIERS FIRED WITHOUT HAVING FIRST GIVEN ANY INDICATION THE REPORTERS SHOULD STOP.

DEV-MUC3-0142 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 MAR 89 (ACAN) -- [TEXT] AFTER A 1ST HOUR IN WHICH THERE WAS A VERY SMALL TURNOUT AT THE POLLS, THE NUMBER OF SALVADORANS GOING TO VOTE IN THE CAPITAL CITY AND OTHER TOWNS IS INCREASING. THOUSANDS OF VOTERS WERE STANDING IN LINES AT MID-MORNING.

ARMY AND POLICE UNITS SURROUND THE POLLS WHILE MILITARY HELICOPTERS CONTINUE TO FLY OVER THE CITY.

FIDEL CHAVEZ MENA OF THE RULING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] TOLD THE PRESS HE HAS RECEIVED REPORTS FROM HIS FOLLOWERS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY TO THE EFFECT THAT 95 PERCENT OF THE POLLS HAVE BEEN INSTALLED AND ARE OPERATING, AFTER OVERCOMING SOME EARLY MORNING PROBLEMS IN SOME OF THE PLACES.

THE POLLS OPENED AT 0700 (1300 GMT) AND WILL CLOSE AT 1700 (2300 GMT).

THE BOMB EXPLOSIONS AND SHOOTING HEARD THROUGHOUT THE EARLY HOURS IN SAN SALVADOR WERE NO LONGER HEARD AFTER 1000 (1600 GMT).

HOWEVER, ATTACKS AGAINST VEHICLES AND CLASHES BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE ARMY CONTINUE TO BE REPORTED IN VARIOUS PARTS OF COUNTRY'S INTERIOR.

THE GUERRILLAS CONTINUE TO BOYCOTT THE ELECTIONS WITH A BLOCKADE OF ALL LAND TRANSPORTATION, BUT THEY HAVE ANNOUNCED THEY WILL NOT DIRECTLY ATTACK THE VOTERS OR THE POLLING STATIONS.

HIGHWAY CHECKPOINT SOLDIERS KILLED TWO SALVADORAN REPORTERS, ROBERTO NAVAS AND MAURICIO PINEDA, IN TWO SEPARATE SHOOTINGS LATE LAST NIGHT AND EARLY THIS MORNING. NAVAS WAS A PHOTOGRAPHER FROM AN INTERNATIONAL NEWS AGENCY, AND PINEDA WAS A SOUND TECHNICIAN FOR A LOCAL TELEVISION CHANNEL.

PROMINENT AMONG THE ELECTORS, BOTH IN THE CAPITAL AND IN NEIGHBORING TOWNS, ARE MANY MEMBERS OF THE MAIN OPPOSITION PARTY, THE RIGHTIST NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA), WHO ARE CARRYING BANNERS AND OTHER VISIBLE SIGNS OF THEIR PARTY PREFERENCE.

SURVEYS HAVE SHOWN ARENA'S CANDIDATE, ALFREDO CRISTIANI, WILL ALMOST CERTAINLY WIN THE ELECTIONS.

ACAN-EFE CORRESPONDENTS WHO TOURED VOTING BOOTHS IN THE CAPITAL AND OTHER TOWNS SAW SOLDIERS AND POLICEMEN CAREFULLY CHECKING ALL VOTERS BEFORE ALLOWING THEM TO ENTER THE VOTING AREAS.

VOTERS WHO ARRIVE IN AUTOMOBILES HAVE TO LEAVE THEM MORE THAN 200 METERS AWAY.

IN APOPA, A TOWN SOME 12 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, THE VOTING BOOTHS OPENED VERY LATE, BECAUSE THEIR LOCATION WAS CHANGED AT THE LAST MINUTE, WHICH GENERATED PROTESTS FROM THE DELEGATES OF SEVERAL PARTIES AND LED TO BRAWLS BETWEEN ARENA AND PDC SUPPORTERS.

IN THE EARLY MORNING, MILITARY HELICOPTERS USED FLARES SEVERAL TIMES TO LIGHT UP APOPA AND ITS ENVIRONS, PRESUMABLY TO LOCATE GUERRILLAS.

MEMBERS OF THE DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE, AN ALLIANCE OF LEFTIST PARTIES, SAID IN APOPA THEY HAVE RECEIVED DEATH THREATS TO DISSUADE THEM FROM VOTING.

IN THE SMALL TOWN OF TONACATEPEQUE, SOME 16 KM NORTHEAST OF SAN SALVADOR, THE DELAY IN BEGINNING THE VOTING WAS ONLY HALF AN HOUR LONG, AND THE ELECTION PROCESS IS PROCEEDING NORMALLY.

IN SAN RAMON, ANOTHER TOWN CLOSE TO THE CAPITAL WITH 30,000 INHABITANTS, THE VOTING BEGAN AFTER A CONSIDERABLE DEALY BECAUSE OF A GUERRILLA INCURSION IN THE DAWN HOURS.

ARMY HELICOPTERS FIRED ROCKETS FOR SEVERAL HOURS AT THE SLOPES OF SAN SALVADOR VOLCANO, IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE CAPITAL, PRESUMABLY AT THE GUERRILLA COLUMNS THAT ATTACKED SAN RAMON.

DEV-MUC3-0147 (BELLCORE)

EL PARAISO (EL SALVADOR), 19 MAR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] COLONEL ALEXANDER MENDEZ, COMMANDER OF THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, THE MAIN GARRISON IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, HAS TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT OVER 500 GUERRILLA FIGHTERS ATTACKED TWO TOWNS IN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT HOURS BEFORE THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS STARTED.

ACCORDING TO THE OFFICER, THE CLASHES, WHICH BEGAN AT 2200 LAST NIGHT AND ENDED AT 0500 TODAY, RESULTED IN THE DEATH OF SEVEN REBELS AND ONE SOLDIER NEAR THE TOWNS OF TEJUTLA AND SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES. ALEXANDER MENDEZ SAID AT THE EL PARAISO GARRISON THAT THE HIGH NUMBER OF GUERRILLA FIGHTERS INCLUDED "ATTACKERS AND OTHERS WHO PROVIDE COOPERATION AND CARE FOR THE WOUNDED."

THE OFFICER REPORTED 17 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING 9 WOUNDED SOLDIERS.

A PEASANT WOMAN DIED WHEN A BOMB EXPLODED IN HER KITCHEN DURING THE ATTACK ON SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES. THE EXPLOSION ALSO BLEW OFF HER SONS' LEGS, THE MILITARY COMMANDER SAID.

MENDEZ STATED THAT FIVE HOUSES WERE DESTROYED DURING THE ATTACK ON SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES, 7 KM FROM THE CAPITAL OF CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

THE SALVADORAN OFFICER CONFIRMED THAT THREE U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS HAD TRAVELED TO CHALATENANGO TO HELP COUNTER THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE.

ACAN-EFE WAS ABLE TO ASCERTAIN THAT ONE OF THE OFFICERS INCLUDED A U.S. AIR FORCE COLONEL, WHO WAS WEARING FATIGUES AND CARRYING AN AR-15 RIFLE ON HIS SHOULDER.

MENDEZ ASSERTED THAT THERE ARE USUALLY FOUR U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS AT THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, AND ADDED THAT THEY ARE ALLOWED TO CARRY WEAPONS LIKE THE AR-15 "WHENEVER THE CIRCUMSTANCES REQUIRE IT," ALTHOUGH THEY MAY NOT PARTICIPATE IN OFFENSIVE OPERATIONS.

THE CLASHES CAUSED PANIC AMONG PEOPLE IN CHALATENANGO WHO COULD HEAR THE HEAVY FIRING BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY SHORTLY AFTER THE VOTING TABLES OPENED.

ACCORDING TO THE SALVADORAN OFFICER, LAST NIGHT'S GUERRILLA ATTACK IS "ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT IN THE LATEST OFFENSIVE" LAUNCHED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT IN SEPTEMBER.

MENDEZ SAID THAT THE GUERRILLA ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT WITH NUMEROUS WEAPONS. HE EMPHASIZED THE USE OF THE NEW AK-M RIFLES, "A NEW VERSION OF THE FAMOUS GDR-MADE AK-47."

DEV-MUC3-0148 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF OPERATIONS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY GENERAL STAFF, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [EXCERPTS] [BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] [WORDS INDISTINCT] HERE IN EL SALVADOR IF THEY WANTED TO ESTABLISH A MECHANISM [WORDS INDISTINCT] TO SLOWLY ESTABLISH PEACE IN THE ENTIRE REGION. THOSE ARE THE EFFORTS [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] WHAT CAN THE GOVERNMENT DO ABOUT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]?

[PONCE] WE CAN ASK THEM TO JOIN THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC, CIVIC LIFE TO [WORDS INDISTINCT] PEOPLE TO LIVE IN PEACE.

[REPORTER] HOW DO YOU VIEW THE VOTING SITUATION AND THE SECURITY AND SURVEILLANCE THE ARMED FORCES IS PROVIDING, ESPECIALLY NOW THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE BEING CHARGED WITH THE DEATH OF TWO JOURNALISTS? I THINK YOU ARE AWARE OF THAT. TELL US SOMETHING ABOUT THAT.

[PONCE] WE ARE THE FIRST ONES TO REGRET THE DEATH OF THE CANAL DOCE NEWSMEN WHO DIED IN SAN MIGUEL AND THE REUTER CORRESPONDENT WHO DIED HERE ON ARMY BOULEVARD. THOSE DEATHS ARE THE RESULT OF THE PREVAILING UNREST AND NERVOUSNESS. THERE ARE BULLETS BEING FIRED ALL OVER THE PLACE AND, UNFORTUNATELY, THOSE REPORTERS WERE THE FIRST TO GET HIT. THIS CONTINUES TO BE A PROBLEM THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAS [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] DID THE ARMY SUFFER CASUALTIES DURING THE INCIDENTS IN SAN RAMON?

[PONCE] I CAN TELL YOU THAT A BRACAMONTE BATTALION CORPORAL DIED AND ANOTHER SOLDIER WAS WOUNDED. HOWEVER, THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE AND BRACAMONTE BATTALION SOLDIERS REACTED QUICKLY AND REPELLED THE TERRORIST ACTIVITY THAT IS CURRENTLY CAUSING CHAOS IN SAN SALVADOR.

[REPORTER] HAVE OTHER INCIDENTS BEEN REPORTED?

[PONCE] IT IS DIFFICULT TO BELIEVE WHAT THE FMLN IS SAYING. THEIR SPOKESMAN IN MEXICO CITY SAID THEY WOULD NOT ATTACK THE VOTING TABLES. HOWEVER, WE HAVE HEARD THAT VOTING TABLES HAVE BEEN ATTACKED IN 15 AREAS OF THE COUNTRY. ATTACKS ON VOTING TABLES WERE REPORTED IN CHALATENANGO, SAN ANTONIO, CIUDAD BARRIOS, CAROLINA, AND NORTH [WORD INDISTINCT]. IN USULUTAN, THE FMLN PLANTED TWO BOMBS JUST OUTSIDE THE CITY TO FRIGHTEN THE PEOPLE. HOWEVER, OUR PEOPLE'S DEMOCRATIC NATURE IS TELLING THE FMLN: WE DO NOT WANT TERRORISM, WE WANT PEACE, AND WE ARE USING PEACEFUL MEANS TO ACHIEVE POWER AND CHOOSE OUR PRESIDENT AND VICE PRESIDENT.

[REPORTER] HOW IS THE VOTING PROCESS PROGRESSING THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY?

[PONCE] THERE ARE 27 MUNICIPALITIES WHERE ELECTIONS ARE NOT BEING HELD. WE KNOW FOR SURE THAT THERE ARE MUNICIPALITIES, LIKE CINQUERA AND ARAMBALA, WHERE [WORDS INDISTINCT], AND WE ALSO KNOW THAT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE KNOW THERE ARE 27 MUNICIPALITIES WHERE THERE WILL BE NO VOTING AND THERE ARE OTHERS THAT [WORDS INDISTINCT] THAT THE REPRESENTATIVES OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES AND MEMBERS OF THE MUNICIPAL VOTING TABLE BOARDS [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] HOW MANY SOLDIERS ARE PROTECTING THE VOTING TABLE BOARDS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY?

[PONCE] ABOUT 80 PERCENT OF OUR SOLDIERS ARE PART OF THE DEMOCRACY PLAN. WE ARE GOING TO CONTINUE OFFERING THE SAME PROTECTION AFTER THE VOTING CENTERS ARE CLOSED [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] WE HAVE READ SOME REPORTS THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE URGING THE PEOPLE TO VOTE FOR THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC]. WILL THE SOLDIERS BE ALLOWED TO VOTE?

[PONCE] FIRST, I EMPHATICALLY AND CATEGORICALLY DENY THAT WE ARE URGING THE PEOPLE TO VOTE FOR THE PDC. WE HAVE SENT A MEMORANDUM TO ALL THE COMMANDERS AND [WORD INDISTINCT] CHIEFS ADVISING THEM THAT WE MUST HAVE A COMPLETELY APOLITICAL ATTITUDE AND REFRAIN FROM PARTICIPATING IN ANY POLITICAL ACTIVITY. WE MUST PROTECT ALL POLITICAL PARTIES, WE MUST PROTECT ALL THE VOTING CENTERS, AND WE MUST ENSURE THE SAFETY OF THE AREAS SURROUNDING THE VOTING CENTERS. WE ARE NOT INTERESTED IN WHO WINS THE ELECTIONS; WE ARE INTERESTED IN MAKING SURE THAT THE WILL OF THE PEOPLE IS RESPECTED AND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THIS IS A DAY FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO PROVE THEIR DEMOCRATIC NATURE.

[REPORTER] WILL SOLDIERS BE ALLOWED TO CAST THEIR VOTES TODAY?

[PONCE] AS SOLDIERS WE ALL HAVE THE RIGHT TO VOTE. BUT BEFORE WE CAST OUR VOTE WE ARE GOING TO FULFILL OUR DUTY. OUR DUTY IS TO GUARANTEE SAFETY. THIS WILL NOT CREATE A PROBLEM. FOR EXAMPLE, IF A SOLDIER'S IDENTIFICATION CARD WAS ISSUED IN SAN SALVADOR BUT HE IS STATIONED IN AGUILARES, HE WILL BE ALLOWED TO VOTE AT A SPECIFIC VOTING CENTER. THOSE WHO CAN VOTE WILL DO SO AS CIVILIANS AND THEY WILL BE UNARMED. [WORDS INDISTINCT] MOSTLY ADMINISTRATIVE PERSONNEL AND [WORD INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE REBELS HAVE THREATENED TO LAUNCH A LARGE ATTACK. DO YOU HAVE ENOUGH MEN TO FIGHT THEM AT THIS TIME?

[PONCE] SINCE 1982, WE HAVE [WORDS INDISTINCT] DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN THE COUNTRY. THE PEOPLE [WORDS INDISTINCT] BEFORE AND AFTER THE ELECTIONS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] AMID SABOTAGE TO THE POWER SYSTEM. WE ARE ALSO EXPERIENCING A WATER PROBLEM [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE ARE GOING TO EXERCISE OUR RIGHT AS ESTABLISHED IN THE CONSTITUTION AND WE ARE GOING PROTECT THE INTEGRITY OF THE PEOPLE, OUR SOVEREIGNTY, AND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0149 (BELLCORE)

HAVANA (CUBA), 20 MAR 89 (TASS) -- [TEXT] JOSE RICARDO PERDOMO, CHAIRMAN OF THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL OF EL SALVADOR, ANNOUNCED THE END OF THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS IN THE COUNTRY IN A TELEPHONE INTERVIEW WITH TASS. THE COUNTING OF VOTES IN SUNDAY'S ELECTION IN THE PRESENCE OF FOREIGN OBSERVERS WAS IN PROGRESS, AND PRELIMINARY RESULTS WOULD BE DECLARED LATER ON MONDAY. POLITICAL OBSERVERS BELIEVE THAT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, CANDIDATE OF THE RIGHT-WING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE, HAS WON.

STAFF MEMBERS OF THE [CENTRAL ELECTORAL] COUNCIL NOTED IN AN INTERVIEW WITH [TASS] THAT VOTING BEGAN SLOWLY IN THE MORNING. A TOTAL OF 1,835,000 VOTERS WERE REGISTERED IN THE COUNTRY WITH A POPULATION OF FIVE MILLION. ACCORDING TO ESTIMATES OF JOURNALISTS IN SAN SALVADOR, THE PERCENTAGE OF SALVADOREANS WHO ABSTAINED FROM VOTING WAS HIGHER THIS TIME THAN AT THE 1984 PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION WHICH WAS WON BY JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, CANDIDATE OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY.

CONSTANT ARMED CLASHES BETWEEN DETACHMENTS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT AND ARMY UNITS INTERFERED WITH THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION. ON THE EVE OF THE ELECTION, THE INSURGENT RADIO STATIONS [VENCEREMOS AND FARABUNDO] MARTI BROADCAST REPORTS THAT GUERILLAS WOULD NOT ATTACK POLLING STATIONS. INSURGENTS ATTACKED MILITARY GARRISONS IN MORER THAN 20 INHABITED LOCALITIES THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY ON SUNDAY, PUTTING OUT OF ACTION SOME 150 GOVERNMENT TROOPS. GUERILLAS ALSO DOWNED A HELICOPTER GUNSHIP IN USULUTAN REGION. AS A RESULT OF INSURGENT ACTIONS, A CONSIDERABLE PART OF THE COUNTRY REMAINS WITHOUT ELECTRICITY OR TELEPHONE COMMUNICATION. THE INSURGENT OPERATION TO BLOCK HIGHWAYS AND RAILWAYS CONTINUES.

[VIDES] CASANOVA, SALVADOREAN MINISTER OF DEFENCE AND PUBLIC SECURITY, ADMITTED THAT THE ELECTION DID NOT TAKE PLACE IN 29 OUT OF 262 DISTRICTS IN THE COUNTRY DUE TO THE FACT THAT THE ARMY COULD NOT RESTORE CONTROL OVER THOSE TERRITORIES.

APART FROM MOTOR VEHICLES WITH TROOPS AND MILITARY PARTOLS, ONLY TAXIS WITH JOURNALISTS COVERING THE VOTING DROVE IN SAN SALVADOR ON THE ELECTION DAY. PRESS CARS HAD WHITE HANDKERCHIEFS FIXED TO AERIALS. THIS PRECAUTION WAS TAKEN AFTER MILITARY PATROLS KILLED THREE JOURNALISTS: ROBNERTO NAVAS, A REUTER NEWS PHOTOGRAPHER, CORONEL LAGROW, A DUTCH TV CORRESPONDENT, AND MAURICIO PINEDA, A STAFF MEMBER OF SALVADOREAN TELEVISION. LUIS GALDAMEZ, ANOTHER REUTER CORRESPONDENT, WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED, AND HIS ARM WILL PROBABLY HAVE TO BE AMPUTATED.

DEV-MUC3-0151 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 21 MAR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE DAY OF FIGHTING THAT RESULTED IN ENORMOUS ABSTENTION DURING THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS REPRESENTED AN OVERWHELMING VICTORY FOR THE PEOPLE. THIS WAS A FIGHTER'S WAY OF REPUDIATING THE WAR ELECTIONS THAT WERE HELD AFTER THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] PEACE PROPOSAL WAS BLOCKED. IT ALSO REPRESENTED A DEFEAT FOR THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION, WHICH WAS BENT ON CARRYING OUT A DEADLY WAR AGAINST OUR PEOPLE DISGUISED AS A HYPOCRITICAL CENTRIST AND FALSELY DEMOCRATIC CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT.

WE STRUGGLE FOR A JUST AND NEGOTIATED PEACE WITH GENUINE DEMOCRACY, SOCIAL JUSTICE, AND NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY, AND WE GAVE A WORLD-RESOUNDING BLOW TO THE ENEMIES OF PEACE. THE THOUSANDS OF FMLN FIGHTERS WHO FOUGHT THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, CITIES AND INTERIOR, ENCOURAGED BY AN UNPRECEDENTED INTENSITY AND SIMULTANEITY; THE TENS OF THOUSANDS OF UNION MEMBERS, PEASANTS, STUDENTS, TEACHERS, DISPLACED PERSONS, UNEMPLOYED PERSONS, GOVERNMENT AND MUNICIPAL WORKERS, MOTHERS AND FAMILY MEMBERS OF POLITICAL PRISONERS AND MISSING PERSONS, MEMBERS OF COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS, BELIEVERS AND REPRESENTATIVES OF ALL THE CHURCHES WHO TOOK TO THE STREET TO DEMAND THAT THE FMLN PEACE PROPOSAL BE ACCEPTED AND WHO LATER REPUDIATED THE 19 MARCH WARMONGERING ELECTIONS; THE HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF CITIZENS, MORE THAN 1 MILLION PERSONS WITH VALID VOTING CARDS, WHO REFUSED TO VOTE, AND THE MORE THAN 200,000 WHO CAST A VOID OR BLANK BALLOT--SOMETHING THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL, THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA], AND THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] ARE TRYING TO HIDE; THE TENS OF THOUSANDS WHO VOTED FOR THE DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE; AND THE HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS WHO WERE NOT INTERESTED IN GETTING THEIR VOTING CARD THAT WOULD ALLOW THEM TO PARTICIPATE IN THESE DISCREDITED ELECTIONS ARE THE IMMENSE MAJORITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WHO SAID NO TO THE COUNTERINSURGENCY WAR AND YES TO A JUST POLITICAL AND NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE NATIONAL CONFLICT. YES TO A REAL DEMOCRACY; NO TO THE TRADITIONAL LIE OF A VOTE THAT ONLY SERVES TO JUSTIFY AND FACILITATE U.S. MILITARY AID, WHICH PROMOTES THE CONTINUATION OF THE WAR AND WORSENS THE SERIOUS PROBLEMS OF POVERTY, MISERY, UNEMPLOYMENT, AND REPRESSION BEING EXPERIENCED BY OUR PEOPLE.

THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS WERE HELD, BUT HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS WHO LIVE ABROAD WERE KEPT FROM VOTING. MANY OF THESE PEOPLE FLED THE COUNTRY BECAUSE THEY WERE BEING PERSECUTED OR BECAUSE THE ARMED FORCES FORCED THEM TO LEAVE THEIR HOMES THROUGH THEIR BOMBINGS AND OTHER ATROCITIES. THEY ARE ACTIVE SALVADORANS. THANKS TO THEIR WORK, HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF OTHER SALVADORANS, MEMBERS OF THEIR FAMILIES WHO HAVE REMAINED IN EL SALVADOR, CAN SURVIVE. HOWEVER, THESE PEOPLE WERE DENIED THEIR RIGHT TO VOTE, A RIGHT THE FMLN PROPOSAL TO TURN THE ELECTIONS INTO A MECHANISM FOR PEACE WOULD HAVE GRANTED THEM.

MR ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS DECLARED HIMSELF THE WINNER IN AN ELECTION THAT SAW THE LARGEST ABSTENTION IN THESE YEARS OF WAR. MORE THAN 60 PERCENT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE DID NOT VOTE OR CAST VOID AND BLANK VOTES. THE VOTES CRISTIANI GOT DO NOT TOTAL 20 PERCENT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. MANY OF THOSE WHO VOTED FOR CRISTIANI WERE DECEIVED BY ARENA'S PROPAGANDA THAT PROMISED EMPLOYMENT, HOUSING, EDUCATION, SCHOOLS, PUBLIC HEALTH, ECONOMIC RECOVERY AND PROSPERITY, ETC. CRISTIANI AND ARENA KNOW THEY ARE GETTING A COUNTRY DROWNING IN AN ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL CRISIS, WITH A GROWING REVOLUTIONARY WAR, AND THEY WILL NOT BE ABLE TO KEEP THOSE PROMISES. NO ONE CAN DO ANYTHING WITHOUT FIRST ACHIEVING A JUST PEACE. FOR ALL THESE REASONS, ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S ELECTION CANNOT BE CONSIDERED EITHER MORALLY OR POLITICALLY LEGITIMATE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0152 (BELLCORE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 21 MAR 89 (BARRICADA) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] FAR FROM ACHIEVING A TRUCE THE DAY THE RECENT PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS WERE HELD, A GENERAL INCREASE IN VIOLENCE THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE COUNTRY WAS THE RESULT OF THE CIVIL WAR IN WHICH THE UNITED STATES AND THE MILITARY HAVE SUBMERGED EL SALVADOR FOR THE PAST 9 YEARS. ON THE ONE HAND THERE WAS THE MILITARIZATION OF THE ELECTIONS THEMSELVES AND THE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING AND MACHINEGUNNING OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, WHICH LEFT A TOLL OF HUNDREDS OF VICTIMS AS WELL AS THREE NEWSMEN MURDERED BY ARMY MEMBERS. ON THE OTHER HAND THERE WERE MILITARY ACTIONS BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN], WHICH, AMONG OTHER THINGS, INFLICTED 150 CASUALTIES ON THE ARMY AND BROUGHT 90 PERCENT OF TRAFFIC TO A STANDSTILL.

THE VOTING STATISTICS PAINT A SIMILAR PICTURE: IN 29 OF THE 262 MUNICIPALITIES IN WHICH THE COUNTRY IS DIVIDED, THERE WAS NO VOTING AT ALL. OF THE 2.2 MILLION SALVADORANS WHO SHOULD BE ON THE VOTING LISTS, ONLY 1.8 MILLION WERE REGISTERED, AND WHILE 60 PERCENT OF THE VOTERS SHOWED UP AT THE POLLS FOR THE 1984 ELECTIONS, THIS FIGURE WAS COMPLETELY INVERTED THIS PAST 19 MARCH.

TODAY -- JUST LIKE BEFORE THE BALLOTING BEGAN -- PEACE, DEMOCRACY, AND SOCIAL HARMONY IN EL SALVADOR [WILL NOT BE REACHED] AS LONG AS THE UNITED STATES AND THE ARMY CONTINUE TO USURP THE POWER FORMALLY REPRESENTED BY A CIVILIAN GOVERNMENT, AND ANY PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS -- IN ADDITION TO YIELDING ANOTHER FARCE SIMILAR TO THE ONE THAT HAS JUST BEEN STAGED -- WILL ONLY RESULT IN AN ATMOSPHERE OF VIOLENCE THAT MIGHT EXTEND EVEN FURTHER AND REACH EVEN BLOODIER PROPORTIONS.

IF, ON THE CONTRARY, THOSE WHO REALLY HOLD POWER WERE INTERESTED IN A NEGOTIATED, PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, THEY WOULD AT LEAST BE TAKING THE FIRST SERIOUS STEPS TO MEET WITH THE OTHER BELLIGERENT FORCE: THE FMLN.

FOR THE TIME BEING, HOWEVER, THE NEW ELECTORAL FARCE HAS ACCOMPLISHED NOTHING BUT TO PROVIDE OVERWHELMING PROOF THAT IT IS ENTIRELY UNVIABLE AND INEFFECTIVE.

DEV-MUC3-0153 (BELLCORE)

EAST BERLIN (EAST GERMANY), 22 MAR 89 (NEUES DEUTSCHLAND) -- [REPORT] [PETER KIRSCHEY] [TEXT] HIS NAME STANDS AT THE TOP OF THE HIT LIST OF THE COLOMBIAN DEATH SQUAD: OSCAR DUENAS, MEMBER OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION (UP) AND CITY COUNSELOR OF TUNJA, NORTH OF THE CAPITAL OF BOGOTA.

IN A TALK DURING HIS VISIT TO BERLIN THIS WEEK, HE EMPHASIZED THE DRAMATIC SITUATION IN HIS HOME COUNTRY. IT IS CHARACTERIZED BY AN UNPRECEDENTED ANNIHILATION CAMPAIGN, WHICH IS AIMED MAINLY AT FUNCTIONARIES AND OFFICIALS OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION -- A MOVEMENT THAT INCLUDES COMMUNIST, LEFT-WING, AND OTHER DEMOCRATIC FORCES. MORE THAN 800 UP POLITICIANS HAVE ALREADY HAD TO PAY FOR THEIR SUPPORT FOR A DEMOCRATIC COLOMBIA WITH THEIR LIVES, OSCAR DUENAS NOTED.

THE COLOMBIAN PATRIOT SAID THAT THE ALL-POWERFUL NARCOTICS MAFIA, IN ALLIANCE WITH THE LARGE LANDOWNERS, RIGHT-WING MILITARY, AND PARTS OF THE OLIGARCHY ARE BEHIND ALL THESE ATTACKS. THEY FEAR FOR THEIR POWER AND ARE PREPARED TO USE ANY MEANS TO PRESERVE IT.

FROM HIS OWN EXPERIENCE, OSCAR DUENAS REPORTED HOW THE DEATH SQUAD PERSECUTES ITS OPPONENTS. A GROUP WHICH CALLS ITSELF "RAMBO" HAS WAYLAID HIM SEVERAL TIMES. HOWEVER, UP TO NOW HE HAS ALWAYS BEEN WARNED IN TIME. THERE IS ALWAYS THE DANGER OF HIS BEING SHOT AT FROM A WINDOW, A PASSING CAR, OR FROM BEHIND A BUSH. THIS IS WHY THE GOVERNMENT PROVIDES HIM -- AND OTHER UP POLITICIANS -- WITH BODYGUARDS AROUND THE CLOCK. "EVEN THOUGH THIS MEANS A PERMANENT THREAT, WE WILL CONTINUE TO FIGHT!" OSCAR DUENAS AFFIRMED.

ASKED ABOUT THE POSSIBILITIES OF A POLITICAL SOLUTION, THE CITY COUNSELOR OF TUNJA SEES AN OPPORTUNITY IF THE GOVERNMENT COOPERATES WITH ALL DEMOCRATS IN THE FIGHT AGAINST GANG TERRORISM AND DOES NOT TRY TO SPLIT UP THE MOVEMENT OF THE LEFT.

DEV-MUC3-0156 (BELLCORE)

LIMA, 27 MAR 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] A LOCAL RADIO STATION HAS REPORTED THAT ALLEGED SHINING PATH MEMBERS AND MERCENARIES AT THE SERVICE OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS TODAY ATTACKED AN IMPORTANT POLICE STATION IN THE JUNGLE DISTRICT OF UCHIZA, AND THAT THERE MAY BE MANY CASUALTIES ON BOTH SIDES.

THE RADIO STATION RADIO PROGRAMAS DEL PERU (PPR) BASES THEIR INFORMATION ON A REPORT FROM A SPOKESMAN OF ANOTHER POLICE STATION OF THE NATIONAL POLICE LOCATED IN TOCACHE, 145 KM SOUTH OF UCHIZA.

THE RADIO STATION SAID THAT IT WAS ABLE TO CONTACT THE TOCACHE POLICE THROUGH A HAM OPERATOR AND THAT THE INFORMATION RECEIVED INDICATES THAT FIGHTING LASTED FOR SEVERAL HOURS MAY HAVE CAUSED MANY CASUALTIES.

RADIO PROGRAMAS SAID THAT THE SO-CALLED "NARCOTERRORISTS" ATTACKED THE POLICE STATION WITH FIREARMS AND EXPLOSIVES.

THE UCHIZA POLICE STATION IS 550 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA AND HAS A COMPLIMENT OF ABOUT 50 POLICEMEN. THE POLICE SPOKESMAN TOLD THE RADIO STATION THAT THE NUMBER OF TERRORISTS WHO ATTACKED THE POLICE STATION IS NOT KNOWN.

A PERUVIAN TELEPHONE COMPANY SOURCE SAID THAT THE COMMUNICATION BETWEEN LIMA AND UCHIZA, BOTH TELEPHONE AND RADIO, "ARE INTERRUPTED" BUT THE REASONS FOR THIS WAS NOT GIVEN.

UCHIZA IS LOCATED IN THE SAN MARTIN DEPARTMENT, IN THE ALTO HUALLAGA REGION, WHICH HAS BEEN DOMINATED BY SHINING PATH FOR THE LAST 2 YEARS AND HAS ALLIED ITSELF WITH POWERFUL DRUG TRAFFICKERS ACCORDING TO PRIME MINISTER ARMANDO VILLANUEVA DEL CAMPO.

BOTH UCHIZA AND TOCACHE ARE CONSIDERED POTENTIAL ZONES FOR GROWING COCA AND FOR MAKING COCAINE BASE. THEY HAVE BEEN UNDER A STATE OF EMERGENCY AND MILITARY CONTROL SINCE 1987.

ACCORDING TO THE NATIONAL POLICE, PERU IS THE LARGEST PRODUCER OF COCA AND THE BIGGEST POTENTIAL SELLER OF COCAINE BASE TO INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

DEV-MUC3-0157 (BELLCORE)

LIMA, 28 MAR 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [INTERIOR MINISTRY] [TEXT] THIS IS COMMUNIQUE NO. 011-89 RELEASED BY THE INTERIOR MINISTRY WHICH STATES:

1. ON 27 MARCH, FROM 1710 TO 2250, THE POLICE BASE IN UCHIZA, MARISCAL CACERES PROVINCE, SAN MARTIN DEPARTMENT, WAS ATTACKED BY ARMED NARCOTERRORISTS.

THE GROUP WAS MADE UP OF APPROXIMATELY 300 MALE MEMBERS OF THE SHINING PATH AND NOTORIOUS LOCAL DRUG TRAFFICKERS, SOME OF WHOM ARE COLOMBIAN. THE MEN ARRIVED IN SIX OR SEVEN TRUCKS FROM TWO OPPOSITE DIRECTIONS. AFTER THE BATTLE, THEY FLED WITH THEIR WOUNDED AND DEAD COMRADES WHICH, ACCORDING TO LOCAL RESIDENTS, TOTALED ABOUT 50 MEN.

2. THIS IS CONSIDERED A NARCOTERRORIST ATTACK BECAUSE ON 25 MARCH AT 0500, THE NATIONAL POLICE ARRESTED NINE COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS FROM WHOM COCAINE BASE AND WEAPONS SIMILAR TO THE ONES USED BY THE ATACKERS WERE CONFISCATED.

3. THE AGGRESSORS USED SOPHISTICATED, LONG-RANGE, AUTOMATIC WEAPONS SUCH AS GRENADE LAUNCHERS. THEY ALSO HAD THREE MORTARS, AN ENOUGH AMMUNITION TO MAINTAIN A LONG FIGHT. SOME OF THE CARTRIDGES FOUND IN THE AREA SHOW THAT THEY COME FROM WEAPONS NOT NORMALLY USED IN PERU.

4. DUE TO A SHORTAGE OF AMMUNITION BECAUSE OF THE ABSENCE OF REINFORCEMENTS, WHO WERE HELD UP BY BAD WEATHER CONDITIONS, THE FOLLOWING POLICEMEN DIED IN COMBAT: MAJOR CARLOS FARFAN CORREA, CAPTAIN WALTER MOSCOSO CARDENAS, LIEUTENANT WALTER RENGUIFO LOPEZ, FIRST SERGEANT WILLIAN ESCALANTE CACERES, CORPORAL ALIPIO ARCELA MADRID, CORPORAL ANTONIO CONTRERAS NAVARRO, CORPORAL LUIS CARDENAS VALERA, CORPORAL REINALDO MACIAS FERNANDEZ, AGENT ERIC FELIX PACHERRI, AGENT HUILA SIBDA AQUINO, OFFICER CARLOS RICRA PAPARA, SERGEANT MAXIMO VERA TOCKSEN, SERGEANT VICTOR SALAZAR CLAVE, SERGEANT VIGIL SEGOVIA REBOLLEDO, SERGEANT RUPERTO MOSCOSO CARRERA, SERGEANT VICTOR RIZO ESCOBEDO, SERGEANT LUIS CASTRO GUISADO, SERGEANT FERNANDO ROJAS BALDEON, SERGEANT LUIS QUIPE MARTINEZ, SERGEANT LEONARDO HUGAZ RAMOS, CORPORAL OLOGUREN GARCIA ORTIZ, CORPORAL ROLANDO AIQUIPA CONTRERAS, GUARD JOSE ZINA CAETANO, AND GUARD ACALARDO JARA SOTO.

CORPORAL ASPILLA CORDOBA IS MISSING. THREE OTHER CIVILIANS, TWO WOMEN AND A MAN, ALSO DIED AND A YOUNG GIRL WAS WOUNDED.

5. AT THE END OF A 6-HOUR COURAGEOUS DEFENSE OF THE UCHIZA POLICE STATION, THE NARCOTERRORIST ATTACKERS ROBBED THE LOCAL BRANCHES OF THE NATIONAL BANK AND OF INTERBANK AND, USING SPECIAL TOOLS, OPENED VAULTS, TOOK FUNDS, AND DESTROYED DOCUMENTS.

THEY ALSO ATTACKED AND ROBBED THREE PHARMACIES AND STORES, THE PUBLIC REGISTRATION OFFICE, AND PRIVATE PROPERTY. THE TERRORISTS ALSO LEFT BULLET HOLES ON THE UCHIZA CHURCH.

6. THE FOLLOWING OFFICIALS WENT TO UCHIZA EARLY THIS MORNING: THE PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS AND INTERIOR MINISTER, THE DEFENSE MINISTER, THE DIRECTOR GENERAL OF THE NATIONAL POLICE AND OTHER SENIOR POLICE OFFICERS. ARMY AND POLICE FORCES WERE ALSO DEPLOYED TO UCHIZA TO SAFEGUARD SECURITY THERE AND IN THE SURROUNDING AREA.

DEV-MUC3-0159 (BELLCORE)

GUATEMALA CITY, 29 MAR 89 (CADENA DE EMISORAS UNIDAS) -- [REPORT] [CONRADO MONROY] [TEXT] THE FOLLOWING IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT. ONE HUNDRED PRISONERS HAVE SUCCEEDED IN EVADING THE SURVEILLANCE OF THE ARMED PRISONERS WHO ARE INSIDE PAVON PRISON. AFTER OVERCOMING A SERIES OF OBSTACLES AND RISKING THEIR LIVES, 100 PRISONERS ESCAPED FROM WHERE THEY HAD BEEN SHUT IN AND WENT TO PAVON PRISON'S ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICES FOR THEIR OWN SAFETY. ONCE THEY ARRIVED, THE PRISONERS ASKED PRISON AUTHORITIES TO TRANSFER THEM ELSEWHERE.

AFTER THE PRISONERS WERE PROPERLY IDENTIFIED AT THE PRISON WARDEN'S OFFICE, THEY WERE TAKEN TO A ZONE 18 PENITENTIARY IN GUATEMALA CITY.

WE REPEAT: ONE HUNDRED PRISONERS ESCAPED AND SOUGHT PROTECTION FROM THE AUTHORITIES, WHO IMMEDIATELY SENT THEM TO A PENITENTIARY IN ZONE 18 FOR THEIR PROTECTION.

ACCORDING TO THE PRISONERS, THE RIOTERS CONTINUE TO MAINTAIN THEIR POSITION THAT THE GOVERNMENT MUST FULFILL ALL THEIR DEMANDS. THE RIOTING PRISONERS SHOT AT THE ESCAPEES, THUS FRIGHTENING THE CHILDREN AND THE ELDERLY WHO REMAIN INSIDE THE PRISON.

DEV-MUC3-0161 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 30 MAR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] A REPORT FROM SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT STATES THAT FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT ANTIAIRCRAFT UNITS AMBUSHED A SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTER IN ARENALES CANTON AT 1700 GMT ON 29 MARCH THAT WAS TRAVELING FROM USULUTAN TO SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT. OUR UNITS' EFFECTIVE ANTIAIRCRAFT FIRE HIT AND DAMAGED THE HELICOPTER. THE HELICOPTER WAS FORCED TO MAKE AN EMERGENCY LANDING IN JUCUAPA.

THIS REPORT CONFIRMS THAT THE PILOT WAS KILLED AND ONE CREWMEMBER WAS INJURED AS A RESULT OF THE EMERGENCY LANDING. WE REPEAT: THE PILOT WAS KILLED AND ONE CREWMEMBER WAS INJURED AS A RESULT OF THE EMERGENCY LANDING. THAT IS THE REPORT WE ARE RECEIVING FROM JUCUAPA, WHERE THE HELICOPTER WAS FORCED TO MAKE AN EMERGENCY LANDING.

THE REPORT ADDS THAT A FEW MINUTES AFTER THE AMBUSH, A HELICOPTER GUNSHIP ARRIVED IN THE AREA LAUNCHING ROCKETS AND INDISCRIMINATELY FIRING AT THE LA NORIA AND LA PENA CANTONS' CIVILIAN POPULATION. WE SEND OUR REVOLUTIONARY GREETINGS TO SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, BECAUSE WE RECOGNIZE OUR COMRADES' GOOD MARKSMANSHIP.

DEV-MUC3-0163 (BELLCORE)

SOFIA (BULGARIA), 31 MAR 89 (BTA) -- [TEXT] MR MANUEL CEPEDA [SPELLING OF NAME AS RECEIVED], MEMBER OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE OF THE CC OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY (PCC) AND EDITOR IN CHIEF OF THE VOZ NEWSPAPER, VISITED THIS COUNTRY FROM MARCH 28 TO MARCH 31.

HE HAD A MEETING WITH MR DIMITUR STANISHEV, SECRETARY OF THE CC [CENTRAL COMMITTEE] OF THE BCP [BULGARIAN COMMUNIST PARTY], WHO ACQUAINTED THE GUEST WITH THE LATEST MOMENTS OF THE ACTIVITY OF THE BCP IN IMPLEMENTATION OF THE TASKS RELATED TO THE INNOVATIVE PROCESSES IN THE DIFFERENT SPHERES OF THE SOCIOPOLITICAL LIFE IN BULGARIA. OPINIONS WERE EXCHANGED ON THE CONDITION OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNIST MOVEMENT, ON THE NEED OF CREATIVE RECONSIDERATION OF THE INTERNAL AND INTERNATIONAL REALITIES IN THE SPIRIT OF THE AIMS AND CONTENT OF THE NEW POLITICAL THINKING.

MR CEPEDA SPOKE OF THE EXCEPTIONALLY HARD AND COMPREHENSIVE CONDITIONS FOR THE ACTIVITY OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNISTS AND THE REPRESENTATIVES OF THE DIFFERENT DEMOCRATIC ORGANIZATIONS IN COLOMBIA. HE SAID THAT ALMOST 1,000 ACTIVISTS AND MEMBERS OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY AND THE PATRIOTIC UNION HAVE DIED DURING THE RECENT YEARS KILLED BY ASSASSINS HIRED BY THE REACTION. IN THIS CONNECTION THE GUEST POINTED OUT THE NEED OF ACTIVATION AND BROADENING OF INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY IN DEFENCE OF THE PROGRESSIVE, PATRIOTIC AND DEMOCRATIC FORCES IN COLOMBIA, SOLIDARITY WITH THE STRUGGLE OF THE PEOPLE'S MASSES IN THE STRUGGLE FOR PRESERVATION OF DEMOCRACY, FOR PEACE AND SOCIAL PROGRESS.

MR MANUEL CEPEDA HAD A MEETING WITH MR RADOSLAV RADEV, EDITOR IN CHIEF OF THE RABOTNICHESKO DELO DAILY. THEY DISCUSSED THE OPPORTUNITIES FOR BROADENING OF THE COOPERATION BETWEEN THE PAPERS OF THE BCP AND THE PCC.

DEV-MUC3-0164 (BELLCORE)

CLANDESTINE, 6 APR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THE FUTURE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] GOVERNMENT IS ILLEGAL BECAUSE THE RESULTS OF THE 19 MARCH ELECTION, MORE SO THAN IN ANY OTHER PAST ELECTION, DO NOT REPRESENT THE WISHES OF THE MAJORITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THOSE ELECTIONS WERE MARKED BY ABSTENTION AS A RESULT OF THE REJECTION OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] PEACE PROPOSAL. THOSE ELECTIONS WERE HELD WHILE THERE WAS A WAR AND WHILE THE COUNTRY WAS DIVIDED. THIS CLEARLY SHOWED THE DUALITY OF POWER THAT EXISTS. THIS CLEARLY SHOWED THAT THE MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE ARE DEMANDING A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE WAR. WITHOUT NEGOTIATION, NO ONE CAN RULE IN EL SALVADOR. THEREFORE, A MILITARY SOLUTION OR THE SURRENDER OF THE FMLN IS NOT POSSIBLE. THE FUTURE GOVERNMENT HAS TWO OPTIONS: TO BE A GOVERNMENT THAT WILL INCREASE THE WAR OR TO BE A GOVERNMENT THAT WILL MOVE TOWARD PEACE.

THE FMLN JOINS ALL THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL FORCES THAT EXPRESSED THEIR CONCERN FOR ARENA'S COMING TO POWER. WE DO NOT BELIEVE IN ITS [WORD INDISTINCT] CAMPAIGN IN WHICH THEY ARE TRYING TO PRESENT THEMSELVES AS MODERATES. IN LESS THAN 20 DAYS, AND WITHOUT FORMALLY ASSUMING POWER, THERE HAS BEEN AN INCREASE IN REPRESSION AND SOCIAL TENSION, AS HAS BEEN EXPRESSED IN DOZENS OF MISSING PERSONS, MURDERS, AND ARRESTS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. LABOR UNION OFFICES AND THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY CAMPUS HAVE BEEN CORDONED OFF; CIVILIANS HAVE BEEN VICTIMS OF TERRORIST ATTACKS; GRENADES AND BOMBS HAVE BEEN EXPLODED IN PUBLIC PLACES; AND THE FMLN IS BLAMED FOR THOSE ATTACKS. JOURNALISTS HAVE BEEN MURDERED; THERE HAS BEEN A SYSTEMATIC INTIMIDATION OF THE PRESS AND ATTEMPTS TO CURB FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION; AND MEMBERS OF THE DEATH SQUADS LINKED TO ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON HAVE BEEN RELEASED FROM PRISON. THERE HAVE BEEN THREATS OF SEIZING LAND THAT BELONGS TO COOPERATIVES; THERE HAVE BEEN ANNOUNCEMENTS THAT THE BANKING SYSTEM AND FOREIGN TRADE WILL BE PRIVATIZED AND THAT MANY GOVERNMENT WORKERS WILL BE FIRED. THERE IS A CLIMATE OF TERROR THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. THIS CLIMATE OF TERROR IS THE RESULT OF THE ARROGANCE AND THE DESIRE FOR REVENGE ON THE PART OF ARENA AND SECTORS OF THE ARMED FORCES. ARENA HAS CLEARLY STATED THAT IT WILL HAVE A POLICY OF KILLINGS AND TOTAL WARFARE AND HAS GIVEN NO SIGN OF WANTING PEACE.

IT IS URGENT THAT AN ADEQUATE FRAMEWORK FOR DIALOGUE BE CREATED. THIS MEANS ARENA MUST:

1. CEASE ALL KILLINGS, ARRESTS, DISAPPEARANCES, AND TERRORIST ATTACKS ON CIVILIANS; IT MUST RESPECT THE PRESS AND FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION AND PUT AN END TO MILITARIZATION OF WORKPLACES, MILITARY CORDONS, AND ALL REPRESSIVE ACTIONS PERPETRATED BY THE ARMED FORCES AND THE DEATH SQUADS.

2. ARENA MUST RESPECT THE NATIONALIZATION OF BANKS, FOREIGN TRADE, AND AGRARIAN REFORM. IT MUST ENSURE THAT COOPERATIVES' PROPERTY WILL BE RESPECTED; THAT THERE WILL BE NO APPROPRIATION HEARINGS INVOLVING PEOPLE WHO HAVE BENEFITED FROM AGRARIAN REFORM; AND THAT THERE WILL BE NO ECONOMIC MEASURES AIMED AT FORCING THOSE PEOPLE INTO BANKRUPTCY OR INTO SELLING THEIR LAND. LIKEWISE, ARENA MUST PROMISE THAT THERE WILL BE NO MASS DISMISSALS OF GOVERNMENT WORKERS.

3. ARENA MUST PROMISE A REAL DIALOGUE AND NOT A USELESS DIALOGUE AIMED AT BRINGING ABOUT THE FMLN'S SURRENDER. ARENA, AND THE SECTORS IT REPRESENTS, HAS AND ALWAYS HAS HAD REAL POWER. THEY ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR ALL THAT HAPPENS IN THE COUNTRY. THEY CANNOT CLAIM, AS SALVADORAN PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE AND THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY HAVE CLAIMED, A LACK OF AUTHORITY TO CONTROL REPRESSION OR A LACK OF POWER TO NEGOTIATE.

ARENA HAS ECONOMIC, JUDICIAL, AND LEGISLATIVE POWER AND IT HAS EVEN SEIZED POWER IN THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH. ARENA HAS ITS OWN PARAMILITARY FORCES, DEATH SQUADS, AND CONTROLS AN IMPORTANT SECTOR OF THE ARMED FORCES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0166 (BELLCORE)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 8 APR 89 (ACAN) -- [TEXT] NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA SAAVEDRA TODAY CRITICIZED THE RATIFICATION OF A BILATERAL MILITARY AID AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNITED STATES AND HONDURAS BECAUSE, HE SAID, IT DEALS A BLOW TO THE PEACE AGREEMENT SIGNED IN EL SALVADOR IN FEBRUARY.

AT THAT MEETING, THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ASKED GOVERNMENTS BOTH IN AND OUTSIDE THE REGION THAT OPENLY OR COVERTLY PROVIDE AID TO UNCONVENTIONAL FORCES TO IMMEDIATELY HALT THEIR AID.

ON 29 MARCH, THE U.S. AND HONDURAN GOVERNMENTS RATIFIED THE ADDITIONAL PROTOCOL OF A BILATERAL MILITARY AID AGREEMENT.

THE NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT MADE THESE REMARKS DURING TODAY'S INAUGURATION OF A HYDROELECTRICAL PROJECT IN ASTURIAS, JINOTEGA, NORTHERN NICARAGUA, THAT WILL SAVE THE COUNTRY APPROXIMATELY 200,000 BARRELS OF OIL EVERY YEAR.

ORTEGA SAID THAT THE UNITED STATES CANNOT CRITICIZE THE ARMS BUILDUP IN THE REGION WHILE IT PROMOTES MILITARY MANEUVERS AND BRINGS WEAPONRY INTO CENTRAL AMERICA, PARTICULARLY INTO HONDURAS.

THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT THE PRESENCE OF U.S. TROOPS IN HONDURAS HEIGHTENS TENSION IN THE REGION AND DEALS A BLOW TO THE EL SALVADOR AGREEMENT.

THE HYDROELECTRIC PROJECT INAUGURATED TODAY IS LOCATED IN APANAS LAKE, JINOTEGA DEPARTMENT. IT WILL SEND ELECTRIC POWER TO THE CENTRAL AMERICA AND CARLOS FONSECA PLANTS, WHICH TOGETHER WILL PRODUCE OVER 4 MILLION KILOWATTS OF ELECTRICITY AN HOUR.

ACCORDING TO AN OFFICIAL SOURCE, LATIN AMERICAN AND EUROPEAN CAPITAL WAS USED FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE ASTURIAS PROJECT, WHICH TOOK 5 YEARS TO COMPLETE.

DEV-MUC3-0168 (BELLCORE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 7 APR 89 (EL NUEVO DIARIO) -- [TEXT] COMMANDER [BAYARDO] ARCE HAS DECRIBED THE OPPOSITION'S TRIP TO GUATEMALA AS A "BLUNDER" AND SAID THAT IT WOULD BE REGRETTABLE IF THE POLITICAL PARTIES WENT TO THAT MEETING TO LOOK FOR A "LEADER" TO CONFRONT THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FSLN] FROM AMONG THOSE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARY CHIEFTAINS.

ARCE, A MEMBER OF THE [FSLN NATIONAL] DIRECTORATE, INSISTED THAT THE OPPOSITION'S MEETING WITH THE MERCENARIES IS A "BLUNDER" FROM ANY POINT OF VIEW SINCE WHICHEVER PARTY DECIDES TO BE THE UMBRELLA ORGANIZATION FOR ALL THESE GROUPS WILL NOT GAIN ANY PRESTIGE.

NONETHELESS, HE SAID THE BEST THING WOULD BE FOR THE CONTRAS TO FIND OUT WHO WILL BE THE STEPPING STONE FOR THEM TO ENTER THE COUNTRY, INASMUCH AS IT IS A DEFEATED MERCENARY FORCE THAT HAS BEEN UNMASKED AS DEPENDENT ON THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.

"I DO NOT BELIEVE THEY HAVE THE NERVE TO SAY THAT THEY ARE NOW A POLITICAL PARTY, AND THAT THEY ARE LOOKING FOR SOMEONE WHO WILL BE THEIR STEPPING STONE IN ORDER FOR THEM TO JOIN THE CIVIC STRUGGLE NOW THAT THE THE WAR OPTION HAS BEEN DEFEATED," HE ADDED.

THE SANDINIST LEADER INSISTED THAT IF THE OPPOSITION GOES TO GUATEMALA TO LOOK FOR A "LEADER" TO CONFRONT THE [FSLN] IN THE ELECTIONS, THIS WILL DEMONSTRATE THAT THE POLITICAL PARTIES ARE WEAK.

HE ADDED THE CONTRA CHIEFTAINS DO NOT HAVE THE QUALIFICATIONS TO BECOME PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES SINCE THEY ARE MORE CRIMINAL THAN THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES THEMSELVES WHO CARRY OUT AMBUSHES, WHILE THEIR CHEIFTAINS SIT IN LUXURY HOTELS IN TEGUCIGALPA, SAN JOSE, MIAMI, AND WASHINGTON ENCOURAGING THE AGGRESSION AGAINST THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE.

WHEN ASKED ABOUT FSLN ACTIVITIES FOR THE NEXT ELECTION CAMPAIGN, ARCE SAID THAT HIS PARTY IS NOT OUT PREPARING FOR ELECTIONS BUT IS CONTINUING TO WORK TOWARD THE FULFILLMENT OF ALL THE TASKS THAT THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE ARE CARRYING OUT, PARTICULARLY THE STRUGGLE FOR PEACE AND FOR THE ECONOMY.

WE WILL PREPARE OUR FORCES FOR THE FEBRUARY 1990 ELECTIONS, BUT FIRST WE HAVE THE TASKS AHEAD FOR CELEBRATING THE 10TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE REVOLUTION, HE ADDED.

THE COMMITTEE THAT WILL ORGANIZE THE CELEBRATIONS WILL BE ANNOUNCED ON 19 APRIL.

[COMMANDER] ARCE SAID THAT THE NEXT ELECTION CAMPAIGN MIGHT BE MORE "INTERESTING" IF THE PARTIES THAT BELIEVED THAT THE [REAGAN] ADMINISTRATION WOULD DEFEAT THE REVOLUTION MILITARILY AND ABSTAINED FROM THE 1984 ELECTION WOULD DECIDE TO JOIN THE CIVIC STRUGGLE.

DUE TO THE PEACE EFFORTS OF THE REVOLUTION, EVEN THE CONTRAS COULD PARTICIPATE IN THE ELECTIONS, AND WE WILL FIND OUT WHO'S WHO AND EACH PARTY WILL BE ABLE TO EXPLAIN WHAT IT HAS DONE FOR THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE, THE SANDINIST LEADER SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0169 (BELLCORE)

QUITO, 11 APR 89 (RADIO QUITO) -- [TEXT] THE MARCH ORGANIZED BY FORMER ECUADORAN PRESIDENT LEON FEBRES CORDERO AND HIS SUPPORTERS HAS TAKEN PLACE IN GUAYAQUIL WITHOUT MAJOR INCIDENT BECAUSE THE SMALL GROUP OF DEMONSTRATORS WAS CONTROLLED BY MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE POSTED ALONG 9 OCTOBER AVENUE, THE SITE OF THE DISTURBANCE. FORMER PRESIDENT LEON FEBRES CORDERO, HIS WIFE, AND SEVERAL OF HIS CLOSE SUPPORTERS MARCHED DOWN THE PORT CITY'S MAIN AVENUE FOR A FEW MINUTES AND THEN, ACCORDING TO REPORTS FROM HIS NEIGHBORS, WENT TO HIS HOUSE. THE FORMER PRESIDENT AND HIS CLOSE FRIENDS HAVE REMAINED INSIDE THE HOUSE SINCE 1705.

THE DISTURBANCES IN GUAYAQUIL RESULTED IN TWO INJURIES. ONE OF THE INJURED PERSONS IS 1ST COMPANY POLICEMAN LUIS CASTRO ROMAN, WHO HAS BEEN ADMITTED TO LUIS VERNAZA HOSPITAL. POLICEMAN CASTRO ROMAN WAS SHOT BY ONE OF THE DEMONSTRATORS. THE BULLET LODGED IN THE RIGHT SIDE OF HIS CHEST. THE BLOODY INCIDENT OCCURRED ON BOYACA AND 9 OCTOBER AVENUES. ALSO INJURED DURING THE DEMONSTRATION WAS A CITIZEN WHO HAS NOT BEEN INDENTIFIED.

SOURCES CLOSE TO THE GOVERNMENT HAVE REPORTED THAT THE NATIONAL POLICE DID NOT USE FIREARMS DURING THE DEMONSTRATION. LEON FEBRES CORDERO'S MARCH IN GUAYAQUIL BEGAN AT 1600 WITH A VERY SMALL GROUP OF PERSONS. THE GROUP GATHERED ON BOYACA AND 9 OCTOBER AVENUES. THE DEMONSTRATORS BEGAN THEIR MARCH BUT WERE IMMEDIATELY CONTROLLED BY THE POLICE WITH THE USE OF TEAR GAS AND WATER. FEBRES CORDERO'S WIFE WAS ALSO PRESENT ON 9 OCTOBER AVENUE; SHE WALKED A SHORT DISTANCE TO MEET HER HUSBAND. THEY THEN LEFT THE AREA WHERE THE DISTURBANCE TOOK PLACE.

IN CONCLUSION, THE DEMONSTRATION PLANNED BY THE SOCIAL CHRISTIANS AND FORMER PRESIDENT FEBRES CORDERO'S SUPPORTERS RESULTED IN TWO INJURIES.

DEV-MUC3-0170 (BELLCORE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 13 APR 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [TEXT] THE GROUP OF 14 OPPOSITION PARTY DELEGATES HAVE RETURNED FROM GUATEMALA, WHERE THEY SIGNED AN ALLIANCE AGREEMENT WITH THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES AND HOSTED A NEWS CONFERENCE AT THE INTERNATIONAL PRESS CLUB IN MANAGUA. GUILLERMO POTOY, DELEGATE FROM THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC PARTY, SAID THAT THE CONTRAS ARE WILLING TO LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS IF THERE IS DEMOCRATIZATION IN THE COUNTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [POTOY] I BELIEVE THAT THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE WOULD BE WILLING TO COME TO NICARAGUA. JUDGING FROM WHAT THEY SAID, I BELIEVE THEY WOULD BE WILLING TO RETURN ONCE IT APPEARS THAT THERE IS DEMOCRATIZATION. THEY TRUST THE 14 OR 15 OPPOSITION POLITICAL PARTIES AND SUPPORT THE DECISIONS MADE BY THESE PARTIES CONCERNING THE ELECTIONS. IN EL SALVADOR, THE WAR INTENSIFIED DURING THE ELECTIONS, AND THOSE WHO FINANCED THE WAR CONTINUED TO FINANCE IT IN ORDER TO [WORDS INDISTINCT]. IN NICARAGUA, THE HUMANITARIAN AID ENSURES THAT NOT A SINGLE SHOT WILL BE FIRED. I BELIEVE THIS IS A POSITIVE CONTRIBUTION. WE MUST BEGIN AT THE BEGINNING, WHICH IS WHERE WE SHOULD HAVE BEEN, AND NOT WHERE WE ARE NOW. [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

JUST LOOK AT WHERE WE ARE NOW. WHAT HAS HAPPENED IN THE LAST FEW YEARS IN NICARAGUA? THERE HAS BEEN PLENTY OF WAR, MANY DEATHS. NOW A PEACE PROCESS HAS BEGUN IN NICARAGUA. THIS HELPS ENSURE THAT NOT A SINGLE SHOT WILL BE FIRED AND THAT THE ELECTIONS WILL BE HELD IN PEACE. THEN WE NICARAGUANS WILL BE ABLE TO COMPLY. IT IS UP TO THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT TO INSTITUTE DEMOCRACY IN NICARAGUA, WHICH WILL ENSURE AN AUTOMATIC END TO THE WAR. I BELIEVE THERE IS NO REASON WHY WE, THE NICARAGUAN CIVIC OPPOSITION, WOULD NOT BE WILLING TO JOIN ANY EFFORT ONCE DEMOCRACY HAS BEEN ACHIEVED IN NICARAGUA. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0171 (BELLCORE)

SOFIA (BULGARIA), 12 APR 89 (RABOTNICHESKO DELO) -- [INTERVIEW WITH MANUEL CEPEDA, MEMBER OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE OF THE CENTRAL COMMITTEE OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF COLOMBIA, BY DETELIN SERTOV, REPRESENTATIVE OF THE RABOTNICHESKO DELO EDITORIAL BOARD] [TEXT] [SERTOV] POLITICAL LIFE IN COLOMBIA IS STILL LINKED WITH VIOLENCE.....

[CEPEDA] COLOMBIA IS EXPERIENCING AN EXTREMELY SEVERE POLITICAL AND INSTITUTIONAL CRISIS, CAUSED BY THE INCOMPATIBILITY BETWEEN THE FAST DEVELOPING PRODUCTIVE FORCES AND THE EXISTING POLITICAL SETUP. FOR EXAMPLE, LAST YEAR COLOMBIA'S ECONOMIC GROWTH WAS 4.5 PERCENT. HOWEVER, POLITICAL LIFE CONTINUES TO BE DOMINATED BY THE TWO OLD PARTIES -- THE LIBERALS AND THE CONSERVATIVES, WHO MAINTAIN A MERELY FORMAL DEMOCRACY. WE SHOULD NOT FORGET COLOMBIA'S STRATEGIC POSITION: IT FORMS A BRIDGE BETWEEN CENTRAL AND SOUTH AMERICA. ALL EVENTS IN COLOMBIA AFFECT THE NEIGHBORING COUNTRIES.

PRECISELY BECAUSE OF THIS, THE SO-CALLED "SANTA FE-2" DOCUMENT, DRAWN UP BY EXTREME RIGHT-WING U.S. POLITICIANS, CONTAINS A PLAN TO APPLY PRESSURE IN COLOMBIA AND, MORE SPECIFICALLY, TO EXPAND THE SO-CALLED LOW-INTENSITY CONFLICT, ONE OF WHOSE MANIFESTATIONS IS THE SO-CALLED "DIRTY WAR" IN THE COUNTRY.

ACCORDINGLY, THE VIOLENCE IN COLOMBIA IS CAUSED BY BOTH INTERNAL FACTORS -- THE CRISIS OF THE INSTITUTIONS -- AND EXTERNAL ONES, NAMELY THE POLICIES OF THE MOST REACTIONARY CIRCLES IN THE UNITED STATES.

[SERTOV] CAN ONE EXPECT THE PEACE SETTLEMENT TO BE FULFILLED UNDER THESE CONDITIONS?

[CEPEDA] THIS IS THE AIM OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF COLOMBIA [PCC]. AT OUR RECENT 15TH CONGRESS, WE MADE A DETAILED ANALYSIS OF THE SITUATION AND CONCLUDED THAT THE CONFLICT IN COLOMBIA MUST BE SETTLED BY POLITICAL MEANS. THE PCC RAISED THE QUESTION OF REMOVING THE SIEGE SITUATION THAT, WITH A FEW INTERRUPTIONS, HAS BEEN MAINTAINED FOR SEVERAL DECADES, AND OF DISBANDING THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS (ACCORDING TO THE MINISTER OF INTERNAL AFFAIRS, ABOUT 140 SUCH GROUPS ARE OPERATING). THESE GROUPS OWE THEIR VERY EXISTENCE TO THE SUPPORT GIVEN BY MILITARY CIRCLES AND THE CLAN CHIEFS TO THE TRADE IN NARCOTICS. (I WILL ADD IN PARENTHESES THAT THIS IS THE REASON FOR THE USE OF THE TERM "NARCOMILITARISM" IN COLOMBIA.) ONE OF THE PCC'S DEMANDS IS THAT THE ARMY SHOULD BE PURGED OF FASCIST ELEMENTS AND THAT A CIVILIAN SHOULD BE PUT IN CHARGE OF THE MINISTRY OF DEFENSE. THE PARTY ALSO RAISED THE QUESTION OF MAKING A START ON THE NECESSARY DEMOCRATIC REFORMS, BUT THE GOVERNMENT PAYS NO HEED TO OUR DEMANDS.

THE GOVERNMENT RECENTLY REACHED AN AGREEMENT WITH "M-19," ONE OF THE PARTISAN GROUPINGS IN THE COUNTRY, BUT DID NOT ACCEPT ANY COMMITMENTS IN PRACTICE. ACCORDINGLY, THERE ARE SOME DOUBTS OVER HOW THE LIVES OF THE PARTISAN LEADERS WILL BE SUBSEQUENTLY GUARANTEED. THE LARGEST PARTISAN GROUP -- THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA -- IS DEMANDING THAT THE GOVERNMENT TAKE SERIOUS STEPS TO LIMIT THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS, IN ORDER TO CONCLUDE A TRUCE.

[SERTOV] CLEARLY, IT WILL NOT BE EASY TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN COLOMBIA.

[CEPEDA] AT THE MOMENT, PEACE SUPPORTERS IN COLOMBIA ARE FORMING A BROAD FRONT, WHICH IN PRACTICE HAS AN ANTIFASCIST ORIENTATION. PEACE DEPENDS ON HOW FAR THIS FRONT WILL SUCCEED IN EXPANDING, HOW THE CONTRADICTIONS WITHIN THE GOVERNMENT ITSELF REGARDING THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS WILL DEEPEN, AND ON WHETHER WE WILL SUCCEED IN ISOLATING THEM. WE ARE OPTIMISTS, BUT ALSO HAVE A GREAT NEED OF INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY.

[SERTOV] HOW DO YOU ASSESS THE POLITICAL PROSPECTS FOR THE UNITED LEFT IN YOUR COUNTRY?

[CEPEDA] THE LEFT FORCES IN COLOMBIA ARE UNITED IN THE PATRIOTIC UNION THAT WAS CREATED 4 YEARS AGO. ITS AIM IS TO ACHIEVE NATIONAL RECONCILIATION IN OUR COUNTRY. HOWEVER, THE UNION IMMEDIATELY BECAME A TARGET OF THE ORGANIZERS OF THE "DIRTY WAR." HUNDREDS OF ITS LEADERS WERE BEATEN UP, MANY OF WHOM WERE PCC MEMBERS. SO FAR, OVER 1,000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED, INCLUDING JAIME PARDO LEAL, LEADER OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION, DEPUTY CHAIRMAN JOSE ANTEGUERA, AND OTHERS. THREATS CONTINUE TO BE MADE AGAINST THE UNION AND AGAINST THE PCC. ALL MEMBERS OF THE PCC LEADERSHIP HAVE RECEIVED DEATH THREATS. THE SAME ALSO APPLIES TO BERNARDO JARAMILLO, THE PRESENT LEADER OF THE UNION, GILBERTO VIEIRA, SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE PCC CENTRAL COMMITTEE, AND OTHERS.

ON 27 FEBRUARY COMRADE FORERO [NAME AS TRANSLITERATED], PCC SECRETARY FOR ORGANIZATIONAL MATTERS, WAS KILLED. HIS WIFE AND COMRADES SOTELO AND SOTOMAYOR ALSO DIED IN THE ATROCITY. NEXT DAY, WE HAD A MEETING WITH VIRGILIO BARCO, PRESIDENT OF COLOMBIA. HE PROMISES TO TAKE SPEEDY MEASURES AGAINST THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS. HOWEVER, ONLY 4 DAYS LATER, ANTEGUERA, THE FORMER LEADER OF THE UNION OF COMMUNIST YOUTH, WAS KILLED AT BOGOTA AIRPORT. SENATOR ERNESTO PISANO, ONE OF THE LIBERAL PARTY CANDIDATES FOR THE PRESIDENCY, WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED AT THE SAME TIME. MANY MEMBERS OF THE MILITARY WERE PRESENT AT THE AIRPORT ON THAT DAY, AS WELL AS THE POLICE CHIEF OF THE CAPITAL, YET ONLY ONE OF THE MURDERERS WAS KILLED, WHILE THE REST ESCAPED. THIS IS WHY WE TOLD PRESIDENT BARCO THAT WE HAD SERIOUS DOUBTS ABOUT THE ARMY'S ROLE IN THIS ASSASSINATION.

NEXT YEAR, PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS AND ELECTIONS OF THE LEGISLATIVE BODIES ARE DUE TO TAKE PLACE IN COLOMBIA. THE PCC AND THE PATRIOTIC UNION WANT TO TAKE PART IN THEM, BUT WE HAVE WARNED THE LEADERS OF THE REPUBLIC THAT UNLESS THE "DIRTY WAR" IS ENDED, WE WILL EXPOSE THE SITUATION IN COLOMBIA TO THE WORLD AND REGARD THE ELECTION RESULTS AS ILLEGAL. DESPITE EVERYTHING, WE CONSIDER THAT THE PATRIOTIC UNION HAS A PROMISING FUTURE, BECAUSE ITS AIMS ARE SUPPORTED BY THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE.

DEV-MUC3-0172 (BELLCORE)

BOGOTA, 14 APR 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT BARCO VIGOROUSLY DEFENDED COLOMBIA'S IMAGE REGARDING ITS STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, TERRORISM, AND COMMON CRIME IN A SPEECH HE GAVE IN WASHINGTON THIS MORNING. HE POINTED TO THE ERADICATION OF ILLITERACY, COMMENTED ON THE NATION'S ECONOMIC INDEXES, AND SAID THAT COUNTLESS COLOMBIANS HAVE BEEN ASSASSINATED IN THEIR STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

PRESIDENT BARCO INVITED OTHER AREA COUNTRIES TO JOIN EFFORTS TO END DRUG CULTIVATION, TRAFFICKING, AND CONSUMPTION. COLOMBIA CANNOT FIGHT THIS EVIL ALONE, BARCO ASSERTED. HE GAVE SPECIFIC STATISTICS ABOUT BLOWS THAT HAVE BEEN STRUCK AGAINST COLOMBIAN DRUG CARTELS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BARCO] I CAME TO MAKE AN APPEAL TO YOU. LET US ALL COMBINE OUR EFFORTS AND ENERGIES IN AN ALLIANCE THAT IS STRONGER AND BETTER COORDINATED THAN THAT OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. WE NEED AN ALLIANCE OF NATIONS AFFECTED BY DRUG TRAFFICKING IN ORDER TO RESPOND EFFECTIVELY. DRUG TRAFFICKING IS NOT THE PROBLEM OF A SINGLE NATION, OR EVEN OF A GROUP OF NATIONS. IT IS A UNIVERSAL OUTRAGE. UNLESS WE DEVISE STRONG AND EFFECTIVE MEANS OF INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION TO FIGHT AGAINST ALL PHASES OF THE PROBLEM, A FINAL VICTORY WILL NOT BE POSSIBLE.

FOR THIS REASON, I WISH TO USE THIS FORUM TO MAKE A NEW PROPOSAL TO REFLECT THE SENSE OF URGENCY THAT WE ALL FEEL WITH REGARD TO THIS PROBLEM. WE -- ALL PRESIDENTS OF THE AMERICAN HEMISPHERE, ALONG WITH PRESIDENT BUSH AND OUR OTHER COLLEAGUES OF THOSE NATIONS MOST AFFECTED BY THE INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING SCOURGE -- SHOULD MEET AS SOON AS POSSIBLE TO JOINTLY EXERCISE THE PUBLIC, POLITICAL AUTHORITY CONFERRED UPON US BY THE WILL OF OUR PEOPLE. [END RECORDING]

THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT REITERATED HIS CONDEMNATION OF WEAPONS PRODUCTION AND TRAFFICKING, HIGHLIGHTED COLOMBIA'S DEMOCRACY, AND SAID THAT HIS COUNTRY WILL INCREASE EFFORTS IN ITS CONTINUED STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

DEV-MUC3-0173 (BELLCORE)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 APR 89 (TCS TELEVISION) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT-ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] YOU MENTIONED THE ATTACK ON THE RESIDENCE OF VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT FRANCISCO MERINO. WE WOULD LIKE YOU TO GIVE US SOME DETAILS ON THIS.

[CRISTIANI] AT APPROXIMATELY 0530 THIS MORNING, THREE EXPLOSIVES WERE HURLED AT HIS RESIDENCE FROM AN EMPTY LOT. THE EXPLOSIVES CAUSED EXTENSIVE DAMAGE TO THE RESIDENCE. THERE WAS RIFLE FIRE TOO, BUT THE RIFLE FIRE WAS ONLY TO DISTRACT SECURITY PERSONNEL IN THE AREA.

THE ATTACKERS ACTED LIKE ANIMALS. MR MERINO IS STILL IN THE UNITED STATES WITH HIS WIFE. HE WILL BE RETURNING THIS AFTERNOON. THEIR FOUR CHILDREN AND THREE OF THE CHILDREN'S FRIENDS WERE AT THE RESIDENCE WHEN THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE. THE CHILDREN COULD HAVE BEEN KILLED. THOSE WHO CARRIED OUT THIS ATTACK ARE PEOPLE WHO FOR A LONG TIME HAVE BEEN TALKING ABOUT HUMAN RIGHTS AND ABOUT INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS. THIS ATTACK ENDANGERED CIVILIANS. THANK GOODNESS ONLY ONE OF THE CHILDREN WAS WOUNDED. ONE OF THE GIRLS WHO WAS VISITING THE HOME WAS HIT BY SOME SHRAPNEL BUT THE WOUND IS NOT SERIOUS. RIGHT NOW WE ARE GETTING A DOCTOR TO EXAMINE THE CHILDREN TO SEE IF THEIR HEARING HAS BEEN DAMAGED BECAUSE TWO OF THE DEVICES EXPLODED IN THE BEDROOM THE CHILDREN WERE IN.

I BELIEVE THIS IS ANOTHER INDICATION THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], FAR FROM SEEKING PEACE AND WANTING PEACE FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WANTS TO CONTINUE ITS TERRORISM, ITS KILLINGS -- ITS IRRATIONAL KILLINGS. I BELIEVE THAT LITTLE CAN BE ACHIEVED IN THE SEARCH FOR PEACE THROUGH DIALOGUE BECAUSE THESE PEOPLE ARE NOT SINCERE WHEN THEY CLAIM THAT THEY WANT TO RESOLVE THE PROBLEM.

THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE TIRED OF VIOLENCE. THEY STATED THEIR OPINION ON 19 MARCH. THE FMLN SHOULD THINK CAREFULLY BECAUSE THE PEOPLE HAVE FLATLY REJECTED VIOLENCE AND THE FMLN. I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT THE MEMBERS OF OUR PARTY WILL BE FRIGHTENED INTO ABANDONING THE STRUGGLE FOR THE CONSOLIDATION OF DEMOCRACY, WHICH IS SOMETHING THE PEOPLE WANT.

I BELIEVE THAT THOSE WHO WANT TO MAKE THE FMLN LOOK LIKE MARTYRS AND LIKE PERSONS WHO WORK FOR THE GOOD OF THE PEOPLE, SHOULD KNOW THE TRUTH: THEY ARE NOTHING BUT SAVAGES WHO LACK HUMAN QUALITIES AND WHO ARE INDISCRIMINATELY KILLING AND WOUNDING CIVILIANS WHO HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH THE CONFLICT. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0174 (BELLCORE)

TEGUCIGALPA, 16 APR 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [EXCERPT] ONE MAN WAS KILLED AND ANOTHER SERIOUSLY INJURED THIS EVENING WHEN A POWERFUL EXPLOSIVE THEY WERE ATTEMPTING TO HURL FROM A PASSING MOTORCYCLE AT A U.S. EMBASSY WAREHOUSE IN TEGUCIGALPA EXPLODED BEFORE THEY COULD THROW IT.

THE DEAD MAN HAS BEEN IDENTIFIED AS 39-YEAR-OLD MIGUEL RODOLFO AGUILAR FLORES OF TEGUCIGALPA. HIS BODY WAS BLOWN TO BITS BY THE EXPLOSION.

THE WOUNDED MAN HAS NOT BEEN IDENTIFIED. HE WAS ADMITTED IN A SEMICONSCIOUS STATE TO THE BURNS UNIT OF THE ESCUELA HOSPITAL.

ACCORDING TO POLICE, THE BOMB WAS CHINESE-MADE AND MIGHT HAVE BEEN DETONATED BY HEAT FROM THE MOTORCYCLE OR FROM FRICTION CREATED AS A RESULT OF BEING PLACE BETWEEN THE TWO MEN ON THE MOTORCYCLE.

ANOTHER THEORY IS THAT THE TWO MEN DROPPED THE BOMB WHEN THEY TRIED TO THROW IT AT THE WAREHOUSE, WHICH IS LOCATED 1 KM NORTHWEST OF THE U.S. EMBASSY. POLICE BELIEVE THAT THE BOMB WAS GOING TO BE PLACED IN THE U.S. EMBASSY WAREHOUSE BY MEMBERS OF THE HONDURAN LEFT TO COMMEMMORATE WHAT PEOPLE HERE CALL "BLACK APRIL" FOR THE UNITED STATES.

ON 7 APRIL 1988, A MOB SET FIRE TO THE U.S. CONSULATE IN TEGUCIGALPA AND TO 30 DIPLOMATIC VEHICLES.

DEV-MUC3-0177 (ADS)

BOGOTA, 18 APRIL 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] MULTI-PARTY TALKS ON INCORPORATING COLOMBIA'S M-19 REBEL GROUP INTO CIVILIAN LIFE WOUND UP TUESDAY WITH AGREEMENT THAT THE PROCESS MUST BE COMPLETED BY JUNE 30.

REPRESENTATIVES OF THE GOVERNMENT, POLITICAL PARTIES AND THE M- 19 GROUP, WHICH ACCEPTED A TRUCE LAST MONTH AFTER 16 YEARS OF FIGHTING, REACHED THE ACCORD AT A "WORKING SESSION" AT THE NATIONAL ASSEMBLY.

NO OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE WAS RELEASED, BUT SOURCES CLOSE TO THE TALKS SAID THE PARTIES HAD AGREED TO CONTINUE BI-WEEKLY PARLEYS AND TO CREATE A GENERAL SECRETARIAT COMPRISING REPRESENTATIVES OF EACH OF THE DELEGATIONS.

THE ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH WAS NAMED AS GUARANTOR OF ANY FINAL AGREEMENT.

THE GUERRILLA GROUP SIGNED ITS TRUCE MARCH 18 UNDER A PEACE PLAN ANNOUNCED IN SEPTEMBER BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, WHO HAS SAID REBEL LEADERS WOULD BE PARDONED.

THE TALKS HAVE YET TO BROACH THE THORNY SUBJECT OF THE 2,500- STRONG GROUP'S HANDING OVER ITS ARMS.

THE GUERRILLA GROUP WAS FORMED IN SEPTEMBER 1973 AS A PROTEST AGAINST WHAT IT SAID WAS ELECTORAL FRAUD COMMITTED BY THEN- STRONGMAN GUSTAVO ROJAS PINILLA. ITS ORIGINAL MEMBERS WERE DISSIDENT GUERRILLAS FROM OTHER GROUPS, PROFESSIONALS, WORKERS, STUDENTS AND FORMER SOLDIERS.

IN JANUARY 1974, THE REBEL GROUP MADE HEADLINES BY STEALING A SWORD THAT HAD BELONGED TO SIMON BOLIVAR -- WHO LED THE WARS OF INDEPENDENCE IN MOST OF NORTHERN SOUTH AMERICA -- WHICH THEY PROMISED TO USE TO "REDEEM" THE COUNTRY.

M-19'S MOST SPECTACULAR OPERATION WAS ITS 1985 TAKEOVER OF THE PALACE OF JUSTICE IN BOGOTA. IN THE MILITARY OPERATION TO RETAKE THE BUILDING, MORE THAN 100 PEOPLE DIED, INCLUDING SIX TOP JUDGES AS WELL AS VISITORS, EMPLOYEES AND REBELS.

THE REBELS WERE REPORTEDLY HIRED BY DRUG KINGPINS TO STORM THE BUILDING AND DESTROY DOCUMENTS TO BE USED IN PROCEEDINGS TO EXTRADITE THE DRUG LORDS TO THE UNITED STATES.

DEV-MUC3-0178 (ADS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 19 APR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] HONDURAN GUERRILLAS CLAIMED CREDIT TODAY FOR THE ATTACK ON A U.S. ARMY CONVOY ON 11 APRIL IN NORTHERN HONDURAS IN WHICH ONE PERSON WAS KILLED, THREE OR FOUR PEOPLE WOUNDED, AND ONE VEHICLE DESTROYED.

THE ATTACK ON AN 11-VEHICLE CONVOY CARRYING U.S. AND HONDURAN SOLDIERS TOOK PLACE 17 KM NORTHEAST OF OLANCHITO, IN YORO DEPARTMENT, ON THE NORTHERN COAST OF HONDURAS.

PEOPLE HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT U.S. AND HONDURAN TROOPS ARE BUILDING A HIGHWAY FOR MILITARY EMERGENCIES AND CIVIL DEVELOPMENT IN THIS AREA.

IN A COMMUNIQUE DISTRIBUTED IN OLANCHITO, THE MORAZANIST PATRIOTIC FRONT (FPM) CLAIMED CREDIT FOR THE ATTACK, AND SAID THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT BY THE RAMON AMAYA AMADOR COMMANDO GROUP [COMANDO RAMON AMAYA AMADOR].

THE GUERRILLA COMMUNIQUE STATED "THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT WITH RIFLE FIRE AND HAND GRENADES, WHICH NEUTRALIZED THE REARGUARD OF THE YANKEE CONVOY AND RESULTED IN ONE DEAD, THREE OR FOUR WOUNDED, AND ONE DESTROYED VEHICLE."

THE COMMUNIQUE ADDED THAT "THE YANKEES REFUSE TO REPORT THEIR CASUALTIES SO AS NOT TO DEMORALIZE THEIR TROOPS. OUR RIFLES WILL BE AIMED AT THE BLONDS FROM THE NORTH WHO ARE TODAY TRAMPLING ON OUR SACRED FATHERLAND."

THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES AND THE U.S. EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA HAVE CONFIRMED THE ATTACK, BUT THEY DID NOT MENTION ANY CASUALTIES, ALTHOUGH THEY ADMIT THAT THE LAST VEHICLE IN THE CONVOY WAS "DAMAGED" BY AN EXPLOSIVE DEVICE THAT WAS HURLED AT IT.

ON 1 FEBRUARY, ANOTHER U.S. MILITARY CONVOY WAS ATTACKED IN THE SAME AREA BY UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS, WITHOUT CAUSING ANY CASUALTIES BUT DAMAGING ONE TRUCK.

THAT ATTACK WAS ALSO CLAIMED BY THE FPM, WHICH SAID IT HAD WOUNDED SOME AMERICANS.

THE FPM FIRST APPEARED IN SAN PEDRO SULA IN 1979 AND HAS TAKEN CREDIT FOR SEVERAL DYNAMITE ATTACKS AND RURAL GUERRILLA ACTIONS.

RAMON AMAYA AMADOR, THE NAME USED BY THE HONDURAN GUERRILLA GROUP, WAS A LEFTIST NOVELIST WHO WROTE ABOUT THE SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC INEQUALITIES AMONG HONDURANS. HE ALSO CONDEMNED FOREIGN INTERVENTION, PARTICULARLY U.S. INTERVENTION, IN HONDURAN ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL AFFAIRS.

DEV-MUC3-0182 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 APR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [REPORT] [CARLOS MARIO MARQUEZ] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [MARQUEZ] REGARDING THIS MORNING'S ATTACK AGAINST SALVADORAN ATTORNEY GENERAL DR ROBERTO GARCIA ALVARADO, A GROUP CALLING ITSELF THE GERARDO BARRIOS COMMANDO UNIT TONIGHT CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK. WE WILL NOW BROADCAST A TELEPHONE CALL THAT ONE OF OUR COLLEAGUES IN THE PRESS DEPARTMENT RECEIVED FROM A PERSON WHO IDENTIFIED HIMSELF ONLY AS A MEMBER OF THIS NEW GUERRILLA COMMANDO UNIT OR DEATH SQUAD.

[COMMANDO] OUR FORCE IS CALLED THE GERARDO BARRIOS CIVIC FORCE. WE WERE BORN MAINLY THROUGH ANTISUBVERSIVE COMBAT; HOWEVER, WE ARE AN ESSENTIALLY DEMOCRATIC FORCE, BECAUSE WE ARE OPPOSED TO... [CORRECTS HIMSELF] WE HAVE CONFRONTED THE MONOPOLIZING AND TOTALITARIAN EFFORTS OF ARENA [NATIONALILST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE]. CAN YOU HEAR ME?

[REPORTER] YES, QUITE CLEARLY.

[COMMANDO] HELLO?

[REPORTER] I CAN HEAR YOU. PLEASE CONTINUE.

[COMMANDO] WE ARE STRATEGICALLY CONFRONTING THE MANIPULATIONS OF THE WORTHLESS [VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT] MERINO AND [ARENA LEADER] D'AUBUISSON. WE GAVE THEM OUR SECOND DISSUASSIVE SIGNAL TODAY. WE HOPE THEY WILL STOP MANAGING GOVERNMENT AFFAIRS BY RAIDING, REMOVING, APPOINTING, AND BEHEADING [DEGOLLAR] PUBLIC OFFICIALS. THIS MUST BE DEALT WITH IN A DIFFERENT FASHION.

WE ALSO WANT THEM TO STOP THEIR INTRIGUES AND CONSPIRACIES WITHIN THE ARMED FORCES AND THEIR PRESSURE ON THE STATE SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS, AS WELL AS ALL GRIEVOUS ACTIONS AIMED AT DISCREDITING DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS SUCH AS THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRACY. WE ALSO WANT FRANCISCO GUERRERO TO STOP HIS FIFTH-COLUMN ACTION IN THE PCN [NATIONAL CONCILIATION PARTY] TO DIVIDE THE PARTY. YOU CANNOT TAKE SUCH ACTIONS AGAINST DEMOCRATIC FORCES. THIS IS A SECOND DISSUASSIVE SIGNAL. CAN YOU HEAR ME?

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE SECOND SIGNAL?

[COMMANDO] WELL, ONLY...

[MARQUEZ] THIS WAS THE TELEPHONE CALL RECEIVED AT RADIO CADENA YSU'S PRESS DEPARTMENT FROM THIS NEW GROUP THAT CALLS ITSELF THE GERARDO BARRIOS CIVIC FORCE, WHICH HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK ON SALVADORAN ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIA ALVARADO. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0184 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 22 APR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE NOW UNFOLDED OUR MILITARY MAP, ON WHICH WE HAVE PLACED A SMALL BLACK CIRCLE AT EACH COMBAT SITE, A RED CIRCLE AT THE SITE OF EACH ACT OF SABOTAGE, AND A GREEN CIRCLE FOR EACH AMBUSH OF MILITARY VEHICLES. OVER THE PAST 24 HOURS, THE BLACK CIRCLES ON OUR MAP HAVE BEEN CONCENTRATED IN SAN SALVADOR AND THE EASTERN REGION. UNDOUBTEDLY, THE MOST PROMINENT ACTION HAS BEEN THE ATTACK ON THE NAVY HEADQUARTERS IN SAN SALVADOR'S DENSELY POPULATED SANTA ANITA NEIGHBORHOOD. WE ARE WAITING FOR AN OFFICIAL WAR BULLETIN ON THAT ACTION.

ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT CHARACTERISTICS OF THAT ATTACK IS THAT IT WAS STAGED DESPITE THE ARMY'S PRESENCE IN THE HEART OF THE CAPITAL, AND IT OCCURRED IN FULL DAYLIGHT. AT NOON ON FRIDAY, A CONTINGENT OF URBAN GUERRILLAS GOT WITHIN 50 METERS OF THE NAVY HEADQUARTERS AND LAUNCHED AN ATTACK WITH RIFLES AND ROCKET LAUNCHERS. EVERY SHOT HIT ITS TARGET. ARMED FORCES PATROLS TRIED TO CUT OFF OUR FIGHTERS' RETREAT THROUGH THE STREETS OF THE CAPITAL, BUT THE SOLDIERS WERE UNSUCCESSFUL BECAUSE IN SAN SALVADOR, THE PEOPLE THEMSELVES FORM A MOUNTAIN THAT PROVIDES COVER FOR OUR URBAN GUERRILLAS.

EARLY ON SATURDAY MORNING, WE AMBUSHED AN ARMY CONVOY ON THE PAN AMERICAN HIGHWAY AT EL PUNTILLAL, YAPATZTEPEQUE, USING EIGHT EXPLOSIVE CHARGES. THE AMBUSHED TROOPS WERE REINFORCED BY OTHER UNITS, WITH WHOM WE FOUGHT FOR AN HOUR. THIS AMBUSH WAS CARRIED OUT AGAINST ENEMY ARMORED UNITS. THE RESULT OF THIS ACTION WAS AN ESTIMATED 35 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING AN OFFICER OF THE TECHUACAN BATTALION'S RECONDO UNIT AND A CAVALRY OFFICER. FOR OUR PART, WE REPORT THE HEROIC LOSS IN BATTLE OF OUR COMRADE JACKSON.

OUR REVOLUTIONARY SALUTE TO THE BRAVE FIGHTERS OF EL PUNTILLAL, WHO INFLICTED THIS LARGE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES ON 5TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS ON THE PAN AMERICAN HIGHWAY.

DEV-MUC3-0185 (ADS)

PRAGUE (CZECHOSLOVAKIA), 21 APR 89 (RUDE PRAVO) -- [INTERVIEW WITH MANUEL CEPEDA, MEMBER OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY CENTRAL COMMITTEE POLITBURO, BY VERA POSLEDNI] [TEXT] RECENTLY COMRADE MANUEL CEPEDA, MEMBER OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY CENTRAL COMMITTEE POLITBURO, VISITED CZECHOSLOVAKIA; WE ASKED HIM FOR AN INTERVIEW.

[POSLEDNI] IN THE COURSE OF A FEW DAYS AT THE BEGINNING OF MARCH, THREE LEADING OFFICIALS OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY AND THE LEFTIST COALITION, THE PATRIOTIC UNION (UP), COMRADES FORERO, SOTELO, AND ANTEQUERA, WERE MURDERED IN COLOMBIA. WHY?

[CEPEDA] IN COLOMBIA THE DIRTY WAR STEMMING FROM THE AMERICAN TACTICS OF SO-CALLED LOW-INTENSITY CONFLICT IS INTENSIFYING. THE INTERNAL POLITICAL CRISIS IS DEEPENED BY AN ALLIANCE BETWEEN THE POWERFUL DRUG SMUGGLING CLANS AND THE MILITARY LEADERSHIP WHICH IS CONDUCTING THE DIRTY WAR. IN THE SANTA FE II DOCUMENT, FORMULATING FUTURE UNITED STATES POLICY IN LATIN AMERICA, IT IS EVEN SAID THAT UNLESS THE UNITED STATES INTERVENES IN THE 1990'S COLOMBIA WILL BECOME ANOTHER EL SALVADOR AND ON A MUCH LARGER SCALE. THE SO-CALLED EXTERMINATION OPERATION, ALSO KNOWN AS THE CONDOR PLAN, IS DIRECTED AGAINST THE COMMUNIST PARTY AND UP, AGAINST THE UNIONS, BUT ALSO AGAINST PRIESTS WHO PREACH LIBERATION THEOLOGY, AND RECENTLY THIS HAS INTENSIFIED. IN COLOMBIA SOME ELEMENTS OF FASCISM OPENLY MANIFEST THEMSELVES. THIS IS MANIFESTED IN HUGE AND UNPUNISHED MASSACRES AND IN THE POWERLESSNESS OF PRESIDENT BARCO AND HIS CIVILIAN MINISTERS WHO ARE NOT MANAGING TO KEEP THE MILITARY LEADERSHIP IN CHECK, ALTHOUGH THE PRESIDENT IS THE SUPREME COMMANDER OF THE ARMED FORCES.

[POSLEDNI] SOMETIMES PARTISANS ARE ALSO ACCUSED OF TERROR.

[CEPEDA] THAT IS ONE OF THE TRAITS OF AMERICAN POLICY -- TO TERM ANY KIND OF REVOLUTIONARY STRUGGLE, OF STRUGGLE FOR DEMOCRACY, AND THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT AS TERRORISM. THEREFORE, IT ALSO LABELS THE SANDINISTAS IN NICARAGUA AS TERRORISTS AND THE CONTRA REBELS AS FREEDOM FIGHTERS. BY THIS I DO NOT WANT TO SAY THAT THE PARTISANS DO NOT MAKE MISTAKES, WE ALSO CRITICIZE THEM. FOR EXAMPLE, WE CONDEMNED THE DESTRUCTION OF OIL PIPLINES BY THE COLOMBIAN PARTISAN ORGANIZATION THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY (ELN). WE DO NOT AGREE WITH KIDNAPPING CIVILIANS IN EXCHANGE FOR RANSOM. WE ANNOUNCED THAT, AS LONG AS IT IS IMPOSSIBLE TO END THE CONFLICT, IT IS NECESSARY TO HUMANIZE IT AND TO RESPECT HUMAN LIVES. THESE ARE THE TACTICS OF SOLDIERS -- TO LABEL THE PARTISANS AS TERRORISTS AND THEN MASSACRE THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AS SUSPECTS WHO ARE COLLABORATING WITH TERRORISM.

[POSLEDNI] PARTISANS FROM THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC) OFFERED THE GOVERNMENT A DIALOGUE ABOUT A TRUCE. HOW DO THEY WANT TO CONDUCT THIS?

[CEPEDA] THE FARC, WHICH IS THE STRONGEST ELEMENT OF THE COLOMBIAN PARTISAN MOVEMENT AND A MEMBER OF ITS COORDINATING COMMITTEE, UNILATERALLY ADOPTED A CEASE-FIRE AND PROPOSED THE CREATION OF A COMMISSION FOR THIS DIALOGUE. IN IT ARE TWO FORMER PRESIDENTS, THE LIBERAL LOPEZ MICHELSEN AND THE CONSERVATIVE PASTRANA, THE CHAIRMAN OF THE ASSOCIATION OF INDUSTRIALISTS ECHEVERRI CORREA, AND BOGOTA'S CARDINAL REBOLLO. THE FARC WANTS THE GOVERNMENT TO DISBAND THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS. THE FORMER INTERIOR MINISTER, GAVIRIA, SAID THAT THERE ARE 140 OF THEM. THIS MEANS THAT THE GOVERNMENT KNOWS THEM. THE FARC IS DEMANDING THE PURGE OF PEOPLE FROM THE ARMY COMMAND INVOLVED IN THE DIRTY WAR, THAT THE DEFENSE MINISTER BE A CIVILIAN, THAT THE STATE OF EMERGENCY BE REVOKED, AND THAT THE ROAD TO REAL DEMOCRACY BE OPENED.

[POSLEDNI] BUT THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEGUN NEGOTIATING WITH PARTISANS FROM M-19.

[CEPEDA] THE EL TIEMPO NEWSPAPER REPORTED THAT THE GOVERNMENT PROMISED THEM REPRESENTATION IN PARLIAMENT BY THEIR INCLUSION AS CANDIDATES OF THE LIBERAL PARTY. THIS IS TO INVOLVE FOUR SEATS AS LONG AS M-19 LAYS DOWN ITS ARMS AND DISBANDS. THE OTHER PARTISANS BITTERLY CRITICIZED THIS AS A BLOW AGAINST THE UNITY OF THE MOVEMENT WHICH WILL BE ABUSED FOR PROPAGANDA PURPOSES. AT THE SAME TIME, M-19 REPRESENTS ONLY 5 PERCENT OF THE MOVEMENT. IT IS THE INTENTION OF THE GOVERNMENT TO DIVIDE THE PARTISANS.

[POSLEDNI] THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY CONGRESS TOOK PLACE IN DECEMBER. HOW DID IT REACT TO THE SITUATION?

[CEPEDA] THE PARTY CALLED FOR PEACE AND OUTLINED THE STRUGGLE FOR A PLURALIST GOVERNMENT OF TRANSITION TOWARDS PEACE AND DEMOCRACY. AT THE END OF FEBRUARY THERE WAS A CENTRAL COMMITTEE SESSION WHICH DISCUSSED THE DIRTY WAR. IT STATED THAT, IN SPITE OF THE TERROR, THERE HAD NOT BEEN WHAT HAD HAPPENED IN SIMILAR SITUATIONS IN OTHER LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES, NAMELY, MASS EMIGRATION. TO ENSURE THAT THIS DOES NOT HAPPEN IN THE FUTURE, THE CENTRAL COMMITTEE DISCUSSED NEW MEASURES, INCLUDING THE TRANSITION OF PART OF THE PARTY TO THE UNDERGROUND. WE WILL NOT ALL TRANSFER, BECAUSE NOW WE MUST STRUGGLE FOR OPEN CONTACT WITH THE MASSES, REGARDLESS OF THE HUGE RISK WHICH IS LINKED TO THIS.

[POSLEDNI] WHERE IS THE PARTY SEEKING ALLIES?

[CEPEDA] COMRADE ANTEQUERA, AS DEPUTY CHAIRMAN OF THE UP, HAD ESTABLISHED A NUMBER OF CONTACTS. HOWEVER, HE WAS MURDERED, AND SENATOR SAMPER PISANO, A POLITICIAN FROM THE RULING LIBERAL PARTY, WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED DURING THE ASSASSINATION AT BOGOTA AIRPORT ON 3 MARCH. THE ASSASSINATION ATTEMPT AGAINST THE 32-YEAR-OLD PROSPECTIVE POLITICIAN OCCURRED THE DAY AFTER HE ANNOUNCED HIS CANDIDACY FOR THE PRESIDENCY. HE ANNOUNCED HIS SUPPORT FOR DEMOCRATIC COEXISTENCE, FOR AN END TO THE DIRTY WAR WHICH, AS HE SAID, IS NOT IN THE INTEREST OF THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE. THEREFORE, HE WAS NOT A CHANCE VICTIM. IT IS ALSO SIGNIFICANT THAT THE CLOSED CIRCUIT TELEVISION COVERING THE AIRPORT, WHICH IS IN THE HANDS OF THE ARMY, WAS SWITCHED OFF. THUS, THEY WANTED TO PREVENT THE MURDERERS BEING FILMED. ONE OF THEM DIED, THEY LET THE OTHER THREE ESCAPE. AT THE SAME TIME, BOGOTA'S CHIEF OF POLICE WAS AT THE AIRPORT ALONG WITH ANOTHER 10 COLONELS AND A NUMBER OF POLICEMEN AND PERSONAL BODYGUARDS.

[POSLEDNI] HOW DID THE OTHER PARTIES REACT TO THE ASSASSINATION?

[CEPEDA] A JOINT DOCUMENT WAS SIGNED BY THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY, THE UP, AND THE LIBERAL PARTY, ON WHOSE BEHALF THE FORMER PRESIDENT TURBAY AYALA SIGNED. IT DEMANDS THAT THE GOVERNMENT DISBAND THE PARAMILITARY SQUADS. IT SHOWS THAT OPINIONS ARE BEGINNING TO DIFFER, EVEN IN THE RULING LIBERAL PARTY. THE CONSERVATIVES ARE ALSO EMPHATICALLY CRITICIZING THE BLOODBATH AND THE PASSIVITY OF THE GOVERNMENT, POINTING OUT THAT THEIR LAST PRESIDENT, BETANCUR, CONDUCTED A DIALOGUE WITH THE PARTISANS. THIS IS ALL HAPPENING BEFORE THE ELECTIONS WHICH WILL TAKE PLACE NEXT YEAR.

[POSLEDNI] THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY LEADERSHIP MET WITH THE PRESIDENT AFTER THE MURDER OF COMRADE FORERO. WHAT WAS THAT ABOUT?

[CEPEDA] IN THE CONVERSATION, WE POINTED TO THE FACT THAT THE DEFENSE MINISTER, GENERAL GUERRERO PAZ, TRAVELS AROUND COLOMBIA ACCOMPANIED BY THE LEADER OF THE ULTRA-RIGHT WING, RETIRED GENERAL LANDAZABAL REYES, WHO IS LEADER OF THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS. WE ASKED WHY THESE TWO ARE TOGETHER. THE PRESIDENT DID NOT ANSWER US. AT THE MEETING WE ALSO SAID THAT, UNLESS THE DIRTY WAR STOPS, THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY FOR THE FIRST TIME IN HISTORY WILL NOT TAKE PART IN THE ELECTIONS. WE WILL NOT BE ABLE TO PARTICIPATE, BECAUSE WE ARE ALL BEING MURDERED. UNLESS THE GOVERNMENT GIVES US A GUARANTEE OF SECURITY, WE WILL NOT SACRIFICE MORE LIVES.

[POSLEDNI] THANK YOU FOR THE INTERVIEW.

DEV-MUC3-0187 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 25 APR 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATEMENT] [COMMANDER ROBERTO ROCA, MEMBER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [EXCERPT] THE AMNESTY MENTIONED BY D'AUBUISSON [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE LEADER] IS NOTHING MORE THAN THE REVIVAL OF SOMETHING THAT HAS ALREADY BEEN SOUNDLY DEFEATED. THIS PROPOSAL IS COMPLETELY OUT OF TOUCH WITH THE CURRENT BALANCE OF FORCES AND, AS WE MAY GATHER FROM HIS STATEMENTS, ESSENTIALLY REFLECTS THE PLANS OF THE NEW ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] GOVERNMENT, WHICH WILL BE IMPOSED ON 1 JUNE, TO INTENSIFY THE WAR.

THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE READY TO FACE THE WARMONGERING MANEUVERS OF THE TRUE REPRESENTATIVE OF ARENA DEATHS SQUADS WHO IS NOW TRYING TO CREATE A TERRORIST STATE THROUGH NEW REPRESSIVE ACTIONS. HOWEVER, SINCE ARENA WON THE MARCH ELECTION FARCE, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE BECOMING INCREASINGLY AWARE OF THE NEED TO CONFRONT SUCH REPRESSIVE ACTIONS.

ARENA HAS NOTHING NEW TO OFFER; IT IS OFFERING OLD AND FAILED TACTICS IN THE FACE OF A NEW SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY; THAT IS, A SIGNFICANT CHANGE IN THE BALANCE OF FORCES IN FAVOR OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AND THE GREAT MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE. THIS WILL UNDOUBTEDLY ENCOURAGE A STRUGGLE AS SOON AS THE NEW ARENA GOVERNMENT IS INSTALLED.

D'AUBUISSON AND ARENA WILL SCARE NOBODY WITH PLANS THAT ARE COMPLETELY DETACHED FROM A GENUINE WILLINGNESS TO ACHIEVE PEACE. THE FMLN HAS PRESENTED A PRUDENT PEACE PROPOSAL BASED ON AN OBJECTIVE ANALYSIS OF THE CURRENT BALANCE OF FORCES.

IT IS IMPORTANT FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO REALIZE THAT THE DEGREE OF UNITY REACHED TO FACE ARENA'S PLANS WILL BE THE KEY TO COUNTER THE REPRESSION THAT THE ARMED FORCES AND ARENA ARE ALREADY PROMOTING.

DEV-MUC3-0189 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 APR 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT DUARTE SAID THIS AFTERNOON THAT PRESIDENT- ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S PEACE PROPOSAL DESERVES RESPECT AND THAT ONE MUST HOPE THAT IT WILL PRODUCE RESULTS THAT WILL BENEFIT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE PRESIDENT MADE THIS STATEMENT AT COMALPA AIRPORT UPON HIS RETURN FROM THE UNITED STATES. HE ADDED THAT HE WILL RESUME HIS DUTIES TOMORROW, EVEN THOUGH HIS CANCER HAS GROWN. THERE HAS BEEN VERY NEGATIVE SPECULATION ABOUT THE PRESIDENT'S HEALTH, BUT HE STATED THAT HE WILL RESUME HIS DUTIES IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUARTE] THE TESTS I UNDERWENT INDICATE THAT THE LIVER CANCER HAS GROWN. IT HAS NOT SPREAD BUT IT HAS GROWN, WHICH ADDS TO THE RISK. I UNDERWENT A 5-DAY TREATMENT, AND I WILL HAVE TO RETURN AS SOON AS I PASS THE PRESIDENCY ON TO MY SUCCESSOR. I WILL RETURN TO THE HOSPITAL ON 2 JUNE FOR ANOTHER CHECKUP AND TREATMENT.

[REPORTER] WHEN WILL YOU RESUME YOUR DUTIES?

[DUARTE] IMMEDIATELY. I AM THE PRESIDENT AND AS SOON AS I SET FOOT ON SALVADORAN SOIL, I RESUME MY DUTIES. [END RECORDING]

IN REGARD TO THE SEARCHES THAT HAVE BEEN CONDUCTED AT VARIOUS UNION HEADQUARTERS, DUARTE SAID HE WAS NOT FULLY AWARE OF THE CIRCUMSTANCES IN WHICH THESE WERE CARRIED OUT. HOWEVER, HE SAID THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS MUST BE DEFENDED WHEN DEMOCRATIC FREEDOMS TURN INTO LIBERTINISM.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUARTE] ONE MUST NOT CONFUSE THE FREEDOM OF ALL SALVADORANS TO EXPRESS THEMSELVES, HOLD DEMONSTRATIONS, JOIN UNIONS, AND WORK FOR THEIR ASPIRATIONS WITH TERRORIST AND SUBVERSIVE ACTIONS THAT ATTACK DEMOCRACY. ONE MUST NOT CONFUSE THESE THINGS. THIS IS ONE OF THE BASIC POINTS I HAVE TRIED TO MAKE ALL SECTORS UNDERSTAND. I HAVE BEEN CREATING POLITICAL OPPORTUNITIES IN THE COUNTRY SO THAT GRADUALLY WE WILL LEARN TO LIVE FREELY IN A DEMOCRACY WHILE RESPECTING ONE ANOTHER. [END RECORDING]

ASKED ABOUT THE UNITED FRONT THAT ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] IS PROMOTING IN THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY, THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT IF THIS BENEFITS THE COUNTRY, IT DESERVES SUPPORT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUARTE] THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A POLICY FOR PEACE HAS ALWAYS BEEN SUPPORTED BY THE OUTGOING PRESIDENT -- IN OTHER WORDS, BY ME. I HAVE PUBLICLY STATED THIS, AND I HAVE TRIED TO ACHIEVE PEACE THROUGH [WORDS INDISTINCT]. IT WILL NOW BE UP TO ANOTHER PRESIDENT. I HAVE TO SHOW RESPECT FOR PRESIDENT-ELECT CRISTIANI, WHO MUST BE GIVEN THE OPPORTUNITY TO BEGIN HIS TERM IN AN ATMOSPHERE IN WHICH HE CAN PRESENT HIS IDEAS, PROPOSALS, AND SOLUTIONS [WORDS INDISTINCT] TO FIND THE PATH TO PEACE. [END RECORDING]

PRESIDENT DUARTE DID NOT COMMENT ON THE PEACE PROPOSAL THAT WAS RECENTLY ANNOUNCED BY ARENA BECAUSE, HE SAID, HE WAS NOT FAMILIAR WITH IT, ADDING THAT IT WOULD BE UNETHICAL TO QUESTION THE PROPOSALS AND EFFORTS OF THE NEXT PRESIDENT. HOWEVER, HE SAID THAT ANY EFFORTS FOR PEACE MUST BE SUPPORTED.

DEV-MUC3-0190 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 APR 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT-ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI YESTERDAY ANNOUNCED CHANGES IN THE ARMY'S STRATEGY TOWARD URBAN TERRORISM AND THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S [FMLN] DIPLOMATIC OFFENSIVE TO ISOLATE THE NEW GOVERNMENT ABROAD.

CRISTIANI SAID: "WE MUST ADJUST OUR POLITICAL-MILITARY STRATEGY AND MODIFY LAWS TO ALLOW US TO PROFESSIONALLY COUNTER THE FMLN'S STRATEGY."

DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE YESTERDAY MORNING, THE PRESIDENT-ELECT AND MEMBER OF THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) PRESENTED THE BASIC VIEWPOINTS OF HIS ADMINISTRATION, WHICH WILL REPLACE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRAT NAPOLEON DUARTE'S ADMINISTRATION ON 1 JUNE.

AS THE PRESIDENT-ELECT WAS MAKING THIS STATEMENT, HE LEARNED ABOUT THE ASSASINATION OF ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIA ALVARADO. [SENTENCE AS PUBLISHED] ALVARADO WAS KILLED BY A BOMB PRESUMABLY PLACED BY AN URBAN GUERRILLA GROUP ON TOP OF HIS ARMORED VEHICLE AS IT STOPPED AT AN INTERSECTION IN SAN MIGUELITO NEIGHBORHOOD, NORTH OF THE CAPITAL.

THE FMLN IS ABANDONING "GUERRILLA WARFARE TACTICS IN RURAL AREAS AND INCREASINGLY RESORTING TO THE ESTABLISHMENT OF CIVILIAN FRONTS IN THE MAIN CITIES AND TO URBAN TERRORISM IN AN ATTEMPT TO DESTABILIZE (THE GOVERNMENT). AT THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL, THE GUERRILLAS ARE TRYING TO ELICIT NEGATIVE REACTION TOWARD THE NEW GOVERNMENT TO ISOLATE US POLITICALLY FROM THE WORLD," CRISTIANI SAID. VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT FRANCISCO MERINO ACCOMPANIED HIM.

HE ADDED: "OBVIOUSLY, IF WARRANTED BY THE SITUATION, WE MUST RESORT TO LEGAL MECHANISMS. SHOULD THE SITUATION BECOME DIFFICULT OR IMPOSSIBLE TO CONTROL, OUR HARSHER MEASURE WOULD BE TO DECLARE A STATE OF SIEGE."

SINCE EARLY APRIL, THE FMLN HAS BEEN CARRYING OUT A STRONG OFFENSIVE AGAINST PRIVATE COMPANIES AND THE BANKING SYSTEM AND HAS STEPPED UP SABOTAGE ACTIONS AGAINST TELEPHONE AND ELECTRICITY NETWORKS.

IN ADDITION TO THE ATTACK ON THE ATTORNEY GENERAL, THERE WERE OTHER ATTACKS, IN WHICH GUERRILLA DESERTER MIGUEL CASTELLANOS AND FRANCISCO PECORRINI, BOTH OF WHOM WERE RIGHT-WING IDEOLOGUES, WERE KILLED AND CARLOS MENDOZA, CHIEF EDITOR OF ANALISIS MAGAZINE, WAS WOUNDED. CASTELLANOS AND PECORRINI WERE CONNECTED WITH THAT MAGAZINE.

DEV-MUC3-0191 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 28 APR 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [EXCERPT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, HAS DISCLOSED A REBEL PLAN TO DESTABILIZE THE COUNTRY THROUGH STREET VIOLENCE. COL PONCE SAID MILITARY INTELLIGENCE UNCOVERED THE PLAN, WHICH INVOLVES SEVERAL UNIONS AND MASS ORGANIZATIONS. ACCORDING TO COL PONCE, THERE WILL BE VIOLENT ACTIONS IN THREE DEPARTMENTS: SAN SALVADOR, SANTA ANA, AND SAN MIGUEL. THE UNTS [NATIONAL UNITY OF SALVADORAN UNIONS], THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR, THE MPTL [BREAD, LAND, WORK, AND LIBERTY MOVEMENT], AND A [WORD INDISTINCT] SHOCK GROUP, WILL LEAD THE ACTIONS.

PONCE SAID HE IS REVEALING THIS TO KEEP THESE ACTIONS FROM TAKING PLACE. HOWEVER, HE SAID, IF THEY ARE CARRIED OUT, THE APPROPRIATE MEASURES HAVE BEEN TAKEN. HE ADDED THE REBELS PLAN TO BURN VEHICLES, DESTROY STORES, BOMB TELEPHONE LINES, AND STEP UP SABOTAGE OF ELECTRICITY LINES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] TO ACCOMPANY THESE VIOLENT MASS ACTIVITIES, THEY PLAN TO ATTACK THE MARIONA JAIL. WE KNOW THE UNTS WILL PAY 7 COLONS TO EVERY PARTICIPANT IN A DEMONSTRATION. THEY ARE ALSO SPONSORING A DEMONSTRATION AT A CAMP FOR DISPLACED PERSONS. HONEST PEOPLE CAN REST AT EASE; THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES WILL TAKE THE APPROPRIATE LEGAL MEASURES TO ENSURE THE RIGHTS OF ALL CITIZENS. WE HAVE ALREADY BEGUN TAKING SOME ACTIONS TO COUNTER ANY VIOLENT ACTIONS THEY MAY CARRY OUT ON 1 MAY. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0192 (ADS)

LIMA, 28 APR 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, CAN YOU GIVE US ACCURATE INFORMATION ON THIS CLASH?

[GARCIA] I CAME HERE [REGION OF LOS MOLINOS, 8 KM NORTHEAST OF THE CITY OF JAUJA, JUNIN DEPARTMENT] WITH THE DEFENSE MINISTER AND WITH THE PRESIDENT OF THE JOINT COMMAND TO OBSERVE THE SITE OF A CLASH THAT OCCURRED THIS MORNING, WHEN AN ARMY PATROL COMING FROM JAUJA AND HEADING FOR JULCAN INTERCEPTED TWO VEHICLES CARRYING A LARGE NUMBER OF HEAVILY ARMED SUBVERSIVES.

ACCORDING TO THE FIRST REPORTS, BASED ON THE DOCUMENTS SEIZED FROM THE SUBVERSIVES, THEY WERE HEADING FOR CONCEPCION, WHICH THEY WERE PLANNING TO ATTACK. FORTUNATELY, THEY WERE INTERCEPTED BY THE ARMY AT THIS PLACE.

WE HAD 6 DEATHS, AMONG THEM A LIEUTENANT, WHILE MORE THAN 60 SUBVERSIVES DIED. A TOTAL OF 47 FAL RIFLES AND SUBMACHINE GUNS WERE RECOVERED. THEY WERE HEAVILY ARMED AND THEY CARRIED KNAPSACKS WITH BOMBS. THEY HAD VEHICLES AN COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT.

WE CAME HERE TO SUPPORT THE ACTION BY THE ARMY, BECAUSE THE ARMY NEEDS OUR SUPPORT, AND TO LET THE ENTIRE COUNTRY BECOME AWARE OF THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE SITUATION AND OF THE MAGNITUDE AND INTENSITY OF THE STRUGGLE THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE NOW WAGING IN DEFENSE OF DEMOCRACY AND OF THE NATION.

I BELIEVE THAT THIS DRAMATIC EVENT AND THE LOSS OF OUR SOLDIERS AND OFFICERS SHOULD MAKE THE ENTIRE COUNTRY AWARE OF THE ENORMOUS RESPONSIBILITY THAT EACH AND EVERY ONE OF US SHARE IN THE ANTISUBVERSIVE STRUGGLE.

ALL THE FORCES OF THE STATE AND ALL THE ARMS OF THE NATION HAVE BEEN PLACED UNDER THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE RESPECTIVE ORGANIZATIONS, OF THE JOINT ARMED FORCES COMMAND, TO FIGHT AND TO ERADICATE THIS TERRIBLE THREAT OF SUBVERSION. SUBVERSIVE VIOLENCE HAS CAUSED DEATH, MATERIAL LOSSES, UNCERTAINTY, FEAR, AND INSECURITY, AND A THREAT TO OUR DEMOCRACY.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, IS THERE INFORMATION ON THE GROUP TO WHICH THE SUBVERSIVES BELONG?

[GARCIA] ACCORDING TO THE FIRST REPORTS, THEY BELONG TO THE SELF- STYLED TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT [MRTA].

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, YOU HAVE TWO PASSPORTS IN YOUR HANDS. WHAT DO THEY SAY? WHERE WERE THEY ISSUED AND TO WHOM DID THEY BELONG?

[GARCIA] IDENTIFICATION PAPERS WERE FOUND ON ALMOST ALL SUBVERSIVES, ALTHOUGH MOST OF THEM ARE FORGED. THESE TWO BOLIVIAN [AS HEARD] PASSPORTS, HOWEVER, ARE AMONG THE PAPERS THAT SEEM TO BE LEGITIMATE. THESE PASSPORTS MARK THE ARRIVALS AN DEPARTURES OF PERSONS WHO, AS WE CAN SEE, HAVE MISUSED THE RIGHT TO ENTER PERU. IT SEEMS THAT THERE ARE OTHER FOREIGNERS AMONG THE DEAD SUBVERSIVES. ACCORDING TO AN INITIAL EVALUATION, MANY OF THOSE WHO ATTACKED THE TOWN OF JUANJUI 1 1/2 YEARS AGO MIGHT BE AMONG THE DEAD.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, WERE THE OWNERS OF THOSE PASSPORTS THE LEADERS OF THE SUBVERSIVE GROUP?

[GARCIA] NO, WE CANNOT CONFIRM THAT THEY WERE THE LEADERS, BUT THEY WERE THE PERSONS TO WHOM THE PASSPORTS WERE ISSUED.

[REPORTER] ARE THERE CHIEFS AMONG THE DEAD SUBVERSIVES?

[GARCIA] ACCORDING TO THE INFORMATION GATHERED BY THE OFFICERS, THERE MIGHT BE CHIEFS AMONG THE DEAD.

[REPORTER] HOW MANY, MR PRESIDENT?

[GARCIA] JUST A FEW, PERHAPS TWO OR THREE, BECAUSE OF THE ARM BANDS THEY WERE WEARING.

[REPORTER] THE GENERAL TOLD US THAT THIS IS ONE OF THE HARSHEST BLOWS THAT THE ARMY HAS DEALT TO SUBVERSIVES.

[GARCIA] IS ONE OF THE STRONGEST BLOWS, AND IT WILL CERTAINLY NOT BE THE LAST ONE. WE HAVE TOTAL CONFIDENCE IN THE ARMED FORCES JOINT COMMAND AND WE FULLY SUPPORT ITS ACTION.

IT IS VERY DEPLORABLE, DRAMATIC, AND TRAGIC THAT THIS DRAMATIC EVENT SHOULD CONVEY THE IMAGE OF PERU TO OUR OWN FELLOW COUNTRYMEN AND POSSIBLY TO FOREIGN COUNTRIES. DEMOCRACY, HOWEVER, SHOULD DEFEND ITSELF. IT IS BOTH NECESSARY AND IMPERATIVE THAT WE END THIS TERRIBLE THREAT THROUGH THE MILITARY POWER OF THE NATION AND THROUGH THE ACTION OF THE GOVERNMENT, WHICH WAS ELECTED BY THE PEOPLE.

THIS HAS BEEN A HARD BLOW, BUT IT SHOULD BE JUST ONE OF THE HARD BLOWS THAT THE POLICE AND THE ARMED FORCES DEAL UNTIL THIS THREAT IS TOTALLY ELIMINATED.

[REPORTER] THANK YOU, VERY MUCH. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0193 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 APR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMY TODAY LAUNCHED A MILITARY OPERATION IN SAN SALVADOR, WHICH INCLUDED VEHICLE SEARCHES, TO PREVENT A "TERRORIST" PLAN THAT TRADE UNIONS WILL SUPPOSEDLY CARRY OUT TOMORROW FOLLOWING GUERRILLA ORDERS.

THOUSANDS OF SOLDIERS AND MILITARY POLICE ARE PATROLLING THE CAPITAL BY LAND AND AIR, CONTROLLING THE ENTRANCES TO SAN SALVADOR, AND HAVE INCREASED SEARCHES OF VEHICLES AND BUSES FOR WEAPONS.

THIS OPERATION TAKES PLACE ON THE EVE OF A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) OFFENSIVE SCHEDULED FOR TOMORROW, WHEN LABOR UNIONS HAVE ANNOUNCED THEY WILL HOLD DEMONSTRATIONS IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER CITIES COMMEMORATING INTERNATIONAL LABOR DAY.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) HAS TELEVISED WARNINGS ACCOMPANIED BY VIDEO CLIPS SHOWING STREET RIOTS, RAIDS ON BUSINESS ESTABLISHMENTS, AND BURNING OF VEHICLES.

THE ARMY'S CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE WORKERS' MARCH WAS PRECEDED BY RAIDS OF FOUR UNION HEADQUARTERS IN SAN SALVADOR AND THE ARREST OF SOME 100 MEMBERS OF HUMANITARIAN AND LABOR ORGANIZATIONS ON CHARGES OF POSSESSING WEAPONS, EXPLOSIVES, AND "SUBVERSIVE" PROPAGANDA.

LEADERS OF THE MAJOR OPPOSITION UNIONS AND LEFTIST POLITICIANS WARNED TODAY THAT THE THREATS AGAINST THE MARCH "REFLECT AN INCREASE OF REPRESSION" BY THE FUTURE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) GOVERNMENT BEFORE ITS 1 JUNE INAUGURATION.

IN A COMMUNIQUE, ARENA STATED THAT THE CAMPAIGN OF VIOLENCE EXPECTED IN MAY "IS BASED ON PLANS BY THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT TO DESTABILIZE AREA GOVERNMENTS."

THE GUERRILLAS HAVE WARNED THAT THEY WILL START A MILITARY OFFENSIVE TOMORROW TO PRESSURE THE GOVERNMENT TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE THAT COULD LEAD TO A POLITICAL SOLUTION OF THE CONFLICT.

THE MAIN SALVADORAN LABOR UNIONS DENIED THE CHARGES MADE BY THE ARMED FORCES AND HAVE INTENSIFIED THEIR CALLS TO THEIR MEMBERS TO MARCH FOR "PEACE WITH JUSTICE, WORK, AND LIBERTY."

A WAR OF WORDS HAS BEEN LAUNCED ON THE MEDIA, WHICH BROADCASTS CALLS FROM THE ARMY ASKING WORKERS NOT TO PARTICIPATE IN THE MARCHES, WHILE UNIONS URGE THEIR MEMBERS TO COMMEMORATE THE CHICAGO INCIDENTS AT THE END OF THE LAST CENTURY.

MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, ARCHBISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, TODAY ASKED THE ARMY TO "ACT CALMLY AND WITHOUT PREJUDICE" AGAINST THE TRADE UNIONS.

"WE HOPE AUTHORITIES WILL NOT SILENCE THE WORKERS' LEGITIMATE CLAMOR FOR MORE JUSTICE AND PEACE," ROSA CHAVEZ SAID.

THE PRELATE SAID THAT "LABOR AND PEASANT GROUPS WILL MARCH PEACEFULLY," AND THAT THEY ARE NOT LOOKING FOR CONFRONTATION, BUT DEMANDING JUSTICE AND PEACE.

ACCORDING TO THE ARMED FORCES, THE GUERRILLAS -- THROUGH "FRONT ORGANIZATIONS" -- WILL CARRY OUT VIOLENT ACTIONS, SUCH AS SABOTAGES ON COMMERCIAL ESTABLISHMENTS, BANKS, DESTRUCTION OF PRIVATE AND PUBLIC VEHICLES IN SAN SALVADOR, SANTA ANA, AND SAN MIGUEL.

DEV-MUC3-0194 (ADS)

BOGOTA, 1 MAY 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [EXCERPTS] GRUPO RADIAL COLOMBIANO NETWORK RADIO STATIONS AND LA REBAJA DRUGSTORES WERE DYNAMITED LAST NIGHT IN BOGOTA, RESULTING IN THE INJURY OF SIX PEOPLE AND MILLIONS IN LOSSES. THE DAMAGE CAUSED BY THE SHOCK WAVES AFFECTED NEARBY VENDORS AND RESIDENTS. OUR REPORTER HERNANDO MARTINEZ HAS THIS REPORT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MARTINEZ] IN LAST NIGHT'S ATTACK ON THREE GRUPO RADIAL COLOMBIANO RADIO STATIONS AND TWO LA REBAJA DRUGSTORES, THE ATTACKERS USED BOMBS THAT CREATED LARGE SHOCK WAVES THAT DAMAGED EVERYTHING IN THEIR PATH. SEVERAL HOMES NEAR THE RADIO STATIONS WERE SERIOUSLY DAMAGED.

AT THE SAME TIME, BOMBS EXPLODED IN THE SAN VICTORINO NEIGHBORHOOD, DESTROYING 2 LA REBAJA DRUGSTORES, 6 OTHER DRUG STORES, 7 HARDWARE STORES, 30 OFFICES IN NEARBY BUILDINGS, AND 22 VENDOR STANDS.

ANOTHER DYNAMITE CHARGE WAS PLACED TODAY AT AN ESTABLISHMENT THAT EVERYBODY KNOWS AS LA REBAJA, BUT WHICH IS NOT CONNECTED TO THE LA REBAJA CHAIN OF DRUGSTORES. THAT BOMB WAS DEFUSED.

THE POLICE HAVE STARTED LOOKING FOR THE TERRORISTS. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0195 (ADS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 1 MAY 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] HONDURAN WORKERS TODAY DEMANDED THE EXPULSION OF U.S. TROOPS AND NICARAGUAN CONTRAS FROM THE COUNTRY, AND THEY DEMANDED HIGHER WAGES, MEASURES TO CONTROL INFLATION, AND THE CREATION OF NEW JOBS.

THE ANTI-AMERICAN FEELING WAS MORE MARKED AMONG THE MEMBERS OF THE LEFTIST UNITED FEDERATION OF HONDURAN WORKERS (FUTH), WHO BURNED EIGHT U.S. FLAGS.

THE DEMONSTRATORS ALSO BURNED A COFFIN SYMBOLIZING THE BURIAL OF THE INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND AND THE U.S. AGENCY FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT (AID). THEY ALSO BURNED A SCALE MODEL OF THE U.S. PALMEROLA MILITARY BASE IN CENTRAL HONDURAS.

THE HONDURAN LABOR ORGANIZATIONS HELD SEPARATE MARCHES. THOSE OF THE RIGHT ENDED THEIR DEMONSTRATION AT THE CENTRAL SQUARE, IN FRONT OF THE STATUE OF CENTRAL AMERICAN HERO FRANCISCO MORAZAN, WHILE THOSE OF THE LEFT ENDED THEIR MARCH IN FRONT OF THE MANUEL BONILLA NATIONAL THEATER.

THE CONSERVATIVE CONFEDERATION OF HONDURAN WORKERS (CTH) AND THE GENERAL WORKERS FEDERATION (CGT) ALSO CONDEMNED THE PRESENCE OF U.S. TROOPS AND OF MORE THAN 10,000 NICARAGUAN CONTRAS IN THE COUNTRY.

"YANKEES GET OUT OF HONDURAS," "CONTRAS GET OUT," "TO PAY THE FOREIGN DEBT IS TO KILL THE PEOPLE," AND "JOBS AND NOT MORE MILITARY AID" WERE SOME OF THE SLOGANS ON PLACARDS AND BANNERS CARRIED BY THE WORKERS.

THE SPEAKERS FROM THE MAIN LABOR ORGANIZATIONS DEMANDED THAT PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA'S GOVERNMENT RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS, AMEND THE LABOR CODE, REFORM THE SOCIAL SECURITY INSTITUTE, INCREASE THE MINIMUM WAGE, AND RESPECT THE RIGHT TO WORK AND JOB SECURITY.

"WE WANT A FREEZE ON PRICES OF STAPLES, HOUSING PROGRAMS, RESPECT FOR NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY, DEMOCRATIZATION IN CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PARLIAMENT," CTH SECRETARY GENERAL VICTOR ARTILES SAID.

THE LABOR ORGANIZATIONS STRESSED THAT THERE CAN BE NO PEACE IN THE COUNTRY WITH MORE THAN 1.2 MILLION UNEMPLOYED AND A POPULATION WITH DEFICIENT HEALTH, EDUCATION, AND FOOD SERVICES.

THEY ALSO SAID THEY ARE AGAINST THE SHIPMENT OF WEAPONS TO HONDURAS AND AGAINST THE CREATION OF NEW MILITARY UNITS.

FUTH PRESIDENT HECTOR HERNANDEZ SAID THAT HONDURAS "IS NOT ONLY FACING CONSTANT PRESSURE TO DEVALUE ITS CURRENCY BUT ALSO DAILY PRESSURE TO DEVALUE OUR DIGNITY AS A NATION."

HERNANDEZ CONDEMNED THE PRESENCE OF U.S. TROOPS AND THE CONTRAS, AND HE SAID THAT "EFFORTS ARE BEING MADE TO MAKE US PAY FOR A FOREIGN DEBT WE DO NOT OWE."

"THAT DEBT WAS PAID A LONG TIME AGO, AND WE MUST ASK WHETHER IT IS THE DEVELOPED CAPITALIST COUNTRIES THAT OWE US BECAUSE OF THEIR LOOTING OF OUR NATURAL RESOURCES," HE ADDED.

OSCAR ANIBAL PUERTO, VICE PRESIDENT OF THE HONDURAN HUMAN RIGHTS DEFENSE COMMITTEE (CODEH), SAID THAT THE UNITED STATES, AND NOT THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT, IS THE ONE THAT ISSUES THE NATIONAL POLICY GUIDELINES.

PUERTO CONDEMNED HUMAN RIGHTS ABUSES THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE THROUGH ILLEGAL ARRESTS AND THE DISAPPEARANCE OF MORE THAN 100 PEOPLE.

DEV-MUC3-0197 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] THE UP TO DATE NEWS TEAM WAS ATTACKED TODAY BY U.S. EMBASSY EMPLOYEES AS THE NEWSMEN WERE COVERING A REPORT ON THE EXPLOSION OF TWO BOMBS IN A BUILDING BELONGING TO THE EMBASSY. THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED AT A U.S. EMBASSY WAREHOUSE LOCATED ON SAN ANTONIO ABAD STREET, NEAR THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL COMPLEX.

[REPORTER] TONIGHT, AT APPROXIMATELY 1940, A BOMB WENT OFF AT A U.S. EMBASSY WAREHOUSE NEAR THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL COMPLEX ON SAN ANTONIO ABAD STREET IN NORTHWEST SAN SALVADOR. THE UP TO DATE NEWS TEAM, WHICH WAS ON THE SCENE SHORTLY AFTER THE INCIDENT, WAS SHOOTING VIDEO FOOTAGE OF THE EXTENSIVE DAMAGE DONE BY THE BOMBS WHEN U.S. EMBASSY EMPLOYEES ATTACKED THE CAMERAMAN AND HIS ASSISTANT. THE VIDEO EQUIPMENT WAS DAMAGED. HERE IS WHAT HAPPENED:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]

[CAMARAMAN] WE DO NOT DESERVE TO BE MISTREATED LIKE THIS.

[UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] WE ARE NOT MISTREATING YOU. GET OUT. [END RECORDING]

[REPORTER] AT THIS POINT, THE CAMERA BELONGING TO THE UP TO DATE NEWS TEAM WAS THROWN ON THE FLOOR. SO FAR, NO GROUP HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK ON THE U.S. EMBASSY WAREHOUSE. SHORTLY AFTER THE EXPLOSION, A SEARCH FOR THE PERPETRATORS OF THE BOMBING WAS BEGUN.

DEV-MUC3-0198 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS TODAY DENIED HAVING CARRIED OUT A DYNAMITE ATTACK AGAINST A U.S. EMBASSY WAREHOUSE IN SAN SALVADOR, AN ATTACK OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE BLAMED ON THE GUERRILLAS. THERE WERE NO INJURIES IN TUESDAY NIGHT'S ATTACK.

OFFICIAL SOURCES REPORT TODAY THAT URBAN GUERRILLAS THREW TWO EXPLOSIVE DEVICES FROM A VEHICLE AT THE SAN JORGE WAREHOUSE, A U.S. EMBASSY FACILITY IN THE SAN ANTONIO ABAD NEIGHBORHOOD IN NORTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR.

A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) SPOKESMAN CLAIMED THAT THE ATTACK WAS "A CRUDE MANEUVER BY THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA), WHICH WILL BE GOVERNING EL SALVADOR AS OF 1 JUNE, TO COMPLICATE THE GUERRILLA DELEGATION'S U.S. VISIT." THE REBEL SOURCE CONFIRMED AN FMLN DECISION FIRST ANNOUNCED 3 MONTHS AGO THAT NO U.S. DIPLOMATIC OR ECONOMIC FACILITY IN EL SALVADOR WILL BE CONSIDERED A MILITARY TARGET.

AN FMLN DELEGATION WILL MEET TODAY IN NEW YORK WITH UN ASSISTANT SECRETARY ALVARO DE SOTO AND PERMANENT UN REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE FRG, CANADA, AND SPAIN. MEMBERS OF THE POLITICAL DIPLOMATIC GUERRILLA DELEGATION, WHICH OBTAINED UNRESTRICTED VISAS, WILL ASK THE UNITED NATIONS TO PARTICIPATE MORE ACTIVELY IN THE SEARCH FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN ARMED CONFLICT. THE GUERRILLAS WILL ALSO ASK THE UNITED NATIONS TO REMAIN ALERT TO THE SITUATION AND TO EXERT PRESSURE ON THE FUTURE ARENA ADMINISTRATION -- TO BE HEADED BY RIGHTIST ALFREDO CRISTIANI -- TO ENSURE THAT IT RESPECTS HUMAN RIGHTS.

LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT RICARDO ALVARENGA VALDIVIESO, AN ARENA MEMBER, DESCRIBED THE REBEL DELEGATION'S U.S. VISIT AS "DANGEROUS AND RIDICULOUS." "I REALLY DO NOT UNDERSTAND HOW THE UNITED STATES COULD GRANT VISAS TO TERRORISTS," ALVARENGA SAID IN REFERENCE TO THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S DENIAL OF A VISA TO EXTREME RIGHT-WING DEPUTY ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON, WHO HAS BEEN LINKED TO THE DEATH SQUADS.

THE DELEGATION, WHOSE U.S. VISIT WILL LAST MORE THAN 8 DAYS, IS HEADED BY SALVADOR SAMAYOA, MIGUEL SAENZ, AND COMMANDER MERCEDES DEL CARMEN LETONA, ALSO KNOWN AS "LUISA."

U.S. EMBASSY OFFICIALS HAD DESTROYED THE CAMERAS OF THE LOCAL NEWSCAST "UP TO DATE," WHOSE REPORTERS ATTEMPTED TO PHOTOGRAPH THE SCENE OF THE ATTACK.

DEV-MUC3-0200 (ADS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 4 MAY 89 (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT-ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS AT GOVERNMENT HOUSE IN TEGUCIGALPA] [TEXT] [REPORTER] [PASSAGE OMITTED] ...FOR PEACE.

[CRISTIANI] PRESIDENT DUARTE HAS NOT HAD THE LUCK OF STRIKING A RESPONSIVE CHORD IN THE SALVADORAN MARXIST GUERRILLAS. WE HOPE THAT WITH NEW EFFORTS AND WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF SALVADORAN POLITICAL FORCES WE [WORDS INDISTINCT] PEACE. WE ALSO BELIEVE IT IS NECESSARY FOR THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT TO BE SEEN IN ITS FULL DIMENSION: IT IS PART OF A REGIONAL PROBLEM, AND, CONSEQUENTLY, THE [CENTRAL AMERICAN] PRESIDENTS HAVE DISCUSSED THE SUBJECT OF THIS INTERNAL CONFLICT AT THEIR MEETINGS.

[REPORTER] I HAVE A QUESTION ON BILATERAL RELATIONS. WILL YOUR GOVERNMENT RESPECT THE RULING BY THE INTERNATIONAL COURT OF JUSTICE [ICJ] AT THE HAGUE REGARDING THE DEMARCATION OF THE BORDER WITH HONDURAS?

[CRISTIANI] WE ARE GOING TO CONTINUE TO RESPECT THE AGREEMENTS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES. WE BELIEVE THAT WE MUST BEGIN TO RESOLVE ALL THE DIFFERENCES THAT OUR TWO COUNTRIES MAY HAVE HAD AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. THIS IS ONE OF THE THINGS THAT WE HAVE MENTIONED TO PRESIDENT AZCONA. CONTRARY TO WHAT SOME PEOPLE MAY HAVE SAID, WE BELIEVE THAT WE MUST SEEK A SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEMS BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES AS SOON AS POSSIBLE AND CONTINUE IMPROVING A RELATIONSHIP THAT HAD BEEN SUSPENDED.

WE ARE GOING TO RESPECT THE PEACE PROCESS THAT IS ALREADY UNDER WAY BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES, AS WELL AS THE AGREEMENT TO TAKE THE MATTER TO THE ICJ FOR RESOLUTION.

[REPORTER] INTERNATIONAL REPORTS STATE THAT VIOLENCE HAS INCREASED IN EL SALVADOR SINCE YOUR PARTY WON THE ELECTIONS. I WOULD LIKE TO ASK IF YOU TRIED TO CONTACT THE GUERRILLAS PRIOR TO THE ELECTIONS OR ARE YOU GOING TO WAIT FOR THE SITUATION TO DETERIORATE EVEN FURTHER? [WORDS INDISTINCT] TAKE POWER?

[CRISTIANI] THE MARXIST GUERRILLA MOVEMENT IN EL SALVADOR HAS PUBLICLY ADMITTED THAT IT IS INCREASING ITS TERRORIST ACTIONS IN OUR COUNTRY IN AN ATTEMPT TO DESTABILIZE THE NEW GOVERNMENT. WE HAVE NOT GENERATED ANY VIOLENCE; I BELIEVE THE VICTORY OF OUR PARTY IN THE RECENT ELECTIONS DID NOT REPRESENT MORE VIOLENCE. VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT MERINO HEADED THE DELEGATION THAT MET WITH THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS IN MEXICO, AND FROM THE VERY BEGINNING WE HAVE EXPRESSED OUR WILLINGNESS TO SEEK, VIA A DIALOGUE, A SOLUTION TO OUR CONFLICT.

NATURALLY, WE CANNOT YET ACT AS A GOVERNMENT, AND WE ARE GOING TO RESPECT THE CURRENT GOVERNMENT'S RELATIONSHIP WITH THE GUERRILLAS. ONCE OUR ADMINISTRATION IS IN PLACE, WE WILL CONTINUE TO MAKE THE GREATEST EFFORT TO SEEK A DIALOGUE AND A SOLUTION.

[REPORTER] ARE YOU PLANNING TO ASK THE UNITED STATES FOR AN INCREASE IN ECONOMIC AND MILITARY AID?

[CRISTIANI] NO. DURING OUR RECENT TRIP TO WASHINGTON, ALL WE SAID IS THAT WE TRUST THAT THE U. S. GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE ARE IN FAVOR OF THE STRENGTHENING OF DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR. ON THIS OCCASION WE BENEFITTED FROM THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, BUT THIS SHOULD NOT GENERATE, A PRIORI, ANY PREJUDICE AGAINST THE NEW SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT THAT COULD RESULT IN A MODIFICATION OF U.S. AID TO OUR COUNTRY.

WE HAVE NOT ASKED FOR ANY INCREASE IN AID. WE BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD DEVELOP OURSELVES AND HAVE EL SALVADOR BECOME SELF-SUPPORTING. WE HOPE THAT WITH THE HELP OF THE LORD WE WILL ACHIEVE THIS [WORDS INDISTINCT] NOT BECAUSE WE DO NOT WANT TO MAINTAIN OUR FRIENDSHIP, BUT BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT EL SALVADOR CAN BECOME SELF-SUPPORTING.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT] [CRISTIANI] FRANKLY, I WAS SURPRISED BY THIS STATEMENT BY DANIEL ORTEGA. I DO NOT KNOW WHAT HE HAS BASED HIS OPINION ON. I DO NOT KNOW IF THIS IS THE RESULT OF MEETINGS THAT HE MIGHT HAVE HAD WITH THE MEMBERS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] WHO HAVE JUST RETURNED FROM NICARAGUA. HOWEVER, AS WE HAVE JUST REITERATED, OUR INTENTION IS TO CONTINUE WITH THE EFFORTS THAT HAVE BEEN UNDER WAY SINCE ESQUIPULAS II WAS SIGNED, AND TO SEEK DEMOCRACY AND PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA BY MEANS OF A JOINT EFFORT BY OUR COUNTRIES.

[REPORTER] IT HAS BEEN CONFIRMED THAT THE NEXT SUMMIT OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS WILL BE HELD IN OUR COUNTRY IN JUNE. YOU ARE SLATED TO ATTEND BECAUSE YOU WILL BE INAUGURATED ON 1 JUNE. WHAT POSITION WILL EL SALVADOR TAKE AT THE MEETING, AND TO WHAT EXTENT HAS YOUR GOVERNMENT COMPLIED WITH THE COSTA DEL SOL AGREEMENTS? [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0201 (ADS)

LIMA, 8 MAY 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [EXCERPTS] SENATOR LUIS ALBERTO SANCHEZ HAS BEEN DESIGNATED NEW PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS. THIS WAS REPORTED BY PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA ON ARRIVING AT GOVERNMENT PALACE AFTER PAYING HOMAGE IN CONGRESS TO LATE [APRA AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE] DEPUTY PABLO LI ORMENO.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ALAN GARCIA] I THINK IT IS A BARBAROUS CRIME WHICH WE MUST REPUDIATE AND AGAINST WHICH WE MUST ALL FIGHT.

WE NEED TO PUT ALL POLICE FORCES IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST TERRORISM. WE CAN NO LONGER SCATTER OUR EFFORTS AND KEEP SOME SECTORS IDLE. I HAVE SEEN POLICE AGENTS WORKING AS DRIVERS, SOME OF THEM PLAYING THE ROLE OF GREAT PERSONALITIES, OF CHIEFS. I HAVE SEEN MANY POLICEMEN DOING ADMINISTRATIVE WORK. WE ARE PAYING THOSE PEOPLE AND WE HAVE TRAINED THEM TO FIGHT AGAINST OUR MAIN ENEMY, WHICH IS TERRORISM.

I WANT TO TELL YOU THAT THE PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS, AND WITH HIM ALL MEMBERS OF THE MINISTERIAL CABINET, HAVE PRESENTED THEIR RESIGNATIONS. PRIME MINISTER ARMANDO VILLANUEVA FEELS THAT A POLITICAL RENEWAL IS NECESSARY TO GIVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO THE DEMOCRATIC SECTORS TO PARTICIPATE MORE ACTIVELY IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST SUBVERSION. THE MURDER OF ANOTHER CONGRESSMAN HAS LED THE MINISTERS TO PRESENT THEIR RESIGNATIONS.

THIS POLITICAL RENEWAL MUST LEAD ALL PERUVIANS TO JOIN EFFORTS. WE MUST FORGET OUR ELECTORAL CONFRONTATIONS AND ADVERSITIES FOR A WHILE AND UNDERSTAND THAT THE STRUGGLE AGAINST TERRORISM IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN THE ELECTIONS. WE MUST UNDERSTAND THAT WE ARE AT WAR AGAINST TERRORISM, THAT WE ARE AT WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, AND THAT THIS WAR REPRESENTS A COST OF THOUSANDS OF MILLIONS OF INTIS, DOZENS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS. WE MUST MAKE THIS TREMENDOUS EFFORT TO END SUBVERSION ONCE AND FOR ALL. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0203 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 MAY 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] OFFICIAL SOURCES REPORTED TODAY THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA GROUPS HAVE INCREASED THEIR SABOTAGE AGAINST THE NATIONAL ELECTRICAL SYSTEM IN THE PAST FEW HOURS, LEAVING 40 PERCENT OF THE NATIONAL TERRITORY WITHOUT ELECTRICITY, WHILE INTERMITTENT BLACKOUTS HAVE OCCURRED IN THE REST OF THE COUNTRY.

THE ENTIRE EASTERN ZONE OF THE COUNTRY WAS WITHOUT ELECTRICITY TODAY, ACCORDING TO A REPORT FROM THE LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION (CEL), WHICH STATED THAT ON MONDAY, FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS BLEW UP SEVERAL STRUCTURES IN THAT REGION.

THE REPORT ADDED THAT THE SABOTAGE OCCURRED ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, WHERE OTHER STRUCTURES WERE ALSO BLOWN UP EARLY THIS MORNING. IN THIS CAPITAL, FMLN URBAN COMMANDOES BLEW UP AT LEAST THREE POLES SUPPORTING SECONDARY LINES, AND AN AS YET UNDETERMINED NUMBER OF POLES AND TOWERS IN DIFFERENT LOCATIONS IN THE COUNTRY'S CENTRAL AND WESTERN REGION.

IN THE WAKE OF THE NEW ATTACKS AGAINST THE ELECTRICAL SYSTEM, ON MONDAY THE CEL STARTED A TURBOGAS PLANT IN THE EASTERN CITY OF SAN MIGUEL TO PARTIALLY SOLVE THE COUNTRY'S ENERGY CRISIS.

MEANWHILE, NATIONAL POLICE DIRECTOR COLONEL CARLOS GUZMAN SAID THAT THE FMLN WILL ACCELERATE THE SABOTAGE AS 1 JUNE APPROACHES, WHEN THE RIGHT-WING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) WILL TAKE POWER.

COL GUZMAN ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT MILITARY INTELLIGENCE HAS DISCOVERED "PLANS TO MURDER" ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND MEMBERS AND FUTURE ARENA ADMINISTRATION OFFICIALS. GUZMAN ADDED THAT THE PLANS WOULD BE CARRIED OUT BY FMLN URBAN COMMANDOS. "THE DEATH THREATS DO NOT FRIGHTEN US," HE SAID, WITHOUT PROVIDING DETAILS ON THE GUERRILLAS' PLANS TO CARRY OUT THE MURDERS.

DEV-MUC3-0204 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 10 MAY 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH COLONEL MAURICIO ERNESTO VARGAS, COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE IN SAN MIGUEL, BY STATION CORRESPONDENT SORTO] [TEXT] CONCERNING A LAST-MINUTE REPORT WHICH INTERNATIONAL NEWS AGENCIES ARE ATTRIBUTING TO A CLANDESTINE RADIO VENCEREMOS ANNOUNCEMENT OF AN OPERATION CONCERNING ATTACKS AGAINST SEVERAL MILITARY GARRISONS IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY, WE INTERVIEWED COLONEL MAURICIO ERNESTO VARGAS, COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE STATIONED IN SAN MIGUEL. WE CONTACTED HIM BY TELEPHONE, AS FOLLOWS:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SORTO] COLONEL, IS IT TRUE THIS IS PART OF A REGIONAL OR NATIONAL OPERATION TO ATTACK THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE?

[VARGAS] I DO NOT KNOW IF THIS IS PART OF A REGIONAL OR NATIONAL OPERATION. ALL I KNOW IS THAT THESE ARE TREACHEROUS, COWARDLY ACTIONS, BECAUSE THEY ARE AFRAID OF CONFRONTING THE SOLDIERS, THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE MILITARY UNITS. IN SAN MIGUEL, THERE WERE FIVE EXPLOSIONS IN OPEN AREAS ABOUT 2 TO 3 KM APART. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES OR MATERIAL DAMAGE INFLICTED ON THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE OR ITS INSTALLATIONS. THEY HIT SOME FUEL TANKS FILLED WITH ABOUT 3,000 GALLONS OF GASOLINE, WHICH STARTED A FIRE. HOWEVER, THE FIRES WERE IN OPEN AREAS, SO THERE HAVE BEEN NO CASUALTIES OR MATERIAL DAMAGE TO THE INSTALLATIONS.

[SORTO] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] CLAIMS IT SEIZED EL SALITRE ESTATE AND, FROM THERE, ATTACKED THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE.

[VARGAS] EL SALITRE ESTATE WAS NOT OCCUPIED. AN OLD SHACK ON THE ESTATE WAS SET ABLAZE, BUT THE FIRE DEPARTMENT CONTROLLED THE FIRE. I THINK THESE ARE THE GREAT REVOLUTIONARY VICTORIES THE FMLN TALKS ABOUT: ATTACKS AGAINST FIXED INSTALLATIONS THAT CONTAIN NO MILITARY UNITS, WHERE NOT EVEN PEASANTS ARE SLEEPING AT THE TIME. I BELIEVE THIS IS WHERE THE FMLN SAYS IT FIGHTS HEROICALLY FOR 4 HOURS TO BURN SEVEN PATCHES OF CROPS AND HOW IT CLAIMS IT HEROICALLY FIGHTS TO DOWN POWER TOWERS, WHICH ARE UNMOVING OBJECTS. THESE ARE THE ONLY GREAT ACTIONS IT CARRIES OUT, BUT THESE ACTIONS ARE AGAINST FIXED TARGETS THAT CANNOT MOVE. I REPEAT, THESE ARE COWARDLY ACTIONS THAT DO NOT CONFRONT THE SOLDIERS WHO REPRESENT THE MILITARY ABILITIES OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE COUNTRY.

[SORTO] DO YOU HAVE ANY UNITS COMBING THE AREA?

[VARGAS] YES, DEFINITELY, WE HAVE MEN IN THE AREA. THE TRUTH IS THAT AT 0200 TODAY, UNITS WERE BEING MOBILIZED. AS I SAID, THESE ARE COWARDLY ACTIONS, CARRIED OUT IN THE DARK, AND THE FMLN FLEES WHEN IT SEES OUR WELL-TRAINED MEN IN MILITARY UNIFORM. THAT IS ALL I HAVE TO SAY.

[SORTO] YOU HAVE PERMANENT GUARDS FOR SAN MIGUEL. SOME OF THE MARKET VENDORS TOLD US FOR THE FIRST TIME, NOT A SINGLE SHOT WAS HEARD.

[VARGAS] YES, THAT IS RIGHT. AS I SAID, THERE HAVE NOT BEEN ANY ATTACKS OR HARASSMENT, JUST FIVE EXPLOSIVE DEVICES, WHICH DOES NOT REPRESENT ANY CHANGES IN THE CORRELATION OF MILITARY FORCES. THE PEOPLE OF SAN MIGUEL SHOULD BE CALM; WE WILL PROVIDE THEM WITH SECURITY. THE PEOPLE OF THE EASTERN AREA OF THE COUNTRY SHOULD BE CALM, BECAUSE WE WILL INCREASE OUR ABILITIES AND EFFORTS TO PROVIDE THEM WITH ALL THE SECURITY POSSIBLE. THE FMLN WILL HAVE TO PAY FOR BEING SO AUDACIOUS.

[SORTO] THE FMLN SAID IT WAS FIGHTING IN BERLIN AND ALEGRIA.

[VARGAS] WE HAVE NO KNOWLEDGE OF ANY ACTION IN BERLIN AND ALEGRIA. WE HAVE REPORTS THAT IN SAN ILDEFONSO, SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT -- SOUTH OF CABANAS -- THERE WERE PROBLEMS BECAUSE THE NATIONAL GUARD -- WHICH WE SUPPORT THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY -- REPORTED SOME CATAPULTS HAD BEEN FIRED. HOWEVER, NOTHING ELSE HAPPENED, AND I HAVE NO REPORTS OF ANY ACTION IN OTHER PLACES.

[SORTO] TODAY IS MOTHER'S DAY.

[VARGAS] YES, DEFINITELY, GREETINGS TO ALL MOTHERS: HAVE FAITH AND HOPE THAT YOUR SONS ARE HERE -- FROM THE GENERAL TO THE LAST SOLDIER -- AND THEY LOVE YOU VERY MUCH AND ARE WORKING FOR YOU, SO YOU WILL HAVE THE PEACE AND TRANQUILITY YOU NEED AS MOTHERS TO GENERATE LOVE AND COURAGE FOR EACH OF YOUR SONS. ON BEHALF OF ALL YOUR SONS, THE SOLDIERS, TO ALL MOTHERS OF THE EASTERN AREA AND OF EL SALVADOR: RECEIVE LOVE AND KISSES. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0205 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 10 MAY 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] REBEL SOURCES HAVE REPORTED THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA MOVEMENT TODAY INFLICTED ALMOST 100 CASUALTIES ON THE SALVADORAN ARMY DURING ATTACKS ON 15 TOWNS IN 7 DEPARTMENTS.

RADIO VENCEREMOS, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S [FMLN] OFFICIAL RADIO STATION, SAID THE REBELS ATTACKED THE GUARDS WHO WATCH OVER THE TOWN OF TEJUTEPEQUE IN THE NORTHEASTERN DEPARTMENT OF CABANAS, INFLICTING 90 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING DEAD OR WOUNDED.

THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, WHICH CONFIRMED THE ATTACK, INDICATED THAT THE REBELS SUSTAINED 19 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING DEAD OR WOUNDED, WHILE 3 SOLDIERS WERE KILLED AND 6 WOUNDED IN A 2-HOUR CLASH THAT TOOK PLACE IN TEJUTEPEQUE, 60 KM NORTHWEST OF SAN SALVADOR.

ACCORDING TO THE REBELS, AN OFFICER AND A SERGEANT WERE KILLED IN THE TEJUTEPEQUE ATTACK, WHICH BEGAN EARLY IN THE MORNING OF 10 MAY.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE, COPREFA, PLAYED DOWN THE REBEL ATTACK AND ADMITTED ANOTHER THREE ARMY CASUALTIES AND THE DEATH OF ONE GUERRILLA DURING VARIOUS ATTACKS ON ARMY POSITIONS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

THE FIRST GUERRILLA MILITARY BULLETIN BROADCAST BY THE CLANDESTINE RADIO STATION DID NOT REPORT ANY REBEL CASUALTIES.

THE NEW REBEL OFFENSIVE ANNOUNCED IN APRIL IS CALLED: "EVERYBODY AGAINST THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) AND TO STRUGGLE FOR PEACE." WITH THAT OFFENSIVE THE REBELS INTEND TO DESTABILIZE THE NEW GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT-ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, WHO IS AN ARENA LEADER.

CRISTIANI WILL ASSUME THE PRESIDENCY ON 1 JUNE AND WILL BE REPLACING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE.

THE REBEL STATION ADDED THAT ANOTHER THREE CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED ON TROOPS OF MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 3, WHO WATCH OVER THE TOWN OF ANAMOROS IN THE EASTERN DEPARTMENT OF LA UNION.

MILITARY SPOKESMEN ASSERTED THAT ONE GUERRILLA WAS KILLED DURING THE ATTACK ON MILITARY POSITIONS IN CHIRILAGUA, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT.

A FUEL PUMP WAS DESTROYED BY SHRAPNEL FROM EXPLOSIVE DEVICES HURLED BY GUERRILLAS AGAINST A GARRISON OF THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE HEADQUARTERED IN SAN MIGUEL, THE COUNTRY'S THIRD MOST IMPORTANT CITY.

COLONEL MAURICIO VARGAS, COMMANDER OF THE 3D BRIGADE, SAID THE REBEL ATTACKS ARE "ACTIONS CARRIED OUT UNDER THE COVER OF DARKNESS AND ARE TREACHEROUS AND COWARDLY ACTS BECAUSE THE REBELS ARE AFRAID TO FACE THE SOLDIERS WHO REPRESENT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE COUNTRY'S MILITARY POWER."

VARGAS SAID THE REBELS DID NOT INFLICT CASUALTIES ON OR CAUSE DAMAGE TO THE GARRISON.

THE GUERRILLAS ALSO ATTACKED THE SOLDIERS GUARDING TWO COFFEE MILLS IN SANTIAGO DE MARIA, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT. THEY DID NOT INFLICT ANY CASUALTIES.

RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTED THAT THE REBELS DESTROYED THE MUNICIPAL OFFICE, A GASOLINE STATION, AND THE CIVIL DEFENSE POST IN EL CONGO, SANTA ANA DEPARTMENT.

ACCORDING TO MILITARY SOURCES, THREE MEMBERS OF THE SO-CALLED CIVIL DEFENSE WERE WOUNDED WHEN THEIR POST WAS ATTACKED IN A VILLAGE NEAR METAPAN, SANTA ANA DEPARTMENT.

A MILITARY SOURCE ADDED THAT A TELECOMMUNICATIONS OFFICE WAS DESTROYED AND FIVE HOUSES DAMAGED BY EXPLOSIVES IN AGUILARES, IN SAN SALVADOR'S NORTHERN SUBURB.

THE REBELS SAID THEY ATTACKED MILITARY POSITIONS IN CHALATENANGO, SAN VICENTE, LA PAZ, AND MORAZAN DEPARTMENTS IN NORTHERN, CENTRAL, AND NORTHWESTERN EL SALVADOR, RESPECTIVELY, WITHOUT INFLICTING ANY CASUALTIES ON GOVERNMENT TROOPS.

DEV-MUC3-0206 (ADS)

HAVANA (CUBA), 10 MAY 89 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [COMMENTARY] [HORACIO GIBEOLA] [TEXT] THE LATEST COUP ATTEMPT AGAINST GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO IS NOT AN ISOLATED EVENT. IT SHOWS THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT'S PRECARIOUSNESS. UNABLE TO MAKE GOOD ITS LUKEWARM ELECTION PROMISES, THIS GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN A COMPLETELY DEFENSIVE POLICY. HARASSED BY ATTEMPTED COUPS, GOVERNMENT CORRUPTION, ADMINISTRATIVE INEPTNESS, AND INSURGENT ACTIVITIES, CEREZO'S ADMINISTRATION IS PLAGUED BY EVIDENT INSTABILITY. HIS GOVERNMENT IS STILL HOSTAGE TO THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND, WHICH TEMPORARILY SURRENDERED POWER AFTER MANY YEARS OF DICTATORSHIP.

NEVERTHELESS, CEREZO IS THE VICTIM OF MILITARY MEN WHO HAVE BEEN KEPT AWAY FROM POSITIONS OF GREATER POWER BY THEIR FELLOW OFFICERS. THIS SEEMS TO HAVE BEEN THE CAUSE OF THE MOST RECENT PLOT AGAINST THE CIVILIAN GOVERNMENT. THIS PLOT, MASTERMINDED BY AIR FORCE OFFICERS, WAS CRUSHED BY OFFICERS WHO DECIDED TO SUPPORT THE PRESIDENT FOR THE TIME BEING.

GUATEMALA, 85 PERCENT OF WHOSE POPULATION LIVES IN POVERTY, IS PLAGUED BY PARAMILITARY GROUPS THAT SPREAD PANIC, PARTICULARLY AMONG THE PEASANT AND INDIAN POPULATION, IN COLLUSION WITH THE POWERFUL AND WELL-ARMED ARMY. ANOTHER SIGN OF THE GOVERNMENT'S INCREASING WEAKNESS IS THAT IMPORTANT DECISIONS ARE MADE BY THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND, WHICH DOMINATES KEY ECONOMIC SECTORS.

CEREZO'S POWER WAS THREATENED A FEW DAYS AGO BY THE DISCLOSURE THAT GUATEMALAN FORCES FOR A LONG TIME HAD BEEN STAGING JOINT COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATIONS WITH U.S. SOLDIERS. THIS PARTICIPATION CASTS DOUBTS ON CEREZO'S ALLEGED ACTIVE NEUTRALITY IN CENTRAL AMERICA AND TURNS GUATEMALA INTO JUST ANOTHER SPRINGBOARD FOR THE DEPLOYMENT OF U.S. FORCES AS PART OF THE SO-CALLED LOW-INTENSITY WAR. ACCORDING TO THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY, WAR EXERCISES ARE STAGED IN GUATEMALA WITH TROOPS FROM THE U.S. BASES IN THE PANAMA CANAL AREA. ON 31 JANUARY, A U.S. PILOT FLYING A U.S. PLANE WAS KILLED WHEN HE TRIED TO LAND AT THE GUATEMALA CITY AIR FORCE BASE. THE REBELS ASSERTED THE PLANE WAS HIT BY ANTIAIRCRAFT FIRE. IN ADDITION, U.S. TROOPS WERE DEPLOYED IN GUATEMALA'S CHIMALTENANGO DEPARTMENT IN NOVEMBER 1988.

SHORTLY AFTER THE MURDER OF 22 PEASANTS LAST FEBRUARY, THE GUERRILLAS NOTICED FLIGHTS NEAR THE SCENE OF THE MASSACRE BY U.S. AIR FORCE CHINOOK HELICOPTERS THAT PARTICIPATED IN COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATIONS OR IN MISSIONS TO SUPPORT THE GUATEMALAN ARMY.

THE MOST RECENT COUP ATTEMPT IN GUATEMALA AND THE DISCOVERY OF AN INCREASING PRESENCE OF U.S. TROOPS IN THAT COUNTRY HAS PLACED CEREZO'S GOVERNMENT IN A SERIOUS, DIFFICULT POSITION. CEREZO SEEMS TO BE FORCED TO OBEY A SOCIETY MADE UP OF PEOPLE MUCH MORE POWERFUL THAN HIM.

DEV-MUC3-0207 (ADS)

LIMA, 14 MAY 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN POLICE TODAY ARRESTED 10 PEOPLE SUSPECTED OF HAVING DETONATED A CAR BOMB SOME 300 METERS FROM GOVERNMENT HOUSE WHERE PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AND HIS FAMILY WERE SLEEPING.

THE POLICE REPORTED THAT THE POWERFUL SHOCK WAVE DESTROYED WINDOWS AND DOORS IN A 400-METER RADIUS, BUT NO INJURIES WERE REPORTED.

THE POLICE ATTRIBUTED THE ATTACK TO THE TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA). THE EXPLOSION TOOK PLACE AT 0150 (0650 GMT) ON BLOCK NO. 3 ON ANCASH STREET, IN FRONT OF THE SAN FRANCISCO MONASTERY AND THE NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF CULTURE.

WITNESSES TOLD POLICE THAT THEY SAW THREE WELL-DRESSED YOUNG MEN ADANDONING THE CAR, APPARENTLY ACTIVATING THE BOMB BY REMOTE CONTROL SOME 100 METERS AWAY. THE SUSPECTS THEN FLED IN ANOTHER CAR THAT WAS AWATING THEM.

THIS IS THE SECOND CAR BOMB PLANTED BY THE MRTA SINCE 7 MAY, WHEN THE TERRORIST GROUP BLEW UP ANOTHER VEHICLE IN FRONT OF THE SAN MARTIN MILITARY QUARTERS, AN ARMY ADMINISTRATIVE UNIT LOCATED IN THE LIMA DISCTRICT OF MIRAFLORES.

THE MRTA, WHICH HAS DETONATED ABOUT 20 CAR BOMBS, BEGAN ITS ACTIVITIES IN 1984. TWO WEEKS AGO, THE ARMY SHOT 65 MRTA MEMBERS IN A CLASH IN JAUJA, IN THE CENTRAL MOUNTIAN REGION.

IN RELATED DEVELOPMENTS, THE DEPARTMENTS OF PASCO, JUNIN, AND HUANUCO RETURNED TO NORMAL TODAY AFTER A 72-HOUR "ARMED STRIKE" CALLED BY THE MAOIST TERRORIST GROUP THE SHINING PATH. TRADE, MINING, AND BANKING ACTIVITIES IN THESE IMPORTANT ANDEAN DEPARTMENTS WERE COMPLETELY PARALYZED DURING THE STRIKE.

ONE ARMY OFFICER AND A CIVILIAN DIED, 5 POLICEMEN AND 2 CIVILIZANS WERE INJURED, AND SOME $20 MILLION WAS LOST IN PROPERTY DAMAGE DURING THE STRIKE.

THE MAIN PERUVIAN MINES OF LEAD, SILVER, ZINC, GOLD, AND COPPER ARE LOCATED IN THESE THREE DEPARTMENTS. APPROXIMATELY 40,000 MINEWORKERS OBSERVED THE STRIKE OUT OF FEAR OF SHINING PATH RETALIATION.

DEV-MUC3-0208 (ADS)

ASUNCION (PARAGUAY), 16 MAY 89 (ABC COLOR) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PERUVIAN FOREIGN MINISTER GUILLERMO LARCO COX BY ABC COLOR REPORTERS] [TEXT] [REPORTER] DOES YOUR PRESENCE HERE SIGNALS THE CREATION OF A KIND OF CONTINENTAL DEMOCRATIC FRONT, SIMILAR TO THE FRONT OF MILITARY GOVERNMENTS OF THE PAST?

[LARCO COX] YES. THE PRESENCE HERE OF THE FOREIGN MINISTERS OF THE GROUP OF 8, WITH JUST ONE EXCEPTION, WAS AGREED DURING A PREVIOUS CONVERSATION IN WHICH WE DECIDED THAT PARAGUAY MUST BE GIVEN THE CHANCE THAT IT DESERVES FOLLOWING THE RECENT ELECTIONS THAT REFLECTED THE WILL OF THE PEOPLE. AND THIS IS WHAT WE WANT, THE STRENGTHENING OF DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS.

[REPORTER] WHAT DOES ALL THAT MEAN?

[LARCO COX] IT MEANS THAT THE PARAGUAYAN OPPOSITION WAS ABLE TO PERFORM ITS SUPERVISORY ROLE WITHOUT OBSTACLES, AND THAT THE PROCESS WAS OBSERVED BY INDEPENDENT JOURNALISTS, WHO MADE USE OF FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION TO GUARANTEE THE LEGITIMACY OF THE PROCESS.

[REPORTER] YOUR REMARKS ARE VERY SIGNIFICANT, PARTICULARLY NOW THAT THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT IS FIGHTING A GUERRILLA FORCE THAT JEOPARDIZES THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM.

[LARCO COX] RIGHT. IN PERU WE ARE FIGHTING FOR HUMAN RIGHTS. IT IS A WELL KNOWN FACT THAT THE WORLD IS RIGHTLY CONCERNED ABOUT THE HUMAN RIGHTS OF THOSE WHO ARE ARRESTED DURING AN ANTISUBVERSIVE ACTION. YET THERE IS LITTLE CONCERN ABOUT THE HUMAN RIGHTS OF THOSE WHO DEFEND DEMOCRACY, WITHIN A DEMOCRACY. DEMOCRACY MUST DEFEND ITSELF. IN THIS CONTEXT THE SUBJECT OF RESPONSIBILITY IS NOT WELL DEFINED.

[REPORTER] DO YOU MEAN THAT A MILITARY GOVERNMENT IS AT TIMES MORE EFFECTIVE?

[LARCO COX] NO. IT IS MUCH MORE EFFECTIVE FOR REPRESSION, BUT I MADE IT CLEAR THAT SUBVERSION IN A DEMOCRACY IS UNJUSTIFIED AND THAT DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS DO NOT PROMOTE HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS. IF THERE ARE ANY HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS IN A DEMOCRACY, THEY STEM FROM EXCESSES BY THE REPRESSIVE FORCES.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE DIFFRENCE BETWEEN THESE TYPES OF REPRESSION?

[LARCO COX] IT IS SIMPLE. IN A DICTATORSHIP, REPRESSION IS WIDESPREAD AND ALMOST ALWAYS ARBITRARY, AND THERE IS NO ONE TO DEFEND HUMAN RIGHTS.

[REPORTER] IT IS ESTIMATED THAT ALAN GACIA HAS ALREADY SHOWN THAT THERE IS A LIMIT TO WHAT A CHARISMATIC LEADER CAN DO. IN FACT, HE IS YOUNG, HANDSOME, AND HE IS A GOOD SPEAKER. HOWEVER, HE COULD NOT SOLVE THE PROBLEMS. WHAT DOES PERU NEED IN ORDER TO IMPLEMENT THE MUCH DESIRED STABILIZATION OF THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS?

[LARCO COX] PERU NEEDS ECONOMIC STABILITY, BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT EXPERIENCE AND WITH A STRONG DESIRE TO DISTRIBUTE WEALTH. THE DISTRIBUTION OF WEALTH WAS DONE DURING THE FIRST 2 AND 1/2 YEARS. THE NEGATIVE SIDE OF THIS IS THAT DOMESTIC CONSUMPTION WAS OVERSTIMULATED. EVEN THOUGH IT MIGHT SEEM CONTRADICTORY, OUR PRODUCTIVE APPARATUS NEEDED MORE IMPORTED MATERIALS IN ORDER TO INCREASE LOCAL PRODUCTION. THIS LED TO A DANGEROUS DECREASE IN OUR RESERVES. SIMULTANEOUSNLY, THE BANK NATIONALIZATION LAW WAS SET IN MOTION. THIS PROVIDED THE PERFECT FRAMEWORK FOR THE DESTRUCTION OF THE SYSTEM. THERE WAS ALSO THE EARLY START TO THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN, AND FINALLY THE RADICAL OPPOSITION BY THE BUSINESS SECTOR OF A DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT.

[REPORTER] THERE HAS ALSO BEEN A GROWTH IN THE CRIME RATE AND THE COSTLY PROCESS OF FIGHTING THE SHINING PATH GUERRILLAS IN THE MOUNTAINS AND IN URBAN TERRORIST ACTIONS. THIS COULD EASILY LEAD TO THE CONCLUSION THAT PERUVIAN DEMOCRACY DOES NOT HAVE GOOD PROSPECTS, RIGHT?

[LARCO COX] QUITO TO THE CONTRARY. DEMOCRACY WILL BE PRESERVED EVEN IF THE NORMAL HANDING OVER OF POWER TO THE NEW ADMINISTRATION BECOMES THE ONLY OBJECTIVE OF THE RECENTLY INSTALLED CABINET. THIS, HOWEVER, WILL BECOME THE SOLE OBJECTIVE ONLY IN AN ESTREME SITUATION. THERE ARE OBVIOUSLY OTHER OBJECTIVES, BUT I WANT TO STRESS THE SIGNIFICANCE THAT WE ATTACH TO THE HANDING OVER OF POWER TO THE WINNER OF CLEAN ELECTIONS, WITH GUARANTEES FOR ALL OPPOSITION PARTIES. THIS IS HOW THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS WILL BE PRESERVED AND THIS IS HOW THIS GOVERNMENT WILL ATTAIN ONE OF ITS MAIN TARGETS.

DEV-MUC3-0209 (ADS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 16 MAY 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] A U.S. HELICOPTER USED TO PROVIDE ASSISTANCE TO THE GUATEMALAN ARMY CRASHED THIS EVENING WHEN TRYING TO LAND AT THE MILITARY AIRPORT IN GUATEMALA CITY.

ACCORDING TO INITIAL REPORTS, SEVERAL PASSENGERS WERE INJURED, INCLUDING U.S. PERSONNEL, WHO WERE TAKEN TO THE MILITARY HOSPITAL IN GUATEMALA CITY.

ACCORDING TO INFORMATION SUPPLIED BY THE GUATEMALAN ARMY, THE U.S. AIRCRAFT WAS BEING USED TO HELP CARRY FOOD AND SUPPLIES TO TOWNS THAT ARE HARD TO REACH.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS SENT BY GUERRILLA GROUPS TO GUATEMALAN NEWSPAPERS -- WHICH HAVE PUBLISHED THESE REPORTS -- THESE FLIGHTS ARE ALL PART OF THE MILITARY SUPPORT IN THE FIGHT AGAINST THE SUBVERSIVES.

THERE IS NO INFORMATION YET ON THE TYPE OF AIRCRAFT INVOLVED IN THE ACCIDENT, WHICH RESULTED WHEN "IT LOST POWER" BEFORE LANDING, ACCORDING TO INITIAL REPORTS. U.S. ARMY "CHINOOK" HELICOPTERS ARE USED IN GUATEMALA FOR VARIOUS OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT BETWEEN GUATEMALA CITY AND AREAS FAR DISTANT FROM THE CAPITAL.

THIS IS THE FOURTH AIRCRAFT ACCIDENT OCCURRING IN RECENT MONTHS. A GUATEMALAN AIR FORCE (FAG) "PILATUS" AIRPLANE CRASHED SOME MONTHS AGO IN CHIMALTENANGO PROVINCE, AND ITS PILOT DIED IN THE ACCIDENT. A FAG HELICOPTER RECENTLY PLUNGED INTO THE PETEN ITZA LAKE, LOCATED IN NORTHERN GUATEMALA; TWO CREWMEN DIED AND TWO SURVIVED THE ACCIDENT.

THE ARMY'S OFFICIAL VERSION REPORTED THAT THESE ACCIDENTS WERE CAUSED BY BAD WEATHER OR MECHANICAL FAILURE. GUERRILLA REPORTS, WHICH HAVE BEEN PUBLISHED IN LOCAL NEWSPAPERS, SAY THAT THE AIRCRAFT WERE SHOT DOWN BY THEIR ANTIAIRCRAFT UNITS.

DEV-MUC3-0210 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 MAY 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [EXCERPTS] GUERRILLA URBAN COMMANDO UNITS ATTACKED THE HOME OF NATIONAL ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT RICARDO ALVARENGA VALDIVIESO TODAY AT NOON, KILLING A NATIONAL POLICE OFFICER GUARDING THE HOUSE.

THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE AT APPROXIMATELY 1330 AND WAS ALLEGEDLY PERPETRATED BY GUERRILLA URBAN COMMANDO UNITS. DURING THE ATTACK, NATIONAL POLICE OFFICER FIDEL SANCHEZ SANCHEZ WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED. HE WAS TAKEN TO A MILITARY HOSPITAL BY MEMBERS OF ALVARENGA'S SECURITY POLICE. ALVARENGA WAS HAVING LUNCH IN HIS HOME WHEN THE POLICE OFFICERS GUARDING HIS HOME WERE ATTACKED.

WITNESSES HAVE REPORTED THAT FOUR YOUTHS IN A RED PICKUP TRUCK SHOT AT THE POLICEMEN FROM A DISTANCE OF 20 METERS. THIS LED TO AN EXCHANGE OF GUNFIRE, ALARMING RESIDENTS IN THE COLONIA MIRAMONTES AREA.

ALVARENGA ACCUSED THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] OF BEING DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ATTACK. HE ATTRIBUTED THE ATTACK TO THE FACT THAT HE IS OPPOSED TO ALLOWING 100 HANDICAPPED GUERRILLAS TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY. ALVARENGA ADDED THAT THE INSURGENTS' ATTITUDE HAS DEFINITELY CLOSED THE DOOR ON THE POSSIBILITY OF CARRYING OUT THIS EVACUATION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ALVARENGA] IT CANNOT BE. TODAY, MORE THAN EVER, I INSIST THAT THESE HANDICAPPED GUERRILLAS SHOULD NOT LEAVE THE COUNTRY. IF THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT, ALL OF THEM, AND THE JUSTICE MINISTER ALLOW THESE HANDICAPPED GUERRILLAS TO LEAVE, THEN WE WILL KEEP FIGHTING AGAINST THAT TYPE OF ACTION. WHY NOT TAKE THE CHILDREN WHO HAVE BEEN MAIMED OUT OF THE COUNTRY? SO MANY CHILDREN HAVE BEEN MAIMED BY BOMBS! I WOULD LIKE TO SEE AT LEAST ONE SALVADORAN CHILD BE TAKEN TO A LARGE HOSPITAL IN GERMANY.

IT IS NOT NECESSARY TO GO TO SUCH EXTREMES. AM I MAKING MYSELF CLEAR? TELL ME, HOW CAN WE SPEAK OF HUMANITARIAN ACTS WHEN OUR SALVADORAN CHILDREN, OUR YOUTH ARE BEING MAIMED? I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT I CANNOT ASSURE YOU THAT WE WILL PREVENT GUERRILLA COERCIVE ACTIONS. THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY CANNOT PREVENT THIS. WHAT WE CAN DO IS LEGISLATE. WE NEED TO LEGISLATE A BIT MORE TO GIVE OUR PEOPLE SECURITY. IF THAT IS A PROBLEM FOR THE FMLN AND, FOR THIS REASON, IT HAS ELEMENTS IT WISHES TO DESTROY... [CHANGES THOUGHT] LOOK, THEY CAN DESTROY ME. THIS IS TRUE. I DO NOT WANT IT TO HAPPEN, BUT THEY CAN DESTROY ME. BUT OTHERS LIKE RICARDO ALVARENGA WILL COME FORWARD. [END RECORDING]

THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE ON BERNAL AVENUE IN COLONIA MIRAMONTES, A FEW MINUTES AFTER ALVARENGA ENTERED HIS HOME. ALVARENGA SUFFERED NO INJURIES. THE FMLN HAS NOT YET CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK.

DEV-MUC3-0211 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 24 MAY 89 (RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] STATES:

1. BY REJECTING OUR PROPOSAL AIMED AT TRANSFORMING THE ELECTIONS INTO A PATH TO ACHIEVE PEACE, THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA] TURNED THE 19 MARCH ELECTIONS INTO A PROCESS OF WAR.

2. ARENA WILL ESTABLISH A GOVERNMENT SUPPORTED ONLY BY THE VOTES OF A MERE 18 PERCENT OF VOTING-AGE SALVADORANS, WHICH MAKES IT AN ILLEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT AND A GOVERNMENT OF MINORITIES FOR MINORITIES.

3. EVER SINCE ELECTION RESULTS WERE REVEALED, THERE HAS BEEN A SIGNIFICANT INCREASE OF REPRESSION AGAINST THE PEOPLE IN THE FORM OF ARRESTS, MURDERS, SEARCHES, RAIDS ON LABOR AND ASSOCIATION OFFICES, ATTACKS AGAINST UNIVERSITIES, AND SO ON.

4. ARENA IS ALREADY ANNOUNCING, AND IN MANY CASES ALREADY IMPLEMENTING, ANTIPOPULAR MEASURES SUCH AS THE FORMATION OF DEATH SQUADS UNDER THE NAME OF PATRIOTIC CIVILIAN DEFENSE, THE ANNULMENT OF DECREE 207, DEVALUATION OF THE CURRENCY, PRIVATIZATIONS, ESTABLISHMENT OF A STATE OF SIEGE, AND OTHER MEASURES THAT WILL HURT THE PEOPLE.

5. ARENA'S POLICY TOWARD THE EVACUATION OF PEOPLE MAIMED IN WAR SHOWS THAT THE ARENA GOVERNMENT WILL FURTHER DEHUMANIZE THE WAR.

6. AS A FIRST REPLY OF OUR FRONT TO THE ARENA GOVERNMENT, THE GENERAL COMMAND DECREES A NATIONAL TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE BEGINNING AT DAWN ON 31 MAY. THE MEASURE MUST BE COMPLIED WITH ON ALL HIGHWAYS OF THE COUNTRY AND IN THE CITIES. WE URGE ALL OUR UNITS TO ENFORCE THIS DECREE AND OUR PEOPLE TO ACTIVELY PARTICIPATE IN THE STOPPAGE TO REPUDIATE THE DEATH SQUAD'S GOVERNMENT AT THE VERY MOMENT OF ITS INAUGURATION.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND COMMANDERS FRANCISCO JOVEL, EDUARDO SANCHO, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, LEONEL GONZALEZ, AND JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS.

DEV-MUC3-0212 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 24 MAY 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] OUR ARMY IS ESSENTIALLY THE PEOPLE'S ARMY, BECAUSE IT WAS BORN OF THE PEOPLE. THROUGHOUT THESE MANY YEARS OF WAR, HUNDREDS OF COUNTRYMEN HAVE SPILLED THEIR BLOOD FOR THE LAND ON WHICH THEY TOIL TO ACHIEVE JUSTICE, DEMOCRACY, AND BETTER LIVING CONDITIONS FOR THE PEOPLE. THESE ARE THE PEOPLE'S MOST HEARTFELT DESIRES. IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE ENEMY, WE HAVE COMMITTED ERRORS IN MILITARY PROCEDURES THAT HAVE RESULTED IN CASUALTIES AMONG THE PEOPLE. TO QUICKLY AND RADICALLY CORRECT THESE REGRETTABLE PROCEDURAL ERRORS, THE FARBUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] GENERAL COMMAND ORDERS ALL COMMANDERS AND COMBATANTS OF OUR MILITARY UNITS TO STUDY AND IMPLEMENT THE FOLLOWING INSTRUCTIONS, WHICH MUST BE STRICTLY FULFILLED:

1. UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCE MUST POPULATED AREAS BE MINED. MINES MUST BE PLACED WHERE ENEMY TROOPS TRAVEL. ALL PRECAUTIONS MUST BE TAKEN IN HIGHWAY AMBUSHES SO THE MINES WILL ONLY AFFECT ENEMY PATROLS AND TRANSPORT VEHICLES.

2. IN THE PLANS TO ATTACK ENEMY GARRISONS, THE COMMANDERS MUST ALWAYS EVALUATE THE CIVILIAN POPULATION'S SITUATION. EVERY EFFORT MUST BE MADE TO CARRY OUT CLEAN ATTACKS. IF THERE IS ANY POSSIBILITY, EVEN AFTER ALL ALTERNATIVES HAVE BEEN EXPLORED, THAT PERSONS HAVING NOTHING TO DO WITH THE ENEMY WOULD BE AFFECTED IF THE ATTACK IS CARRIED OUT, THE OPERATION MUST BE SUSPENDED.

3. BEFORE PUNISHING THE OWNERS OF PRIVATE VEHICLES AND BUSES WHO VIOLATE THE PROVISIONS OF THE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE, OUR UNITS MUST BE ABSOLUTELY SURE THE OWNER VIOLATED THE PROVISION.

4. IN CARRYING OUT SABOTAGE OPERATIONS, IT MUST BE CONSIDERED WHO WOULD BE AFFECTED BY THE ACTION. TO THE SAME EXTENT OUR SABOTAGE OPERATIONS MUST BE IMPLACABLE WITH THE REGIME AND THE OLIGARCHY, THOSE OPERATIONS MUST NOT AFFECT WORKERS, SMALL OWNERS, PEASANTS, OR THE LOWER CLASSES.

5. BEFORE CARRYING OUT EXECUTIONS, AN EXHAUSTIVE INVESTIGATION MUST BE CONDUCTED UNTIL IT IS CONFIRMED THAT THE TARGET OF THE OPERATION IS AN ENEMY OF THE PEOPLE.

6. ALL OUR MILITARY OPERATIONS, INCLUDING THE EXECUTIONS, MUST BE PUBLICLY RECOGNIZED SO AS TO AVOID CONFUSION WITH THE ENEMY'S DIRTY WAR PROCEDURES.

EVERY FMLN COMBATANT MUST BEAR IN MIND THAT WE ARE COMMITTED TO THE PEOPLE AND THAT OUR STRUGGLE IS OF THE PEOPLE AND FOR THE PEOPLE. THEREFORE, WE MUST ACT CONSISTENT WITH THIS REVOLUTIONARY PRINCIPLE.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, MAY 1989

DEV-MUC3-0213 (ADS)

LA PAZ, 26 MAY 89 (LA RED PANAMERICANA) -- [TEXT] INTERIOR MINISTER EDUARDO PEREZ BELTRAN HAS DISCARDED THE POSSIBILITY OF A NEW, QUOTE, TERRORIST OR GUERRILLA GROUP, UNQUOTE, OUTBREAK IN THE COUNTRY. HE MADE THIS STATEMENT REFERRING TO THE MURDER OF TWO U.S. MISSIONARIES LAST WEDNESDAY NIGHT.

TO REMIND THE PEOPLE OF THIS CASE, DURING THE EVENING OF 24 MAY TWO U.S. CITIZENS, WHO BELONGED TO A RELIGIOUS ORGANIZATION, WERE MURDERED BY A SELF-STYLED ZARATE WILKA ARMED FORCES OF LIBERATION [FAL] GROUP IN DOWNTOWN LA PAZ.

THE INTERIOR MINISTER ADDED THAT THIS ALLEGED ORGANIZATION THAT CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER, HAS NO TIES WITH THE PERUVIAN SHINING PATH TERRORIST GROUP.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PEREZ BELTRAN] TO THIS MOMENT, AND DUE TO THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE CASE, I DO NOT DARE TO ADMIT THE EXISTANCE OF ANY RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THESE TWO TERRORIST GROUPS. IF THE SHINING PATH IS OPERATING IN BOLIVIA, IT SHOULD ANNOUNCE THAT IT IS IN FACT SHINING PATH THAT IS COMMITTING THESE CRIMES.

WE CAN SAY THE SAME THING ABOUT THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY IN THE 1960'S, WHEN IT DID NOT HIDE ITS IDENTITY. THIS WAS AN INTERNATIONAL GROUP. THEY ARRIVED IN BOLIVIA WITHOUT HIDING THEIR INTERNATIONAL IDENTITY, AND THERE ARE MANY BOLIVIANS WHO CAN TELL US ABOUT THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY.

NOW, IF THIS CRIME WAS COMMITTED BY THE SHINING PATH, THEN IT WAS COMMITTED BY THE SHINING PATH AND NOT BY THE ZARATE WILKA GROUP. I DO NOT WANT TO DISCARD THIS POSSIBILITY, HOWEVER, I DO NOT WANT TO ADMIT IT AS SOMETHING VERIFIED AND CONFIRMED. OUR OBLIGATION, AS MEMBERS OF THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH, IS TO RELEASE THE RESULTS OF SOMETHING OBVIOUS, FULLY VERIFIED AND CONFIRMED. [END RECORDING]

THE INTERIOR MINISTER ADDED THAT THE EXISTENCE OF THE SELF-STYLED FAL-ZARATE WILKA GROUP AND OF SHINING PATH MEMBERS IN BOLIVIA IS DOUBTFUL, BECAUSE IN THE CRIMINAL CASES RECORDED IN COCHABAMBA AND IN ORURO RECENTLY, THE POLICE DISCOVERED THAT COMMON CRIMINALS, AND ESPECIALLY THOSE LINKED TO THE WORLD OF DRUG ADDITION AND DRUG TRAFFICKING WERE DIRECTLY INVOLVED IN THOSE CRIMES.

REGARDING THE MURDER OF THE TWO MISSIONARIES IN LA PAZ LAST WEDNESDAY, THE INTERIOR MINISTER STATED THAT NO ONE HAS BEEN DETAINED, BUT THAT THE INVESTIGATIONS BY THE INTELLIGENCE SERVICES CONTINUE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[PEREZ BELTRAN] NO. WE CANNOT SUPPOSE THE EXISTENCE OF A TERRORIST GROUP IN BOLIVIA.

[REPORTER] AND WHAT ABOUT THESE MURDER CASES?

[PEREZ BELTRAN] I DO NOT KNOW. MANY PEOPLE CAN BE HIDING BEHIND THIS ZARATE WILKA GROUP. WE DO NOT KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT THIS ZARATE WILKA GROUP. WE DO NOT KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT THEIR POLITICAL LEANINGS, OR WHAT PARTY IS BEHIND THIS GROUP. THIS COULD HAVE BEEN A COMMON CRIME, OR MAYBE NOT.

BUT WE CANNOT JUST GO OUT AND SAY: YES, THIS GROUP LAST NIGHT MACHINEGUNNED THESE PEOPLE, THAT THEY ESCAPED, ETC. THIS WOULD MEAN A VERY IRRESPONSIBLE BEHAVIOR. THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH WANTS TO DEAL WITH THIS CASE AS SERIOUSLY AS POSSIBLE AND NOT CAUSE THE PEOPLE TO PANIC.

WE MUST DO SOMETHING FOR THE COUNTRY. WE SHOULD UNITE OUR FORCES, ALL COALITION PARTIES, THE RULING PARTY, THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH, THE ARMED FORCES, THE NATIONAL POLICE, AND ALL BOLIVIANS, TO DEFEND OUR DEMOCRACY. THIS WOULD REPRESENT A REAL BOLIVIAN STRUGGLE AGAINST THOSE WHO INTEND TO DISRUPT OUR PROCESS OF LIBERTY, TO FIGHT FOR THE FUTURE OF OUR CHILDREN AND OF THE FATHERLAND. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0214 (ADS)

LA PAZ, 26 MAY 89 (RADIO FIDES) -- [EXCERPT] THE MURDER BY MACHINEGUN FIRE OF TWO U.S. MISSIONARIES TODAY PROMPTED AN EMERGENCY MEETING OF THE BOLIVIAN POLICE HIGH COMMAND.

THE U.S. EMBASSY IN LA PAZ WILL COOPERATE IN THE INVESTIGATIONS OF THE MURDER BECAUSE THEY CONSIDERED AN ANTI-U.S. ACTION.

ACCORDING TO SOME POLITICAL REACTIONS, THIS CRIMES COMMITTED BY THE SELF-STYLED ZARATE-WILKA GROUP, SHOWS THAT THERE ARE ARMED GROUPS OPERATING IN BOLIVIA.

LESS THAN 40 HOURS AFTER THE MURDER OF THE TWO MORMON MISSIONARIES BY AN IRREGULAR ARMED GROUP IN LA PAZ, THE POLICE HIGH COMMAND HAS DECLARED AN EMERGENCY STATE ALL CADRES IN AN EFFORT TO CAPTURE THE PERPETRATORS OF THIS CRIME.

THE BOLIVIAN POLICE HIGH COMMAND THIS MORNING CALLED AN EMERGENCY MEETING TO BEGIN THE OFFICIAL INVESTIGATIONS. AFTER BRIEFING THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC, INTERIOR MINISTER EDUARDO PEREZ BELTRAN ALSO WENT TO THE POLICE HEADQUARTERS TO SEEK FURTHER INFORMATION ON THE MURDER CASE.

THE INTERIOR MINISTER PROMISED TO RELEASE THE FIRST RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS AT 1700 THIS AFTERNOON. TODD RAY WILSON, 20 YEARS OLD, AND JEFFREY BRENT BALL, 21, WERE MURDERED BY MACHINEGUN BURSTS WHEN THEY WERE WALKING HOME ON ANCASH STREET ON WEDNESDAY NIGHT.

THE ZARATE WILKA GROUP HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER OF THESE TWO MISSIONARIES. THIS GROUP REPORTEDLY COMMITTED THIS CRIME TO PROTEST U.S. MEDDLING IN BOLIVIA.

DEV-MUC3-0215 (ADS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 29 MAY 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES TODAY CONFIRMED THAT HEAVY CLASHES TOOK PLACE BETWEEN HONDURAN AND SALVADORAN TROOPS OVER THE WEEKEND. ACCORDING TO A LOCAL RADIO STATION, BOTH HONDURAN AND SALVADORAN CIVILIANS AND SOLDIERS WERE KILLED.

JUAN SIERRA, A HONDURAN ARMED FORCES SOURCE, TOLD REUTER: "WE ARE CERTAIN THERE WERE CLASHES, BUT THE DETAILS WILL BE AVAILABLE LATER."

THE HONDURAN RADIO STATION RADIO AMERICA, QUOTING A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] SOURCE, SAID AN UNSPECIFIED NUMBER OF CIVILIANS AND SOLDIERS WERE KILLED WHEN SALVADORAN TROOPS ENTERED HONDURAN TERRITORY ON SATURDAY.

THE FMLN, QUOTED BY RADIO AMERICA, SAID THE FIGHTING IN THE HONDURAN DEPARTMENT OF INTIBUCA, ON THE PLAINS NEAR THE SALVADORAN BORDER, LASTED 4 HOURS. DURING THE FIGHTING, A SALVADORAN HELICOPTER BOMBED HONDURAN CIVILIANS, KILLING OR WOUNDING A NUMBER OF THEM, THE FMLN SAID.

RADIO AMERICA SAID: "WE DO NOT KNOW THE EXACT NUMBER OF DEAD AND WOUNDED. (THE FMLN) ONLY SAID IT WAS CONFIRMED THAT CIVILIANS WERE KILLED OR WOUNDED IN THE CLASH."

THE TROOPS OF BOTH COUNTRIES HAVE PREVIOUSLY CLASHED AT THE BORDER AS THE RESULT OF TENSION CAUSED BY TERRITORIAL DISPUTES AND ALSO BECAUSE OF THE PRESENCE OF LARGE CONTINGENTS OF SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS NEAR THE BORDER. THE TWO ARMIES HAVE PREVIOUSLY HELD JOINT ANTIGUERRILLA OPERATIONS. ON ONE OCCASION, SALVADORAN SOLDIERS ATTACKED HONDURAN TROOPS, MISTAKING THEM FOR REBELS.

THE TENSION BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES REACHED ITS PEAK DURING THE SO-CALLED SOCCER WAR IN 1969, WHEN THE TWO COUNTRIES FOUGHT FOR 100 HOURS OVER A TERRITORIAL DISPUTE.

DEV-MUC3-0217 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 28 MAY 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] AT 1400 ON 27 MAY, SPECIAL HONDURAN TROOPS ENTERED SAN ANDRES AND TIERRA AGRIA, SAN GERARDO JURISDICTION, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, WHEN ARCE BATTALION TROOPS WERE CARRYING OUT AN OPERATION IN THE AREA. THEY CLASHED NEAR EL CHENGUE HILL AND ALONG THE SHORES OF TOROLA RIVER. DURING THIS CLASH, WHICH LASTED 4 HOURS, ARCE BATTALION WAS SUPPORTED BY TWO ROCKET-FIRING HELICOPTERS, A HUGHES 500, AND A A-37 PLANE.

SALVADORAN TROOPS SUSTAINED NUMEROUS CASUALTIES, INCLUDING A WOUNDED ARCE BATTALION OFFICER. HONDURAN TROOPS WERE PUSHED BACK AND CORNERED IN LOS LLANITOS, SANTA LUCIA JURISDICTION, INTIBUCA DEPARTMENT, HONDURAS. ARCE BATTALION LANDED TROOPS FROM FOUR HELICOPTERS IN THAT VILLAGE. AN HONDURAN HELICOPTER, WHICH WAS EVACUATING CASUALTIES, WAS ATTACKED AND PURSUED 7 KM INTO HONDURAN TERRITORY BY A SALVADORAN HELICOPTER, WHICH FIRED ROCKETS AND MACHINEGUNS.

ARCE BATTALION, WHICH SURROUNDED HONDURAN TROOPS IN LOS LLANITOS, CAPTURED AN UNDETERMINED NUMBER OF PRISONERS. IN THIS CLASH, RESIDENTS OF THE SAN ANDRES, [WORDS INDISTINCT] CANTONS, AND RESIDENTS OF LOS CASTANOS, LOS LLANITOS, AND LA CEIBITA WERE ROCKETED AND MACHINEGUNNED BY SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS.

THERE ARE REPORTS ABOUT PARTIALLY DESTROYED HOMES AND ANIMALS THAT WERE KILLED. WE ARE TRYING TO INVESTIGATE THE NAMES OF THE WOUNDED AND DEAD AMONG AREA RESIDENTS.

WE URGE THE HONDURAN PEOPLE TO REFLECT ON THE SERIOUSNESS AND REPERCUSSIONS OF THESE CLASHES. THIS IS THE RESULT OF THE HONDURAN ARMY'S POLICY OF INVOLVMENT IN THE SALVADORAN WAR.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAD WARNED THAT HONDURAN TROOPS' COOPERATION AND INVOLVEMENT IN THE SALVADORAN WAR, FOLLOWING A U.S. DECISION, WOULD EVENTUALLY LEAD TO A CLASH BETWEEN THE TWO ARMIES. IT IS A SECRET TO NOBODY THAT THE OLIGARCHS WHO HAVE REACHED POWER WITH THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE GOVERNMENT ARE THE SAME ONES WHO PROMOTED THE INVASION OF HONDURAS IN 1969 AND THAT THE OFFICERS WHO WERE RESPONSIBLE AT THE TIME FOR MASSACRES, RAIDS, AND ABUSES AGAINST THE HONDURAN PEOPLE ARE THE SAME ONES WHO ARE IN THE HIERARCHY OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY.

WE BELIEVE HONDURANS MUST THINK ABOUT THIS SITUATION, BECAUSE THIS LEVEL OF CONFRONTATION WITH INFANTRY TROOPS AND AIRCRAFT WILL SET THE TONE OF THE CONFLICT FOR THE DEFINITION OF THE BORDER CONFLICT OF A GOVERNMENT OF OLIGARCHS WHO HAVE ALWAYS SUPPORTED AN EXPANSIONIST POLICY TOWARD HONDURAS.

ONCE AGAIN, WE CALL ON THE HONDURAN PEOPLE TO STOP THEIR ARMY'S INVOLVEMENT IN SOMEONE ELSE'S WAR [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN EL SALVADOR, ITS MAIN ENEMY.

WE CALL ON THE NATIONAL AND INTERNAL PRESS, ESPECIALLY HONDURAN MEDIA, TO VISIT LOS LLANITOS, SANTA LUCIA, INTIBUCA DEPARTMENT, TO CONFIRM THESE SERIOUS INCIDENTS. WE CALL ON HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS TO HELP THE INJURED CIVILIANS.

[SIGNED] [FMLN] EL SALVADOR, 28 MAY 1989

DEV-MUC3-0219 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 28 MAY 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATEMENT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] POLITICAL PROPOSAL TO THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY:

THE 1 JUNE SWEARING-IN OF THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA] GOVERNMENT MEANS THE WORSENING AND THE PROLONGATION OF THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR. MEASURES CONDUCIVE TO INCREASING REPRESSION, LEGALIZING DEATH SQUADS POSING AS CIVIL DEFENSE UNITS, GIVING TOTAL IMMUNITY TO DEATH SQUAD MEMBERS IMPLICATED IN MURDERS SUCH AS THAT OF MSGR ARNULFO ROMERO, WORSENING SOCIAL CONFLICT WITH THE DIRECT OR INDIRECT ABOLITION OF FLEDGLING ECONOMIC REFORMS, AND DISMISSING PUBLIC EMPLOYEES EN MASSE CREATE A CLIMATE TOTALLY UNFAVORABLE TO TALKS BETWEEN THE SIDES.

IN THE LIGHT OF THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE SITUATION, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] ONCE AGAIN MAKES A NEW EFFORT AND PROPOSES A PRACTICAL WAY TO OPEN UP THE POSSIBILITY OF TALKS AND UNDERSTANDING THAT MAY LEAD TO A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION AND LASTING PEACE IN EL SALVADOR:

1. RESUMPTION OF TALKS WITH POLITICAL PARTIES. THE FMLN FEELS POLITICAL PARTIES NOT PARTICIPATING IN THE ARENA GOVERNMENT MAY PLAY THE ROLE OF SPONSORS AND NEGOTIATORS OF THE DIALOGUE UNTIL DIRECT NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN IS ACHIEVED. DURING THE OAXTEPEC MEETING, THE POLITICAL PARTIES ESTABLISHED THE NEED TO CONTINUE THE TALKS PAST 19 MARCH. THE FMLN DEEMS IT APPROPRIATE NOW TO REAFFIRM THIS NEED AND TO BEGIN TALKS AT A MUTUALLY AGREED ON PLACE AND DATE. DURING THESE MEETINGS BETWEEN THE OPPOSITION PARTIES THE FMLN, WE WOULD PROPOSE THE FOLLOWING PLATFORM OF COMMITMENTS WE FEEL THE FMLN AND THE NEW GOVERNMENT MUST ACCEPT AS MEASURES CONDUCIVE TOWARD CREATING THE CONDITIONS FOR A DIALOGUE AND DIRECT NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE SIDES:

2. POLITICAL COMMITMENTS OF THE FMLN:

A. TO ABSTAIN FROM ANY FORM OF ATTACK AGAINST POLITICAL LEADERS OF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT.

B. TO SUSPEND NATIONWIDE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGES AND THUS SUSPEND SABOTAGE OF PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION.

C. TO RESPECT THE LIVES, FREEDOM, AND WELL-BEING OF RELATIVES OF POLITICAL LEADERS AND OFFICERS IN THE GOVERNMENT AND IN THE ARMED FORCES AND TO RESPECT THEIR RESIDENCES.

D. TO CONTINUE TO REFRAIN FROM USING ARTILLERY-EQUIPPED PLATFORMS, KNOW AS CAR BOMBS.

E. TO RESPECT U.S. PERSONNEL AND INFRASTRUCTURE IN EL SALVADOR.

F. TO SUSPEND SABOTAGE OF URBAN POWER POLES AND SHOPPING CENTERS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0225 (ADS)

BOGOTA, 30 MAY 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] GENERAL MIGUEL ALFREDO MAZA MARQUEZ, DIRECTOR OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY OF COLOMBIA (DAS, SECRET POLICE), BLAMED "NARCOMILITARY" ORGANIZATIONS FOR A CAR-BOMB ATTACK FROM WHICH HE ESCAPED UNHARMED TODAY.

MAZA STATED THIS WHEN HE READ AN OPEN LETTER HE ADDRESSED TO THE NATION'S ATTORNEY GENERAL (TOP PROSECUTOR) ALFONSO GOMEZ MENDEZ A FEW HOURS AFTER THE ATTACK. IN THAT LETTER, MAZA STATES HE HAS ATTACHED "OVERWHELMING PROOF" ABOUT THE IDENTITY OF THE ATTACKERS.

IN THE TERRORIST ACTION, WHICH TOOK PLACE IN A DOWNTOWN BOGOTA STREET AT 1210 GMT, FOUR PEDESTRIANS WERE KILLED AND SEVERAL OTHERS INJURED.

GEN MAZA POINTED OUT THAT ON 25 MAY, THE NATIONAL POLICE ARRESTED ARMY CAPTAIN LUIS JAVIER WULMEN CAMARGO, RETIRED, AND CIVILIAN JOSE JAVIER RIVERA AND FOUND DOCUMENTS LINKING RIGHT-WING PARAMILITARY GROUPS WITH TODAY'S ATTACK AND OTHER POLITICAL CRIMES.

MAZA ADDED THAT THE DEPUTY NATIONAL POLICE DIRECTOR INFORMED HIM YESTERDAY THAT ONE OF THOSE DOCUMENTS FOUND ON THE RETIRED CAPTAIN IS THE "PLAN" [LIBRETO] OF THE ATTACK THAT WAS CARRIED OUT AGAINST HIM TODAY.

THAT DOCUMENT IS TITLED "CONFIDENTIAL REPORT FOR MR DE LAS FLORES." THE GENERAL ASKED THE ATTORNEY GENERAL TO CONDUCT A FULL INVESTIGATION OF THE ARRESTED MEN AND THE DOCUMENTS FOUND ON THEM; HE URGED THE ATTORNEY GENERAL TO GUARENTEE THE SAFETY OF THE TWO ARRESTED MEN, BECAUSE "THE PLAN FAILED AND ATTEMPTS AGAINST THEIR LIVES CANNOT BE RULED OUT."

IN HIS LETTER TO THE ATTORNEY GENERAL, MAZA STATES THAT THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS ARE FINANCED BY THE "MEDELLIN CARTEL" DRUG- TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATION AND GROUPS MOVED BY POLITICAL INTERESTS THAT FREQUENTLY RESORT TO "BRIBING" AND "CORRUPTING OFFICIALS."

THE MILITARY MAN EXPRESSED HIS CONFIDENCE TO THE ATTORNEY GENERAL THAT THE TWO ARRESTED MEN AND THE MATERIAL FOUND ON THEM WILL HELP DETERMINE THE IDENTITY OF THE PLANNERS AND PERPETRATORS -- NOT ONLY OF THIS ATTACK, BUT OF MANY POLITICAL CRIMES.

HE ADDED THAT THE INCIDENT CALLS FOR THE ATTORNEY GENERAL HIMSELF TO CARRY OUT THE INVESTIGATION AND; THUS, HE PREFERS THAT DAS AND OTHER ORGANIZATIONS ABSTAIN FROM PARTICIPATING.

"I WANT JUSTICE TO BE SERVED; I WANT THE TRUTH," MAZA TOLD THE REPORTERS AFTER READING THE LETTER.

DEV-MUC3-0226 (ADS)

ROSARIO, 30 MAY 89 (DYN) -- [TEXT] MAYOR SANTOS MAURO, A MEMBER OF THE JUSTICIALIST PARTY, HAS SENT AN ALARMING REPORT WHICH STATES THAT THE ADJACENT CITY OF VILLA GOBERNADOR HAS BEEN VIRTUALLY RAIDED BY LOOTERS. VILLA GOBERNADOR HAS ABOUT 100,000 INHABITANTS AND IS THE THIRD MOST IMPORTANT CITY IN SANTA FE PROVINCE.

MAURO WENT TONIGHT TO ROSARIO TO ASK FOR MILITARY REINFORCEMENTS IN VIEW OF THE ALARMING WAVE OF LOOTING BEING PERPETRATED, EVEN AGAINST PRIVATE HOUSES. HE WAS TOLD THAT SOME 200 POLICEMEN WILL BE SENT TO VILLA GOBERNADOR.

MAUTO TOLD THE LOCAL JOURNALISTS THAT "LOOTERS HAVE STOLEN ALMOST EVERYTHING FROM THE SUPERMARKETS, STORES, AND SHOESHOPS."

THE LOOTING BEGAN EARLY THIS MORNING IN ALL TYPE OF STORES. ACCORDING TO THE MAYOR IT IS STILL GOING ON, AND THE PRIVATE HOUSES WHICH WERE RAIDED EARLY TONIGHT "WERE CRUELLY AND TREACHEROUSLY DAMAGED."

A HOUSE THAT HAS BEEN COMPLETELY DISMANTLED SHOWED THAT THE LOOTERS ALSO USED VIOLENCE. PROOF OF THIS WAS A LUXURIOUS PIANO THAT WAS COMPLETELY DESTROYED BY THE LOOTERS BECAUSE THEY WERE UNABLE TO TAKE IT AWAY.

CLASHES AND SHOOTOUTS HAVE TAKEN PLACE SINCE THIS MORNING NEAR THE PALADINI, SUGAROSA AND LA TROPA DE GALVEZ FROZEN MEAT PACKING PLANTS BETWEEN THE POLICE AND PEOPLE WHO WANT TO STEAL SIDES OF BEEF.

THE INCIDENTS STILL CONTINUE AT THOSE PLANTS, BUT THE PEOPLE HAVE NOT YET OVERPOWERED THE POLICEMEN.

MEANWHILE, BLACKOUTS CAUSED BY SABOTAGE HAVE OCCURRED IN SEVERAL TOWNSHIPS OF GREATER ROSARIO WHERE UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE STOLE 100,000 LITERS OF PROCESSED MILK FROM A WAREHOUSE OWNED BY LA SERENISIMA FIRM LOCATED ON THE CORNER OF SANTA FE AND PARANA STREETS.

THE INTERIOR MINISTRY OF THE SANTA FE PROVINCE HAS ISSUED ITS 9TH COMMUNIQUE REPORTING THAT A STATE OF EMERGENCY HAS BEEN DECREED IN ALL CITIES AND TOWNSHIPS OF THE ROSARIO DEPARTMENT, WHOSE MAIN URBAN CENTERS ARE SAN LORENZO, VILLA GOBERNADOR, AND CAPITAN BERMUDEZ.

DEV-MUC3-0227 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 MAY 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] ON THIS 1ST DAY OF THE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE CALLED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN], EVERYTHING IS NORMAL IN SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT. TRAFFIC IS 95 PERCENT NORMAL IN THE DEPARTMENTAL CAPITAL AND IN OTHER TOWNS, ALTHOUGH BUS SERVICE HAS LESSENED VISIBLY.

THE ARMY AND SECURITY CORPS HAVE ESTABLISHED AROUND-THE-CLOCK VIGILANCE ON ALL THE PRIMARY AND SECONDARY HIGHWAYS TO COUNTERACT ANY ACTION AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND PRIVATE PROPERTY.

MEANWHILE, BUS DEPOTS ARE DESERTED AND MANY PEOPLE ARE AWAITING SOME MEANS OF TRANSPORTATION TO GO TO WORK, ALTHOUGH TOMORROW, 1 JUNE, ALL GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES WILL HAVE THE DAY OFF ON THE OCCASION OF THE PRESIDENTIAL INAUGURATION.

AT DAWN TODAY, STRONG EXPLOSIONS WERE HEARD IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE DEPARTMENTAL CAPITAL, AND, AS OF 0400, INTENSE SHOOTING WAS HEARD IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF THE DEPARTMENT. AIR FORCE PLANES HAVE OVERFLOWN THE AREA IN AN EFFORT TO DETERMINE FMLN REBEL POSITIONS. AT 0500, SHOOTING COULD STILL BE HEARD.

IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT 5TH BRIGADE TROOPS CLASHED WITH FMLN COLUMNS NEAR [WORD INDISTINCT] IN JIBOA, AND THAT HELICOPTER GUNSHIPS AND AIRPLANES LENT AIR SUPPORT TO THE GROUND FORCES. REGARDING THE EXPLOSIONS, OUR SOURCE DID NOT DISCLOSE WHERE THEY TOOK PLACE. IT IS BELIEVED THAT POWER POSTS WERE SABOTAGED BECAUSE THERE WERE BRIEF BLACKOUTS AT APPROXIMATELY 0330 TODAY. SAN VICENTE NOW HAS ELECTRICITY AND POTABLE WATER.

ANOTHER REPORT INDICATES THAT EARLY THIS MORNING, FLARES WERE USED TO DETERMINE REBEL POSITIONS IN THE AFOREMENTIONED AREAS. JIBOA SUGAR MILL EMPLOYEES SAID THAT THE FMLN HARASSED ARTILLERY COMMAND POSITIONS NEAR THE SUGAR MILL.

REPORTS INDICATE THAT AT 0320, HARASSMENT BEGAN IN THE WESTERN, EASTERN, AND NORTHERN PARTS OF THE DEPARTMENT, AND THAT THE REBELS HAD SUFFERED CASUALTIES DURING CLASHES THIS MORNING NEAR THE JIBOA SUGAR MILL. THE REPORTS POINT OUT THAT NO VICTIMS OR DAMAGE HAVE BEEN REPORTED AT THE MILL.

DEV-MUC3-0229 (ADS)

BOGOTA, 31 MAY 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [ALVARO AYALA] [TEXT] TERRORISM SEEMS NOT TO HAVE LET UP THROUGHOUT COLOMBIA. BOGOTA, CALI, AND MEDELLIN HAVE BEEN THE TARGETS OF DYNAMITE ATTACKS. LAST NIGHT, WHILE THE COUNTRY WAS STILL IN SHOCK OVER THE ATTACK AGAINST DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] DIRECTOR GENERAL MIGUEL ALFREDO MAZA MARQUEZ, A SHOPPING MALL IN MEDELLIN WAS SHAKEN BY THE EXPLOSION OF AN AVERAGE - SIZED BOMB AT THE CICLOTECNICA STORE ON 33D AND 42D STREETS. ORLANDO GOMEZ, A STREET VENDOR WALKING THROUGH THE AREA, WAS KILLED. TWO MORE PEOPLE WERE SERIOUSLY WOUNDED. ONE OF THE VICTIMS HAS NOT YET BEEN IDENTIFIED. MEANWHILE, THE OTHER VICTIM, GIOVANNI MADRIGAL, IS RECOVERING IN A MEDELLIN HOSPITAL.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS BY MEDELLIN METROPOLITAN POLICE EXPERTS, THE BOMB WAS LEFT BY UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS AT THE ELITE BAR'S PARKING LOT. SEVERAL VEHICLES WERE DAMAGED BY THE EXPLOSION, WHICH RESULTED IN HEAVY FINANCIAL LOSSES. LAST WEEK, ANOTHER MEDELLIN SHOPPING MALL WAS ALSO ATTACKED BY TERRORISTS.

DEV-MUC3-0230 (ADS)

LA PAZ, 26 MAY 89 (PRESENCIA) -- [EXCERPTS] INTERIOR MINISTER EDUARDO PEREZ BELTRAN HAS BLAMED THE MURDER OF TWO U.S. MORMON MISSIONARIES ON NARCOTERRORISTS, WHO WANT TO GIVE IT A POLITICAL CONNOTATION. "DRUG TRAFFICKERS MIGHT BE INVOLVED IN THIS CRIME, AND THEY WANT TO GIVE IT POLITICAL CONNOTATIONS," PEREZ SAID.

PEREZ SAID THAT THE MRUDER OF THE TWO MISSIONARIES MIGHT BE A "COPYCAT MURDER" DONE WITH THE INTENTION OF BLAMING THE "ZARATE WILKA GROUP WITH HAVING DONE IT." HE ADDED THAT THE GROUP IS NAMED AFTER A PEASANT LEADER WHO LIVED EARLY THIS CENTURY. THE PEASANT HAD NO POLITICAL AFFILIATION WHATSOEVER. THIS IS WHY WE CAN NOT SAY WITH ABSOLUTE CERTAINTY THAT GUERRILLA GROUPS ARE OPERATING IN THE COUNTRY.

THE FAL-ZARATE WILKA GROUP, WHICH CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS CRIME, LEFT A HANDWRITTEN MESSAGE TO THE EFFECT THAT THEIR WAR IS TO KILL "THE YANKEE INVADERS WHO COME HERE TO MASSACRE OUR PEASANT BROTHERS."

REFERRING TO THE MESSAGE LEFT AT THE SCENE, THE INTERIOR MINISTER SAID THAT AN INITIAL ANALYSIS OF THE MESSAGE REVEALS THAT IT WAS WRITTEN IN LANGUAGUE NOT COMMONLY USED BY A LEFTIST POLITICAL ORGANIZATION. THE MESSAGE IS VAGUE WHEN IT REFERS TO BOTH NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY AND THE EXPLOITATION OF PEASANTS. THIS IS A CRIME IN WHICH DRUG TRAFFICKERS MIGHT BE INVOLVED AND TO WHICH THEY WANT TO ATTACH A POLITICAL CONNOTATION," PEREZ SAID.

PEREZ ADDED THAT IN RECENT DAYS "THERE HAVE BEEN RUMORS THAT MEMBERS OF THE U.S. ARMED FORCES HAVE COME TO BOLIVIA WITH PLANS TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING. WE HAVE TO REJECT THOSE RUMORS."

HE SAID THAT THIS CRIME IS IN NO WAY LINKED TO THE PRESENCE OF "SHINING PATH" TERRORISTS IN BOLIVIA. HE SAID: "IF THIS TERRORIST GROUP IS OPERATING IN BOLIVIA, IT SHOULD HAVE CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS CRIME, LIKE THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY (ELN) DID IN THE 1960'S WHEN THEY REVEALED THAT THEY CARRIED OUT TERRORIST ACTIVITIES ABROAD."

PEREZ STATED THAT MURDER OF THE U.S. MORMON MISSIONARIES SHOULD BE SERIUSLY ANALYZED SO THAT A RELIABLE REPORT IS RELEASED.

DEV-MUC3-0231 (ADS)

LA PAZ, 2 JUN 89 (LA RED PANAMERICANA) -- [TEXT] GENERAL MARIO MOLINA, CHIEF OF THE BOLIVIAN POLICE, HAS ADMITTED THAT THE COUNTRY IS SUFFERING THE EFFECTS OF PSYCHOLOGICAL TERRORISM PRACTICED BY EXTREMIST GROUPS WHICH HAVE NOT YET BEEN OFFICIALLY IDENTIFIED. THE POLICE CHIEF REQUESTED THE COOPERATION OF THE CITIZENRY BY REPORTING ANY INFORMATION ON EXTREMISTS. HE GUARANTEED THAT ANYONE REPORTING ON EXTREMISTS WILL REMAIN ANONYMOUS.

GEN MOLINA SAID THAT THE POLICE CONTINUE TO INVESTIGATE THE MURDER OF TWO AMERICAN CITIZENS WITH THE AID OF U.S. EXPERTS WHO ARE GIVING BOLIVIA POLICE LOGISTIC AND SCIENTIFIC SUPPORT. THEIR SUPPORT, HE SAID, ALLOWS THE BOLIVIA POLICE THEIR OWN LIMITATIONS.

THE POLICE CHIEF SAID THAT THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] OBJECTS FOUND IN THE SCENE OF THE MURDER HAVE BEEN SENT TO WASHINGTON FOR BALLISTIC AND LABORATORY EXAMINATIONS. MEANWHILE, THE POLICE ARE PREPARING THE IDENTI-KIT OF THE ALLEGED MURDERERS BASED ON THE DESCRIPTION OF WITNESSES. THE POLICE HAVE SO FAR OBTAINED 150 UNSWORN DECLARATIONS, 50 WRITTEN DECLARATIONS, WHILE THE PERSONAL [WORD INDISTINCT] CONTINUE. [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]

DEV-MUC3-0232 (ADS)

SAN JOSE (COSTA RICA), 2 JUN 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] GENERAL COMMAND HAS AGREED TO "CONTINUE" THE DIALOGUE WITH THE NEW SALAVADORAN GOVERNMENT, WHICH WAS SWORN IN YESTERDAY. THE FMLN ALSO PROPOSES CHANNELS TO FOLLOW FOR STARTING THE DIALOGUE.

SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI OF THE RIGHT-WING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) YESTERDAY PROPOSED TO THE GUERRILLAS THAT THEY BEGIN A DIALOGUE TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION THAT WILL END THE ARMED CONFLICT IN THAT NATION.

A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION "CAN LEAD TO PEACE IN EL SALVADOR," THE FMLN ASSERTED IN A COMMUNIQUE ISSUED TODAY IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, AND SIGNED BY COMMANDERS FRANCISCO JOVEL, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, EDUARDO SANCHO, AND JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS.

THE FMLN PROPOSES "COORDINATING A CEASE-FIRE WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF AN OVERALL NEGOTIATION OF THE CONFLICT," WITHOUT TRYING TO "APPLY THE SAME MEANS USED IN THE CASE OF THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS."

IN EXCHANGE, THE REBELS DEMAND "THE TRIAL OF FORMER MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON AND ALL THOSE INVOLVED IN MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO'S MURDER," AS WELL AS "THE COMPLETE EXCLUSION" OF D'AUBUISSON FROM ANY GOVERNMENT POSITION. D'AUBUISSON, WHO HAS DENIED ANY INVOLVEMENT IN THE SALVADORAN ARCHBISHOP'S ASSASSINATION, FOUNDED ARENA, WHICH WON THE 19 MARCH PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS.

THE GUERRILLAS DEMAND "THE DISBANDMENT OF THE DEATH SQUADS." THEY ALSO WANT THE GOVERNMENT NOT TO PROCEED WITH THE CREATION OF THE PATRIOTIC CIVIL DEFENSE GROUPS. THE REBELS REQUEST "THE IMMEDIATE RELEASE" OF LABOR LEADERS, MASS MOVEMENT ACTIVISTS, AND DETAINED POLITICAL PRISONERS, AND THEY DEMAND THAT MURDERS, KIDNAPPINGS, AND ALL OTHER FORMS OF REPRESSION AGAINST THE OPPOSITION PARTIES CEASE.

THE COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT THE REBELS ARE WILLING TO AGREE TO A CEASE-FIRE AGREEMENT "WHEN IT IS AGREED UPON AND IMPLEMENTED UNDER INTERNATIONAL SUPERVISION," AS WELL AS TO A MULTILATERAL CUTBACK OF MILITARY SUPPLIES "OF ANY KIND TO ALL THE CENTRAL AMERICAN GOVERNMENTS AND GROUPS INVOLVED IN A CONFLICT."

THE FMLN COMMAND PLEDGES THAT ONCE THE DIALOGUE HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED, IT WILL "REFRAIN FROM ATTACKING POLITICAL LEADERS OF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT" AND FROM ENFORCING NATIONWIDE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGES. THE FMLN OFFERS TO "RESPECT THE LIVES AND LIBERTY" OF POLITICAL AND MILITARY LEADERS' RELATIVES, AS WELL AS TO "SUSPEND" THE USE OF CAR BOMBS IN THE CITIES.

THE GUERRILLAS ALSO COMMIT THEMSELVES TO RESPECTING "U.S. PERSONNEL AND INSTALLATIONS IN EL SALVADOR" AND TO SUSPENDING ATTACKS ON THE ELECTRICAL SYSTEM AND ON URBAN SHOPPING CENTERS.

DURING THE FIRST PHASE OF TALKS, THE GUERRILLAS POINT OUT, THE POLITICAL PARTIES NOT PARTICIPATING IN THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) GOVERNMENT COULD PROMOTE AND ARRANGE THE DIALOGUE UNTIL "A DIRECT NEGOTIATION BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN" IN PLACES AND ON DATES "MUTUALLY AGREED UPON" IS ACHIEVED.

THE INSURGENT LEADERSHIP WARNS THAT IF A DIALOGUE BETWEEN BOTH PARTIES DOES NOT TAKE PLACE, THE INAUGURATION OF THE ARENA GOVERNMENT WILL MEAN "THE HEIGHTENING AND PROLONGATION OF THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR."

THE FMLN COMMUNIQUE ALSO PROPOSES THAT AGRARIAN REFORM BE CONTINUED. THE REBELS ALSO WANT THE NATIONALIZATION OF BANKING AND OF FOREIGN TRADE, UNRESTRICTED FREEDOM OF INFORMATION, AND RESPECT FOR THE COMMITMENT MADE BY THE DUARTE ADMINISTRATION TO "EVACUATE THE WOUNDED AND MAIMED GUERRILLAS" AND TO RESPECT THE LIVES OF RELATIVES OF THE LEADERS OF MASS MOVEMENTS, OPPOSITION PARTIES, AND THE FMLN.

DEV-MUC3-0233 (ADS)

BRASILIA (BRAZIL), 2 JUN 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN GUERRILLAS TODAY RELEASED THREE BRAZILIAN ENGINEERS WHO WERE KIDNAPPED MORE THAN A MONTH AGO IN BOGOTA. ENGINEERS AUGUSTO CARNEIRO MOREIRA JUNIOR, CESAR PAIM DE OLIVEIRA, AND JOSE ROBERTO REIS WERE RELEASED TODAY BY THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY GUERRILLAS OF COLOMBIA. THE OFFICIAL ANNOUNCEMENT WAS MADE BY ACTING FOREIGN MINISTER PAULO TARSO FLECHA DE LIMA AFTER RECEIVING A PHONE CALL FROM THE BRAZILIAN AMBASSADOR TO COLOMBIA, ALVARO FRANCO, AND DETAILS OF THE OUTCOME OF THIS CASE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [FLECHA DE LIMA] I DO NOT HAVE DETAILS ON HOW THIS HAPPENED. THOSE DETAILS MUST BE EVALUATED. [END RECORDING]

BERMEJA. FROM THERE THEY WERE TAKEN TO BOGOTA, CAPITAL OF COLOMBIA, WHERE THEY BOARDED A PLANE THAT WILL FLY TO RIO DE JANEIRO AFTER A STOPOVER IN MANAUS.

PETROBRAS HAS RELEASED AN OFFICIAL NOTE SAYING THAT TWO OF THREE ENGINEERS WHO WERE KIDNAPPED IN COLOMBIA AND RELEASED TODAY WILL ARRIVE IN RIO DE JANEIRO EARLY TOMORROW MORNING. ENGINEERS AUGUSTO CARNEIRO MOREIRA JUNIOR AND JOSE ROBERTO REIS WERE SET FREE TODAY IN THE TOWN OF BARRANCA BERMEJA, WITH THE RECOMMENDATION THAT THEY TAKE A TAXI TO A HOTEL IN BUCARAMANGA WHERE THE KIDNAPPERS HAD MET WITH THE TEAM OF NEGOTIATORS -- PETROBRAS REPRESENTATIVE RAIMUNDO DE OLIVEIRA, RIO DE JANEIRO OIL WORKERS UNION REPRESENTATIVE [NAME INDISTINCT], AND REPRESENTATIVES OF CUT.

ACCORDING TO ITAMARATY, THE NEGOTIATORS ACTED IN A IRREPROACHABLE MANNER. ENGINEER PAULO CESAR PAIM DE OLIVEIRA REMAINED IN COLOMBIA WITH HIS RELATIVES. THIS INFORMATION WAS MADE PUBLIC TONIGHT BY PETROBRAS. ITAMARATY ALSO REPORTED THAT THE HOSTAGES WERE RELEASED WITHOUT PAYING RANSOM, SINCE THE COLOMBIAN GUERRILLAS WERE SEEKING ONLY PUBLICITY FOR THEIR MOVEMENT.

DEV-MUC3-0235 (ADS)

LIMA, 4 JUN 89 (EFE) -- [EXCERPTS] IT WAS REPORTED HERE TODAY THAT OVER 5,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN ARRESTED IN SEVERAL SECTORS OF LIMA BY POLICE AND MILITARY PATROLS FOLLOWING THE TERRORIST ATTACK ON 3 JUNE IN WHICH 7 MEMBERS OF THE SECURITY FORCES WERE KILLED.

NEWS MEDIA REPORTED TODAY THAT DURING COMBINED OPERATIONS IN DOWNTOWN LIMA AND ITS OUTSKIRTS, ABOUT 300 VEHICLES WERE DETAINED ON THE ROADS LINKING LIMA WITH THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY.

THE POLICE AND MILITARY DETAINED ABOUT 5,300 PEOPLE SUSPECTED OF HAVING PARTICIPATED IN THE BOMBING OF THE BUS THAT CARRIED 24 SOLDIERS OF THE PRESIDENTIAL ESCORT REGIMENT. THE ATTACK ON THE PRESIDENTIAL ESCORT REGIMENT, WHICH IS KNOWN AS "HUSARES DE JUNIN," TOOK PLACE SOME 10 BLOCKS FROM THE GOVERNMENT PALACE.

NO GUERRILLA GROUP HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK. PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA SAID, HOWEVER, THAT ACCORDING TO SOME POLICEMEN, THE TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT [MRTA] COULD BE INVOLVED IN THE ATTACK, ALTHOUGH SHINING PATH INVOLVEMENT IS NOT RULED OUT.

DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE, GARCIA SAID THAT THE TERRORISTS COULD HAVE PERPETRATED THIS ATTACK IN RETALIATION FOR THE DEATH OF 60 MRTA GUERRILLAS IN A CLASH WITH ARMY FORCES IN JAUJA, IN THE PERUVIAN CENTRAL MOUNTAIN RANGE, IN APRIL.

THE MURDER OF THE 6 SOLDIERS AND 1 POLICEMAN RAISED TO 36 THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE KILLED BY TERRORISTS DURING THE FIRST 3 DAYS OF JUNE. THAT IS AN AVERAGE OF 12 DEATHS EACH DAY.

DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL JULIO VELASQUEZ GIACARINI TODAY TOLD THE PRESS THAT HE GREATLY LAMENTED THIS INCIDENT AND THAT PRIME MINISTER LUIS ALBERTO SANCHEZ, IN HIS SPEECH AT CONGRESS ON 6 JUNE, WILL RELEASE THE GUIDELINES OF THE ANTISUBVERSIVE POLICY FORMULATED BY THE GOVERNMENT IN RESPONSE TO INCREASING TERRORIST ACTIVITIES.

DEV-MUC3-0242 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 JUN 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [EXCERPTS] THE RULING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) IN EL SALVADOR TODAY CONDEMNED THE MURDER OF PRESIDENCY MINISTER ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH AND TWO OF HIS BODYGUARDS PERPETRATED BY PRESUMED GUERRILLAS.

THE MINISTER AND HIS TWO BODYGUARDS DIED WHEN RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S RESIDENCE IN SAN SALVADOR WAS MACHINEGUNNED.

ARENA DEPUTIES DID NOT DISMISS THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE RULING PARTY MAY WITHDRAW PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S DIALOGUE OFFER TO THE GUERRILLAS IF IT IS CONFIRMED THAT THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) CARRIED OUT THE ATTACK.

HOWEVER, ARENA LEADERS WHO ARRIVED AT RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S RESIDENCE DISMISSED THE POSSIBILITY THAT "OTHER GROUPS INTERESTED IN THE CONTINUATION OF VIOLENCE" COULD HAVE PERPETRATED THE ATTACK. THE DEPUTIES DID NOT IDENTIFY THESE GROUPS.

THUS FAR, NEITHER THE GUERRILLAS NOR ANY OTHER ORGANIZATION HAVE CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER OF THE MINISTER, WHO WAS ONE OF THE MOST PROMIMENT MEMBERS OF CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT, AS WELL AS OF SALVADORAN PRIVATE ENTERPRISE.

THE SALVADORAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE ALSO CONDEMNED THE MURDER OF MINISTER RODRIGUEZ PORTH, WHO WAS A FORMER DIRECTOR OF THAT BUSINESS ORGANIZATION, AND RECALLED HIS LINKS WITH SALVADORAN PRIVATE ENTERPRISE.

PRESIDENT CRISTIANI IS CURRENTLY HOLDING A SPECIAL GOVERNMENT MEETING TO ASSESS THE SITUATION FOLLOWING THE MINISTER'S DEATH. AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE IS EXPECTED IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

DEV-MUC3-0243 (ADS)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 JUN 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH DR EDUARDO COLINDRES, LEADER OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY, BY NELSON LOPEZ] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [COLINDRES] THE PDC [CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY] CONDEMNS THE ASSASSINATION OF PRESIDENCY MINISTER DR ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH. IT BELIEVES VIOLENCE WILL NOT SOLVE THE COUNTRY'S PROBLEMS, IS NOT THE WAY TO SETTLE IDEOLOGICAL DIFFERENCES, AND WILL NOT LEAD TO PEACE AND DEVELOPMENT.

WE HOPE THIS CONDEMNABLE ACT WILL NOT BE FOLLOWED BY AN ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE AND REVENGE THAT WOULD ONLY SERVE TO FURTHER POLARIZE SALVADORAN SOCIETY. THE PDC EXPRESSES ITS CONDOLENCES TO THE REPUBLIC'S GOVERNMENT, THAT IS, THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE, AND RODRIGUEZ' GRIEVING FAMILY. WE URGE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, BASED ON MUTUAL RESPECT, TO FIND A POLITICAL AND PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS THAT IS CURRENTLY AFFLICTING OUR SOCIETY. THIS IS THE PDC'S POSITION ON THE CONDEMNABLE ASSASSINATION OF DR ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH.

[LOPEZ] DR COLINDRES, DO YOU NOT BELIEVE THIS COULD LEAD TO AN ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE BY THE EXTREME RIGHT?

[COLINDRES] WE HOPE REASON WILL PREVAIL IN THE COUNTRY. WE BELIEVE THIS OR ANY OTHER INCIDENT SHOULD NOT LEAD TO AN ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE, BECAUSE THAT WOULD ONLY RESULT IN MORE BLOODLETTING AMONG THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. I BELIEVE WE MUST NOT FALL FOR THE TRAP OF VIOLENCE THAT WOULD ONLY DESTROY US.

[LOPEZ] IT IS PRESUMED THAT THIS ACTION INVOLVED LEFTIST URBAN COMMANDOS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. DO YOU BELIEVE THAT POLITICAL GROUP IS RESPONSIBLE?

[COLINDRES] LET US WAIT AND SEE WHAT WILL HAPPEN, BECAUSE IT COULD HAVE BEEN THE FMLN OR ULTRARIGHTIST FACTIONS SEEKING FURTHER POLARIZATION AND BLOODLETTING. WE DO NOT WANT TO PASS JUDGMENT YET. REGARDLESS OF WHO DID IT, THIS IS AN ASSASSINATION, WHICH IS NOT THE PROPER WAY TO SOLVE PROBLEMS AMONG SALVADORANS.

[LOPEZ] IN THE PDC'S OPINION, WHAT SHOULD BE THE ROLE OF THE ARMED FORCES IN THE WAKE OF DR RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S ASSASSINATION?

[COLINDRES] I BELIEVE THE ARMED FORCES MUST CONTINUE THEIR POLICY OF PROFESSIONALISM AND RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, BECAUSE THIS IMPLIES RESPECTING THE LAW AND STRENGTHENING THE INSTITUTION OF THE ARMED FORCES. THEY HAVE THE CONSTITUTIONAL DUTY TO GUARANTEE THE SAFETY AND CALM OF THE ENTIRE POPULATION.

[LOPEZ] WOULD YOU LIKE TO ADD ANYTHING?

[COLINDRES] ONLY THAT WE HOPE THIS KIND OF REGRETTABLE AND CONDEMNABLE INCIDENT WILL NOT BE REPEATED. WE ALSO HOPE THAT VIOLENCE AND DESTRUCTION AMONG SALVADORAN BROTHERS WILL END ONCE AND FOR ALL. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0244 (ADS)

SAN PEDRO SULA, 9 JUN 89 (TIEMPO) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] WHEN WE ASKED THE FOREIGN MINISTRY WHY THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT HAS NOT PROTESTED THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ATTACKS ON HONDURAN ARMY SOLDIERS AND A HELICOPTER IN LOS LLANITOS (INTIBUCA), THE ANSWER WAS VERY SIMPLE, BUT IT SHOWS THE IMPORTANCE THAT IS GIVEN TO NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY AND INTEGRITY: THE ARMED FORCES HAVE NOT INFORMED US OF ANYTHING AT ALL -- THEY SAID -- AND WHAT THE MEDIA SAYS IS NOT ACCURATE.

THE NEWSPAPERS TIEMPO AND LA PRENSA PUBLISHED REPORTS OF THE INCIDENT WITH PHOTOGRAPHS THAT CONFIRMED THE AGGRESSION, THE BOMBING AND SHELLING OF VILLAGES IN OUR TERRITORY, AND PROVIDED ACCOUNTS BY EYEWITNESSES AND MUNICIPAL AUTHORITIES, BUT WHICH, ACCORDING TO THE FOREIGN MINISTRY, LACK CREDIBILITY OR IMPORTANCE.

LATER FOREIGN NEWSMEN WENT TO THESE PLACES AND CONFIRMED WHAT TIEMPO AND LA PRENSA HAD REPORTED. THEY ALSO OBTAINED OTHER DETAILS ON THE INCIDENTS. WHILE THE HONDURAN AND SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES DENIED THE INCIDENT, DESPITE THE EVIDENCE, THE TRUTH IS THERE FOR THE GENTLEMEN OF THE FOREIGN MINISTRY TO SEE.

ACCORDING TO STATEMENTS BY THE VILLAGERS WHO WERE THE VICTIMS OF THE SALVADORAN AGGRESSION, THE HONDURAN MILITARY THREATENED THEM AND ORDERED THEM TO BE SILENT OR TO LIE ABOUT WHAT HAD HAPPENED. IT WAS NECESSARY FOR THE SANTA LUCIA MAYOR TO INTERVENE BEFORE THEY COULD TELL NEWSMEN WHAT HAD HAPPENED. A REPORTER FOR LA PRENSA WAS SIDETRACKED BY A COMMANDER, NO DOUBT TO KEEP HIM FROM DOING HIS JOB AS A JOURNALIST.

THE HONDURAN ARMY'S WEAPONS SERVED TO KEEP THE AGGRESSION QUIET INSTEAD OF REPELLING IT, TO THREATEN HONDURAN BORDER VILLAGERS INSTEAD OF PROTECTING THEM, WHILE THE ARMY TURNED ITS BACK ON THE ENEMY ARMED FORCES -- WHICH HAVE TRAMPLED ON OUR TERRITORY AND HUMILIATED US -- INSTEAD OF FIGHTING THEM. IN SHORT, THE WEAPONS THAT WE HONDURANS AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE OBTAINED WITH SO MUCH SACRIFICE, EVEN AT THE EXPENSE OF GOING WITHOUT FOOD AND MEDICINE, ARE USED AGAINST HONDURAS AND ITS PEOPLE.

THIS SITUATION SHOULD CAUSE US TO GIVE MUCH THOUGHT TO THE EXISTENCE OF THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES. WE ANTICIPATED THIS WHEN THE REGIONAL MILITARY TRAINING AND SECURITY CENTER (CREMS) WAS CREATED EXCLUSIVELY TO TRAIN 10,000 SALVADORAN TROOPS -- THE SAME ARMY THAT INVADED US IN 1969 AND THAT IS ATTACKING US AGAIN.

WE WONDER IF WE ARE NOT ACQUIRING A MERCENARY MENTALITY IN HONDURAS, WHEREBY THE STATE'S WEAPONS GO TO THE HIGHEST BIDDER RATHER THAN BEING USED IN THE NATIONAL INTEREST. FOR THE PAST 7 YEARS THEY HAVE BEEN USED FOR ECONOMIC -- THOUGH IDEOLOGICALLY DISGUISED -- BENEFITS.

NO NATIONAL MILITARY FORCE CAN FUNCTION LIKE THIS ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD. IN ANY EVENT, THE IDEOLOGY OF ANY ARMY SHOULD BE NATIONALISTIC, EVEN IN THE CASE OF POWERS AND SUPERPOWERS THAT INVENT AND USE INTERNATIONALIST IDEOLOGIES FOR THEIR HEGEMONIC STRUGGLES.

HERE IN HONDURAS THE CASE OF THE ARMED FORCES IS JUST THE OPPOSITE. TO THE MILITARY INSTITUTE'S WAY OF THINKING, THOSE WHO ARE DEMANDING THE DEFENSE OF SOVEREIGNTY AND TERRITORIAL INTEGRITY ARE SUBVERSIVES WHO ARE ALLIED WITH SUBVERSIVES FROM OTHER COUNTRIES. AN AGGRESSION AGAINST HONDURAS BY A FOREIGN ARMY IS LEGITIMIZED BY THE PEOPLE ATTACKED AND THOSE WHO INFORM AND PROTEST ARE ENEMIES OF THE FATHERLAND.

THIS WAS STATED IN AN EDITORIAL OF THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES' "MILITARY PROJECTIONS" PROGRAM. THE EDITORIAL SAID THAT THE REPORT WAS ISSUED "WITHOUT PRIOR INVESTIGATION" AND WAS BASED SOLELY "ON INFORMATION PROVIDED BY THESE GROUPS TO CONFUSE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION."

"THE IRRESPONSIBILITY OF SOME PRINT AND BROADCAST MEDIA DIRECTORS HAS REACHED THE POINT THAT THEY ARE PROMOTING THESE CLEARLY MARXIST - LENINIST SUBVERSIVES, FINANCED BY CUBA AND NICARAGUA, AND THOSE WHO DO NOT HIDE THEIR OPEN SYMPATHY WITH PSEUDO-PROFESSIONAL POSITIONS. THEY ATTEMPT TO CONCEAL THIS BY CLAIMING THAT RADIO STATIONS OR NEWSPAPERS HAVE UNRESTRICTED FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION."

A SIMILAR EXPLANATION WAS PRESENTED BY THE SALVADORAN EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA IN A PRESS COMMUNIQUE DISTRIBUTED TO THE MEDIA, WHICH PUBLISHED AND DISSEMINATED IT -- ALTHOUGH IT APPEARS INCREDIBLE -- THROUGH THE OFFICIAL PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE BULLETINS. WE MIGHT ADD THAT THE HONDURAN ARMY HAS ECHOED SUCH REPORTS, AS AN ACCOMPLICE TO A PROPAGANDA PLOY TO COVER UP AN AGGRESSION AGAINST OUR COUNTRY.

WE ASK, THEREFORE: "WHAT IS LEFT OF OUR NATIONAL INSTITUTIONS? WHAT IS HONDURAS? WHO ARE HONDURANS?"

DEV-MUC3-0246 (ADS)

PERTH (AUSTRALIA), 11 JUN 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] DEPORTED CHILEAN SECURITY WAS TIGHT AT PERTH INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT AS MR. BUSCHMANN, 46, WAS GIVEN AN ENTHUSIASTIC SEND-OFF BY ABOUT 50 LOCAL SUPPORTERS, MOST OF THEM MEMBERS OF THE WESTERN AUSTRALIAN CHILEAN COMMUNITY.

BEFORE BOARDING HIS AIRCRAFT, MR. BUSCHMANN SAID THROUGH AN INTERPRETER THAT HE HAD ACHIEVED HIS GOAL IN AUSTRALIA BY PUBLICISING THE POSITION OF THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT IN CHILE.

THERE WAS NO IMMEDIATE INDICATION OF MR. BUSCHMANN'S ULTIMATE DESTINATION, WHICH WAS EXPECTED TO BE SOMEWHERE IN EUROPE.

HE HAS REFUGEE STATUS IN SWEDEN, THE COUNTRY FROM WHICH HE MADE HIS VISA APPLICATION BEFORE BEING ALLOWED INTO AUSTRALIA LAST MONTH. THE AUSTRALIAN IMMIGRATION DEPARTMENT ARRANGED HIS SUNDAY NIGHT FLIGHT ON SATURDAY AFTER THE FEDERAL COURT HERE HAD UPHELD A DEPORTATION ORDER AGAINST HIM ON FRIDAY.

MR. BUSCHMANN HAD ORIGINALLY PLANNED TO SPEND TWO MONTHS IN AUSTRALIA PUBLICISING, AND RAISING FUNDS FOR, THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ MOVEMENT, WHICH IS OPPOSED TO THE REGIME OF GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET AND WHICH HE HEADS.

THE IMMIGRATION DEPARTMENT CUT SHORT HIS TRIP, CLAIMING HE HAD MADE FALSE OR MISLEADING STATEMENTS IN HIS VISA APPLICATION.

MR. BUSCHMANN WAS ARRESTED AND DETAINED IN PERTH FOR THREE DAYS BEFORE BEING RELEASED FIVE DAYS AGO ON THE ORDERS OF THE FEDERAL COURT TO BE PLACED UNDER VIRTUAL HOUSE ARREST PENDING THE OUTCOME OF FRIDAY'S HEARING.

HE HAD BEEN STAYING AT THE HOME OF WESTERN AUSTRALIAN STATE LABOR MEMBER OF PARLIAMENT, DR. IAN ALEXANDER.

HE PARTICULARLY UPSET THE AUSTRALIAN AUTHORITIES BY PUBLICLY CALLING FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF GEN. PINOCHET. AFTER HIS ARRIVAL SANTIAGO APPLIED TO CANBERRA FOR HIS EXTRADITION.

DEV-MUC3-0247 (ADS)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 15 JUN 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER MIGUEL D'ESCOTO] [TEXT] MR MINISTER [HONDURAN FOREIGN MINISTER CARLOS LOPEZ CONTRERAS]: VARIOUS HONDURAN PRESS SOURCES HAVE REPORTED ON THE 13 JUNE MEETING BETWEEN THE U.S. VICE PRESIDENT AND LEADERS OF THE MERCENARY GROUPS, AMONG THEM ENRIQUE BERMUDEZ, WHO HAVE BEEN USING HONDURAN TERRITORY AS A BASE AND SANCTUARY FOR ITS CRIMINAL ACTIONS AGAINST NICARAGUA.

THESE MERCENARY GROUPS HAVE CONTINUED THEIR ATTACKS AGAINST NICARAGUA, ADDING NEW VICTIMS TO THE THOUSANDS OF CITIZENS WHO HAVE ALREADY SUFFERED THE EFFECTS OF U.S. AGGRESSION AND THE PARTICIPATION AND COMPLICITY OF YOUR GOVERNMENT WITH THAT ILLEGAL POLICY.

THE WELL-KNOWN U.S. POLICY OF MAINTAINING CONTRA FORCES IN HONDURAN TERRITORY AND ITS CONSTANT CRIMINAL ATTACKS AGAINST THE NICARAGUAN POPULATION -- WHICH HAVE LEFT 163 CIVILIAN VICTIMS SINCE THE COSTA DEL SOL SUMMIT ON 31 MAY -- CHARACTERIZES THE TALKS BETWEEN U.S. GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS AND CONTRA LEADERS, AS WELL AS THE TRAGIC CONSEQUENCES IN THE LOSS OF HUMAN LIVES AND PROPERTY DAMAGE IN MY COUNTRY.

WHILE VICE PRESIDENT QUAYLE WAS MEETING WITH THE MERCENARIES, PASTORAL REPRESENTATIVES IN WASLALA AND LAS MINAS INFORMED THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY OF THE HUNDREDS OF PEASANTS WHO HAVE BEEN MURDERED, KIDNAPPED, AND TORTURED BY THE MERCENARY GROUPS THAT INFILTRATE NICARAGUA FROM HONDURAS.

AT THE SAME TIME, THE DEFENSE MINISTRY REPORTED ON THE CONTINUATION OF ATTACKS AGAINST AGRICULTURAL COOPERATIVES, AMONG THEM ONE IN SAN JOSE, TIJUANA, SOUTHEAST OF ASTURIAS, JINOTEGA DEPARTMENT, WHERE FOUR PEASANTS WERE KILLED ON 10 JUNE.

IN THE COSTA DEL SOL DECLARATION, THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS COMMITTED THEMSELVES TO CARRYING OUT THE DEMOBILIZATION, REPATRIATION, AND RELOCATION OF THE MERCENARY GROUPS CURRENTLY BASED IN YOUR COUNTRY. HOWEVER, YOUR GOVERNMENT HAS SUPPORTED -- AGAINST THE LEGITIMATE INTERESTS OF THE HONDURAN PEOPLE -- THE OPTION SET FORTH BY A U.S. BIPARTISAN AGREEMENT AIMED AT MAINTAINING THE CONTRAS IN HONDURAN TERRITORY.

INTERVIEWS WITH HONDURAN POLITICAL LEADERS, SUCH AS THE ONE PUBLISHED IN THE DAILY LA TRIBUNA IN ITS 13 JUNE EDITION, CLEARLY STATE THAT THE U.S. VICE PRESIDENT DID NOT GO TO HONDURAS TO SOLVE ITS ECONOMIC PROBLEMS, BUT TO OBTAIN A CONFIRMATION FROM THE GOVERNMENT THAT IT WILL NOT EXPEL THE CONTRAS FROM HONDURAN TERRITORY.

IN CONSENTING TO THE CONTINUED PRESENCE IN ITS TERRITORY OF MERCENARY FORCES -- WHICH WERE CREATED TO ATTACK MY COUNTRY -- THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT IS NOT ONLY HELPING TO BRING MORE SUFFERING AND DESTRUCTION TO THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE AND NATION, BUT IS ALSO CONTINUING THE HEAVY BURDEN ON THE HONDURAN PEOPLE, WHO HAVE ALSO BEEN THE VICTIMS OF CRIMINAL AND TERRORIST ACTIONS.

WITH THIS BEHAVIOR, THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT ONCE AGAIN EVINCES ITS TOTAL NONCOMPLIANCE WITH INTERNATIONAL COMMITMENTS, WHICH ARE ALSO EXPRESSED IN THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENTS, TO NOT PERMIT THE USE OF ITS TERRITORY TO ATTACK OTHER STATES AND TO DISCONTINUE ITS SUPPORT FOR IRREGULAR FORCES.

THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT STRONGLY PROTESTS THE FACT THAT YOUR COUNTRY CONTINUES TO ALLOW THE USE OF ITS TERRITORY TO CONDUCT ILLEGAL POLICIES THAT GO AGAINST THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENTS AND THE PEACE EFFORTS AND THAT VIOLATE THE PRINCIPLES AND NORMS ESTABLISHED BY INTERNATIONAL LAW TO GUARANTEE THE PEACEFUL COEXISTENCE OF STATES.

YOUR GOVERNMENT SHOULD REFLECT ON THIS AND HEED THE CALLS MADE BY THE HONDURAN PEOPLE THEMSELVES, WHO DEMAND AN END TO THE COUNTRY'S INVOLVEMENT IN AN ILLEGAL AND ADVENTUROUS POLICY AND THAT THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED IN COSTA DEL SOL CALLING FOR THE IMPLEMENTATION OF A JOINT PLAN FOR THE DEMOBILIZATION, REPATRIATION, AND RELOCATION OF THE IRREGULAR FORCES BASED IN YOUR COUNTRY BE HONORED.

I TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO REITERATE MY ESTEEM TO YOUR EXCELLENCY.

[SIGNED] MIGUEL D'ESCOTO BROCKMAN, FOREIGN MINISTER, REPUBLIC OF NICARAGUA

DEV-MUC3-0248 (ADS)

SAO PAULO (BRAZIL), 14 JUN 89 (FOLHA DE SAO PAULO) -- [TEXT] THE ARGENTINA GOVERNMENT HAS SENT TO BRAZIL A REQUEST OF PREVENTIVE IMPRISONMENT FOR THE EXTRADITION OF 16 PEOPLE (14 ARGENTINES AND 2 FRENCHMEN) CHARGED WITH BELONGING TO THE "ALL FOR THE FATHERLAND" TERRORIST GROUP. THE MEN ARE BELIEVED TO HAVE TAKEN PART IN THE ATTACK ON THE LA TABLADA MILITARY UNIT IN BUENOS AIRES PROVINCE LAST JANUARY.

AT THE ARGENTINE GOVERNMENT'S REQUEST, FERNANDO CARLOS FALCO WAS ARRESTED ON 9 JUNE. HE REMAINS IN CUSTODY IN FEDERAL POLICE QUARTERS IN BRASILIA, AND HE IS WAITING THE EXTRADITION RULING, WHICH WILL BE MADE BY THE FEDERAL SUPREME CORT (STF).

ANOTHER ARGENTINE, DAMIAN MAGUE, WHO WAS ALSO INVOLVED IN THE LA TABLADA ATTACK, WAS ARRESTED WITH FALCO ON THE SAME DAY. MAGUE WAS RELEASED BECAUSE THE ARGENTINE GOVERNMENT DID NOT REQUEST HIS PREVENTIVE IMPRISONMENT, THE STF SAID. IN FALCO'S CASE, THE ARGENTINE COURTS HAVE 45 DAYS TO SEND THE STF A COPY OF THE LEGAL CASE AGAINST HIM. THE TRIAL WILL BE BASED ON THE LEGAL EXTRADITION REQUISITES AND NOT ON THE CRIMINAL ACCUSATIONS AGAINST FALCO.

DEV-MUC3-0249 (ADS)

CLANDESTINE, 15 JUN 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] CONCERNING DR JOSE ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S DEATH, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND REPORTS THE FOLLOWING TO ALL SALVADORANS:

1. AS A RESULT OF INVESTIGATIONS WE HAVE CONDUCTED, WE CONFIRM THAT THE FMLN BEARS NO RESPONSIBILITY WHATSOEVER FOR THE ATTACK ON DR RODRIGUEZ PORTH. WE DELAYED MAKING THIS STATEMENT TO MAKE CERTAIN THAT THERE WERE NO CIRCUMSTANTIAL OR OTHER REASONS THAT COULD HAVE INVOLVED US IN THE ATTACK.

2. FOLLOWING RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S DEATH, SEVERAL GROUPS HAVE CONDUCTED MARKEDLY VENGEFUL ACTIONS. COLONEL OCHOA PEREZ, FOR EXAMPLE, HAS PROPOSED FIGHTING FIRE WITH FIRE. FRANCISCO MERINO HAS THREATENED OPPOSITION LEADERS WITH DEATH. RICARDO ALVARENGA VALDIVIESO HAS PROPOSED REPRESSIVE NEW LAWS.

WE HEREBY WARN THAT IF REPRISALS ARE TAKEN AGAINST THE OPPOSITION MOVEMENT, WE WILL TAKE FIRM AND RESOLUTE ACTION AGAINST ANY ESCALATION IN REPRESSION.

3. WE FIND THE FALSE COMMOTION AMONG THE RANKS OF THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] PARTY REPULSIVE, BECAUSE EVERYONE KNOWS OF THEIR RESPONSIBILITY IN KILLINGS LIKE THAT OF MONSIGNOR ROMERO, OF THE MEMBERS OF THE FDR [REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT] EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE, AND SO MANY OTHERS. WE DO NOT BELIEVE IN THEIR ALLEGED INNOCENCE, AND DO EVEN LESS AT A TIME WHEN REPRESSIVE ACTIONS ARE BEING INTENSIFIED.

4. OUR ATTENTION HAS BEEN DRAWN TO THE FACT THAT THE ATTACK ON RODRIGUEZ PORTH OCCURRED WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF AN INTENSE STRUGGLE BETWEEN THE ENTREPRENEURIAL SECTOR [OF ARENA] AND D'AUBUISSON'S SUPPORTERS TO GAIN CONTROL OF THE PARTY, AND WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF A DISPUTE FOR THE DEFENSE MINISTRY. IN THE LATTER CASE, RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S ACTIONS DID AWAY WITH GENERAL BUSTILLO'S ASPIRATIONS. THERE ARE PRECEDENTS FOR THE LINE OF CONDUCT OF ARENA FACTIONS AND FOR THESE INTERNAL CONFRONTATIONS. WE RECALL THE ATTACK THAT ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON PERPETRATED AGAINST FORMER U.S. AMBASSADOR THOMAS PICKERING. WE ALSO REMEMBER HOW IMPORTANT MEN CLOSE TO MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSION PARTICIPATED IN THE KIDNAPPING OF BUSINESSMEN. MAJOR D'AUBUISSION'S SILENCE CONCERNING THE ATTACK ON RODRIGUEZ PORTH IS NOTEWORTHY.

THE FMLN UNDERSTANDS THE CONCERN OF THE VARIOUS NATIONAL SECTORS AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY IN THE SENSE THAT ARENA MAY USE THIS FACT TO JUSTIFY IRRATIONAL RETALIATORY ACTIONS. IF A SITUATION IS BROUGHT ABOUT, INVOLVING AN INCREASE IN VIOLENCE AND EXPANSION OF THE WAR, IT WILL BE THE ARENA GOVERNMENT'S SOLE RESPONSIBILITY, NOT OURS.

FOR THIS REASON, WE HAVE RAISED WITH THE POLITICAL PARTIES THE NEED TO CREATE CONDITIONS FOR ESTABLISHING A FAVORABLE CLIMATE FOR DIALOGUE AND A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION. WE REITERATE OUR TOTAL READINESS TO CONTRIBUTE TOWARD THIS EFFORT. THE FMLN REASSERTS TO ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT WE WILL CONTINUE TO ADHERE TO THE TRUTH AND THAT THAT WE WILL BE FULLY RESPONSIBLE FOR OUR ACTIONS AT ALL TIMES AND UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[DATED] 15 JUNE 198, EL SALVADOR

DEV-MUC3-0250 (ADS)

SANTIAGO, 16 JUN 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] TODAY, THE CHILEAN MILITARY GOVERNMENT HAS REPORTED THE EXISTENCE OF A SELECTIVE TERRORIST PLAN TO ATTACK GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, A PLAN THAT COULD BE LINKED TO THE SHINING PATH, A PERUVIAN TERRORIST GROUP.

GENERAL OSCAR VARGAS, THE MINISTER SECRETARY GENERAL OF GOVERNMENT, REPORTED ON THIS PLAN DURING A 2-HOUR CABINET MEETING THAT WAS CHAIRED BY CHILEAN PRESIDENT GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET.

THE MINISTER SAID THAT THERE ARE CLEAR INDICATIONS OF SUCH A PLAN, EMPHASIZING THAT THE CIVILIANS HAVE GREAT RESPONSIBILITY BECAUSE THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE SUBVERSION CANNOT BE CONDUCTED WITHOUT THE ASSISTANCE OF CIVILIANS.

GEN VARGAS POINTED OUT THAT THE RECENT ATTACKS ON ARMED FORCES AND THE SECURITY SERVICES PERSONNEL, THE ROBBERY OF CARS -- ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, A MILITARY TRUCK AND 18 PRIVATE VEHICLES HAVE BEEN STOLEN -- AND THE STEALING OF CAR LICENSE PLATES AT THE MUNICIPALITIES ARE A CLEAR INDICATION THAT THESE GROUPS ARE ABOUT TO BEGIN THEIR ACTIVITIES.

THIS WEEK, SEVERAL UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS ATTACKED AN ARMY NON- COMMISSIONED OFFICER, WHO IS A MEMBER OF THE NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER (CNI, THE SECRET POLICE) AND WHO WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED, AND LAST WEEK A RETIRED AIR FORCE OFFICER WAS MURDERED.

THE MINISTER ADDED THAT A COORDINATION AMONG ALL THE TERRORIST GROUPS THAT ARE OPERATING IN THE AREA HAS BEEN NOTICED, ESPECIALLY BY THE SHINING PATH. THIS MATTER WAS DISCUSSED BY THE PERUVIAN DEFENSE MINISTER IN A SPEECH HE MADE IN LIMA LAST WEEK.

CONCERNING THE MEASURES TAKEN, GEN VARGAS SAID: "ALL GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES HAVE BEEN INSTRUCTED TO TAKE CARE."

GEN VARGAS CATEGORICALLY DENIED THAT THE POSSIBILITY THAT GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET COULD RUN IN THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS SCHEDULED FOR 14 DECEMBER 1989 WAS DISCUSSED IN THE CABINET MEETING HELD TODAY AT THE LA MONEDA PRESIDENTIAL PALACE.

FOR HIS PART AND IN A NEWS CONFERENCE, SERGIO ONOFRE JARPA, A RIGHTWING PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE AND THE PRESIDENT OF THE PROGOVERNMENT NATIONAL RENEWAL PARTY, SAID THAT HIS NOMINATION "WOULD NOT MAKE ANY SENSE IF PINOCHET RUNS FOR THE SAME POLITICAL SECTOR."

JARPA REITERATED THAT IF THE INCUMBENT, WHO HAS BEEN PRESIDENT SINCE 1973, WANTS TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT, "IT WILL BE NECESSARY TO REFORM THE 1980 CONSTITUTION" BECAUSE ARTICLE 25 PREVENTS THE CHILEAN PRESIDENT FROM SEEKING RE-ELECTION.

DEV-MUC3-0251 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 JUN 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY RENE HURTADO] [TEXT] HURTADO PRESIDENT CRISTIANI THIS MORNING DELIVERED PART OF THE COFFEE TAX, WHICH WILL BE DISTRIBUTED AMONG ALL THE MAYORS' OFFICES IN THE COUNTRY. AFTER THE EVENT AT A SAN SALVADOR HOTEL, CRISTIANI ANSWERED QUESTIONS, FIRST ON THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] COMMUNIQUE DENYING PARTICIPATION IN THE MURDER OF PRESIDENCY MINISTER JOSE ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH. IN THE COMMUNIQUE, THE FMLN FLATLY DECLARED THAT NONE OF THEIR MEMBERS HAD HAD ANYTHING TO DO WITH THE MURDER. CRISTIANI HAD THIS TO SAY:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND SAID THEY HAD NOT ORDERED THE ASSASSINATION AND ADDED THAT APPARENTLY A GROUP GOT OUT OF HAND AND PERPETRATED THE CRIME. I THINK THE FMLN HAS REALIZED THE GENERAL REPUDIATION THIS ACTION HAS ELICITED. I AM CONVINCED THE FMLN IS TRYING TO EXCUSE THE ACTION, THUS AVOIDING ALL RESPONSIBILITY. WE THINK THEY ARE TRYING TO SEEK A WAY OUT OF THE PROBLEM CAUSED BY THE ASSASSINATION OF AN AGED, DEFENSELESS PERSON. BUT THERE IS NO WAY OUT FOR THEM NOW.

[HURTADO] THE FMLN HAS DENIED THAT ANY OF ITS MEMBERS PARTICIPATED IN THE ACTION.

[CRISTIANI] OF COURSE, THEY ARE NOW TRYING TO DENY IT AFTER THEY LEARNED OF THE REPUDIATION BOTH HERE AND ABROAD. IN ADDITION, THEY WAITED A CONSIDERABLE TIME TO DENY THEIR PARTICIPATION. THEY HAD A COMPLETE PLAN AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT. AS YOU KNOW, THE PLAN IS CALLED "ALL AGAINST ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE]." THIS MURDER WAS PART OF THEIR PLAN. RODRIGUEZ PORTH HAD NO ENEMIES. HE WAS A PEACEFUL MAN WHO STRUGGLED WITH HIS PEN AND IDEAS. ONLY AN IRRATIONAL MIND, LIKE THAT OF THOSE WHO ADVOCATE VIOLENCE, COULD HAVE CONCEIVED THIS ACTION. I AM CONVINCED THE FMLN DID IT.

[HURTADO] MR PRESIDENT, IF YOU AND THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] ARE CONVINCED THE FMLN IS GUILTY, WHAT WILL BECOME OF THE DIALOGUE?

[CRITIANI] WE THINK WE SHOULD OVERCOME THE EFFECT OF THIS HEAVY BLOW CAUSED BY THE LOSS, NOT ONLY OF A COLUMN OF THE PARTY AND OF OUR IDEOLOGY, BUT ALSO OF A PERSONAL FRIEND. AS MEMBERS OF THE GOVERNMENT, WE SHOULD OVERCOME OUR GRIEF AND SEEK THE GOOD OF THE COUNTRY. WE BELIEVE [WORDS INDISTINCT] VIOLENCE IS REPUDIATED AND REJECTED IN THE COUNTRY. IT IS TIME FOR THE FMLN TO TALK ABOUT ITS OBJECTIVES. THEY HAVE REJECTED THE OPPORTUNITY TO TALK WITH THE GOVERNMENT WITH UNACCEPTABLE AND UNJUSTIFIABLE ARGUMENTS. BUT OUR PROPOSAL FOR DIALOGUE IS STILL GOOD. WE ARE WILLING TO SIT DOWN AND TALK WITH THEM SO THIS VIOLENCE CAN END.

[HURTADO] HAS A COMMISSION ALREADY BEEN FORMED?

[CRISTIANI] WE ARE IN THE PROCESS OF FORMING IT. SOME OF THE PROPOSED PERSONS HAVE ALREADY AGREED TO BE MEMBERS. WE HOPE TO HAVE FORMED THE COMMISSION BY THE END OF THE WEEK. AS SOON AS WE HAVE IT, WE WILL GLADLY ANNOUNCE THE MEMBERS' NAMES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0252 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SANTIAGO, 26 JUN 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] TERRORIST SERGIO BUSCHMANN, WHO HAD BEEN HELD IN PREVENTIVE CUSTODY IN ALASKA, WAS SET FREE BY U.S. AUTHORITIES. THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT HAS EXPRESSED ITS FRUSTRATION OVER THAT DECISION, NOTING THAT IT WILL CONTINUE TO TAKE ALL NECESSARY STEPS AT EVERY OCCASION TO BRING SERGIO BUSCHMANN TO COURT IN CHILE.

THE INFORMATION WAS MADE PUBLIC BY CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTRY SPOKESMAN CARLOS DUCCI WHEN HE RELEASED AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE FROM THE FOREIGN MINISTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUCCI] THE FOREIGN MINISTRY WAS INFORMED TODAY BY THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE THAT BECAUSE OF LEGAL TECHNICALITIES RELATED TO INTERPRETATIONS OF THE BILATERAL EXTRADITION TREATY OF 1900, IT CANNOT KEEP SERGIO BUSCHMANN IN PREVENTIVE CUSTODY, NOR CAN IT COMPLY WITH THE EXTRADITION REQUEST THAT IS BEING PREPARED IN CHILE. THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT MAKES PUBLIC ITS DISAPPOINTMENT AT THIS DECISION BY THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE AND THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE. IT IS NOT SUFFICIENT IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM THAT SOME COUNTRIES SHOULD LIMIT THEMSELVES TO EXPELLING THE TERRORIST BUSCHMANN FROM THEIR TERRITORY. WE HAVE REQUESTED THAT JUSTICE BE ALLOWED TO OPERATE SO THAT BUSCHMANN CAN BE SUBMITTED TO DUE PROCESS IN A CASE OF A STRICTLY JUDICIAL NATURE.

BUSCHMANN HAS BEEN INTERNATIONALLY RECOGNIZED AS A TERRORIST; HE HAS ENDORSED VIOLENCE, INCITED ASSASSINATION, AND RAISED FUNDS FOR THE PURCHASE OF ARMS TO KILL CHILEANS. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS HAD AT THE PROPER TIME THE OPPORTUNITY TO INSPECT THE ARMS CLANDESTINELY INTRODUCED IN CHILE FOR TERRORIST PURPOSES BY SERGIO BUSCHMANN. THIS ACT HAS BEEN PUBLICLY CONDEMNED BY THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE, BECAUSE IT REVEALED THE THREAT INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM POSES TO THE SECURITY OF THE HEMISPHERE. THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN AND WILL TAKE ALL NECESSARY STEPS AT EVERY OPPORTUNITY TO BRING BUSCHMANN TO COURT, AND IT MUST NOW DEPLORE AND REJECT THE IMPUNITY WITH WHICH THIS AVOWED CRIMINAL WILL CONTINUE TO ENDORSE TERRORISM AND VIOLENCE ON THE INTERNATIONAL STAGE. [END RECORDING]

TERRORIST SERGIO BUSCHMANN, SPOKESMAN FOR THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT, HAS THE STATUS OF POLITICAL REFUGEE IN SWEDEN. WHEN CARLOS DUCCI WAS ASKED IF BUSCHMANN HAS TRAVELED TO SWEDEN, HE REPLIED THAT HE DID NOT KNOW AND THAT HE ONLY HAS INFORMATION THAT BUSCHMANN HAS BEEN SET FREE.

DEV-MUC3-0253 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 17 JUN 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [TEXT] NICARAGUA HAS DENIED ANY LINKS WITH THE ASSASSINATION OF SALVADORAN PRESIDENCY MINISTER ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH 8 DAYS AGO, AN ALLEGATION MADE BY THE SALVADORAN ARMY. AT A NEWS CONFERENCE, COMMANDER BAYARDO ARCE, VICE COORDINATOR OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMISSION OF THE RULING SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FSLN, TERMED IRRESPONSIBLE THE CHARGES MADE IN SAN SALVADOR THAT NICARAGUA TRAINED THE COMMANDO WHO KILLED RODRIGUEZ PORTH.

ARCE SAID: WE LACK THE EXPERIENCE FOR SUCH ATTACKS AND THEREFORE COULD NOT HAVE TRAINED ANYONE. HE RECALLED THAT THE FSLN NEVER RESORTED TO THAT TYPE OF ACTION DURING ITS STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DICTATOR ANASTASIO SOMOZA, WHO WAS OVERTHROWN IN 1979.

THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAVE CLAIMED THAT RODRIGUEZ PORTH WAS KILLED BY A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT COMMANDO TRAINED IN NICARAGUA. HOWEVER, THAT GUERRILLA GROUP HAS DENIED ANY RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ACTION.

ARCE ALSO DENIED THAT NICARAGUA HAS SENT WEAPONS TO PANAMA WHEN TENSION WITH THE UNITED STATES INCREASED LAST MONTH, AS REPORTED IN THE U.S. MEDIA. I AM NOT SURPRISED BY THOSE STATEMENTS, ARCE SAID, ADDING THAT THE UNITED STATES CONTINUES ITS EFFORTS TO DISCREDIT THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT WITH SUCH LIES.

DEV-MUC3-0255 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 19 JUN 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO A LAST - MINUTE OFFICIAL REPORT, SIX GUERRILLAS OF THE SO-CALLED CAMILIST UNION OF THE SO-CALLED ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION ELN DIED TODAY DURING FIGHTING WITH (LA POPA) BATTALION TROOPS IN THE SLOPES OF THE PERIJA MOUNTAIN RANGE. A MILITARY COMMAND SPOKESMAN SAID THAT THE FIGHTING TOOK PLACE A SCANT 10 KM FROM THE VILLAGE OF SAN JACINTO IN SAN DIEGO MUNICIPALITY, WHERE FOUR SOLDIERS DIED LAST WEEK IN AN AMBUSH.

POLICE AND MILITARY FORCES HAVE STEPPED UP SURVEILLANCE AROUND THE CANO LIMON - COVENAS PIPELINE AFTER TWO NEW ATTACKS, ALSO BY THE ELN, OCCURRED IN HUILA AND NORTH SANTANDER DEPARTMENTS.

THE TERRORIST ATTACK IN HUILA DEPARTMENT TOOK PLACE IN LA MOTOSA, NEAR AIPE MUNICIPALITY, WHERE THE PIPELINE THAT PUMPS CRUDE OIL BETWEEN NEIVA AND LA DORADA WAS DYNAMITED. HUMBERTO BRINES TRAVELED EARLY TODAY TO THE SCENE OF THE EVENTS AND REPORTED THE FOLLOWING:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BRINES] A NEW ATTACK WAS PERPETRATED LAST NIGHT AGAINST THE PIPELINE THAT PUMPS CRUDE OIL FROM NEIVA TO DORADA. SUSPECTED ELN GUERRILLAS PLACED A DYNAMITE CHARGE AT THE PLACE CALLED LA MOTOSA, NEAR AIPE MUNICIPALITY, WHICH COMPLETELY DESTROYED THE GUARD POST AND A STRETCH OF THE PIPELINE. A FIRE IMMEDIATELY BROKE OUT AND THE INSTALLATION WAS COMPLETELY GUTTED.

CRUDE OIL PUMPING WAS SUSPENDED AND EFFORTS TO CONTAIN THE FIRE AND TO REPAIR THE PIPELINE BEGAN AT 2300. THE EXTENT OF THE LOSSES HAS NOT YET BEEN ASSESSED. THIS PIPELINE PUMPS 58,000 BARRELS OF OIL PER DAY. THE MAIN PUMPING STATION IS LOCATED IN AIPE MUNICIPALITY. WORKERS FROM (JOCOL) AND ECOPETROL [COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE] WORKED INTENSELY ALL THROUGH THE PREDAWN HOURS TO REPAIR THE PIPELINE, ENABLING IT TO RESUME PUMPING OPERATIONS AT 1000.

EVEN THOUGH THE ELN HAS REPEATEDLY THREATENED THE OIL PIPELINES, WORK HAS CONTINUED ON THE CONSTRUCTION OF A NEW MULTIPLE PIPELINE IN HUILA, WHICH WILL PUMP 138,000 BARRELS OF OIL PER DAY BETWEEN NEIVA AND COVENAS. THE SAME PIPELINE WAS BLOWN UP ONLY 1 MONTH AGO, A SCARCE 25 KM FROM THAT PLACE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0256 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 20 JUN 89 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] THE DAMAGE CAUSED BY THE LATEST TERRORIST ATTACKS AGAINST THE COUNTRY'S OIL PIPELINE HAS SO FAR BEEN ESTIMATED AT ALMOST 75 BILLION PESOS. ACCORDING TO ECOPETROL [COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE], THERE HAVE BEEN FOUR DYNAMITE ATTACKS ON THE PIPELINE IN THE LAST 72 HOURS. BECAUSE OF THE ATTACKS, COLOMBIA WILL HAVE TO ABSTAIN FROM MARKETING CRUDE OIL ABROAD FOR 3 WEEKS, THUS LOSING $150 MILLION. THE DAMAGE CAUSED TO THE COVENAS PLANT AMOUNTS TO $7 MILLION; ANOTHER $7 MILLION WILL HAVE TO BE SPENT ON REPAIRS.

ECOPETROL PRESIDENT ANDRES RESTREPO LONDONO SAID THAT THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE WILL FEEL THE IMPACT OF THESE ATTACKS. ALREADY THE ROYALTIES GIVEN TO THE MUNICIPALITIES HAVE BEEN SUSPENDED, AND AN INCREASE IN FUEL PRICES WILL BE NECESSARY, ACCORDING TO THE FIRST SPECIAL MEETING OF THE COUNTRY'S PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE AUTHORITIES.

MEANWHILE, THE ARMY HAS INCREASED ITS COUNTEROFFENSIVE AGAINST ELN [ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION] GUERRILLAS, WHICH HAVE CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACKS ON THE OIL PIPELINE, EXERTING PRESSURE TO MODIFY THE OIL POLICY. THE LATEST ATTACK ON THE PIPELINE OCCURRED AT THE LISAMA INSTALLATIONS, LOCATED BETWEEN BARRANCABERMEJA AND BUCARAMANGA. ELN GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THESE INSTALLLATIONS, WHICH ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR PRODUCING GAS AND PETROLEUM. THE GUERRILLAS CUT 80 PERCENT OF THE CABLES ATTACHED TO THE MOTORS WHICH EXTRACT FUEL.

A DYNAMITE CHARGE WAS ALSO PLACED ON THE PIPELINE AT KM-28 IN CANO LIMON-COVENAS, IN THE AREA OF CARMEN, NEAR THE TONCHALA RIVER, IN NORTHERN SANTANDER. NO FUEL, HOWEVER, WAS LOST. THE ATTACKS HAVE NOW EXTENDED TO HUILA DEPARTMENT FOR THE FIRST TIME, DAMAGING FUEL INSTALLATIONS. HERE THE OIL SPILL WAS STOPPED BY CLOSING DOWN THE INSTALLATIONS.

FURTHERMORE, NINE GUERRILLAS HAVE BEEN KILLED, EIGHT MORE HAVE BEEN CAPTURED, AND AN ELN TRAINING CENTER HAS BEEN DISMANTLED. THIS IS THE RESULT OF THE ARMY'S FIRST COUNTERINSURGENCY ACTIONS AGAINST THOSE DETERMINED TO DO AWAY WITH THE NATION'S RESOURCES BY ATTACKING THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS PIPELINE. MILITARY AUTHORITIES HAVE REPORTED THAT NEAR SERRANIA DE PERIJA, CESAR DEPARTMENT, THE 2D BRIGADE'S (LA POPA) BATTALION TROOPS CLASHED WITH ELN GUERRILLAS. THE CLASH RESULTED IN THE DEATH OF SIX GUERRILLAS AND THE CONFISCATION OF A GREAT AMOUNT OF WAR MATERIEL.

IN ADDITION, [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE ARMY DISMANTLED AN ELN URBAN NETWORK, CAPTURING EIGHT OF ITS MEMBERS. MEANWHILE, THE 14TH BRIGADE'S (LUCIANO DE LURIA) BATTALION TROOPS KILLED JOSE ANTONIO VELASCO, A FARC [REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA] LEADER. FINALLY, 5TH BRIGADE TROOPS ARE CONTINUING THEIR ACTIONS IN THE CACATUMBO AREA, WHERE THE ELN HAS TAKEN REFUGE. THE ELN, COMMANDED BY SPANISH PRIEST MANUEL PEREZ, HAS BASED ITS OPERATIONS IN EASTERN COLOMBIA.

DEV-MUC3-0257 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 21 JUN 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) ANNOUNCED TODAY FOR THE FIRST THAT THAT IT IS WILLING TO ENGAGE IN A DIALOGUE ON THE COUNTRY'S OIL POLICY. THE ELN HAS CARRIED OUT A DESTRUCTIVE WAVE OF ATTACKS AGAINST THE COLOMBIAN OIL INDUSTRY TO FORCE THE GOVERNMENT TO NATIONALIZE THIS INDUSTRY.

THE GUERRILLA GROUP'S WILLINGNESS TO PARTICIPATE IN A DIALOGUE IS CONVEYED IN A TAPE SENT TO CONSERVATIVE SENATOR ALVARO LEYVA FROM FORMER SPANISH PRIEST MANUEL PEREZ, WHO IS THE ELN'S FOUNDER AND LEADER. ACCORDING TO LEYVA, PEREZ EXPRESSED HIS WILLINGNESS TO MEET WITH HIM TO EXPLAIN THE GUERRILLA GROUP'S IDEAS ON WHAT COLOMBIA'S OIL POLICY SHOULD BE. LEYVA SAID THAT THE ELN ALSO DEMANDED THAT NATIONALIZATION BE APPLIED TO OTHER NATURAL RESOURCES.

FURTHERMORE, THE ELN -- WHICH HAS PREVIOUSLY REJECTED THE GOVERNMENT'S PEACE OFFER -- REITERATED ITS DESIRE TO "HUMANIZE" THE CONFLICT BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE ARMY, SO THAT THE CIVILIAN POPULATION WILL NOT BE AFFECTED.

LEYVA HAS PLAYED A LEADING ROLE IN SEEKING A RAPPROCHEMENT BETWEEN GUERRILLA GROUPS AND THE GOVERNMENT. TO THIS END HE HAS MET SEVERAL TIMES WITH M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] AND REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC) COMMANDERS, WHICH IS WHY THE ELN SELECTED HIM AS THE BEARER OF ITS MESSAGE.

THE ELN HAS CONCENTRATED ITS TERRORIST ATTACKS AGAINST THE COUNTRY'S MAIN OIL PIPELINE, WHICH EXTENDS 800 KM FROM THE EASTERN TO THE NORTHWESTERN REGIONS OF COLOMBIA. IT HAS CAUSED MILLIONS IN LOSSES TO THE STATE COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE [ECOPETROL] AND SERIOUS ECOLOGICAL DAMAGE RESULTING FROM OIL SPILLS.

IN 1988, IT ATTACKED THE NATION'S PIPELINES APPROXIMATELY 50 TIMES, AND THUS FAR THIS YEAR THE ELN HAS CARRIED OUT 21 ATTACKS. ON 16 JUNE, THE MAIN OIL RESERVES IN THE CARIBBEAN PORT CITY OF COVENAS WERE VIRTUALLY DESTROYED BY SEVERAL DYNAMITE BLASTS SET OFF BY THE GUERRILLAS.

THIS WAS THE ELN'S MOST DARING AND SERIOUS ATTACK TO DATE. THE ELN CLAIMS THAT THE MULTINATIONAL COMPANIES THAT CARRY OUT OIL EXPLORATION AND DRILLING WITH ECOPETROL ARE "PLUNDERING" COLOMBIA'S NATURAL RESOURCES.

DEV-MUC3-0263 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 26 JUN 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [ZORAIDA CAICEDO] [TEXT] THE CAMILIST UNION - ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION ELN HAS CARRIED OUT A NEW ATTACK ON THE PACIFIC OIL PIPELINE IN MULALO, YUMBO MUNICIPALITY. THE ATTACK OCCURRED AT APPROXIMATELY 2200 YESTERDAY WHEN TWO MEN ON A MOTORCYCLE SET OFF 5 KG OF DYNAMITE. THE EXPLOSION DESTROYED THREE SECTIONS OF THE PIPELINE THAT CARRIES GASOLINE FROM TANKERS IN BUENAVENTURA TO THE [ECOPETROL COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE] PLANT IN YUMBO. APPROXIMATELY 18,000 BARRELS OF GASOLINE ARE PUMPED THROUGH THIS SECTION OF THE PIPELINE DAILY. PUMPING HAS BEEN HALTED WHILE THE PIPELINE IS REPAIRED. ALTHOUGH THE EXACT AMOUNT OF THE DAMAGE IS STILL UNKNOWN, IT IS ESTIMATED THAT LOSSES FROM THE SPILLED GASOLINE AND THE DAMAGE TO THE PIPELINE ARE CLOSE TO 20 MILLION PESOS.

THIS IS THE FIFTH DYNAMITE ATTACK ON THE PACIFIC PIPELINE BY THE ELN IN VALLE DEL CAUCA DEPARTMENT IN THE PAST 6 MONTHS. ONE OCCURRED IN BUGA MUNICIPALITY 1 MONTH AGO, AND THE OTHER FOUR HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN THE MULALO AREA.

DEV-MUC3-0265 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 27 JUN 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] AN ALLEGED SANDINIST OFFICER WHO CLAIMS TO HAVE CARRIED OUT ESPIONAGE ACTIVITIES AGAINST THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES AND GOVERNMENT TURNED HIMSELF OVER TO HONDURAN MILITARY AUTHORITIES TODAY.

THE INDIVIDUAL IDENTIFIED HIMSELF AS CAPTAIN ADAN SOLORZANO MARTINEZ, SAID HE HAD BEEN TRAINED IN CUBA IN 1980, AND SAID WAS IN HONDURAS ON AN ESPIONAGE MISSION WITH TWO OTHER MEMBERS OF THE SANDINIST ARMY, WHOM HE DID NOT IDENTIFY.

SOLORZANO CALLED TOGETHER A GROUP OF NEWSMEN IN THE CITY OF SAN PEDRO SULA, IN NORTHERN HONDURAS, AND TURNED HIMSELF OVER TO THE MILITARY AUTHORITIES IN THE REPORTERS' PRESENCE.

THE OFFICER DECLINED TO GIVE DETAILS ABOUT "DELICATE MATTERS" ABOUT WHICH HE WILL BRIEF THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES. HE SAID THEY CONCERN HIS ACTIVITIES IN THIS COUNTRY SINCE MAY.

THE DEFECTOR SAID HE ARRIVED IN HONDURAS IN AUGUST 1988 WITH AN IDENTIFICATION CARD FROM THE HONDURAN NATIONAL REGISTRY OF PERSONS IDENTIFYING HIM AS A HONDURAN FROM COMAYAGUA, IN THE CENTRAL PART OF THE COUNTRY.

HE TOLD THE PRESS HE HAS BEEN A SANDINIST SINCE 1974 AND HAD BEEN AN URBAN GUERRILLA LEADER DURING THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE SOMOZIST REGIME IN NICARAGUA.

HE SAID THE DE FACTO GOVERNMENT AND THE CONTINUED RETENTION OF POWER BY THE SANDINISTS FORCED HIM TO DEFECT. HE ADDED THAT GROUPS OF SANDINISTS HAVE BEEN INFILTRATED INTO TEGUCIGALPA, SAN PEDRO SULA, AND OTHER PARTS OF HONDURAS TO CAUSE SOCIAL DESTABILIZATION.

HE EXPLAINED THAT AMONG OTHER ACTIVITIES, THEIR MISSION WAS TO KILL LEADERS OF MASS ORGANIZATIONS AND THEN ATTRIBUTE THE DEATHS TO THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES, THEREBY FOMENTING SOCIAL DESTABILIZATION IN THE COUNTRY.

HE ADDED THAT HIS CONTACTS WERE OUTSIDE THE COUNTRY AND THAT HE RECEIVED $2,500 A MONTH TO CARRY OUT HIS ACTIVITIES IN HONDURAS.

THE DEFECTOR SAID SANDINIST OFFICERS DIRECT THE GUERRILLAS IN EL SALVADOR AND THAT THE ASSASSINATION IN FEBRUARY OF GENERAL GUSTAVO ALVAREZ MARTINEZ, FORMER COMMANDER OF THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES, WAS PLOTTED IN MANAGUA.

THE DEFECTOR SAID ALVAREZ HAD ALWAYS BEEN IN THE SANDINISTS' SIGHTS BECAUSE HE WAS THE MAIN PROMOTER OF THE CONTRAS (NICARAGUAN ARMED OPPOSITION).

SOLORZANO SAID NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER MIGUEL D'ESCOTO HAS MANY "DELICATE THINGS" TO SAY AGAINST HONDURAS AND COSTA RICA. [AS RECEIVED]

DEV-MUC3-0266 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

GUATEMALA CITY, 27 JUN 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO TODAY REVEALED THERE HAVE BEEN TWO ATTEMPTS TO MURDER HIM SINCE HE ASSUMED THE PRESIDENTCY ON 14 JANUARY 1986.

CEREZO, WHO AVOIDED GIVING DETAILS ABOUT THE TWO ATTEMPTS, STATED THAT "THERE IS SPECIFIC INFORMATION" ABOUT AN ALLEGED PLAN TO MURDER HIM. HE ADDED, HOWEVER, THAT NO ONE CAN BE ARRESTED WITHOUT EVIDENCE.

CEREZO ASSERTED THAT HE WITHDREW LAST WEEK TO SANTO TOMAS FARM, APPROXIMATELY 43 KM SOUTH OF GUATEMALA CITY, TO THINK, STUDY GUATEMALA'S PROBLEMS, AND REST.

CEREZO SAID HE ALSO RETREATED TO HIS FARM TO GIVE HIS SECURITY OFFICIALS AN OPPORTUNITY TO RESCHEDULE ACTIVITIES AND CHANGE METHODS TO INCREASE THEIR PROTECTION WITHOUT AFFECTING THE POPULATION OR THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE PRESIDENT AND THE PEOPLE.

ANSWERING QUESTIONS ABOUT THE SUMMONING OF FOUR CIVILIANS WHO WERE LINKED WITH ONE OF THE PLANS TO MURDER HIM, CEREZO SAID THEY WERE SUMMONED BY THE POLICE TO PROVIDE INFORMATION ABOUT THE ALLEGED PLAN.

THE SECOND PLAN WAS REVEALED EARLY THIS MONTH BY HUGO ARCE, A COLUMNIST OF THE GUATEMALAN OPPOSITION NEWSPAPER EL GRAFICO, WHO THE MURDER WAS GOING TO BE CARRIED OUT BY A LIBYAN COMMANDO UNIT THAT HAD ENTERED GUATEMALA IN DECEMBER 1988 AND HAD BEEN TRAINED IN CUBA.

CEREZO SAID THAT ARCE MUST TELL EVERYTHING HE KNOWS, BECAUSE OTHERWISE "HE WOULD BE CONCEALING THE PLAN, WHICH IS A CRIME TO DO."

OTHER CIVILIANS WHO WILL ALSO BE SUMMONED BY THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE ARE MARIO DAVID GARCIA, NICOLAS BUONAFINA, BOTH SUSPECTED OF INVOLVEMENT IN THE ATTEMPTED COUP OF MAY 1988, AND JUAN MAEGLI.

PRESIDENT CEREZO SAID HE TRUSTS HIS SECURITY FORCES AND THAT IT IS VERY EASY TO DISPLAY A LARGE-SCALE PROTECTION SYSTEM, BUT "THAT IS NEITHER MY STYLE NOR THAT OF MY ASSISTANTS," CEREZO STRESSED.

CEREZO ADDED THAT THE STATE HAS SECURITY MECHANISMS TO DETERMINE WHETHER STRANGE THINGS ARE HAPPENING IN THE COUNTRY BUT THOSE MECHANISMS CANNOT ALWAYS BE USED AS EVIDENCE TO ARREST A PERSON.

CEREZO DID NOT PROVIDE INFORMATION ABOUT THE FIRST ALLEGED PLAN TO MURDER HIM.

DEV-MUC3-0267 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

LA PAZ, 29 JUN 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] BOLIVIAN LABOR CONFEDERATION (COB) REPRESENTATIVES REPORTED TODAY THAT THREE STUDENTS HAVE BEEN CHARGED WITH THE KILLING OF TWO U.S. MORMON MISSIONARIES. THE KILLINGS OCCURRED IN LA PAZ ON 24 MAY.

THE KILLING OF THE TWO U.S. MISSIONARIES WAS CLAIMED BY A SELF- STYLED "ZARATE WILLCA ARMED FORCES LIBERATION" GROUP. THIS IS THE SAME GROUP THAT CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK ON GEORGE SHULTZ WHEN HE VISITED LA PAZ IN AUGUST 1988 IN HIS CAPACITY AS U.S. SECRETARY OF STATE.

IN THE LAST FEW DAYS, BOLIVIAN AUTHORITIES HAVE ARRESTED DOZENS OF UNIVERSITY STUDENTS. THEIR RELATIVES AND COB OFFICIALS HAVE CRITICIZED THESE ARRESTS, WHICH THEY CLAIM "ARE AN ILLEGAL AND ARBITRARY ACTION."

THE COB LEADERS HAVE REPORTED THAT THOSE ARRESTED HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED AS CONSTANTINO YUJRA, A SOCIOLOGY STUDENT; TELMA SALAZAR, A NURSING STUDENT; AND ALBERTO MENDOZA, A STUDENT AT THE WARISATA RURAL SCHOOL.

MOREOVER, THE SOCIAL SCIENCE SCHOOL OF THE SAN ANDRES UNIVERSITY HAS DECLARED ITSELF IN A "STATE OF EMERGENCY" UNTIL THE STUDENTS ARE RELEASED. THE SCHOOL HAS ALSO CALLED A PROTEST MEETING FOR 30 JUNE.

MORMON MISSIONARIES JEFFREY BRENT BALL AND RAY TODD WILSON WERE THE MISSIONARIES KILLED. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS OFFERED A $500,000-REWARD TO ANYONE WHO HELPS WITH THE CAPTURE OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THEIR KILLINGS.

DEV-MUC3-0268 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

LA PAZ, 29 JUN 89 (RADIO FIDES) -- [EXCERPTS] DIEGO MORALES, LEADER OF COCHABAMBA'S PEASANT FEDERATION, IS SERIOUSLY INJURED AND IN A COMA. HE IS BEING TREATED AT A CHIMORE HOSPITAL. UMOPAR [MOBILE UNITS FOR RURAL AREAS] AGENTS FIRED MACHINEGUNS AT THE AREA FROM HELICOPTERS TO SCARE THE LOCAL POPULATION AFTER COCA PRODUCERS BLOCKED THE ROAD TO STOP AN UMOPAR VEHICLE TO FIRE.

HUGO ZALAZAR FROM THE SINGLE TRADE UNION CONFEDERATION OF BOLIVIAN PEASANT WORKERS SAID THAT UMOPAR AGENTS PROTECT DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THE CONFEDERATION WILL CONVENE A NATIONAL EMERGENCY MEETING TO PROTECT COCA GROWERS FROM VIOLENT UMOPAR RAIDS. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE BOLIVIAN LABOR CONFEDERATION [COB] CONDEMEND THE RAIDS AND DENIED THAT PEASANTS HAD AMBUSHED THE UMOPAR PATROL. COB LEADER ALEJANDRO GUZMAN REPORTS:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GUZMAN] I MUST SAY THAT THE REPORT OF AN ALLEGED AMBUSH IS COMPLETELY FALSE. PEASANTS HAVE NOT CAPTURED UMOPAR OR DEA HOSTAGES. THERE WAS, HOWEVER, A VIOLENT ATTACK AGAINST COMPANERO DIEGO MORALES ON HIS LAND, IN FRONT OF OTHER COCA GROWERS. [END RECORDING] [PASSAGE OMITTED]

UMOPAR FORCES HAVE ALSO ARRESTED 30 PEASANTS IN PUERTO SAN FRANCISCO, CHAPARE, AFTER A POLICE PATROL WAS FORCED TO RELEASE 2 DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND HAD TO FLEE FROM A CROWD OF NEARLY 1,000 PEASANTS.

SOCIAL DEFENSE UNDER SECRETARY GENARO MARQUEZ SAID THE INCIDENT OCCURRED AFTER A MINE-MAN UMOPAR PATROL CAPTURED TWO DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THE PEASANTS INTERCEPTED THE VEHICLE IN WHICH THE TWO DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE BEING TAKEN TO CHIMORE. THE POLICE AGENTS HAD TO RELEASE THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS AFTER THE PEASANTS THREATENED TO SHOOT THEM.

THE CROWD CONTINUED TO THREATEN THE PATROL, FORCING THE UMOPAR AGENTS TO FLEE INTO THE WOODS. THE PEASANTS -- SOME 400 STRONG -- BURNED THE UMOPAR PICKUP AND CHASED THE POLICE INTO THE WOODS.

UNDER SECRETARY GENARO MARQUEZ EXPLAINTS:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MARQUEZ] YESTERDAY, UMOPAR RAIDED SOME AREAS DURING THE MORNING AND CLASHED WITH A LARGE GROUP OF PEASANTS IN PUERTO SAN FRANCISCO, WHO ATTACKED THE PATROL AFTER LEARNING WHAT HAPPENED TO DIEGO MORALES. THE AGENTS HAD TO RELEASE TWO DRUG TRAFFICKERS THEY WERE BRINGING WITH THEM. THEY WERE ABLE TO FLEE THE AREA AFTER SOME DIFFICULTIES BUT WILL CONTINUE INVESTIGATING. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

MARQUEZ SAID THE 30 ARRESTED PEASANTS WILL BE QUESTIONED TO DETERMINE THEIR RESPONSIBILITY IN THE INCIDENT AND THOSE WHO ARE INNOCENT WILL BE RELEASED. MARQUEZ ALSO SAID POLICE SEIZED ARMS AND STICKS OF DYNAMITE.

DEV-MUC3-0271 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 JUN 89 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS BLAMED FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] GUERRILLAS FOR THE MURDER OF POLITICAL ANALYST EDGAR CHACON AND HAS STRESSED THAT, DESPITE THESE ACTIONS, HE IS UNDETERRED FROM HIS INTENTION TO SIT DOWN AND TALK WITH THE REBELS TO PUT AN END TO THE CONFLICT.

PRESIDENT CRISTIANI SAID THAT HIS GOVERNMENT WOULD NOT BE BLACKMAILED BY THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE UNLEASHED BY THE FMLN. THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT THESE ACTIONS ONLY SERVE TO CONFIRM THE WEAKNESS OF THE FMLN, WHICH SEEKS POWER THROUGH VIOLENCE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] THE FMLN'S POWERLESSNESS AND INABILITY TO DO BATTLE USING IDEAS RATHER THAN VIOLENCE BECAME EVIDENT AGAIN TODAY. THE FMLN HAS AGAIN TRIED TO SILENCE THE VOICE OF ANOTHER SALVADORAN WHO FOUGHT WITH WORDS AND THOUGHTS. IN EVERY SENSE, THIS HAS BEEN A COWARDLY ACT AND IT CAN ONLY BE DESCRIBED AS THAT. IT IS THE WORK OF SICK MINDS. I BELIEVE THAT THIS IS WHAT THE FMLN HAS PROVEN TO BE -- A GROUP OF SICK PEOPLE WHO DO NOT UNDERSTAND THE CLAMOR OF A PEOPLE WHO WISH TO TALK RATHER THAN USE VIOLENCE, A PEOPLE WHO WANT PEACE IN EL SALVADOR.

WE ARE ON THE SIDE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WANT US TO DO WHAT WE CAN TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. BECAUSE WE WISH TO DO WHAT THE PEOPLE WANT, WE WILL ALWAYS HAVE THE DOORS OPEN IN THE HOPE OF ACHIEVING PEACE IN OUR HOMELAND. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0272 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 2 JUL 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] FOUR COLOMBIAN LEFTIST GUERRILLA GROUPS ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT THEY ARE WILLING TO PROMOTE A DIRECT PEACE DIALOGUE WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, THIS WILL BRING TO FIVE THE NUMBER OF REBEL GROUPS THAT HAVE REPORTEDLY ACCEPTED THE PEACE PROPOSAL THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT MADE IN SEPTEMBER 1988.

THE LEFTIST M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT], WHICH APPEARED IN THE MID-1970'S, KIDNAPPED 20 AMBASSADORS IN AN ATTACK ON THE DOMINICAN EMBASSY IN BOGOTA, AND OCCUPIED THE JUSTICE PALACE IN NOVEMBER 1985 -- AN ACTION THAT RESULTED IN THE DEATHS OF 100 PEOPLE -- HAS BEEN HOLDING PEACE TALKS WITH THE BARCO GOVERNMENT SINCE DECEMBER.

BOGOTA'S RADIO CADENA NACIONAL REPORTED THAT THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA (FARC, COMMUNIST), THE MARXIST-LENINIST POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY (EPL), THE INDIAN QUINTIN LAME COMMANDO UNIT, AND THE REVOLUTIONARY WORKERS PARTY (PRT) ATTENDED A GUERRILLA SUMMIT HELD IN THE PARAMO DE SUMAPAZ MOUNTAINS, IN SOUTHWEST BOGOTA, THIS WEEKEND.

DURING THE GUERRILLA SUMMIT, THE FOURTH SINCE THE CREATION OF THE SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD (CNGSM), A DOCUMENT WAS DRAFTED PROPOSING DIRECT DIALOGUE WITH THE GOVERNMENT.

ACCORDING TO THE DOCUMENT BROADCAST BY RADIO CADENA NATIONAL, A DIALOGUE, SIMILAR TO THE ONE BEING HELD WITH M-19, "WOULD SERVE TO ESTABLISH THE NECESSARY CONDITIONS FOR PEACE AND NATIONAL HARMONY."

CONTRARY TO WHAT COULD HAVE BEEN EXPECTED, THE PROPOSAL WAS NOT SENT TO PRESIDENT BARCO, BUT TO MISAEL PASTRANA BORRERO, FORMER OPPOSITION SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PARTY PRESIDENT WHO RULED FROM 1970 - 1974. PASTRANA IS A MEMBER OF A COMMISSION OF NOTABLES CREATED TO MEDIATE FOR PEACE. THIS COMMISSION SHOULD ANALYZE THE PROPOSAL AND PRESENT IT TO THE GOVERNMENT IN A FEW DAYS.

APPARENTLY ALSO PARTICIPATING IN THE SIMON BOLIVAR SUMMIT WERE DELEGATES OF M-19 AND THE ELN, A GROUP THAT HAS UNLEASHED A VIOLENT CAMPAIGN TO DESTROY THE OIL INDUSTRY INFRASTRUCTURE, PARTICULARLY THE LEADING CANO LIMON-COVENAS OIL PIPELINE THAT CROSSES THE COUNTRY EAST TO WEST AND COVERS NEARLY 800 KMS.

THE DOCUMENT STRESSES THE NEED TO REACH A PEACEFUL POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE ARMED CONFLICT, WHICH THE COUNTRY HAS HAD TO PUT UP WITH FOR THE PAST 40 YEARS.

THE SIGNATORIES OF THE DOCUMENT ASSERTED THAT "DIRECT DIALOGUE WITH THE GOVERNMENT IS ONE OF THE MECHANISMS THAT COULD LEAD TO A SOLUTION." THE GOVERNMENT MUST CARRY OUT ITS STRUGGLE AGAINST THE SO-CALLED PARAMILITARY (SELF-DEFENSE) GROUPS WITH EVEN MORE DETERMINATION, THE DOCUMENT SAID.

THEY ALSO DEMAND AN END TO THE "DIRTY WAR."

MEANWHILE, IT WAS LEARNED THAT FORMER PRESIDENT MISAEL PATRANA BORRERO HAS SUMMONED THE NOTABLES COMMISSION, COMPRISED OF FABIO ECHEVERRI CORREA, PRESIDENT OF THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF INDUSTRIALISTS (ANDI) AND CARDINAL MARIO REVOLLO CORREA, TO A MEETING ON MONDAY TO REVIEW THE DOCUMENT AND PRESENT IT TO PRESIDENT BARCO.

THE PROPOSAL PRESENTED BY THE FARC, THE EPL, THE QUINTIN LAME, AND THE PRT -- ORGANIZATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN ABIDING BY THE UNILATERAL TRUCE SINCE EARLY THIS YEAR -- LEAVES THE ELN AS THE ONLY ACTIVE COLOMBIAN GUERRILLA GROUP.

HOWEVER, THAT SUBVERSIVE GROUP, LED BY SPANISH PRIEST MANUEL PEREZ, ANNOUNCED LAST WEEK THE POSSIBILITY OF OPENING CHANNELS FOR PEACE IF A DATE IS SET FOR A MEETING, IN THE NEAR FUTURE, TO ANALYZE THE COUNTRY'S CURRENT OIL POLICIES.

THE ELN HAS OFFERED TO STOP ITS ATTACKS IF THE OIL INDUSTRY IN THE COUNTRY IS NATIONALIZED.

DEV-MUC3-0273 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 2 JUL 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] IN AN ATTACK THAT OCCURRED NEAR SAN SALVADOR A GROUP OF UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS THIS EVENING WOUNDED MAURICIO GUTIERREZ CASTRO, PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE. ONE OF HIS BODYGUARDS WAS WAS KILLED.

THE PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE, WHO TOOK OFFICE ON FRIDAY, WAS SLIGHTLY WOUNDED IN THE NECK.

GUTIERREZ CASTRO, A 48-YEAR-OLD MAN, WAS RETURNING TO SAN SALVADOR FROM THE BEACH IN LA LIBERTAD WHEN HIS CAR WAS SHOT AT NEAR THE TOWN OF ZARAGOZA, APPROXIMATELY 10 KM FROM SAN SALVADOR. GUTIERREZ CASTRO WAS IN THE CAR WITH HIS TWO SONS.

ONE OF HIS BODYGUARDS, WHOM THE AUTHORITIES DID NOT IDENTIFY, DIED ON THE SPOT, WHILE HIS CHILDREN AND THE OTHER MEMBER OF HIS ESCORT WERE NOT INJURED.

IN A DECLARATION IN WHICH HE CONDEMNED ALL TYPES OF VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY, "REGARDLESS OF WHERE IT COMES FROM," THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE PRESIDENT TOLD THE MEDIA THAT HE DID NOT KNOW IF HE WAS THE TARGET OF THE ATTACK.

GUTIERREZ CASTRO REPLACES FRANCISCO JOSE GUERRERO, WHO COMPLETED HIS 5-YEAR TERM.

NO ORGANIZATION HAS YET CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK.

THE LAST ATTACK WITH SIMILAR CHARACTERISTICS OCCURRED IN JUNE, AND THE AUTHORITIES ATTRIBUTED IT TO THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN), BUT THE GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION DENIED THE ACCUSATION.

ON THAT OCCASION THREE UNIDENTIFIED MEN SHOT AND KILLED 65-YEAR- OLD PRESIDENCY MINISTER ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH.

DEV-MUC3-0278 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 3 JUL 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] ARMED FORCES COMMANDER GENERAL OSCAR BOTERO RESTREPO REPORTED TODAY THAT GUERRILLAS OF THE PRO - CASTRO ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) SET FIRE TO THREE TANK TRUCKS THAT WERE CARRYING OIL FROM THE CANO LIMON OILFIELD IN ARAUCA DEPARTMENT, WHICH BORDERS VENEZUELA, TO COLOMBIA'S INTERIOR.

THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT IN BOQUERON, BETWEEN PAJARITO AND YOPAL, IN CASANARE DEPARTMENT, WHERE THE SUBVERSIVES HAVE UNLEASHED A VIOLENT CAMPAIGN AGAINST COLOMBIA'S OIL INFRASTRUCTURE TO FORCE THEIR DEMANDS FOR THE NATIONALIZATION OF THE OIL INDUSTRY.

GEN BOTERO SAID THAT THE REBELS -- WHO HAVE DYNAMITED THE COUNTRY'S MAIN OIL PIPELINE, THE CANO LIMON - CONVENAS PIPELINE, 23 TIMES THUS FAR THIS YEAR -- INTERCEPTED THE VEHICLES IN THE MIDDLE OF THE HIGHWAY AND SET THEM ON FIRE AFTER FORCING THE DRIVERS TO GET OUT OF THE VEHICLES. THE ELN GUERRILLAS SIMULTANEOUSLY WROTE SLOGANS IN SUPPORT OF THE SO-CALLED SIMON BOLIVAR NATIONAL GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD. DURING THE LAST FEW HOURS, THIS GROUP AGREED WITH PRESIDENT BARCO'S ADMINISTRATION TO BEGIN A DIRECT DIALOGUE TO SEEK PEACE IN COLOMBIA.

NO DEATHS WERE REPORTED IN THE ATTACK BY THE ELN, WHICH WAS FOUNDED DURING THE 1960'S AND IS LED BY MANUEL PEREZ, A SPANISH PRIEST.

MEANWHILE, ANOTHER COMMANDO GROUP FROM THE CAMILIST UNION (NAMED IN MEMORY OF COLOMBIAN PRIEST CAMILO RESTREPO, WHO WAS KILLED BY SOLDIERS IN 1966 WHILE STILL A MEMBER OF THE ELN), AMBUSHED A MILITARY PATROL ON THE AGUA AZUL - TERRANOVA HIGHWAY, ALSO IN CASANARE, KILLING TWO SOLDIERS. GEN BOTERO SAID THAT TWO SOLDIERS STEPPED ON A MINE DURING THE GUERRILLA ATTACK AND THREE OTHER SOLDIERS WERE WOUNDED.

DEV-MUC3-0279 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 4 JUL 89 (RUDE PRAVO) -- [ARTICLE] [MANUEL CEPEDA, MEMBER OF THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY CENTRAL COMMITTEE POLITBURO] [TEXT] RECENTLY NEW PHENOMENA HAVE MADE THEIR WAY ONTO THE COLOMBIAN POLITICAL SCENE. THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS HAS BEEN FORCED TO ADOPT MEASURES AGAINST ULTRA RIGHT-WING PARAMILITARY ORGANIZATIONS AND DIFFERENCES ARE BEGINNING TO APPEAR IN THE GOVERNMENT AND IN THE ARMED FORCES.

THESE ARGUMENTS ARE TAKING PLACE IN CONNECTION WITH DISCUSSIONS PRIOR TO THE ELECTIONS WHICH ARE EXPECTED TO TAKE PLACE IN COLOMBIA IN 1990. AFTER THE COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY [CCP] HAD DEMANDED FROM THE GOVERNMENT SECURE GUARANTEES THAT IT CAN PARTICIPATE IN THEM, IT ANNOUNCED THAT IT WILL BECOME INVOLVED IN THE ELECTORAL PROCESS AND NOW IT IS STRIVING TO CREATE A BROAD DEMOCRATIC COALITION.

THE APPROACHING ELECTIONS AS WELL AS THE WIDESPREAD INTERNATIONAL CONDEMNATION OF THE "DIRTY WAR" IN COLOMBIA FORCED THE GOVERNMENT TO TAKE MORE DECISIVE STEPS IN A NUMBER OF SPHERES. THE MOST IMPORTANT OF THESE ARE:

-- ISSUING PRESIDENTIALLY PROCLAIMED DECREES AGAINST HIRED ASSASSINS AND CREATING AN ELITE MILITARY FORCE FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THEM; ORGANIZING A STRUGGLE AGAINST ULTRA RIGHT-WING PARAMILITARY GROUPS AND INCREASING PRISON SENTENCES UP TO 20-30 YEARS FOR SOLDIERS AND CIVILIANS WHO ARE MEMBERS OF THEM;

-- CONDUCTING A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE LEFTIST COALITION PATRIOTIC UNION (WHICH THE CCP IS A MEMBER OF) AND THE SUPREME COMMANDER OF THE ARMY WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF THE MINISTER OF DEFENSE;

-- CONDUCTING A PURGE IN THE ARMY DIRECTED AGAINST THE OFFICERS WHO ARE ASSOCIATED WITH WITH GROUPS OF HIRED ASSASSINS.

THE REASON FOR ACCELERATING THESE MEASURES WAS THE ASSASSINATION ATTEMPT AGAINST THE HEAD OF THE SECRET POLICE (DAS), GENERAL MIGUEL MAZA MARQUEZ, CARRIED OUT ON 30 MAY BY PARAMILITARY GROUPS WHICH ARE CONTROLLED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS. A VEHICLE FILLED WITH 100 KG OF DYNAMITE WAS USED TO TRY TO ASSASSINATE THE HEAD OF STATE SECURITY. THE GENERAL ESCAPED WITHOUT INJURY BUT DURING THE ASSASSINATION ATTEMPT 7 PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND MORE THAN 50 WERE WOUNDED. BECAUSE OF THIS ACT DIFFERENCES IN THE ARMED FORCES AND IN THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT FURTHER INTENSIFIED.

MAZA MARQUEZ HAS BEEN THE SWORN ENEMY OF THE MAFIA AND THE OBJECT OF THEIR THREATS SINCE HE REVEALED THAT THE GANGS WHICH CARRY OUT ASSASSINATION ATTEMPTS AGAINST THE CCP AND THE PATRIOTIC UNION ARE TRAINED MERCENARIES FROM THE UNITED STATES, ISRAEL, THE FRG, AND GREAT BRITAIN. AFTER ESCAPING FROM AN ASSASSINATION ATTEMPT ON 3 MAY, GENERAL MAZA MARQUEZ SENT A LETTER TO THE STATE PROSECUTOR. IN IT HE SAID THAT CERTAIN GROUPS IN THE ARMY KNEW ABOUT THE ASSASSINATION ATTEMPT WHICH HAD BEEN PREPARED AGAINST HIM.

DURING THE SAME PERIOD CAPTAIN WANUMEN [NAME AS PUBLISHED] WAS IMPRISONED; HE HAD SECRET DOCUMENTS FROM THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS, THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL, THE U.S. EMBASSY IN BOGOTA, THE DAS, AND THE AMERICAN CIA WHICH LIST HIGHLY PLACED INDIVIDUALS IN THE GOVERNMENT WHO WORK AS "SPIES" FOR THE BENEFIT OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS FROM THE MEDELLIN AND CALI CARTELS. ALTHOUGH PRESIDENT BARCO VARGAS DENIED THE AUTHENTICITY OF THE DOCUMENTS, REPORTS ARE GENERALLY DISSEMINATED THAT THE RULING ELITE HAS BEEN INFILTRATED WITH MAFIA AGENTS.

IN THIS SITUATION SPACE OPENS UP FOR THE CCP'S PROPOSAL TO INTRODUCE PEACE TO THE COUNTRY BY WAY OF A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND ALL PARTISAN GROUPS, NOT JUST WITH THE M-19 MOVEMENT, AS THE GOVERNMENT HAS PRACTICED TO DATE. ALTHOUGH THE SITUATION IN COLOMBIA IS STILL SERIOUS, THERE ARE DEFINITE SIGNS OF A TURNAROUND FOR THE BETTER.

DEV-MUC3-0280 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

MOSCOW (USSR), 6 JUL 89 (TASS) -- [TEXT] THE SOVIET AMBASSADOR TO PERU MADE A REPRESENTATION TO THE MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS OF THE COUNTRY IN CONNECTION WITH THE FACT THAT IN THE PERUVIAN PORT OF CALLAO, A BOMB HAD BEEN PLANTED AND DETONATED LAST WEDNESDAY UNDER A BUS CARRYING CREW MEMBERS OF THE TRAWLER SHIPS "KURASOV" AND "LAZURNY", YURIY GREMITSKIKH, FIRST DEPUTY CHIEF OF THE FOREIGN MINISTRY INFORMATION DIRECTORATE, TOLD REPORTERS AT A BRIEFING HERE TODAY. AS A RESULT OF THE TERRORIST ACTION 16 SOVIET SAILORS WERE INJURED. NONE WAS KILLED. ALL THE INJURED SAILORS ARE GETTING MEDICAL ATTENTION.

THE SOVIET AMBASSADOR STATED THAT THE SOVIET SIDE EXPECTED THAT THE INCIDENT WOULD BE THOROUGHLY INVESTIGATED AND THE CRIMINALS PUNISHED. HE ALSO DEMANDED THAT APPROPRIATE ACTION BE TAKEN TO ENSURE THE SAFETY OF SOVIET CITIZENS AND OFFICES IN THAT COUNTRY. THE PERUVIAN SIDE EXPRESSED A FEELING OF REGRET CONCERNING THE INCIDENT AND ASSURED THAT ALL NECESSARY STEPS WOULD BE TAKEN TO LOCATE GUILTY PERSONS AND ENSURE THE SAFETY OF SOVIET PEOPLE.

THE SOVIET TRAWLER SHIPS WERE IN CALLAO IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE INTER-GOVERNMENTAL AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE USSR AND PERU ON COOPERATION IN FISHING.

DEV-MUC3-0281 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 5 JUL 89 (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FOREIGN MINISTRY] [TEXT] THE HONDURAN FOREIGN RELATIONS MINISTRY, BASED ON REPORTS FROM AUTHORITIES IN CHARGE OF SECURITY MATTERS RELATED TO THE INTERROGATION OF CAPTAIN ADAN SOLORZANO MARTINEZ -- AN INTELLIGENCE AGENT OF THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT -- INFORMS THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OF THE FOLLOWING:

IT IS A KNOWN FACT THAT WITH THE INTENSIFICATION OF THE ARMS RACE BY THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT AND THE USE OF NICARAGUAN TERRITORY AS A POLITICAL AND MILITARY BASE FOR SUBVERSIVE GROUPS, THERE HAS BEEN AN INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES, ASSASSINATIONS, TERRORIST ATTACKS, AND OTHER FORMS OF POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND SOCIAL DESTABILIZATION IN THE REGION.

OVER THE PAST 9 YEARS, EL SALVADOR HAS BEEN THE PRIMARY TARGET OF INTERNATIONAL SUBVERSION AND TERRORISM. HONDURAS, HOWEVER, HAS ALSO BEEN AFFECTED BY THESE ACTIONS ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS.

WE RECALL THE DEPLORABLE KIDNAPPING OF 100 PERSONS AT THE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE AND INDUSTRIES IN CORTES IN 1982; THE ILLEGAL HIJACKING OF TAN-SAHSA AIRCRAFT BY TERRORIST COMMANDOS WHO ALWAYS ENDED UP SEEKING REFUGE IN MANAGUA OR HAVANA; THE PLANTING OF TWO BOMBS THAT DESTROYED POWER PLANTS IN TEGUCIGALPA, AS WELL AS OTHER TERRORIST ACTS AGAINST HONDURAS BOTH INSIDE AND OUTSIDE THE COUNTRY; CLANDESTINE ARMS TRAFFICKING, ETC.

ON 27-28 JUNE, THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE WERE SHOCKED BY A STATEMENT MADE IN SAN PEDRO SULA BY A NICARAGUAN CITIZEN WHO, ACCORDING TO HIS STATEMENTS, IS AN ARMY CAPTAIN AND INTELLIGENCE AGENT FOR THE SANDINIST REGIME. HE DISCLOSED THAT, IN AUGUST 1988, HE WAS ASSIGNED THE MISSIONS OF PLANNING THE ASSASSINATION OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND THE BEHEADING OF THE HONDURAN SPIRITUAL AND POLITICAL LEADERSHIP THROUGH THE PHYSICAL ELIMINATION OF HONDURAN ARCHBISHOP MSGR HECTOR ENRIQUE SANTOS AND PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES CARLOS ROBERTO FLORES AND RAFAEL LEONARDO CALLEJAS ROMERO, OF THE LIBERAL AND NATIONAL PARTIES RESPECTIVELY.

THE SANDINIST FOREIGN MINISTRY RESPONDED TO THESE REPORTS BY ISSUING A 29 JULY 1989 COMMUNIQUE, IN WHICH IT OPENLY ADMITTED THAT NICARAGUAN CITIZEN ORLANDO ADAN SOLORZANO MARTINEZ WAS AN ARMY LIEUTENANT -- NOT A CAPTAIN -- AND THAT HE HAD WORKED FOR THE NICARAGUAN INTERIOR MINISTRY FOR 7 AND 1/2 YEARS, FROM 20 AUGUST 1979 TO 28 JANUARY 1987.

THE COMMUNIQUE ADDED THAT ON 28 JANUARY 1987, SOLORZANO HAD BEEN FIRED AND THAT HIS RECORD SHOWED A LONG LIST OF DISCIPLINARY ACTIONS. THIS EXPLANATION VERY CONVENIENTLY ALLOWS NICARAGUA TO DISASSOCIATE ITSELF FROM THE ESPIONAGE AND TERRORIST ACTIVITIES OF ITS INTELLIGENCE AGENT IN THE EVENT HE WAS CAUGHT OR DESERTED. UNDOUBTEDLY, THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT, BECAUSE OF ITS IDEOLOGY AND BECAUSE IT HAS CLOSE TIES TO THE FINANCING AND TRAINING -- BOTH POLITICALLY AND MILITARILY -- OF CENTRAL AMERICAN TERRRORIST GROUPS, HAS BEEN DIRECTLY INVOLVED AT VARIOUS LEVELS IN THESE GROUPS' CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES, WHICH VIOLATE INTERNATIONAL NORMS ON PEACEFUL COEXISTENCE AND HUMAN RIGHTS. THIS SITUATION HAS GIVEN RISE TO THE DIFFERENT PEACE EFFORTS THAT HAVE SPRUNG UP IN THE REGION TO ATTEMPT TO PUT AN END TO THESE ACTIONS. THE HONDURAN SECURITY AUTHORITIES HAVE KNOWN FOR A LONG TIME ABOUT ESPIONAGE ACTIVITIES AGAINST HONDURAS AND THE LINKS BETWEEN NICARAGUAN EMBASSY PERSONNEL IN TEGUCIGALPA AND HONDURAN REBEL GROUPS THAT HAVE BEEN TRAINED IN SPECIAL CAMPS IN NICARAGUA AND OTHER TOTALITARIAN COUNTRIES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0282 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

NO CITY (ARGENTINA), 08 JUL 89 -- [SPEECH] [MENEM] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] OUR MOST PROMISING FUTURE DOES NOT DEPEND ON WHAT WILL HAPPEN, BUT ON WHAT WE WILL BE ABLE TO BUILD TOGETHER, ALL UNITED. THIS IS THE CHALLENGE WE ARGENTINES ARE FACING -- THE CHALLENGE OF BEING ABLE TO TRANSFORM THIS CRISIS INTO A FERTILE SCENARIO.

THIS IS THE TIME FOR REFLECTION AND IMAGINATION. THIS IS THE TIME FOR IDEAS, AS WELL AS FOR CREATIVITY AND BOLDNESS. THIS IS THE TIME TO ELIMINATE WHAT IS DECREPIT AND WELCOME WHAT IS BEGINNING. THIS IS THE TIME FOR CREATIVE BOLDNESS, INNOVATION, AND COURAGE.

THE ARGENTINE PEOPLE HAVE CHOSEN THE PATH OF DEMOCRACY WITH A SOCIAL ACCENT. THE ARGENTINE PEOPLE HAVE CHOSEN LIBERTY AND JUSTICE, PEACE AND DEVELOPMENT.

THE ARGENTINE PEOPLE HAVE OPTED TO TRANSFORM OUR DECADENCE, TO OVERCOME OUR PETTY DISAGREEMENTS, AND TO MOUNT A COLLECTIVE EFFORT.

THE ARGENTINE PEOPLE HAVE VOTED FOR THE EPIC OF NATIONAL UNITY. THEREFORE, OURS IS A GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL UNITY. IN OUR OPINION, NATIONAL UNITY IS NOT STRENGTHENED BY HEGEMONIC PROJECTS, PATERNAL ATTITUDES, PASSIONATE FITS, OR FLEETING EMOTIONS.

GOVERNMENT OF THE PEOPLE, BY THE PEOPLE, AND FOR THE PEOPLE CANNOT DEPEND ON THE MANDATE OF A SINGLE MAN, THE WHIM OF A PARTY, OR THE IMPOSITION OF A SECTOR. APPLAUSE

THE GOVERNMENT OF NATIONAL UNITY IS THE PROPERTY OF ALL ARGENTINES. NO ONE CAN FEEL UNINTERESTED. NO ONE CAN FEEL UNINVITED.

IF ARGENTINA IS NOT OCCUPYING ITS PROPER PLACE, IT IS NOT THE COUNTRY'S BUT ALL ARGENTINES RESPONSIBILITY. IT SHOULD BE BLAMED ON OUR DIVISIONS, HISTORIC BURDENS, IDEOLOGICAL PREJUDICES, AND SECTARIANISMS.

WE HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO FORMULATE AN HONEST BALANCE OF OUR COUNTRY'S VICTORIES AND FAILURES, ITS WEAK AND STRONG POINTS, AND ITS MISTAKES AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS.

THIS IS THE FIRST LESSON WE HAVE ALREADY LEARNED TOGETHER BECAUSE THE TIME OF THE WORST UNDERDEVELOPMENT, THE UNDERDEVELOPMENT OF CONSIDERING THOSE WHO THINK DIFFERENTLY AN ENEMY, HAS ENDED IN THIS COUNTRY. APPLAUSE

THANK GOD, THE COUNTRY WHERE THE LAW OF THE JUNGLE PREVAILED HAS ENDED. THE EXISTENCE OF BOTH AN OFFICIAL COUNTRY AND A SUBMERGED COUNTRY HAS ENDED. THE EXISTENCE OF BOTH A VISIBLE COUNTRY AND A REAL COUNTRY HAS ENDED.

I HAVE COME TO UNITE THOSE TWO ARGENTINAS. I HAVE COME TO STRUGGLE FOR THE RENDEZVOUS OF THOSE TWO FATHERLANDS.

I DO NOT WANT TO BE THE PRESIDENT OF A FACTION, A GROUP, A SECTOR, OR A POLITICAL EXPRESSION. I DO NOT WANT TO BE THE PRESIDENT OF YET ANOTHER FRUSTRATION. I WANT TO BE THE PRESIDENT OF A UNITED ARGENTINA THAT PROGRESSES DESPITE DISSENT. [APPLAUSE]

I WANT TO BE THE PRESIDENT OF THE ARGENTINA OF [JUAN MANUEL DE] ROSAS [A CAUDILLO THAT DOMINATED THE ARGENTINE SCENE 1829-1852] AND [DOMINGO FAUSTINO] SARMIENTO [ARGENTINE PRESIDENT 1868-74], THE ARGENTINA OF [BARTOLOME] MITRE [ARGENTINE PRESIDENT 1862-68] AND FACUNDO QUIROGA, [A CAUDILLO FROM LA RIOJA PROVINCE WHO WAS ASSASSINATED IN 1835] [APPLAUSE], THE ARGENTINA OF ANGEL VICENTE PENALOZA [A CAUDILLO BORN IN LA RIOJA PROVINCE WHO WAS OPPOSED TO CENTRAL CONTROL FROM BUENOS AIRES] AND JUAN BAUTISTA ALBERDI [AN INTELLECTUAL WHO WAS INVOLVED IN DRAFTING THE 1853 CONSTITUTION], THE ARGENTINA OF [CARLOS] PELLEGRINI [ARGENTINE PRESIDENT 1890-92] AND [HIPOLITO] YRIGOYEN [LEADER OF THE RADICAL CIVIC UNION PARTY AND ARGENTINE PRESIDENT 1916-1922 AND 1928-30], AND THE ARGENTINA OF [JUAN DOMINGO] PERON AND [RICARDO] BALBIN [A WELL-KNOWN LEADER OF THE RADICAL CIVIC UNION WHO RAN FOR PRESIDENT IN THE ELECTION OF 23 SEPTEMBER 1973] [APPLAUSE] [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0283 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 9 JUL 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] THE ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY ELN HAS PROMISED TO RELEASE NORWEGIAN ANTHROPOLOGIST BRUCE OLSON WITHIN THE NEXT FEW DAYS. THE ELN HAD KIDNAPPED AND SENTENCED OLSON TO DEATH. ELN MILITARY COMMANDER NICOLAS RODRIGUEZ ANNOUNCED THIS DECISION TO REPORTERS FROM THE SPANISH NEWS AGENCY EFE.

OLSON, A PHILOSOPHER AND ANTHROPOLOGIST, ARRIVED IN COLOMBIA 30 YEARS AGO AND WAS WORKING WITH THE MOTILONES INDIANS IN THE CATATUMBO JUNGLE AT THE TIME OF HIS CAPTURE. HE HAD BUILT 14 SCHOOLS AND SEVERAL HEALTH CENTERS IN THE AREA. HE HAD ALSO WRITTEN SEVERAL BOOKS ON THE MOTILO INDIAN LANGUAGE. THE ELN, HOWEVER, ACCUSED HIM OF BEING A CIA AGENT AND AN EXPLOITER OF THE INDIAN PEOPLE. THE ELN KIDNAPPED OLSON, DECLARED HIM A PRISONER OF WAR, AND SENTENCED HIM TO DEATH. HOWEVER, THIS NIGHTMARE IS NOW OVER. THE ELN HAS PROMISED TO TURN OLSON OVER SAFE AND SOUND TO THE RED CROSS IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS.

IN ADDITION, THE ELN SENT A LETTER TO PRESIDENT BARCO. PARLIAMENTARIANS GUILLERMO ALBERTO GONZALEZ AND ORLANDO GOMEZ WILL DELIVER THE LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT TOMORROW. IN THIS LETTER, THE ELN LISTS ITS DEMANDS, WHICH, IF MET, WOULD LEAD THEM TO HALT THE BLOWING UP OF OIL PIPELINES.

ACCORDING TO GONZALEZ, THE GUERRILLA GROUP DEMANDS THE DISMISSAL OF MINES MINISTER OSCAR MEJIA AND ECOPETROL [COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE] PRESIDENT ANDRES RESTREPO. THE ELN ALSO CONDITIONED THEIR SUSPENSION OF ATTACKS AGAINST THE PIPELINES ON THE CREATION OF A NATIONAL PETROLEUM COUNCIL AND A FORUM FOR A DEBATE TO REVIEW THE CURRENT OIL POLICY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GONZALEZ] MY IMPRESSION DURING MY 2 DAYS OF CAPTIVITY IS THAT THEY ATTACH GREAT IMPORTANCE TO A DEBATE ON THE NATION'S OIL POLICY. THEY DEMAND THAT THIS DEBATE BE CARRIED OUT THROUGH A COUNCIL MEETING, WHICH WOULD INCLUDE REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE GOVERNMENT, LABOR UNIONS -- PARTICULARLY THE (USO) AND ECOPETROL UNIONS -- AS WELL AS SEVERAL PROMINENT FIGURES WHOM THEY LISTED IN THE LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT. [END RECORDING]

GONZALEZ ADDED THAT HE AGREES WITH COMPTROLLER RODOLFO GONZALEZ THAT THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD TALK WITH THE ELN, A GUERRILLA GROUP WHICH IN THE PAST HAS BEEN THE MOST UNWILLING TO JOIN THE PEACE PROCESS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GONZALEZ] IF THE DIALOGUE RESULTS IN A SOLUTION TO COLOMBIA'S PUBLIC UNREST, THEN WE MUST NOT AVOID THE DIALOGUE; WE MUST HOLD IT. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0284 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 10 JUL 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] THE MAYORS OF COCORNA, SAN CARLOS, AND SAN FRANCISCO WERE RELEASED IN THE MUNICIPALITY OF SAN FRANCISCO, ANTIOQUIA, THIS MORNING. THEY WERE KIDNAPPED LAST SATURDAY BY THE ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION [ELN]. OUR REPORTER LAYS VARGAS HAS MORE ON THIS:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VARGAS] THE MAYORS OF COCORNA, SAN CARLOS, AND SAN FRANCISCO WERE RELEASED AT 0430 THIS MORNING ON SAN LORENZO AVENUE OF COCORNA MUNICIPALITY. THEY HAD BEEN KIDNAPPED THIS PAST WEEKEND BY THE ELN. THE PURPOSE OF THE KIDNAPPING WAS TO PUBLICIZE, THROUGH THE MAYORS, A COMMUNIQUE IN WHICH THE REBEL GROUP ANNOUNCES ITS CAMPAIGN WAR FOR LIFE, COMES OUT AGAINST THE DIRTY WAR, AND MAKES A NEW CALL FOR A NATIONAL OIL FORUM FOR VARIOUS POLITICAL AND LABOR ORGANIZATIONS TO DISCUSS THE STATUS OF THIS VITAL PRODUCT OF OUR ECONOMY. THE ELN HOPES TO PRESENT THROUGH THIS FORUM ITS VIEWS ON OIL POLICY.

[MAYOR NEVARDO MORALES] THEY ASSURED US THAT NOTHING WOULD HAPPEN TO US, THAT EVERYTHING WOULD BE ALL RIGHT BECAUSE THIS WAS ONLY PART OF A CAMPAIGN THEY ARE WAGING CALLED THE WAR FOR LIFE. THEY KIDNAPPED ME AND TOOK ME TO THEIR CAMP.

[VARGAS] WHAT IS IN THE COMMUNIQUE, MAYOR?

[MORALES] THE COMMUNIQUE IS BEING HELD BY THE MAYOR OF SAN CARLOS. IN ANY EVENT, WE WANT TO SPEAK TO THE GOVERNMENT SECRETARY TOMORROW OR THIS AFTERNOON TO GIVE HIM THE COMMUNIQUE. WE DO NOT KNOW WHEN IT WILL BE POSSIBLE TO SPEAK TO HIM.

[VARGAS] IN THE COMING HOURS, THE MAYORS OF COCORNA, SAN FRANCISCO, AND SAN CARLOS WILL TRAVEL TO MEDELLIN TO MEET WITH THE GOVERNMENT SECRETARY. TOMORROW THEY PLAN TO HOLD A NEWS CONFERENCE DURING WHICH THEY WILL PRESENT THE COMMUNIQUE GIVEN TO THEM BY THE ELN. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0285 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

MOSCOW (USSR), 9 JUL 89 (IZVESTIYA) -- [REPORT] [A. CHEREPANOV, MEXICO CITY CORRESPONDENT] [TEXT] AS IZVESTIYA HAS ALREADY REPORTED, ON 5 JULY AT 1000 HOURS LOCAL [PERU] TIME, A BUS WITH SOVIET SEAMEN ON BOARD WAS BLOWN UP BY A BOMB. AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION 20 PEOPLE WERE INJURED, OF WHOM 17 WERE HOSPITALIZED, 3 OF THEM IN A SERIOUS CONDITION.

OUR MEXICO CITY CORRESPONDENT A. CHEREPANOV CALLED EMBASSY AND MINISTRY OF THE FISHING INDUSTRY REPRESENTATIVES IN LIMA. HERE ARE THE ADDITIONAL DETAILS HE MANAGED TO OBTAIN. ON THE MORNING OF 5 JULY A GROUP OF 52 PEOPLE IN TWO BUSES VISITED THE "ALBATROS" STORE, AS IS THE CUSTOM AMONG OFF-DUTY CREWS FROM SOVIET FISHING VESSELS WORKING IN PERUVIAN COASTAL WATERS. THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED ON ONE OF THE BUSES AS IT WAS ABOUT TO LEAVE.

FORTUNATELY, THE BOMB WAS HOMEMADE AND NOT THAT POWERFUL. AND IT HAD OBVIOUSLY BEEN HASTILY PLANTED (ACCORDING TO WITNESSES, FOUR SUSPICIOUS CHARACTERS HAD BEEN HANGING AROUND THE BUS). THE PASSENGERS WERE INJURED MAINLY BY PIECES OF BROKEN GLASS.

THE POLICE AND EMERGENCY SERVICES WERE ON THE SCENE IMMEDIATELY. NEARLY ALL THE CASUALTIES WERE IMMEDIATELY HOSPITALIZED. IT IS TRUE THAT AT FIRST THERE WAS A MIXUP IN THE HOSPITAL OVER RUSSIAN NAMES -- IT TOOK THE DOCTORS A WHILE TO WORK OUT WHICH PHOTOGRAPH BELONGED TO WHOM. REPRESENTATIVES OF THE SOVIET EMBASSY AND CONSULATE CAME TO THEIR AID. ON THE SAME DAY SKILLED OPERATIONS WERE CARRIED OUT ON ALL THOSE WHO REQUIRED THEM. THE IZVESTIYA CORRESPONDENT WAS OFFICIALLY INFORMED THAT THE SERIOUSLY INJURED SOVIET SEAMEN WERE OUT OF DANGER. THEIR FAMILIES HAD BEEN INFORMED.

THE PERUVIAN PRESS BELIEVES THAT THE TERRORIST ACT CARRIED OUT AGAINST SOVIET CITIZENS WAS THE WORK OF THE MAOIST-INCLINED LEFTIST ARMED GROUPING "SENDERO LUMINOSO." BUT THERE IS ANOTHER VERSION: IT MIGHT HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT BY ULTRARIGHTISTS OPPOSING THE FISHING AGREEMENTS SIGNED BETWEEN PERU AND THE USSR.

DEV-MUC3-0286 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

MOSCOW (USSR), 7 JUL 89 (IZVESTIYA) -- [REPORT] [V. ZAYKIN] [TEXT] THIRTYTHREE SOVIET SEAMEN HAVE BEEN INJURED IN THE PERUVIAN PORT OF CALLAO AS A RESULT OF AN EXPLOSION CAUSED BY A BOMB PLANTED UNDER A BUS STANDING IN THE STREET.

OUR CORRESPONDENT TELEPHONED THE USSR MINISTRY OF THE FISH INDUSTRY AND ASKED FOR INFORMATION ON THE INCIDENT.

"IT HAPPENED ON 5 JULY AT 1010 HOURS LOCAL TIME," S. SVINARENKO, DEPUTY CHIEF OF THE USSR MINISTRY OF THE FISH INDUSTRY FOREIGN RELATIONS ADMINISTRATION DEPARTMENT, SAID. "SIXTEEN SEAMEN HAD TO BE HOSPITALIZED. FORTUNATELY, NO ONE WAS SERIOUSLY HURT. THE SEAMEN MAINLY SUFFERED FRACTURES, CUTS, AND BURNS. THE VICTIMS WERE MEMBERS OF THE CREWS OF TWO LARGE, AUTONOMOUS TRAWLERS -- THE 'VLADIMIR KURASOV' AND THE 'LAZURNYY' -- WHO WERE ON SHORE LEAVE THAT DAY.

"OUR SEAMEN ARE WORKING IN THIS REGION ON THE BASIS OF AN AGREEMENT ON COOPERATION BETWEEN PERU AND THE SOVIET UNION. WE ASSIST THE PERUVIANS IN THE DEVELOPMENT OF THEIR FISHING INDUSTRY, GET OUR SHIPS REPAIRED IN LOCAL PORTS, AND FISH WITHIN A 200-MILE ZONE OF THAT COUNTRY...."

REUTER AND AFP HAVE REPORTED THAT, IN THE OPINION OF THE CALLAO POLICE, THE EXPLOSION WAS ORGANIZED BY THE "SENDERO LUMINOSO," A REBEL GROUP OF MAOIST PERSUASION. "THERE IS ABSOLUTELY NO DOUBT THAT THIS ACT, WHICH DESERVES TO BE CONDEMNED, WAS DIRECTED AGAINST TOTALLY INNOCENT CITIZENS," PERUVIAN FOREIGN MINISTER GUILLERMO LARCO COX SAID.

THE SOVIET SEAMEN WERE ON A BUS WHICH HAD STOPPED AT A STORE WHEN THE BOMB, PLANTED UNDER AN EMPTY BUS STANDING NEARBY, WAS DETONATED.

ACCORDING TO EYE WITNESSES, FOUR YOUNG PEOPLE WEARING SCHOOL UNIFORM WERE SEEN AT THE SCENE OF THE INCIDENT A FEW MOMENTS BEFORE THE EXPLOSION, PLACING A PACKAGE UNDER THE BUS.

"SENDERO LUMINOSO" IS AN EXTREME LEFT-WING REBEL ORGANIZATION WAGING A GUERRILLA WAR AGAINST THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT.

"SENDERO LUMINOSO" HAS BEEN IN EXISTENCE FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS. IT BEGAN ITS ARMED STRUGGLE IN 1980. SINCE THEN, PERU HAS KNOWN NO PEACE. REPORTS OF MURDERS AND ACTS OF SABOTAGE COMMITTED BY THIS ORGANIZATION ARE APPEARING WITH INCREASING FREQUENCY IN THE WORLD PRESS. THE TERRORISTS' VICTIMS ARE POLITICIANS, MEMBERS OF THE POLICE FORCE, SOLDIERS, PEASANTS.... THE TERRORISTS OFTEN INVOLVE JUVENILES IN THEIR ACTS OF SABOTAGE.

THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN FORCED TO RELY MORE AND MORE EXTENSIVELY ON THE ARMED FORCES IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THIS TERRORIST ORGANIZATION. BUT SO FAR THIS HAS FAILED TO PRODUCE TANGIBLE RESULTS.

DEV-MUC3-0287 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 10 JUL 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] AFTER SPENDING 130 DAYS ABROAD, BERNARDO JARAMILLO, PRESIDENT OF THE LEFT-WING PATRIOTIC UNION (UP), RETURNED TO COLOMBIA TODAY TO URGE THE CASTROITE ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) TO JOIN THE PEACE PROCESS BEING PROMOTED BY THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT.

JARAMILLO, A 35-YEAR-OLD LEGISLATOR, REPLACED JAIME PARDO LEAL AS UP PRESIDENT AFTER PARDO LEAL WAS ASSASSINATED IN OCTOBER 1987. JARAMILLO HAD LEFT THE COUNTRY AFTER RECEIVING MANY DEATH THREATS.

THE ELN IS THE ONLY COLOMBIAN SUBVERSIVE GROUP THAT REFUSES TO ACCEPT THE PEACE PROPOSALS FORMULATED BY THE ADMINISTRATION OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO AND INSTEAD HAS INCREASED ITS ATTACKS ON THE COUNTRY'S PETROLEUM INSTALLATIONS TO DEMAND THE NATIONALIZATION OF THAT INDUSTRY.

JARAMILLO ASKED THE ELN TO STOP ITS VIOLENT ACTIONS, WHICH, HE SAID, DO NOT IN ANY WAY BENEFIT COLOMBIA.

THE LEFTIST LEADER SAID HE IS WELL INFORMED ABOUT THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL DEVELOPMENT AND ADDED THAT "THE SOCIAL AND POLITICAL ENVIRONMENT HAS IMPROVED."

THE BARCO ADMINISTRATION, HE SAID, HAS BEGUN TO TAKE MEASURES TO PROTECT CITIZENS.

"MORE SECURITY MEASURES ARE NEEDED, BUT SOME MEASURES ARE BEING ADOPTED," JARAMILLO SAID. HE STRESSED THAT IF ALL THE SUBVERSIVE GROUPS DECIDE TO HOLD A SINCERE DIALOGUE FOR PEACE, IT WOULD BE VERY POSITIVE FOR THE COUNTRY.

DEV-MUC3-0290 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 13 JUL 89 (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [INTERVIEW WITH COLONEL ERIC SANCHEZ, COMMANDER OF 4TH INFANTRY BATTALION, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [SANCHEZ] GOOD MORNING, HRN [VOZ DE HONDURAS] LISTENERS. I AM A BIT CONCERNED OVER WHAT I HAVE HEARD ON THIS RADIO STATION. THE TRUTH IS THAT AT APPROXIMATELY 0030 TODAY, THERE WAS AN ATTACK WITH A HOMEMADE BOMB IN LA CEIBA, AND, AS A RESULT, SEVEN U.S. SOLDIERS -- NOT SIX -- WERE WOUNDED. FOUR SUSTAINED VERY MINOR INJURIES, WHILE THREE WERE SOMEWHAT SERIOUSLY WOUNDED, BUT THEY ARE NOT IN DANGER OF DYING. NINE SOLDIERS WERE IN THAT GROUP. THEY WERE NOT ON LEAVE; THEY WERE ON A MISSION FROM THE ENRIQUE SOTO CANO HONDURAN AIR BASE AT PALMEROLA.

THEY PROVOKED... [CHANGES THOUGHT]. INSTEAD, I SHOULD SAY THAT THEY WENT TO HAVE SOME FUN AT THE DILIDO DISCOTEQUE. OUR MILITARY POLICE PATROLS WERE IN THE AREA AND SAW THE ATTACK. WE CAPTURED TWO SUSPECTS. OUR MEN WERE ABOUT 100 METERS AWAY WHEN THE ATTACK OCCURRED, AND, UNFORTUNATELY, THE TWO SUSPECTS ARE U.S. CITIZENS. IN OTHER WORDS, PEOPLE WERE IN THE AREA AND NO ONE KNEW WHAT THEY WERE DOING. THIS IS AN OFFICIAL REPORT; THIS IS WHAT TOOK PLACE IN LA CEIBA. THE TWO SUSPECTS WERE ARRESTED, AND THEY MUST KNOW SOMETHING ABOUT THE SEVEN WHO WERE WOUNDED, WHO ARE AT THE [WORD INDISTINCT] HOSPITAL. WHAT YOU REPORTED OVER THE RADIO IS CORRECT. THERE IS NO NEED TO BE ALARMED. IT WAS A HOMEMADE BOMB, AND THE DAMAGE WAS CAUSED BY THE SHRAPNEL, CEMENT, AND STONES THAT WERE THROWN INTO THE AIR BY THE EXPLOSION.

HOWEVER, I WOULD LIKE TO DENY A REPORT BY THE MILKMAN FROM [WORD INDISTINCT], WHO SAID THAT THE CITY HAS BEEN SHUT DOWN AND IS BEING HELD HOSTAGE. THAT IS NOT TRUE. WHEN THE INCIDENT OCCURRED, [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE PATROLS WERE ALREADY ON THE STREETS AND REPORTED THE INCIDENT. FUSEP [THE PUBLIC SECURITY FORCE] WAS INSTRUCTED TO CONDUCT INVESTIGATIONS, AND THEREFORE VEHICLES ENTERING OR LEAVING LA CEIBA WERE STOPPED AND SEARCHED. THAT IS ALL; STANDSTILL MERELY BECAUSE THREE OR FOUR PEOPLE HAVE BEEN WOUNDED, OR BECAUSE TWO OR THREE ARE CRITICALLY WOUNDED.

THE CITY MUST FUNCTION NORMALLY. THE ARMED FORCES ARE INTERESTED IN THE CONTINUATION OF PRODUCTION. SO THE MAN FROM [WORD INDISTINCT] WHO CALLED AND SAID THAT HE WAS LOSING 100,000 LEMPIRAS [AS A RESULT OF THE VEHICLE SEARCHES] THIS MORNING WAS TELLING A LIE. WE GAVE SPECIFIC INSTRUCTIONS THAT THE INSPECTION OF VEHICLES SHOULD BE CARRIED UNTIL 0500, AND THAT THE VEHICLES SHOULD NOT BE DETAINED.

[REPORTER] COLONEL, IT WAS THE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE PRESIDENT WHO PROVIDED THE REPORT AND SAID THAT THE DELIVERY OF MILK HAD BEEN STOPPED.

[SANCHEZ] WITH ALL DUE RESPECT FOR HIM -- WHOM I DO NOT KNOW PERSONALLY -- I MUST SAY THAT IT IS NOT TRUE THAT WE ARE STOPPING VEHICLES [AS HEARD]. WE STOPPED A VERY SMALL WHITE VAN WITH SOME LABORERS IN IT TO SEARCH THE VAN. I WAS THERE ON THE HIGHWAY. THERE WAS NO MILK ON THAT BUS; THERE WERE PEOPLE ON THAT BUS, AND I MYSELF ALLOWED THEM TO CONTINUE. I AM SORRY THAT THE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE HAS BEEN MISINFORMED. WE ARE NOT PARALYZING ACTIVITIES, NOR ARE WE HOLDING THE CITY HOSTAGE. AS I SAID, WE ARE TRYING TO CONDUCT AN INVESTIGATION AND WE HAVE ARRESTED TWO PEOPLE. WE ARE NOT SURE IF THEY WERE THE ONES WHO PERPETRATED THE ATTACK; WE ARE NOT SURE OF ANYTHING. WE ARE MERELY CONDUCTING INVESTIGATIONS AND TAKING PREVENTIVE MEASURES.

[REPORTER] COLONEL, ARE THE TWO MEN YOU HAVE IN CUSTODY THE SAME U.S. CITIZENS YOU MENTIONED AT THE BEGINNING OF THIS REPORT?

[SANCHEZ] YES. THE LIEUTENANT IN CHARGE OF THE PATROL [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE PANTS, CLOTHES, AND THE COLOR OF WHAT THEY WERE WEARING INDICATED THAT THEY WERE CIVILIANS. LIEUTENANT SALGADO OF THE 4TH BATTALION WAS 50 METERS AWAY WHEN THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED. TWO PERSONS WERE CAPTURED. HOWEVER, THEY HAVE DENIED THAT EITHER OF THEM WAS INVOLVED. THAT REMAINS TO BE SEEN. WE HAVE BEEN WAITING FOR ABOUT 30 MINUTES FOR THE ARMED FORCES INVESTIGATIVE PERSONNEL TO ARRIVE TO LEARN THE IDENTITIES OF THE TWO MEN WHO ARE BEING HELD. THE INVESTIGATION WILL BE COMPLETELY PROFESSIONAL. WE [WORDS INDISTINCT] TWO OR THREE PERSONS WERE INJURED. WE ARE NOT PARALYZING PRODUCTION; I WANT TO MADE THIS CLEAR.

[REPORTER] YES, OF COURSE. COLONEL, GIVEN THE SITUATION, DO YOU BELIEVE THAT THE SITUATION IN THE ARMED FORCES IS COMPLETELY NORMAL?

[SANCHEZ] OF COURSE IT IS COMPLETELY NORMAL. WE ARE NOT RESTRICTING ANYONE'S FREEDOM. WHEN IT GETS DARK, WE WILL PROCEED TO ASK FOR IDENTIFICATION PAPERS; WE WILL STOP AND CHECK VEHICLES, WHICH IS NORMAL IN THIS TYPE OF SITUATION. HOWEVER, AT NO TIME WILL WE PARALYZE PRODUCTION OR NORMAL DAILY ACTIVITIES. WE ARE TRYING TO FIND THE CULPRITS RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS ATTACK. REGARDLESS OF WHETHER IT WAS AN ATTACK AGAINST U.S. CITIZENS, IT WAS CERTAINLY AN ATTACK AGAINST PEACE AND ORDER. WE THEREFORE HAVE TO INVESTIGATE IT, REGARDLESS OF WHETHER OR NOT IT INVOLVED U.S. CITIZENS. IN THIS CASE, AND IN VIEW OF THIS SITUATION, I PERSONALLY ISSUED ORDERS AND FOLLOWED THE INVESTIGATION UNTIL 0500, WHEN I SUSPENDED ALL OPERATIONS. I PERSONALLY ORDERED THESE MEASURES. I AM AMAZED THAT THE CATTLEMEN DO NOT TRANSPORT MILK BEFORE 0500.

[REPORTER] ONE LAST QUESTION ON THIS MATTER: IS THE SITUATION IN LA CEIBA RELATED TO THE LATEST VIOLENT INCIDENTS IN SAN PEDRO SULA?

[SANCHEZ] I BELIEVE SO. A SERIES OF CRIMINAL ACTIONS HAS BEEN LAUNCHED AGAINST SOCIAL PEACE IN HONDURAS. THIS STATION'S LISTENERS AND LISTENERS OF ALL OTHER HONDURAN RADIO STATIONS KNOW THE HIGH - CALIBER OF THE ARMED FORCES PERSONNEL, BEGINNING WITH THE TOP COMMANDERS AND CONTINUING WITH OFFICERS DOWN THE CHAIN OF COMMAND. WE ARE SENSITIVE TO SOCIAL ISSES AND ARE NOT MOTIVATED BY VESTED INTERESTS OF ANY KIND. I BELIEVE THAT THESE ACTS OF BLOODSHED, WHICH ARE [WORDS INDISTINCT], ARE PART OF A SERIES OF FULLY PLANNED, COLDLY CALULATED ACTIONS.

I DO NOT WANT TO SOUND LIKE A COMIC STRIP CHARACTER, BUT I BELIEVE THAT THESE ACTIONS ARE CONNECTED AND OVERLAP. I HAVE THE IMPRESSION THAT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE ARE WITNESSING THE EMERGENCE OF THE SO-CALLED WHITE HANDS AND BLACK HANDS [DEATH SQUADS], WHICH CONCERN US VERY MUCH. WE ARE TALKING ABOUT HONDURANS KILLING HONDURANS.

[REPORTER] THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR KINDNESS TO THIS STATION. WE WILL BE CONTACTING YOU DURING THE NEXT FEW HOURS TO LEARN THE RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS INTO THIS HOMEMADE BOMB ATTACK IN LA CEIBA.

[SANCHEZ] WE ARE COMPLETELY AT YOUR SERVICE. WE ARE WILLING TO OFFER YOU INFORMATION AS IT COMES IN. WE ARE A COMPLETELY OPEN, NOT CLOSED, ORGANIZATION. WE WILL GIVE YOU TRUTHFUL, FACTUAL INFORMATION FOR THE BENEFIT OF ALL HONDURANS.

[REPORTER] THANK YOU AND GOOD MORNING, COLONEL.

DEV-MUC3-0291 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 13 JUL 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] TEN PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN COLOMBIA DURING A THWARTED ATTACK AGAINST PATIOTIC UNION COUNCILMAN GONZALO ALVAREZ HENAO IN MEDELLIN. THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE IN THE EL PEDREGAL NEIGHBORHOOD, BELLO MUNICIPALITY, IN THE NORTHERN PART OF ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT'S CAPITAL CITY. AUTHORITIES REPORT THAT ALL THOSE KILLED BELONGED TO A GROUP OF HIRED ASSASSINS. TWO POLICEMEN WERE AMONG THOSE KILLED. OUR REPORTER LAYS VARGAS HAS THIS REPORT:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VARGAS] THE ASSAILANTS ARRIVED AT THE COUNCILMAN'S HOME IN SEVERAL VEHICLES. THEY OPENED FIRE ON THE HOUSE. GONZALO ALVAREZ' BODYGUARDS REPELLED THE ASSAILANTS AND THE COUNCILMAN ESCAPED UNHARMED. A POLICE PATROL IN THE AREA HEARD THE SHOOTOUT AND HELPED SEARCH FOR THE ASSAILANTS. THE SEARCH WAS CONDUCTED IN THE AREA BETWEEN THE EL PEDREGAL AND LA CABANA NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE AREA BETWEEN MEDELLIN AND BELLO.

THE PAID ASSASSINS CLASHED WITH AUTHORITIES FOR ALMOST 3 HOURS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE NORTHWESTERN COMMUNITY. SOME OF THE ASSAILANTS SOUGHT REFUGE IN A LA CABANA NEIGHBORHOOD HOME. THE POLICE ARRIVED AT THE HOME AND A LONG SHOOT-OUT ENSUED, RESULTING IN THE DEATHS OF THE PAID ASSASSINS. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0294 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 JUL 89 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [EXCERPTS] THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAVE BANNED ENTRANCE INTO THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR CAMPUS AND ARE THREATENING TO FIRE ON ANYONE WHO DISOBEYS THIS ORDER. THIS AFTERNOON, THE ARMY ALLOWED NEITHER VEHICLES NOR STUDENTS TO ENTER THE UNIVERSITY CAMPUS. ACCORDING TO MILITARY OFFICIALS, ORDERS WERE GIVEN TO SHOOT ANYONE WHO DISOBEYED BY ATTEMPTING TO ENTER THE UNIVERSITY CAMPUS. THE MEASURE WENT INTO EFFECT AT 1730. THE SITUATION GREW TENSE WHEN PRIVATE CARS ATTEMPTED TO ENTER THE CAMPUS GROUNDS.

UNIVERSITY OFFICIALS MET WITH THE MILITARY. ACCORDING TO THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND, SINCE 23 DECEMBER 1988, THE MILITARY HAS NOT ALLOWED WEAPONS TO BE INTRODUCED INTO OR TAKEN OUT OF THE UNIVERSITY CAMPUS. THE DISCUSSION ON WHETHER TO ALLOW THE ENTRANCE OF STUDENTS AND VEHICLES BECAME HEATED. UNIVERSITY GENERAL MANAGER MARIO ALFREDO CABRERA SAID THAT THIS MEASURE IS INTENDED TO SHUT DOWN THE UNIVERSITY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CABRERA] ALL OF THIS FALLS UNDER THE GENERAL CAMPAIGN OF PSYCHOLOGICAL AGGRESSION AGAINST THE UNIVERSITY TO MINIMIZE ITS AUTHORITY IN LIGHT OF ITS ROLE AS THE GOVERNMENT'S AND THE NATION'S CONSCIENCE, WHICH OFFICIALS -- WHO ARE NOT LEADING THE COUNTRY ALONG THE CORRECT PATH -- DO NOT LIKE. WE BELIEVE THAT THIS IS THE BASIC REASON BEHIND THIS AND OTHER MEASURES. THESE MEASURES INCLUDE HELICOPTERS OVERFLYING THE CAMPUS AT VERY LOW ALTITUDES AND SOLDIERS THREATENING TO SHOOT TO KILL IF THE ORDER IS DISOBEYED. [END RECORDING]

SINCE THE MILITARY BLOCKADE WENT INTO EFFECT, SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS HAVE BEEN OVERFLYING THE CAMPUS.

DEV-MUC3-0295 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

CLANDESTINE, 15 JUL 89 (RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THIS IS OUR WAR BULLETIN FROM THE MODESTO RAMIREZ CENTRAL FRONT IN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

ON 15 JULY, GUERRILLAS BEGAN THE OPERATION CALLED WE WILL DEFEAT ARENA'S [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] DICTATORSHIP BY HITTING THE PUPPET ARMY. THIS OPERATION WAS CARRIED OUT AGAINST TWO POSITIONS OF THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE'S AZMITIA BATTALION STATIONED IN CHALATENANGO, SPECIFICALLY AGAINST AN IRA [INSTITUTE OF SUPPLY REGULATION] CENTER IN SAN JOSE EL CARAO, EL PARAISO. THIS IS HOW THE OPERATION WAS CARRIED OUT:

SIMULTANEOUS ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT ON THREE OF THE ARMY'S FORTIFIED PERIPHERAL DEFENSE POSITIONS. ONE OF THESE POSITIONS WAS COMPLETELY DESTROYED, RESULTING IN 11 OF THE ENEMY KILLED. FOUR ADDITIONAL CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED ON THE ENEMY IN THE THREE OTHER DEFENSE FORTIFICATIONS, WHICH WERE ALSO DESTROYED.

WE ALSO ATTACKED THE MAIN SUPPLY CENTER FACILITIES AND STORMED THREE DEFENSIVE POSITIONS IN THE INTERIOR. AS A RESULT OF THIS ATTACK, FOUR OF THE ENEMY WERE KILLED AND FIVE WERE WOUNDED. IN ADDITION, WE DESTROYED THE OFFICES AND A GRAIN DRYER AND DAMAGED THE STORAGE BINS AND GRAIN STORAGE AREAS. WE CONCLUDED THE ATTACK BY SETTING THE ENTIRE FACILITY ON FIRE.

THE FOLLOWING MILITARY EQUIPMENT WAS SEIZED FROM THE ENEMY DURING THIS VICTORIOUS OPERATION: 3 M-16 RIFLES, 3 FULL SETS [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED], 1 M-79 GRENADE LAUNCHER WITH 9 GRENADES, 550 5.56-MM ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION, 2 100-CARTRIDGE M-60 AMMUNITION BELTS, UNIFORMS, BOOTS, AND OTHER MILITARY SUPPLIES.

ONE HOUR AFTER THE ATTACK BEGAN, THE ENEMY WAS REINFORCED BY A ROCKET-FIRING HELICOPTER, ONE PUSH-PULL O-2 AIRCRAFT, AND ONE C-47 AIRCRAFT. IN ADDITION, THE ENEMY RECEIVED ARTILLERY SUPPORT FROM THE AREAS ABOVE THE INSTALLATIONS UNDER ATTACK, BUT THIS FIRE AND THE AIR SUPPORT WERE INEFFECTIVE. THE C-47 AIRCRAFT STRAFED LAS PENAS, WITH COMPLETE DISREGARD FOR THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, A REPRESSIVE ACTION WE VEHEMENTLY DENOUNCE.

LATER, AT 0300, THE ENEMY TROOPS WERE REINFORCED BY TWO ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS AND FOUR MILITARY TRUCKS, WHICH TOOK TROOPS TO A PLACE NEAR THE IRA INSTALLATION. THESE REINFORCEMENTS WERE QUICKLY NEUTRALIZED BY OUR RIFLE FIRE. IN ADDITION, THE OPERATION INCLUDED A LARGE NUMBER OF MILITIAMEN AND REBEL TROOPS, WHO ERECTED ROADBLOCKS ON THE STREETS OF NUEVA CONCEPCION, BLEW UP SIX TELEPHONE POSTS, PLACED A LARGE BANNER ACROSS THE STREET, AND DISTRIBUTED PROPAGANDA. OTHER PROPAGANDA ACTIVITIES OCCURRED IN SAN JOSE PATARES, LA SIEMBRE, GUAYABITO, AND HORCONES IN LA PALMA JUSRISDICTION.

IN ALL, WE INFLICTED 24 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING DEAD AND WOUNDED, ON THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE; HOWEVER, WE LOST COMRADE OTONIEL IN THE ATTACK.

DEV-MUC3-0296 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 17 JUL 89 (VENEZOLANA DE TELEVISION CANAL 8) -- [INTERVIEW WITH VENEZUELAN DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL FILMO LOPEZ UZCATEGUI BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [LOPEZ] WE HAVE REPORTS THAT NORBERTO RODRIGUEZ [PRESIDENT PEREZ' BROTHER-IN-LAW] COULD STILL BE IN THE BORDER REGION, NEAR THE SPOT WHERE HE WAS KIDNAPPED BY THOSE PEOPLE. WE DO NOT KNOW WHO THE KIDNAPPERS ARE. WE ARE WORKING ON THIS.

[REPORTER] HAVE YOU STEPPED UP SURVEILLANCE IN THE AREA? HAS FINDING THE STATION WAGON GIVEN YOU ANY CLUES?

[LOPEZ] YES, OF COURSE, WE ARE LOOKING INTO THIS. THE COLOMBIAN POLICE HAVE THE INFORMATION AND ARE WORKING BASED ON THIS.

[REPORTER] WHAT ABOUT A RANSOM? HAS THE VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT BEEN CONTACTED?

[LOPEZ] THERE HAS BEEN NO CONTACT. WE ARE HOPING THERE WILL BE A CONTACT SO THAT WE CAN PROCEED FROM THERE.

[REPORTER] IS IT TRUE A RANSOM HAS BEEN DEMANDED?

[LOPEZ] I HAVE NO PROOF OF THAT. I DO NOT HAVE THAT INFORMATION.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE MOST RECENT INFORMATION THE VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT HAS RECEIVED?

[LOPEZ] WE WERE BRIEFED ON THE WORK BEING COORDINATED WITH THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES. WE ARE WORKING VERY CLOSELY WITH THEM, LIKE BROTHERS. THE TWO ARMIES AND THE AUTHORITIES ARE WORKING TOGETHER.

[REPORTER] IF A RANSOM IS DEMANDED, IS THE GOVERNMENT WILLING TO PAY IT?

[LOPEZ] I CANNOT ANSWER THAT QUESTION; THAT WOULD DEPEND ON RODRIGUEZ' FAMILY.

[REPORTER] THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS MUCH EXPERIENCE WITH KIDNAPPINGS. WHAT DO THEY SAY ABOUT THIS CASE? WHAT DO THEY THINK THE OUTCOME WILL BE?

[LOPEZ] WE ALWAYS WORK BASED ON OUR EXPERIENCE WITH SIMILAR CASES. THIS KIDNAPPING COULD HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT BY THE REBELS, AND WE ALREADY KNOW HOW THE REBELS OPERATE. HE ALSO COULD HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED BY COMMON CRIMINALS. EVEN THOUGH IT MAY SEEM THAT THE CASE WOULD BE HANDLED SIMILARLY IN BOTH INSTANCES, IT IS NOT SO. WE ARE GOING TO WAIT A BIT LONGER. WE BELIEVE WE MAY GET MORE INFORMATION TODAY.

[REPORTER] IT IS NOT VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT POLICY TO PAY RANSOM IN CASES SUCH AS THIS ONE. WILL AN EXCEPTION BE MADE IN THIS CASE?

[LOPEZ] I BELIEVE WE SHOULD FOLLOW OUR POLICY. THERE ARE MEANS THAT CAN BE USED TO REACH AN UNDERSTANDING; THIS WOULD HAPPEN ONCE WE HAVE SPECIFIC INFORMATION.

DEV-MUC3-0298 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SANTIAGO, 18 JUL 89 (TELEVISION NACIONAL DE CHILE NETWORK) -- [TEXT] INTERIOR MINISTER CARLOS CACERES TODAY STATED THAT THE GANG-STYLE ACTION AKEN YESTERDAY BY SOME PEOPLE TO OCCUPY PRIVATE PROPERTY WILL NOT INTIMIDATE THE GOVERNMENT.

[BEGIN CACERES RECORDING] YESTERDAY, A WELL-ORGANIZED GROUP OF APPROXIMATELY 300 PEOPLE ATTEMPTED TO USURP PRIVATE PROPERTY USING MOLOTOV COCKTAILS, STONES AND FIREARMS. THEIR ACTION CAUSED ONE UNFORTUNATE DEATH, INJURIES, AND DAMAGE -- WHICH WERE REPORTED EARLIER -- TO THE DETRIMENT OF A LARGE NUMBER OF POOR FAMILIES.

IT IS PUBLICLY EVIDENT THAT THE COMMUNISTS AND THEIR CLOSEST ALLIES WERE BEHIND THE PREPARATION, COORDINATION AND EXECUTION OF THESE CRIMINALS ACTIONS.

UNFORTUNATELY, ONE CANNOT FAIL TO LINK THESE ACTIONS TO THE THREATENING, VIOLENT SPEECHES -- FOLLOWING THE STYLE USED BY THE POPULAR UNITY MEMBERS -- WITH WHICH SOME LEADERS OF THE OPPOSITION COALITION OPENED THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN OF THEIR CANDIDATE PATRICIO AYLWIN.

IT IS EVEN POSSIBLE TO REGARD THESE AGGRESSIONS AS SIGNALS AND WARNINGS OF THE INCONSISTENCIES AND CONTRADICTIONS THAT EXIST WITHIN SOME POLITICAL UMBRELLA GROUPS. THESE GROUPS CONSIST OF SECTORS ADVOCATING A PEACEFUL DEMOCRATIC COEXISTENCE ON THE ONE HAND, AND OTHER SECTORS THAT FOLLOW THE LINE OF THOSE WHO IN THE PAST DESTROYED OUR TRADITIONAL WAY OF LIFE ON THE OTHER HAND.

ALTHOUGH THE GOVERNMENT HAS STATED ITS DECISION NOT TO GET INVOLVED IN THE POLITICAL CAMPAIGN, IT CANNOT FAIL TO ANNOUNCE ITS POSITION AND TO STATE ITS OUTRIGHT REJECTION OF A MALICIOUS AND DEMAGOGICAL RHETORIC THAT POSES A THREAT TO PUBLIC TRANQUILLITY.

UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES WILL THE GOVERNMENT YIELD TO THOSE WHO TIME AND AGAIN SEEK AND PROMOTE SUBVERSION AND TO DISRUPT OUR DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONAL ORDER. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0299 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

CLANDESTINE, 18 JUL 89 (RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] CONCERNING MONDAY'S INCIDENTS NEAR EL SALVADOR UNIVERSITY, THE FMLN STATES:

1. NONE OF OUR UNITS WERE OPERATING AROUND EL SALVADOR UNIVERSITY OR THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE CAPITAL ON THAT DAY.

2. THE CLASHES THAT OCCURRED NEAR THE UNIVERSITY WERE CARRIED OUT BY ARMED FORCES TROOPS ALONE. IN AN EFFORT TO SEARCH THE UNIVERSITY, THE TROOPS FIRED THEIR WEAPONS [WORDS INDISTINCT] AS STUDENT DEMONSTRATORS WERE ENTERING THE CAMPUS.

3. THIS ACTION IS PART OF A PLAN THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE TOP COMMAND OF THE ARMED FORCES ARE PROMOTING AGAINST EL SALVADOR UNIVERSITY. THIS PLAN IS BEING CARRIED OUT BY COLONEL FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES, COMMANDER OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE. THE PLAN INVOLVES THREATS, ARRESTS, MURDERS, AND OTHER REPRESSIVE ACTS.

4. IT IS PREDICTABLE THAT THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE TOP COMMAND OF THE ARMED FORCES WILL SAY THAT WHAT OCCURRED AT THE UNIVERSITY WAS THE RESULT OF A CLASH BETWEEN THE ARMY AND THE FMLN, AND THIS IS COMPLETELY FALSE. CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE SOLELY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE VIOLENT INCIDENTS THAT CLAIMED SEVERAL VICTIMS IN THE AREA AROUND EL SALVADOR UNIVERSITY.

[SIGNED] [FMLN, EL SALVADOR, 17 JULY 1989]

DEV-MUC3-0301 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADROR, 19 JUL 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS GIVEN ASSURANCES THAT THERE WILL BE NO MILITARY INTERVENTION AT THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR CAMPUS, DESPITE THE VIOLENT INCIDENTS THAT HAVE OCCURRED OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS. THESE INCIDENTS HAVE NOT RESULTED IN ANY DEATHS, ALTHOUGH SEVERAL PEOPLE HAVE BEEN INJURED. THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT THE INCIDENTS AT THE UNIVERSITY ARE PART OF A BROADER PLAN TO PROVOKE THE 1ST BRIGADE TROOPS PATROLLING THE AREA. HOWEVER, THE PRESIDENT ADDED, THERE WILL BE NO MILITARY INTERVENTION AT THE UNIVERSITY, EVEN IF THE SOLDIERS WHO ARE SURROUNDING THE CAMPUS ARE PROVOKED.

TWO STUDENTS WHO WERE ARRESTED LAST WEEK AND WHO WERE PRESENTED BY THE TREASURY POLICE HAVE ADMITTED THEIR PARTICIPATION IN LEFTIST, DESTABILIZING GROUPS' ACTIVITIES. ONE OF THE STUDENTS ARRESTED IS LUIS OSVALDO SANDOVAL, A FIFTH - GRADE STUDENT AT THE JOSE MATIAS SALGADO SCHOOL, WHO ADMITTED BEING A MEMBER OF THE BREAD, LAND, WORK, AND FREEDOM MOVEMENT AND THAT HE HAS PARTICIPATED IN ACTIVITIES SUCH AS WRITING MESSAGES AND PASTING PROPAGANDA ON WALLS AND BURNING VEHICLES.

THE SECOND STUDENT ARRESTED IS RAMON PARADA GARCIA, A 2D - YEAR STUDENT AT THE (ALFREDO BAN FERRER NATIONAL INSTITUTE), WHO SAID THAT HE IS A MEMBER OF THE ERP [PEOPLE'S REVOLUTIONARY ARMY]. THE TWO YOUTHS SAID THAT THEY JOINED THESE ORGANIZATIONS BECAUSE THEY ARE PAID ON A MONTHLY BASIS, EXPLAINING THAT THEIR FAMILIES HAVE NO OTHER SOURCE OF INCOME. THE TREASURY POLICE SAID THAT THE ARRESTED STUDENTS HAVE REQUESTED THE PROTECTION OF THAT SECURITY FORCE.

DEV-MUC3-0303 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

HAMBURG (WEST GERMANY), 20 JUL 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] TELEVISION STATION AND AT LEAST ONE RADIO STATION, SPOKESMEN OF TELEVISION CHANNEL 7 -- WHICH WAS THE TELEVISION STATION AFFECTED BY THE BLAST -- TOLD DPA.

ACCORDING TO INITIAL REPORTS, THE BOMB WAS SET OFF ON ALUX MOUNTAIN, APPROXIMATELY 20 KM WEST OF THE GUATEMALAN CAPITAL. MOST RADIO AND TELEVISION STATIONS HAVE TRANSMISSION TOWERS ON THAT MOUNTAIN BECAUSE IT TOWERS OVER A VAST AREA OF GUATEMALA.

IT HAS BEEN LEARNED THAT A MAN, WHO IS BELIEVED TO HAVE BEEN THE WATCHMAN AT CHANNEL 7'S TOWER, WAS KILLED BY THE BOMB. THE SPOKESMEN [FOR CHANNEL 7] SAID THAT RESCUE UNITS SENT TO THE SITE HAVE YET TO RETURN TO THE CAPITAL.

THE EXPLOSION WAS FELT IN SEVERAL NEARBY COMMUNITIES AND IN A SECTOR OF GUATEMALA CITY. CHANNEL 7 SUDDENLY WENT OFF THE AIR JUST AS GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO AREVALO WAS ABOUT TO DELIVER A SPEECH. NEVERTHELESS, THE SPEECH WAS BROADCAST BY THE OTHER FOUR TELEVISION CHANNELS THAT OPERATE IN GUATEMALA.

THIS TERRORIST ACTION COMES IN THE WAKE OF A SERIES OF INCIDENTS THAT HAVE OCCURRED IN THE PAST FEW DAYS AS A RESULT OF STRIKES BY TEACHERS, POST OFFICE WORKERS, FINANCE MINISTRY EMPLOYEES, AND OTHER SECTORS DEMANDING WAGE INCREASES.

A BOMB WAS FOUND BEFORE IT EXPLODED IN A BANK IN THE AFTERNOON OF 19 JULY, AND SEVERAL ANONYMOUS CALLERS WARNED ABOUT OTHER TERRORIST BOMBS LAST NIGHT; HOWEVER, THESE TURNED OUT TO BE FALSE ALARMS.

DEV-MUC3-0304 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

TEGUCIGALPA, 20 JUL 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] WITH SIMULTANEOUS BOMB EXPLOSIONS IN THE HONDURAN CAPITAL AND LA CEIBA PORT, LOCATED APPROXIMATELY 355 KM FROM TEGUCIGALPA ON THE ATLANTIC COAST, A NEW GUERRILLA GROUP CALLING ITSELF THE "9 MAY" PEOPLE'S LIBERATION FORCES, FPL, ANNOUNCED ITS EMERGENCE AS ONE OF THE ARMED ORGANIZATIONS STRUGGLING FOR POWER.

THREE BOMBS WENT OFF SIMULTANEOUSLY IN TEGUCIGALPA, ONE AT THE CENTRAL PARK, ANOTHER AT THE STATE-RUN UNIVERSITY OF HONDURAS, AND ANOTHER AT A TRAINING SCHOOL FOR TEACHERS. AT THE SAME TIME, A BOMB EXPLODED AT A UNIVERSITY BRANCH IN LA CEIBA.

ALL THE BLASTS OCCURRED AT 1130 (LOCAL TIME). ONLY ONE PERSON WHO HAPPENED TO BE PASSING BY THE CENTRAL PARK IN TEGUCIGALPA AT THE TIME OF THE EXPLOSION WAS WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF THE BLASTS. A COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE NEW GROUP POINTS OUT THAT "ONE DOES NOT WEEP FOR MARTYRS, BUT AVENGES THEM" AND ADDS THAT "TRAITOR INDIANS COME BEFORE THE INVADING GRINGOS."

THE PROCLAMATION CRITICIZES THE MURDER OF POPULAR LEADERS THAT TOOK PLACE IN THE COUNTRY IN EARLY JULY AND DENOUNCES OTHER LEFTIST LABOR AND GUERRILLA ORGANIZATIONS.

THE ARMED FORCES, THROUGH ITS COMMANDER, GENERAL HUMBERTO REGALADO HERNANDEZ, RESPONDED IMMEDIATELY BY STATING THAT "THE ONLY REAL COMMUNISTS LEFT IN THE WORLD ARE HONDURANS, BECAUSE THEY ARE CHANGING IN OTHER COUNTRIES" AND ARE NO LONGER EXPLODING BOMBS.

THE MILITARY LEADER ASKED PEOPLE TO ATTACH NO SIGNIFICANCE TO THE INCIDENT AND SAID THAT SHOULD THE WAVE OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE CONTINUE, LEFTIST GROUPS WOULD HAVE TO BE CALLED TO A DIALOGUE TO AVOID OTHER SIMILAR ACTIONS.

THE "9 MAY" FPL PROCLAMATION WAS ISSUED IN THE NORTHERN CITY OF SAN PEDRO SULA, 255 KM FROM TEGUCIGALPA.

DEV-MUC3-0305 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN PEDRO SULA, 20 JUL 89 (TIEMPO) -- [TEXT] TEGUCIGALPA -- THE PEOPLE'S ORGANIZATIONS COORDINATING COMMITTEE (CCOP) AND THE UNITED FEDERATION OF HONDURAN WORKERS (FUTH) CHARGED YESTERDAY THAT THERE IS A TERRORIST PLAN TO ELIMINATE EVERYONE WHO OPPOSES THE U.S. MILITARY OCCUPATION OF THE COUNTRY.

IN A NEWS CONFERENCE, THE LEADERS OF THE ORGANIZATIONS SAID THAT THE DEATH THREATS AGAINST LABOR AND THE PEOPLE'S LEADERS ARE INCLUDED IN THIS PLAN, WHICH FORMS PART OF THE U.S. POLICY ON HONDURAS.

REFERRING TO THE RECENT ASSASSINATIONS IN SAN PEDRO SULA, CCOP COORDINATOR JUAN ALMENDARES BONILLA SAID THAT HONDURAS "IS AN OCCUPIED COUNTRY WHERE THERE IS A U.S.-SPONSORED POLICY OF TERROR THAT SEEKS TO ANNIHILATE ALL THE GROUPS THAT PROTEST THE VIOLATION OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY."

HE EXPLAINED THAT THERE ARE VARIOUS FORMS OF TERROR. FOR EXAMPLE, HE SAID ARMED GROUPS ARRIVE AT HOUSES AT NIGHT AND RAPE ENTIRE FAMILIES. "THESE POLICIES OF TERROR HAVE BEEN USED IN BRAZIL, CHILE, VIETNAM, EL SALVADOR, AND GUATEMALA, AMONG OTHER COUNTRIES," HE SAID.

THE FORMER UNIVERSITY RECTOR SAID THAT THIS POLICY OF TERROR, WHICH HAS RECENTLY BEEN INTENSIFIED, TRIES TO MAKE PEOPLE BELIEVE THAT THERE IS A SUBVERSIVE CELL THAT IS DESTABILIZING THE COUNTRY PRIOR TO THE HOLDING OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT IN TELA, ATLANTIDA DEPARTMENT.

THE PEOPLE'S LEADERS SAID THAT "THE TERRORISM OF THE HONDURAN DEMOCRATIC STATE IS ALSO SHOWN BY AN ELECTORAL PROCESS THAT IS EXTENSIVELY CONTROLLED BY THE AGENCY FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND THE EXECUTION OF POOR HONDURANS BY REPRESSIVE FORCES THAT HAVE BEEN TRAINED BY U.S. EXPERTS."

THEY SAID THE TERRORISM IS ALSO DEMOSTRATED IN THE NONFULFILLMENT OF THE ESQUIPULAS II PEACE AGREEMENTS, BY A POLICY THAT CAPITULATES TO THE IMF AND THE WORLD BANK, THE MAINTENANCE OF EXTREME SECURITY, AND THE FACILITIES GIVEN TO THE THE CONTRAS AND THE U.S. ARMY.

AFTER MAKING THE PREVIOUS ANALYSIS, THE FUTH AND THE CCOP ASKED THE GOVERNMENT TO HALT STATE TERRORISM AND TO BRING TO JUSTICE THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE POLITICAL CRIMES AGAINST THE PEOPLE'S LEADERS. THEY ALSO DEMANDED THAT THE PEACE AGREEMENTS BE RESPECTED, THAT THE NATIONAL RECONCILIATION COMMISSION'S REPORT ON REPRESSION BE MADE KNOWN, AND THAT THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS BE DEMOBILIZED.

THEY ALSO PROPOSED THAT THE STATE CARRY OUT A REAL POLICY OF DEMOCRATIZATION WITH THE PEOPLE'S PARTICIPATION IN THE FACE OF PRESSURE FROM THE IMF, THE WORLD BANK, AND THE U.S. EMBASSY.

THEY ALSO DEMANDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT ADOPT A PATRIOTIC POSITION SO THAT THE U.S. BASES AND THE CONTRAS WILL BE WITHDRAWN FROM HONDURAS BECAUSE THEY CONSTITUTE A THREAT TO PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA.

THE CCOP AND THE FUTH ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT THEY HAVE SCHEDULED "A GREAT MARCH FOR NATIONAL DIGNITY" THIS AFTERNOON TO MARK THE HEROIC DEEDS OF LEMPIRA, THE DEFENDER OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY AND DIGNITY.

THE MARCH WILL BEGIN AT 1600 AT THE COMAYAGUELA OBELISK AND END AT TEGUCIGALPA'S MAIN SQUARE.

THE DEMONSTRATION WILL ALSO DEMAND THE REJECTION OF THE IMF AND WORLD BANK'S PROPOSALS, THE EXPULSION OF THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS AND RESPECT FOR THE ESQUIPULAS II AGREEMENTS.

DEV-MUC3-0306 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BOGOTA, 20 JUL 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE NATIONAL POLICE REPORTED THAT THE ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION-CAMILIST UNION (UC-ELN) TODAY CARRIED OUT ITS SIXTH ATTACK THIS YEAR AGAINST THE PACIFIC OIL PIPELINE, WHICH LINKS THE COLOMBIAN TOWNS OF ORITO AND TUMACO NEAR THE COLOMBIAN-ECUADORAN BORDER.

THE REBELS USED EXPLOSIVES TO BLOW UP 1 METER OF PIPELINE. THIS IS THE REBELS' 33D ATTACK AGAINST THE COUNTRY'S OIL NETWORK IN 1989. THE AUTHORITIES REPORTED THAT THERE WAS NO OIL SPILL BECAUSE AT THE TIME OF THE ATTACK, NO OIL WAS BEING PUMPED THROUGH THE PIPELINE.

A WOMAN WHO SAID SHE WAS SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE UC-ELN CALLED THE CALI MEDIA TO CLAIM RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK.

THE UC-ELN IS ATTACKING COLOMBIA'S OIL PIPELINES AS A WAY TO PRESSURE THE GOVERNMENT TO NATIONALIZE THE OIL INDUSTRY AND TO SIGN MORE FAVORABLE CONTRACTS WITH MULTINATIONAL OIL COMPANIES. THIS YEAR ALONE, THE UC-ELN LAUNCHED 25 ATTACKS ON THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS OIL PIPELINE, THE LONGEST IN COLOMBIA. THE ATTACKS ON THE CANO LIMON- COVENAS PIPELINE HAVE CAUSED APPROXIMATE $150 MILLION IN DAMAGE.

IF THE SIX ATTACKS ON THE PACIFIC OIL PIPELINE AND THE TWO ON THE DINA-SALGAR OIL PIPELINE ARE TAKEN INTO CONSIDERATION, LOSSES AMOUNT TO APPROXIMATELY $200 MILLION. THE DINA-SALGAR PIPELINE CARRIES CRUDE OIL FROM THE OIL FIELDS IN TOLIMA TO THE REFINERY IN BARRANCABERMEJA.

DEV-MUC3-0307 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 JUL 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] SALVADORAN PEOPLE: I ADDRESS YOU ON THIS OCCASION TO GIVE YOU MY FIRST REPORT ON THE STATE OF THE COUNTRY. I MAKE THIS REPORT 50 DAYS AFTER ASSUMING POWER. AT THIS TIME I WANT TO TELL YOU THE TRUTH; I WANT TELL YOU EXACTLY WHAT OUR SITUATION IS SO THAT WE WILL ALL UNDERSTAND WHAT WE MUST DO IN THE FUTURE. EVERY SALVADORAN MUST SHARE IN THE SACRIFICE AND EFFORT. THOSE OF US WHO HAVE A BIT MUST SHOW SOLIDARITY WITH THOSE WHO HAVE NOTHING OR VERY LITTLE.

THE SITUATION IS CRITICAL, BUT WE MUST CONFRONT IT. THAT IS WHY WE HAVE A GOVERNMENT: TO SOLVE PROBLEMS. WE ARE WILLING TO DO THIS RESPONSIBLY, BECAUSE WE KNOW THAT DOING NOTHING WOULD MEAN A GREATER CRISIS FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND WOULD SINK OUR HOMELAND EVEN DEEPER IN THE BLACK ABYSS.

WE KNOW THAT THERE ARE MANY CONCERNS; WE HAVE HEARD DIFFERENT GROUPS ASKING THAT THE GOVERNMENT STATE WHAT IT IS PLANNING TO DO TO SOLVE THE PROBLEMS. I WOULD LIKE TO STATE, HOWEVER, THAT WE PREFER TO ACT CALMLY, STUDY THE PROBLEM IN DEPTH, AND FIND A SOLUTION THAT WILL TRULY SOLVE THE PROBLEM. WE WOULD RATHER DO THIS THAN MAKE A RASH DECISION AND MAKE A MISTAKE. THIS IS A TRULY DIFFICULT TASK.

BECAUSE I WANT TO TELL YOU IN ALL HONESTY WHAT IS HAPPENING IN THE COUNTRY, I WISH TO TOUCH ON THE THREE MAJOR AREAS THAT CREATE CONCERN AND THAT I FEEL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SHOULD KNOW ABOUT.

FIRST, LET US TALK ABOUT PEACE. SINCE THIS GOVERNMENT WAS SWORN AND INDISCRIMINATE MURDERS. THERE IS NO REASON FOR THIS, BECAUSE ON 1 JUNE WE EXPRESSED OUR RESOLVE TO SIT DOWN AND TALK TO FIND A PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT. THE FMLN'S RESPONSE, HOWEVER, HAS BEEN MORE VIOLENCE.

WE KNOW MANY GROUPS COMPLAIN ABOUT THE VIOLENCE AND INSECURITY; THEY HAVE EVERY REASON TO COMPLAIN. THE ARMED FORCES ARE WILLING TO DO ALL THEY CAN TO PROTECT EVERYONE. THEY HAVE BEEN DOING THIS IN THE PAST DAYS, ESPECIALLY IN THOSE AREAS WHERE THE TERRORIST ATTACKS HAVE BEEN STRONGER. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN CRITICIZED MANY TIMES AND BY MANY GROUPS, ESPECIALLY THOSE GROUPS THAT IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER SHARE THE FMLN'S IDEAS. THEY CLAIM THAT THE ARMED FORCES ACT IN A REPRESSIVE MANNER. DEAR SALVADORAN PEOPLE, LET US ANALYZE WHAT REALLY IS HAPPENING IN OUR COUNTRY.

THE ARMED FORCES' DUTY IS TO CONTROL ALL THOSE SITUATIONS IN WHICH THE LAW IS BROKEN. THE ARMED FORCES ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR MAINTAINING PUBLIC ORDER. THE ARMED FORCES ONLY TAKE ACTION WHEN THERE ARE GROUPS THAT ONLY CREATE VIOLENCE AND DISRUPT PUBLIC ORDER. THE ARMED FORCES DO NOT TAKE ACTION JUST BECAUSE THEY WANT TO TAKE ACTION. WE HAVE AN ARMED FORCES TO DEFEND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND NEVER TO ATTACK THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THEREFORE, WHAT WE MUST DO IS LOOK AROUND AND SEE WHO IS REFUSING TO MAKE A COMMITMENT AND WHO IS REFUSING TO SIT DOWN, IN A RATIONAL AND PEACEFUL MANNER, TO FIND A SOLUTION TO THIS CONFLICT THAT NO LONGER HAS A PLACE IN OUR HISTORY. THEREFORE, I WOULD LIKE TO REPEAT WHAT WE, AS A GOVERNMENT, SAID ON 1 JUNE. ON THAT DAY WE EXPRESSED OUR WILLINGNESS TO SIT DOWN AND TALK. I WOULD LIKE TO DISCUSS THIS A BIT, BECAUSE THERE HAVE BEEN MISUNDERSTANDINGS OVER OUR INTENTIONS IN THIS DIALOGUE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0308 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] SMUGGLING CAN BE HELD IN CHECK ONLY WITH MEASURES SUCH AS THESE. WE HAVE ALREADY BEGUN TO TAKE THE SEVEREST ACTIONS AGAINST THOSE WHO SMUGGLE MERCHANDISE INTO OUR COUNTRY. AN INVESTIGATION IS WELL UNDER WAY INTO A CORPORATION WHICH HAS BEEN SMUGGLING MERCHANDISE INTO OUR COUNTRY. THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS WILL SOON BE BROUGHT TO TRIAL IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE LAW. WE WANT TO WARN ALL THOSE WHO SOMEHOW HAVE SMUGGLED OR WHO ARE PLANNING TO SMUGGLE THAT THEY SHOULD STOP THIS ACTIVITY. WE BELIEVE THAT SMUGGLING CONSTITUTES CORRUPTION AND THAT CORRUPTION IS A CRIME OF HIGH TREASON. WE CANNOT ALLOW CORRUPTION IN OUR COUNTRY. WE WILL TAKE HARSH ACTIONS AGAINST EVERY TYPE OF CORRUPTION, INCLUDING SMUGGLING. I AM ASKING THOSE WHO MIGHT BE APPROACHED BY UNSCRUPULOUS INDIVIDUALS WHO HAVE IN THEIR POSSESSION SMUGGLED GOODS TO REFRAIN FROM PURCHASING THOSE PRODUCTS. LET US NOT PROMOTE SMUGGLING. I AM ASKING ALL GOOD SALVADORAN BUSINESSMEN NOT TO PURCHASE ANY SMUGGLED GOODS. SMUGGLING CONSTITUTES AN ATTACK AGAINST OUR HOMELAND AND ENCOURAGES CORRUPTION, WHICH MUST BE ERADICATED FROM OUR COUNTRY.

REGARDING OUR FISCAL POLICY, WE MUST TRY TO DETERMINE WAYS TO MORE DIRECTLY MAKE UP FOR THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN REVENUE AND DISBURSEMENTS IN THE COUNTRY. WE BELIEVE THAT WE CAN BRIDGE THIS FISCAL DEFICIT IN TWO WAYS -- WE MUST EITHER INCREASE OUR REVENUE OR LOWER OUR DISBURSEMENTS. THIS GOVERNMENT HAS ALREADY TAKEN AUSTERITY MEASURES REGARDING THE LATTER. THE GOVERNMENT HAS DETERMINED NOT ONLY TO MAINTAIN EXPENDITURES AT THE CURRENT LEVEL, BUT TO REDUCE THEM BY 15 PERCENT. WE WANT TO MAKE CLEAR THAT OUR GOVERNMENT'S AUSTERITY MEASURES MUST BE GENUINE AND SHOULD BE AIMED AT MAKING MORE EFFICIENT USE OF SCANT RESOURCES. THIS IS WHY WE ARE ASKING PUBLIC EMPLOYEES TO UNDERSTAND THAT IF THE GOVERNMENT IS TO BE MORE EFFICIENT, THE GOVERNMENT MUST PROVIDE BETTER SERVICES FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. AFTER ALL, IT IS THE PEOPLE WHO PAY OUR SALARIES AND PROVIDE THE REVENUE THAT ALLOWS THE GOVERNMENT TO OPERATE.

WE MUST SPEND OUR MONEY WISELY. ALL PUBLIC OFFICIALS AND EMPLOYEES MUST GUARD AGAINST CORRUPTION. WE MUST TAKE PAINS TO SERVE THE POPULATION AND TO IMPROVE THE QUALITY OF THE SERVICES THAT THE PEOPLE ARE RECEIVING AND DESERVE. ONLY WHEN THE GOVERNMENT IS RUN EFFICIENTLY, WHEN ITS ACTIONS ARE CRYSTAL CLEAR, WHEN THE GOVERNMENT RIDS ITSELF OF CORRUPTION, AND WHEN THE MONEY THAT THE TAXPAYERS PAY IS USED FOR THE GOOD OF THE PEOPLE, WILL WE BE ABLE TO ELICIT A POSITIVE REACTION FROM THE TAXPAYERS. THEY HAVE TO PAY TAXES. WHEN TAXES ARE SQUANDERED, MISUSED, OR STOLEN, NO ONE WILL PAY THEM WILLINGLY. IF WE, AS THE GOVERNMENT, ACT HONESTLY, SERVE THE NATION WELL, AND IMPLEMENT PROGRAMS TO BENEFIT THE MAJORITY, ONLY DISLOYAL SALVADORANS WILL BE UNWILLING TO PAY TAXES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0309 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE -- [SPEECH] [CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] SECOND, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S HEALTH. WE BELIEVE THAT IN THE VERY SHORT TERM, WE HAD TO SUPPLY ALL THE HEALTH FACILITIES AND HOSPITALS WITH AT LEAST THE MOST URGENTLY NEEDED MEDICINES FOR THE PEOPLE. WE HAVE ALLOTTED 17 MILLION COLONS FOR THE HEALTH MINISTRY FOR THE PURCHASE OF THE MOST URGENTLY NEEDED MEDICINES AND FOR THE DISTRIBUTION OF THIS MEDICINE THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY SO THAT THE POOR WILL RECEIVE THE EFFICIENT HEALTH SERVICES THAT THE GOVERNMENT MUST PROVIDE.

THE EDUCATION MINISTRY HAS BEEN ASKED TO GIVE STUDENTS THE MATERIALS THEY NEED TO PURSUE THEIR STUDIES. A CERTAIN AMOUNT OF MONEY HAS BEEN ALLOTTED FOR THE PURCHASE OF EQUIPMENT NEEDED BY THE SCHOOLS. WHEN THE 1990 SCHOOL YEAR BEGINS, WE MUST BE PREPARED TO PROVIDE THE SCHOOLS AND STUDENTS WITH THE MATERIAL THEY NEED. WE ALSO BELIEVE THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO BEGIN, AS SOON AS POSSIBLE, REPAIRING THE STREETS AND ROADS. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE CAN SEE THAT THIS IS ALREADY BEING DONE.

FINALLY, LOW-INCOME HOUSING. NEXT WEEK THE PUBLIC WORKS MINISTER WILL ANNOUNCE THE LOW-INCOME HOUSING PLAN, AND HE WILL EXPLAIN HOW WE WILL HELP LOW-INCOME FAMILIES BUY HOMES. THIS WILL BE DONE THROUGH A SUBSIDY PLAN ENSURING THAT LOW-INCOME GROUPS WILL NOT BE AFFECTED BY STEEP PAYMENTS AND WILL HAVE MONEY LEFT OVER FOR FOOD AND OTHER BASIC NECESSITIES.

WE HAVE ALREADY DRAFTED A SOCIAL EMERGENCY PLAN. THIS PLAN WILL BE IMPLEMENTED IN SEPTEMBER, AND ITS FIRST PHASE WILL BE CARRIED OUT IN THE HIGHLY POPULATED URBAN AREAS. THE PLAN WILL BENEFIT APPROXIMATELY 200 COMMUNITIES AND, AS OF NOW, I ASK THE MAYORS FOR THEIR HELP, BECAUSE WE WANT TO WORK WITH THE MUNICIPAL GOVERNMENTS. THIS FIRST PHASE WILL BE AIMED AT PROVIDING LOW-INCOME COMMUNITIES WITH PUBLIC UTILITIES. WE WILL PROVIDE THEM WITH ELECTRICITY AND RUNNING WATER, WE WILL BUILD SEWER SYSTEMS, AND WE WILL HELP THEM IMPROVE THEIR HEALTH AND NUTRITION. AMID THE CRISIS WE ARE EXPERIENCING, WE BELIEVE THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO SUPPORT THE SMALL - SCALE BUSINESSMEN IN THESE COMMUNITIES. WE WILL ORGANIZE A LOAN SYSTEM FOR SMALL - SIZE BUSINESSES FOR DEVELOPMENT WITHIN THESE COMMUNITIES. I REPEAT: THIS SOCIAL EMERGENCY PLAN WILL BE IMPLEMENTED IN SEPTEMBER. IN THE NEXT FEW WEEKS, WE WILL BEGIN TO SEEK THE COOPERATION OF THOSE MUNICIPAL GOVERNMENTS THAT WILL BE INVOLVED IN THE PLAN.

THERE IS SOMETHING ELSE THAT WE MUST ALL STRUGGLE FOR, AND THAT IS TO ABOLISH UNEMPLOYMENT. WE MUST STRUGGLE SO THAT EVERY SALVADORAN WILL HAVE THE CHANCE TO EARN AN HONEST LIVING. WE THEREFORE WISH TO LAUNCH AN OFFENSIVE AGAINST UNEMPLOYMENT. WE ALSO BELIEVE THAT THE BEST WAY TO FIGHT VIOLENCE IS THROUGH EMPLOYMENT OPPORTUNITIES, SO THAT THE PEOPLE WILL NOT FIND THEMSELVES IN THE SITUATION WHERE THEY BELIEVE THAT THEY MUST COMMIT CRIMES TO SURVIVE OR THAT THEY MUST GET INVOLVED IN THE TYPE OF VIOLENCE SPONSORED BY THE FMLN TERRORISTS. THEREFORE, IN SEPTEMBER, WE WILL ALSO IMPLEMENT AN EMERGENCY PLAN TO GENERATE EMPLOYMENT. THIS PLAN HAS SOME SPECIFIC GOALS: FIRST, TO PROVIDE A BASIC JOB FOR THOSE PERSONS WHO ARE UNEMPLOYED OR UNDEREMPLOYED. OUR GOAL IS TO CREATE 20,000 JOBS PER MONTH FOR THESE PEOPLE. THIS PLAN WILL BE DRAFTED IN THE NEXT FEW WEEKS, AND WE WILL IMPLEMENT IT DURING THOSE MONTHS WHEN THERE IS USUALLY A DROP IN EMPLOYMENT. I MUST STRESS THAT WE ARE NOT GOING TO IMPLEMENT THE PLAN DURING THE SOWING AND HARVEST SEASONS, BECAUSE DURING THOSE SEASONS THERE IS AN OVERABUNDANCE OF JOBS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0310 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 22 JUL 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE, COPREFA] [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN NATIONAL POLICE REPORTED THIS MORNING THAT UNIDENTIFIED MEN SET OFF BOMBS AT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN JOSE SIMEON CANAS UNIVERSITY, UCA, LOCATED IN SOUTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR.

ACCORDING TO THE REPORT, THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE AT 0200. ONE ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE, ONE BUS, AND ONE ELECTRICAL TRANSFORMER WERE DAMAGED AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION OF AT LEAST FOUR BOMBS THAT WENT OFF INSIDE THE UCA CAMPUS.

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ALWAYS CONDEMNED THIS KIND OF ATTACK, WHICH IS USUALLY CARRIED OUT BY CERTAIN GROUPS THAT OPPOSE PEACE. THE ARMED FORCES BELIEVE THAT SUCH ATTACKS ARE NOT THE WAY TO SOLVE THE COUNTRY'S SOCIAL AND POLITICAL PROBLEMS.

IN ADDITION, THESE VIOLENT ACTIONS ONLY CONFUSE THE PUBLIC, BECAUSE UNSCRUPULOUS PEOPLE ALWAYS BLAME THE ARMY FOR ANY SUCH ACTION, WITHOUT FIRST CONDUCTING AN IN-DEPTH INVESTIGATION OF THE ORIGIN OF THE ATTACKS.

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ALWAYS REITERATED THEIR WILLINGNESS TO ENSURE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, PUBLIC AND PRIVATE PROPERTY, AND THE LIFE AND SAFETY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THEREFORE, FROM THIS VERY MOMENT, THE ARMED FORCES REJECT ANY ACCUSATION IMPLICATING THEM IN THE ATTACK AGAINST UCA, WHICH TOOK PLACE EARLY THIS MORNING.

DEV-MUC3-0311 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 JUL 89 (LA PRENSA GRAFICA) -- [SPEECH] [SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] DEAR PEASANT FRIENDS:

FROM THE VERY 1ST DAY OF OUR ADMINISTRATION, WE HAVE PLEDGED OUR FULL COMMITMENT TO NATIONAL PROGRAMS AND HAVE SAID THAT "AT NO TIME AND FOR NO REASON WILL WE FORGET THE MANY NEEDY PEOPLE IN THE COUNTRY -- THAT IS, THE NOBLE AND LONG-SUFFERING PEASANTS, WHO ARE THE MAIN VICTIMS OF TERRORIST VIOLENCE."

THIS CEREMONY REAFFIRMS OUR GOVERNMENT'S COMMITMENT TO CONTINUE AGRARIAN REFORM.

WE WANT YOU TO REALIZE THE SERIOUSNESS OF OUR WORDS THROUGH OUR DEEDS. THIS PRESENTATION OF 8,000 PERMANENT LAND TITLE DEEDS TO THE BENEFICIARIES OF DECREE 207 -- THROUGH THE NATIONAL FINANCIAL INSTITUTION FOR AGRICULTURAL LANDS (FINATA) -- REFLECTS OUR OBJECTIVES.

WE HAVE CATEGORICALLY SAID THAT WE WILL NOT TURN BACK THE AGRARIAN REFORM PROCESS. QUITE TO THE CONTRARY, WE WANT TO FULLY SUPPORT IT IN ORDER TO GUARANTEE THAT PEASANTS IN AREAS AFFECTED BY THE AGRARIAN REFORM ARE FREE TO CHOOSE THE KIND OF PROPERTY OWNERSHIP THAT BEST SUITS THEIR NEEDS, IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE GREAT FREEDOMS GUARANTEED IN THE CONSTITUTION AND LAWS OF THE REPUBLIC.

OUR GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO WORK HARD TO ENSURE THAT OUR BROTHER PEASANTS ARE INDEED BENEFITED BY THE AGRARIAN REFORM AND THAT THEY WILL NOT BE USED AS A DEMAGOGICAL BANNER AT THE SERVICE OF POLITICAL IDEOLOGY, AS WAS THE CASE UNTIL RECENTLY. WE WANT PEASANTS' WELFARE TO BE THE OBJECTIVE OF OUR AGRARIAN REFORM; WE WANT AGRARIAN REFORM TO DEVELOP WITHIN A LEGAL, HONEST, AND PATRIOTIC FRAMEWORK.

WE ARE AGAINST THE DEMAGOGUERY OF STATIC PATERNALISM, BECAUSE WE WANT PEASANTS TO DETERMINE THEIR OWN FATE, TO TRULY PARTICIPATE IN THEIR PRODUCTION UNITS' DECISIONMAKING PROCESS, IN THE MARKETING OF THEIR PRODUCTS, AND IN THE DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUE.

IT IS NEITHER FAIR NOR CORRECT, AS HAS BEEN THE CASE IN THE PAST, TO BENEFIT OFFICE WORKERS, WHO HAVE NEVER SWEATED IN THE FIELDS UNDER THE AGRARIAN REFORM, WHEN YOU -- THE PEASANTS -- ARE NOW FACING DEBTS AND ARE WORSE OFF THAN BEFORE YOU OWNED LAND.

OUR GOVERNMENT AND YOU WILL GRADUALLY CHANGE THIS SITUATION TO ENSURE THAT YOU WILL ENTHUSIASTICALLY WORK YOUR LAND, KNOWING THAT THE FRUIT OF YOUR LABOR WILL DIRECTLY BENEFIT YOUR FAMILIES. WE ARE SURE THAT WITH EFFICIENT ORGANIZATION, PROMPT CREDIT, ADEQUATE TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE, AND THE HARDWORKING LEGACY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE WILL TURN THE AGRARIAN REFORM INTO AN OPPORTUNITY FOR ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT, WHICH WILL BENEFIT ALL SALVADORANS BY PROMOTING PRODUCTION AND PRODUCTIVITY.

DEAR PEASANTS:

WE WISH TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THIS OPPORTUNITY TO TELL YOU THAT OUR GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO WORK WITH YOU. THROUGH THE RELEVANT ORGANIZATIONS, THE GOVERNMENT WILL IMPLEMENT PROGRAMS TO COMPLETELY UPGRADE THE SALVADORAN PEASANTS' CONDITIONS.

THROUGH FINATA, WE WILL CONTINUE TO FINANCE THE ACQUISITION OF MORE LAND FOR DISTRIBUTION AMONG THOUSANDS OF PEASANT FAMILIES.

DEAR FRIENDS:

OUR GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO ACHIEVE PEACE, BECAUSE WE ARE AWARE THAT THE FMLN'S TERRORIST VIOLENCE DISTURBS THE CALM AND NORMAL PROCEDURE OF RURAL ACTIVITIES; WE REALIZE THAT WE MUST END THE VIOLENCE SO THAT WE CAN ALL GO BACK TO WORK AND BRING ABOUT A NATIONAL RECOVERY. PEASANTS HAVE SUFFERED THE MOST THROUGHOUT THE CONFLICT UNLEASHED BY THE TERRORIST MARXIST-LENINIST GROUPS, AND WE BELIEVE THAT THE TIME HAS COME TO SEEK THE PEACE THAT WE ALL WANT IN ORDER TO RESTORE SOCIAL HARMONY, MUTUAL RESPECT, AND FRATERNAL LOVE AMONG ALL SALVADORANS WITHOUT EXCEPTION.

ON BEHALF OF THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC, WE HAVE BEEN PARTICULARLY PLEASED TO PRESENT THESE PERMANENT LAND TITLE DEEDS TO THE BENEFICIARIES OF DECREE 207. WE CONGRATULATE AND INVITE YOU TO CONTINUE WORKING TOGETHER TO HELP THE FATHERLAND RECOVER FROM THE CRISIS AND TO BUILD FOR OUR CHILDREN AND ALL SALVADORANS A FUTURE OF PEACE, JUSTICE, LIBERTY, AND PROGRESS.

DEV-MUC3-0312 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

LIMA, 28 JUL 89 -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] LIMA TELEVISION PERUANA NETWORK IN SPANISH 1733 GMT ON 28 JULY, CONTINUING ITS LIVE COVERAGE OF FESTIVITIES ON THE OCCASION OF PERUVIAN NATIONAL DAY, BROADCASTS A SPEECH TO THE NATION BY PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA LIVE FROM THE NATIONAL CONGRESS CHAMBER IN LIMA.

PRESIDENT GARCIA NOTES THAT HIS PRESIDENCY HAS BEEN A TESTIMONY OF FAITH TO DEMOCRACY BASED ON THE PERUVIAN CONSTITUTION, WHICH PROVIDES THE FRAMEWORK FOR GOVERNING A FREE PERU. NOTING THAT THIS SPEECH IS HIS LAST MESSAGE TO THE COUNTRY FROM CONGRESS, GARCIA BEGINS TO COMMENT ON THE ACHIEVEMENTS AND EVENTS OF HIS LAST YEAR IN OFFICE. AFTER STRESSING THE IMPORTANCE OF DEMOCRACY AND EDUCATION TO OVERCOME PROBLEMS OF THE ECONOMY AND OF VIOLENCE, GARCIA DECLARES: "I AM HEREBY CALL FOR GENERAL ELECTIONS TO CHOOSE PRESIDENT AND THE MEMBERS OF CONGRESS ON 8 APRIL 1990. APPLAUSE

"I WOULD LIKE TO REMARK THAT I AM A POLITICIAN, THAT I PARTICIPATE IN DEBATES, AND THAT MY LIFE IS INDEBTED TO THE APRA [AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE] MOVEMENT. YET AS PRESIDENT I HAVE A MAJOR SACRED MISSION, THAT OF GUARANTEEING THAT THE ELECTIONS WILL BE ABSOLUTELY FAIR AND CLEAN."

GARCIA NOTES THAT THE ELECTORAL AUTHORITIES WILL BE REPLACED AND THAT THE NATIONAL MEDIA ARE FROM THIS MOMENT ON PLACED AT THE DISPOSAL OF THE CANDIDATES. HE CALLS ON THE ARMED FORCES TO DEFEND DEMOCRACY.

THE PRESIDENT CALLS ON PERUVIAN YOUTH TO ESCHEW VIOLENCE IN FAVOR OF EDUCATION AND WORKING TOWARD PROMOTING DEMOCRACY.

GARCIA THEN TURNS HIS ATTENTION TO THE QUESTION OF REGIONALIZATION, NOTING THAT MANY GOVERNMENTAL INSTITUTIONS ARE BEING REORGANIZED TO BETTER SERVE THE PEOPLE. WHEN EACH REGION HAS ITS OWN ELECTED OFFICIALS, HE SAYS, THE PEOPLE WILL EXERT MORE CONTROL OVER OFFICIALS' ACTIVITIES, AND CORRUPTION WILL BE REDUCED. PERU WILL NOT NEED TO ACCEPT INTERNATIONAL SOLUTIONS TO ITS NATIONAL PROBLEMS.

AFTER CALLING ON THE JUSTICE JUDICIAL BRANCH TO IMPROVE ITS ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE, GARCIA ANNOUNCES: "I HEREBY CALL ELECTIONS -- FOLLOWING A CONSULTATION WITH THE NATIONAL ELECTORAL COURT -- FOR REGIONAL GOVERNMENT REPRESENTATIVES OF THE GRAU REGION, CREATED ON 1 MARCH 1988, MADE UP OF THE FOLLOWING PROVINCES: TUMBES, CONTRALMIRANTE VILLAR, ZARUMILLA, HUANCABAMBA, MORROPON, PAITA, SULLANA, TALARA, AYABACA, AND PIURA ON 12 NOVEMBER 1989." GARCIA ALSO ISSUES AN OFFICIAL CALL FOR 12 NOVEMBER ELECTIONS IN THE AMAZONAS, AREQUIPA, AND MOQUEGUA-TACNA-PUNO REGIONS.

AT 1801 GMT GARCIA BEGINS TO SPEAK ON THE SUBJECT OF TERRORISM AND VIOLENCE. HE CALLS ON THE PEOPLE AS WELL AS ALL POLTIICAL PARTIES TO SUPPORT THE ARMED FORCES IN PUTTING AN END TO VIOLENCE. HE PROPOSES THAT TERRORISTS BE TRIED IN MILITARY COURTS.

ON THE SUBJECT OF THE ECONOMIC CRISIS IN PERU, PRESIDENT GARCIA REITERATES THAT HIS GOVERNMENT IS PROMOTING AN INCREASE IN FOREIGN RESERVES AS WELL AS REACTIVATING THE PRODUCTION SECTOR. HE NOTES THE IMPORTANCE OF FURTHER DEVELOPING AGRICULTURE AND PETROLEUM. HE REVIEWS THE PUBLIC WORKS PROJECTS, INCLUDING IRRIGATION AND RURAL ELECTRICIFICATION WORKS, THAT HAVE BEEN INITIATED OR COMPLETED DURING HIS PRESIDENCY.

GARCIA CALLS ON THE PEOPLE NOT TO BE DEFEATED BY TERRORISM, SENSATIONALISM, OR PESSIMISM. NOTING THAT THE PEOPLE ARE PERU'S MOST IMPORTANT RESOURCE, THE PRESIDENT CALLS FOR IMPROVING THE SOCIAL WELFARE SECTOR. HE DENIES THE RUMOR THAT SECTOR WILL BE PRIVATIZED.

GARCIA ENDS HIS SPEECH AT 1851 GMT.

DEV-MUC3-0313 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

BUENOS AIRES, 28 JUL 89 (ARGENTINA TELEVISORA COLOR NETWORK) -- [SPEECH] [ALVARO ALSOGARAY, PRESIDENTIAL ADVISER ON FOREIGN DEBT MATTERS] [EXCERPTS] GOOD EVENING LADIES AND GENTLEMEN. TODAY WE WILL DISCUSS THE FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM. THIS SUBJECT COULD PERHAPS SEEM A BIT OUT PLACE AT A TIME WHEN MORE TROUBLESOME MATTERS AFFECT ALL ARGENTINE FAMILIES, SUCH AS HIGH PUBLIC UTILITY RATES, PRICES, CONTROLS, DIFFICULTIES, ETC. HOWEVER, WE MUST ATTEND TO THE FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM BECAUSE MOST OUR DIFFICULTIES COME FROM IT.

OF WHAT DOES THIS PROBLEM CONSIST? WE CURRENTLY OWE $64 BILLION. THIS REPRESENTS A BURDEN OF $6 BILLION YEARLY IN INTEREST PAYMENTS. SINCE ARGENTINA IS CURRENTLY EXPORTING $9 BILLION ANNUALLY, AND IF WE PAID $6 BILLION IN INTEREST, WE WOULD ONLY HAVE $3 BILLION LEFT ANNUALLY TO ATTEND TO ALL OUR NATIONAL NEEDS, THAT IS, THE NEEDS OF INDUSTRY, COMMERCE, ETC.

OBVIOUSLY THIS IS NOT ENOUGH MONEY, AND WE CANNOT PAY $6 BILLION IN INTEREST EACH YEAR WITH $9 BILLION WORTH OF ANNUAL EXPORTS.

THIS IS NOT NEW. THIS IS A HEAVY INHERITANCE, WHICH ORIGINATED NOT IN THE RECENT PAST BUT MORE THAN 10 YEARS AGO. WHEN MARTINEZ DE HOZ BECAME ECONOMY MINISTER [MARCH 1976], THE FOREIGN DEBT AMOUNTED TO $9 BILLION. WHEN HE CONCLUDED HIS TERM, THE DEBT AMOUNTED TO $29 BILLION. THE MILITARY GOVERNMENTS THAT CAME AFTER HIM DRAGGED THE DEBT ALONG AND INCREASED IT TO $44 BILLION WHICH THEY PASSED TO PRESIDENT ALFONSIN. ALFONSIN'S ADMINISTRATION INCREASED THE DEBT BY AN ADDITIONAL $20 BILLION. SO TODAY OUR DEBT AMOUNTS TO $64 BILLION.

THIS IS NOT ALL. WE CEASED HONORING OUR COMMITMENTS ABROAD. WE HAVE NOT EVEN PAID INTEREST SINCE APRIL LAST YEAR. WE HAVE ONLY MADE TOKEN PAYMENTS. THIS REFUTES THE IDEAS OF THOSE WHO SAY: LET US STOP PAYING OUR DEBT AND USE THE RESOURCES TO MAKE THE COUNTRY GROW. WE ARE NOT PAYING ANYTHING.

FOR MORE THAN A YEAR WE HAVE NOT BEEN PAYING ANYTHING, AND NOT ONLY HAS THE ECONOMY NOT GROWN, BUT IT SHRANK.

ARGENTINA HAS AN EXTREMELY LOW CREDIT RATING. COUNTRIES ARE INTERNATIONALLY CLASSIFIED BY THEIR CREDIT, AND WE ARE IN ONE OF THE LOWEST CATEGORIES. OUR COMMERCIAL CREDIT IS ALSO BEING CURTAILED. COMMERCIAL CREDITS ARE THE ONES THAT ALLOW US TO IMPORT, EXPORT, AND MEET OUR DAILY NEEDS.

WHEN THE NEW ADMINISTRATION ASSUMED POWER ON 8 APRIL 1989, THE CENTRAL BANK'S FOREIGN RESERVES WERE EXHAUSTED. THIS SITUATION CAN TURN INTO A CRISIS AT ANY MOMENT. WE CANNOT CONTINUE LIKE THIS.

THE COMING OF THIS NEW GOVERNMENT, WHICH HAS BROUGHT ABOUT POSITIVE EXPECTATIONS AND HOPE, AND WHICH IS UNDERTAKING REMARKABLE CHANGES -- MAINLY CHANGES OF MENTALITY -- HAS STOPPED THE CRISIS FROM EXPLODING. BUT WE CANNOT REST ON OUR ACHIEVEMENTS. WE MUST FACE THIS PROBLEM IMMEDIATELY.

OUR STARTING POINT IN CERTAINLY VERY UNCOMFORTABLE. OUR COUNTRY HAS NO PRESTIGE ABROAD; WE HAVE LOST OUR CREDIBILITY. NO ONE EVEN WANTS TO HEAR ABOUT ARGENTINA, OR AT LEAST ABOUT ITS DEBT. IN THE PAST FEW YEARS WE HAVE NOT HONORED ANY OF OUR COMMIETMENTS. EVERY TIME WE SIGNED A LETTER OF INTENT WITH THE IMF, WE KNEW THAT WE COULD NOT COMPLY WITH IT. THERE HAVE BEEN SEVERAL LETTERS OF INTENT WE DID NOT COMPLY WITH.

WHAT POLICY WILL WE FOLLOW IN THE FUTURE? THE PRESIDENT DEFINED IT IN HIS MESSAGE TO CONGRESS ON 8 JULY. HE SAID WE HAVE A HEAVY BURDEN, A DEBT THAT WAS UNWISELY CONTRACTED, BUT IT IS A COMMITMENT OF HONOR. HE USED WORDS THAT WERE COMMON IN ARGENTINA IN THE PAST.

IT WAS ONCE SAID: WE WILL COMPLY WITH OUR COMMITMENTS, EVEN AT THE COST OF HUNGER AND THIRST FOR THE ARGENTINE PEOPLE. THE PRESIDENT HAS MADE HIS OWN COMMITMENT ON THIS SUBJECT. WE WILL PAY ACCORDING TO THE CAPABILITY OF THE NATION, AND THE ONLY THING WE REQUIRE IS A BIT OF TIME AND, OF COURSE, FLEXIBILITY ON THE PART OF OUR CREDITORS.

IF WE DID NOT HONOR OUR COMMITMENTS, IF WE HAD SAID WE ARE NOT GOING TO PAY, THE SITUATION IN OUR COUNTRY WOULD BE DRAMATICALLY WORSE. WE WOULD BE ISOLATED. WE WOULD NOT BE ABLE TO OBTAIN CREDITS, WE WOULD NOT BE ABLE TO OBTAIN FOREIGN CAPITAL INVESTMENTS. IN A WORD, WE WOULD NOT BE ABLE TO INTEGRATE THE REST OF THE WORLD, WHICH IS QUICKLY EXPANDING AND PROGRESSING. WE WOULD BE MUCH MORE BACKWARD THAN WE ARE TODAY. THEREFORE THERE IS REALLY NO QUESTION OF PAYING OR NOT PAYING. THE HONOR OF THE COUNTRY IS AT STAKE.

WHAT IS THE ROLE OF THE FOREIGN DEBT IN OUR ECONOMIC RECOVERY? YOU KNOW THAT WE HAVE EVERYTHING NECESSARY. WE HAVE NATURAL RESOURCES, FOOD, ENERGY, FISHING, MINING, ETC. WE HAVE HUMAN RESOURCES. YOU KNOW THAT WHEN ARGENTINES WORK ABROAD THEY ARE EFFICIENT AND THEY ARE RECOGNIZED AS SUCH. WE HAVE NO INTERNAL RELIGIOUS, RACIAL, OR INDIAN PROBLEMS, NOT EVEN PROBLEMS WITH OUR NEIGHBORS.

WHAT ARE WE MISSING? WHY ARE WE WHERE WE ARE, AND WHY CAN'T WE SURVIVE? WE NEED TWO THINGS: FIRST, WE NEED AN APPROPRIATE ECONOMIC ORDER. WE LIVE IN A DEEP ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DISORDER. SECOND, WE NEED CAPITAL. CAPITAL IS ABSOLUTELY NECESSARY.

I SAID THAT I WAS GOING TO DISCUSS THE SAVINGS IN ARGENTINA THAT CAN BE TAPPED. FOR YEARS, ARGENTINA'S SAVINGS HAVE BEEN CONSTANTLY PUNISHED BY GOVERNMENT ACTIONS, SUCH AS ABUSIVE TAXES, MANDATORY SAVINGS, AND, ABOVE ALL, THE GREAT EROSION CAUSED BY INFLATION THAT DESTROYS THE CURRENCY. JUST REMEMBER HOW MANY TIMES WE HAVE CHANGED OUR CURRENCY. TO PROTECT THEMSELVES FROM THESE LOSSES, WHAT DID SAVERS DO? THEY EITHER TOOK THEIR MONEY ABROAD OR HID IT UNDER THEIR MATTRESSES. WE WILL FOCUS TODAY ON THE MONEY UNDER THE MATTRESSES, ALTHOUGH WHAT I WILL SAY NOW WILL ALSO BE RELEVANT FOR THOSE WHO HAVE THEIR SAVINGS ABROAD. ACCORDING TO CALCULATIONS, THERE ARE SMALL, MEDIUM, AND LARGE SAVINGS ADDING UP TO NEARLY $5 BILLION IN THE COUNTRY. A PERSON WAS ASSAULTED IN CORDOBA THE OTHER DAY AND $250,000 WAS FOUND IN HIS MATTRESS. MONEY UNDER THE MATTRESS IS AT RISK, DOES NOT ACCRUE INTEREST, DOES NOT WORK FOR THE COUNTRY, AND DOES NOT GIVE ANY BENEFIT TO THE OWNERS NOR THE COUNTRY.

SOME OF OUR HOPE LIES IN THESE SAVINGS INSIDE AND OUTSIDE OF THE COUNTRY, BECAUSE THEY REPRESENT A RESERVE THAT WE HAVE ON HAND. WE ARE NOT BANKRUPT. WE HAVE THOSE RESERVES, ALTHOUGH THEY ARE NOT WORKING. THE SECRET IS TO USE THEM FOR THE COUNTRY'S BENEFIT. ARGENTINA'S PROBLEMS CAN BE RESOLVED IF THESE SAVINGS ARE USED. NOW, TO TAP INTO THESE SAVINGS, THE GOVERNMENT HAS MADE A DECISION, AND THE CENTRAL BANK HAS ALREADY TRANSLATED IT INTO A RESOLUTION. INTO BANKS HERE IN THE COUNTRY IN DOLLARS, YEN, DEUTSCHE MARKS, OR ANY OTHER CURRENCY. THEY WILL BE ABLE TO MAKE WITHDRAWALS WHENEVER THEY WANT IN THE SAME CURRENCY IN WHICH THEIR SAVINGS WERE DEPOSITED. NOBODY WILL BE ALLOWED TO TOUCH THEM. THIS WILL BE REINFORCED BY A LAW GRANTING SAVERS THE MAXIMUM GUARANTEE THAT NO PUBLIC POWER CAN INTERVENE IN THOSE SAVINGS; THAT IS, THERE WILL BE A FINANCIAL SYSTEM INTO WHICH THOSE SAVINGS, IN ANY CURRENCY, CAN BE PLACED FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE COUNTRY AND, OF COURSE, THE DEPOSITOR. ANYBODY WHO HAS $10,000 UNDER HIS MATTRESS CAN TAKE IT OUT, GO TO THE BANK, AND, UNDER THE GUARANTEE OF THE BANK -- NOT THE CENTRAL BANK OR THE NATION, WHICH HAVE BEEN DISCREDITED -- THE MONEY WILL BE AT HIS DISPOSAL AT ANY TIME. THE BANK WILL LEND THE MONEY FOR EXPORT OPERATIONS AND FOR MOVING THE COUNTRY'S WEALTH. NEW BLOOD WILL THUS HAVE BEEN INJECTED INTO THE ARGENTINE FINANCIAL SYSTEM.

I POINT OUT THAT THE LAW WILL GIVE MAXIMUM GUARANTEES. NO PUBLIC POWER WILL HAVE THE RIGHT TO SEIZE THE SAVINGS, NOR FREEZE THEM, NOR POSTPONE THEIR WITHDRAWAL. THESE ARE THE MAXIMUM GUARANTEES THAT CAN BE GIVEN; MORE IS IMPOSSIBLE. EACH ARGENTINE MUST NOW THINK ABOUT WHAT THIS MEANS. IT HAS A CRUCIAL IMPORTANCE, BECAUSE IT INJECTS BLOOD INTO THE SOCIAL BODY; IT MOVES THE COUNTRY. MOREOVER, FROM THE MORAL STANDPOINT, IF WE DO NOT DO THIS, HOW CAN WE GO ABROAD AND ASK FOREIGNERS TO INVEST IN ARGENTINA -- TO BRING THEIR MONEY TO ARGENTINA -- IF AT THE SAME TIME I DO NOT INVEST HERE BECAUSE I DO NOT HAVE CONFIDENCE IN MY COUNTRY? THIS IS AN IMMORAL POSITION.

IF WE MAKE THE INITIAL EFFORT AND DEPOSIT $2, 3 OR 4 BILLION IN THE COUNTRY, OUR NEGOTIATIONS ABROAD TAKE A NEW TWIST, BECAUSE WE CAN SAY THAT THE ARGENTINES HAVE MADE THE FIRST EFFORT. ALL THIS NATURALLY DEPENDS ON CONFIDENCE, AND CONFIDENCE IN TURN DEPENDS ON TAKING THIS FIRST STEP. THIS IS A RECIPROCAL EFFECT. TO CREATE CONFIDENCE, MEASURES SUCH AS THOSE ADOPTED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE CENTRAL BANK HAVE TO BE ADOPTED. THESE MEASURES CREATE CONFIDENCE, AND WITH CONFIDENCE THE COUNTRY WILL QUICKLY RECOVER. WE HAVE MANY OTHER THINGS TO SAY ABOUT THIS, BUT WITHIN THE LIMITATION OF TIME, WE CAN STOP HERE.

DEV-MUC3-0314 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

LIMA, 28 JUL 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [SPEECH] [PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA] [EXCERPTS] MR PRESIDENT OF CONGRESS, GENTLEMEN MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL CONGRESS:

TEN YEARS AGO, THE MEMBERS OF THE CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY PRESIDED OVER BY HAYA DE LA TORRE, CALLING UP ON LORD GOD FOR STRENGTH AND IN KEEPING WITH THE POWERS VESTED IN US BY THE SOVEREIGN WILL OF THE PEOPLE, APPROVED THE NATIONAL CONSTITUTION. WE BELIEVE THAT THE HUMAN BEING COMES FIRST AND THAT ALL HONORABLE PEOPLE HAVE UNIVERSALLY VALID RIGHTS. THUS WE DECIDED TO WORK FOR A FREE AND JUST SOCIETY AND FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF A DEMOCRATIC STATE BASED ON POPULAR WILL AND ON THE FREE, PERIODIC CONSULTATION OF THIS WILL.

WE BET ON CIVILIZED COEXISTENCE AS A WAY OF LAUNCHING A PROCESS BASED ON STABLE AND LEGITIMATE INSTITUTIONS. THE MOST IMPORTANT CONDITIONS, HOWEVER, WERE SET FORTH IN CHAPTER 1, WHICH RECOGNIZED THE INDIVIDUAL'S BASIC RIGHTS AND DUTIES FOR THE FREE DEVELOPMENT OF HIS PERSONALITY.

OUR CONSTITUTION WAS A RESULT OF THE BALANCE ACHIEVED AMONG VARIOUS AND SOMETIMES ANTAGONISTIC POLITICAL FORCES. THUS, SOME OF ITS ECONOMIC ARTICLES MAY SEEM VAGUE. HOWEVER, UNDER THIS CONSTITUTION ANY IDEOLOGY CAN GOVERN THE COUNTRY AND MAKE CHANGES IN ANY DIRECTION WHATSOEVER, AS LONG AS THOSE FIRST CONDITIONS AGREED UPON BY CONSENSUS ARE RESPECTED. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THIS IS THE LAST MESSAGE I WILL DELIVER TO CONGRESS AS PRESIDENT BEFORE I TURN THE PRESIDENCY OVER TO A CITIZEN ELECTED BY THE PEOPLE.

I CANNOT FAIL TO EXPAND ON THE ACHIEVEMENTS MADE THIS YEAR, WHICH, HONESTLY SPEAKING ARE MUCH FEWER THAN IN PREVIOUS YEARS. I AM DELIVERING A SUMMARY OF THESE ACHIEVEMENTS IN WRITING, AS ESTABLISH BY THE CONSTITUTION, FOR THE USE OF THE LEGISLATORS. IT IS A SUMMARY OF MATERIAL ACHIEVEMENTS.

IT IS NOW MORE IMPORTANT TO ME TO SAY THAT THE MAIN OBJECTIVE OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THE NEXT 12 MONTHS WILL BE TO REAFFIRM THE SYSTEM OF DEMOCRATIC FREEDOM, WHICH IS THE MOST IMPORTANT SYSTEM PERU HAS. WITH THIS FREEDOM, EVEN THE MOST EXTREME POSITIONS CAN EXIST. THE REACTIONARY POSITIONS OF THE ULTRARIGHT AND RADICAL IDEOLOGIES CAN ALSO LIVE IN FREEDOM. VIOLENCE HAS LESS CHANCE OF DEVELOPING IN FREEDOM. THE NATION HAS MORE LEGITIMATE MEANS TO ERADICATE VIOLENCE UNDER FREEDOM.

LIKE ANY OTHER CITIZEN, I ALSO BELIEVE THAT SOMETIMES DISAGREEMENTS, POLITICAL PARTIES, LAWS, AND SKILLFUL LEGAL PROCEDURES CAN OBSTRUCT MANY THINGS AND STOP DECISIONS. BUT THIS IS THE PRICE FOR A CIVILIZED LIFESTYLE. DEMOCRACY DOES NOT HAVE THE FORTHRIGHTNESS OF A DICTATORSHIP. DEMOCRACY IS SLOWER, BUT DEMANDS MORE FIRMNESS, MORE CONVICTION, MORE PATIENCE. DEMOCRACY DEMANDS THE GRADUAL EDUCATION OF THE PEOPLE; THIS TAKES A LONG TIME. I AM SAYING THIS BECAUSE THE COUNTRY HAS BEEN SUFFERING A DRAMATIC ECONOMIC CRISIS SINCE SEPTEMBER 1988, AND IT HAS BEEN NECESSARY TO MAKE HARSH CHANGES AT A TIME WHEN VIOLENCE HAS SEEMED TO INCREASE.

WE HEARD SOME PEOPLE WHO HAD LOST THEIR COOL DEMANDING AN INTERRUPTION OF OUR DEMOCRACY. THEY CALLED FOR A SHORTER GOVERNMENT TERM. THEY ALSO SAID THAT THE COUNTRY COULD DEFEAT THE TERRORIST VIOLENCE AND THE ECONOMIC CRISIS BY RESTRICTING FREEDOM AND ESTABLISHING AN AUTHORITARIAN REGIME.

I BELIEVE THAT THOSE WERE IMMATURE VOICES, DECEITFUL TEMPTATIONS. MANY OF THOSE VOICES UNFORTUNATELY CAME FROM PEOPLE WHO HAVE MORE WEALTH. BY DOING THIS THEY HAVE SHOWN THAT THEY ARE NOT YET READY TO COEXIST DEMOCRATICALLY AND TO ACCEPT THAT SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC TENSIONS, EVEN AT THE WORSE TIMES, SHOULD BE HANDLED WITH SERENITY AND PATIENCE. A DICTATORSHIP THAT VIOLATES LEGAL PROCEDURES WILL ONLY HELP TO INCREASE VIOLENCE AND LEGITIMATE INSURGENCY, AND WOULD STIMULATE THE CREATION OF NEW SUBVERSIVE GROUPS. A DICTATORSHIP CANNOT SOLVE THE ECONOMIC CRISIS. IT WOULD ONLY HAVE LIMITED POWER AND WOULD IMPOSE A TRAUMATIC EXPERIENCE THAT WOULD LEAD NOWHERE.

I AM REFERRING TO THIS ISSUE BECAUSE THE NEXT 12 MONTHS WILL BE A CRUCIAL PERIOD. I CALL ON THE PERUVIAN PEOPLE TO LOOK AT THE FUTURE OF OUR DEMOCRACY BY REALIZING THAT IN A DEMOCRACY THE PROBLEMS ARE SOLVED WITH MORE DEMOCRACY, WITH MORE FREEDOM, AND WITH MORE PARTICIPATION. TO HAVE DEMOCRACY, ONE MUST HAVE A GREAT DEAL OF PATIENCE.

THIS IS MY LAST MESSAGE TO CONGRESS. I AM COMMITTED TO MORE FREEDOM AND MORE FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION, WHICH SOMETIMES WE DOUBT BECAUSE OF EXCESSES. BUT FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION WILL ALWAYS BE POSITIVE, BECAUSE WITHOUT FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION ABUSE WILL PREVAIL. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0317 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

GUATEMALA CITY, 1 AUG 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO SAID TODAY THAT DANILO BARILLAS, FORMER AMBASSADOR AND LEADER OF THE RULING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC], WAS THE "VICTIM OF THE POLITICAL INTOLERANCE OF GROUPS WHO DO NOT WANT TO LIVE IN DEMOCRACY."

IN STATEMENTS TO NEWSMEN, CEREZO SAID THAT THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR KILLING BARILLAS "ARE EXTREME RIGHTIST GROUPS SEEKING TO DESTABILIZE THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS BEGUN ON 14 JANUARY 1986," AFTER 2 DECADES OF MILITARY REGIMES.

POLICE SOURCES REPORTED THAT BARILLAS, AMBASSADOR TO SPAIN DURING THE FIRST 2 YEARS OF CEREZO'S ADMINISTRATION, WHICH BEGAN IN 1986, WAS GUNNED DOWN BY UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS AS HE WAS RETURNING TO HIS HOME IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF THE CAPITAL AFTER TAKING ONE OF HIS DAUGHTERS TO A NEARBY BUS STOP.

OFFICIAL REPORTS INDICATE THAT THE ATTACKERS, WHO WERE TRAVELING IN TWO VEHICLES WITH TINTED WINDOWS, HAD BEEN WAITING FOR BARILLAS SINCE VERY EARLY IN THE MORNING. DE POLITICAL LEADER MANAGED TO AVOID THE FIRST SHOTS THAT WERE FIRED AT HIM AND TOOK REFUGE UNDER A PARKED CAR, WHERE THE ASSAILANTS PUMPED 6 ROUNDS INTO HIM.

BARILLAS, 50, WAS SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE PDC FROM 1970 TO 1974.

PRESIDENT CEREZO AND ALFONSO CABRERA, PDC SECRETARY AND PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL FOR THAT PARTY, WENT TO BARILLAS' HOME WHERE THEY VEHEMENTLY CONDEMNED THE CRIME.

CABRERA TERMED THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE KILLING "COWARDS," AND SAID THAT THE CRIME IS PART OF A TERRORIST WAVE THAT HAS GRIPPED GUATEMALA FOR OVER 15 DAYS.

BARILLAS WAS A MEMBER OF THE GUATEMALAN DELEGATION THAT PARTICIPATED IN A MEETING WITH LEADERS OF THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY (URNG) HELD IN MADRID, SPAIN, IN OCTOBER 1987, WHEN HE WAS AMBASSADOR TO THAT EUROPEAN COUNTRY.

AFTER LEAVING THAT POST LAST YEAR HE WAS APPOINTED BY PRESIDENT CEREZO AS DIRECTOR OF THE SO-CALLED "METROPOLITAN DEVELOPMENT COUNCILS," WHICH PROVIDE REFUGE FOR PEASANTS AFFECTED BY THE COUNTERINSURGENCY STRUGGLE.

DEV-MUC3-0319 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

CLANDESTINE, 1 AUG 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] URBAN GUERRILLAS, CLANDESTINE MILITIAS, AND GUERRILLAS. ACCORDING TO THE REPORTS WE HAVE RECEIVED THUS FAR, THE OPERATION HAS BEEN CARRIED OUT AS FOLLOWS:

1. GUERRILLA COLUMNS ATTACKED SAN RAMON -- SPECIFICALLY THE PARAMILITARY FORCES HEADQUARTERS AND THE NATIONAL GUARD POSTS -- AND CARRIED OUT SABOTAGE ACTIONS, AMBUSHES OF ENEMY REINFORCEMENTS, AND COMBAT WITH ARMY PATROLS, AS WELL AS DISTRIBUTING PROPAGANDA.

2. ATTACKS ON THE CIVIL DEFENSE GARRISON IN MEJICANOS AND COMBAT ACTIONS IN EL PISO, AS WELL AS THE DISTRIBUTION OF PROPAGANDA.

3. SABOTAGE ACTIONS AGAINST THE ELECTRICITY SYSTEM IN THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS AND OTHER POINTS IN THE CAPITAL CITY, WHICH HAS BEEN LEFT WITHOUT ELECTRICITY AND [WORDS INDISTINCT].

4. DISTRIBUTION OF PROPAGANDA IN THE DOWNTOWN AREA OF THE CAPITAL CITY AND ARMY BOULEVARD. 5. AMBUSHES OF MILITARY DETACHMENTS. 6. COMBAT

ACTIONS AGAINST ARMY UNITS IN THE MIRALVALLE, SATELITE, MONTE BELLO, ZACAMIL, ADUC, AND OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS. DURING THIS OPERATION, WE HAVE TAKEN A QUALITATIVE LEAP IN COORDINATING OUR URBAN FORCES IN SIMULTANEOUS ATTACKS.

THIS IS OUR RESPONSE TO THE DEATH SQUADS' ECONOMIC POLICY [WORDS INDISTINCT] HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, RAIDS, TORTURES, AND MURDERS OF LABOR UNION MOVEMENT MEMBERS. AS WE HAVE DEMONSTRATED THROUGH OUR URBAN OPERATION, THE [WORD INDISTINCT] PLAN IS NOT AGAINST THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], BUT AGAINST ALL NATIONAL SECTORS WITH THE AIM OF STIFLING ALL OPPOSITION TO THE ARENA'S [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] PLANS OF PERMANENTLY PLACING IN POWER THE OLIGARCHIC MINORITY IT REPRESENTS.

THE FMLN CALLS ON ALL NATIONAL SECTORS TO JOIN EFFORTS TO DEFEAT ARENA'S TOTAL WAR PLANS SO THAT ALL SALVADORANS UNITED AGAINST FASCISM WILL FIND A NATIONAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, 1 AUGUST 1989

DEV-MUC3-0321 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 AUG 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [EXCERPT] TWO PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND THREE WOUNDED IN AN ATTACK ON THE LOCAL MILITARY COMMAND POST IN SAN RAMON BY FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] UNITS.

THE GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THE COMMAND POST IN SAN RAMON WITH MORTARS AND RIFLE FIRE. THE FIGHTING LASTED NEARLY 2 HOURS. ONE CIVILIAN AND ONE SOLDIER WERE KILLED, AND SEVERAL PARAMILITARY SQUAD MEMBERS AND CIVILIANS WERE WOUNDED.

AFTER THE FIGHTING, OUR CAMERAMEN TOOK THESE CLIPS, WHICH SHOW THE HARSHNESS AND CRUELTY OF THIS WAR, WHICH HAS AFFECTED MANY CIVILIANS. AS CAN BE SEEN, THE CIVILIANS WERE WAITING TO BE RESCUED BY HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, BUT FOR SOME PEOPLE IT WAS ALREADY TOO LATE, BECAUSE THEY WERE KILLED IN THE CROSSFIRE.

THE COMMAND POST IN SOYAPANGO WAS ALSO ATTACKED ON 30 JULY, AND ONE PERSON WAS KILLED. DURING TODAY'S ATTACK ON SAN RAMON, THE CIVIL DEFENSE UNITS WERE SUPPORTED BY THE RAMON BELLOSO BATTALION, WHICH WAS ABLE TO GAIN CONTROL OF THE SITUATION BY NIGHTFALL. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0322 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 2 AUG 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [EXCERPTS] THE SALVADORAN ARMY IS ON A STATE OF ALERT AND HAS INCREASED ITS SURVEILLANCE IN SAN SALVADOR TO COUNTER A NEW GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE, WHICH HAS CAUSED AT LEAST 48 MILITARY CASUALTIES OVER THE PAST 24 HOURS IN SEVERAL ACTIONS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

TREASURY POLICE DIRECTOR COLONEL HERIBERTO HERNANDEZ REPORTED THAT THE STATE OF ALERT IS DESIGNED TO PREVENT SABOTAGE AND THE DELIVERY OF WEAPONS FOR THE GUERRILLAS. IT INCLUDES AN INCREASE IN LAND AND AIR PATROLS AND SEARCHES OF BUSES AND PRIVATE VEHICLES.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) OFFENSIVE HAS BEEN LAUNCHED TO PROTEST THE GOVERNMENT'S LATEST ECONOMIC MEASURES, INCLUDING THE DEREGULATION OF STAPLE PRICES, THE PRIVATIZATION OF COFFEE EXPORTS AND BANKING ACTIVITIES, AND AN INCREASE IN BUS FARES AND ELECTRICITY BILLS.

COL HERNANDEZ SAID: "THE GOVERNMENT WANTS WHAT IS BEST FOR THE PEOPLE, SO LAND TRANSPORTATION USERS WILL LOGICALLY BE AFFECTED BY THE INCREASE, BUT BUSINESSMEN ARE ALSO TRYING TO SOLVE THEIR PROBLEMS."

A CLANDESTINE REBEL STATION ASSERTED THAT THE ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT IN MORAZAN, USULUTAN, METAPAN, SAN MIGUEL, CABANAS, SAN VICENTE, LA PAZ, SAN SALVADOR, AND THE CONFLICT-RIDDEN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

THE ARMED FORCES CLAIMED THEY HAD NO INFORMATION ON THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES OR THE CLASHES ANNOUNCED BY THE FMLN AND ASSERTED THAT, CONTRARY TO THE FMLN REPORT, THREE GUERRILLA FIGHTERS HAD DIED AND FIVE HAD BEEN KILLED IN VARIOUS CLASHES THAT OCCURRED IN NORTHERN AND EASTERN TOWNS, AND IN THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL.

NEVERTHELESS, THE ARMY RECOGNIZED THAT TWO SOLDIERS AND TWO CIVILIANS HAD DIED, AND FOUR WERE WOUNDED IN ATTACKS ON ARMY POSITIONS AND IN AMBUSHES AGAINST ARMY AND GOVERNMENT VEHICLES.

THE REBELS ALSO INCREASED THEIR SABOTAGE ACTIVITIES AGAINST THE ELECTRICAL POWER SYSTEM AND BLEW UP A STILL UNDETERMINED NUMBER OF STRUCTURES AND TELEPHONE EXCHANGE BOXES IN SAN SALVADOR. THEY ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT THEY HAVE PLACED EXPLOSIVE DEVICES ON SOME OF THE COUNTRY'S MAIN HIGHWAYS.

DEV-MUC3-0325 (INTEL TEXT PROC)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 JUL 89 (EL MUNDO) -- [TEXT] "I DO NOT WANT TO INTERFERE AT ALL. THE JUDGE WILL PRONOUNCE THE VERDICT; MEANWHILE, I WILL WAIT AND KEEP SILENT," MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, AUXILIARY BISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, SAID YESTERDAY REGARDING HIS BROTHER SHORTLY AFTER ENDING SUNDAY'S [30 JULY] HOMILY AT THE CATHEDRAL.

THE PRELATE WAS REFERRING TO THE ARREST OF SALOMON ENRIQUE ROSA CHAVEZ, WHO WAS TURNED OVER TO THE FIRST CRIMINAL COURT BY THE NATIONAL POLICE AND ACCUSED OF BELONGING TO THE PEOPLE'S REVOLUTIONARY ARMY (ERP). THE FIRST CRIMINAL COURT JUDGE ORDERED HIS TEMPORARY ARREST FOLLOWING A 72 - HOUR PERIOD, AS ESTABLISHED BY LAW FOR CRIMES OF BEARING COUNTERFEIT DOCUMENTS AND FOR BRIBERY; THESE CRIMES DO NOT REQUIRE A PRISON SENTENCE.

THE AUXILIARY BISHOP SAID: "I HAVE REMAINED SILENT OUT OF RESPECT FOR THE LEGAL PROCESS, WHICH IS STILL UNDER WAY. MY BROTHER IS STILL IN PRISON, AND THAT IS WHY I PREFER TO WAIT FOR THE PROCESS TO END," HE SAID. THE PRISONER WAS NOT RELEASED ON SATURDAY, BUT HE WILL BE RELASED ON MONDAY, 7 AUGUST.

ASKED BY REPORTERS IF THE CHARGES MADE AGAINST HIS BROTHER WOULD HURT HIS [MSGR ROSA CHAVEZ'S] IMAGE OR THAT OF THE CHURCH, HE SAID THAT THE CHURCH'S DUTY TO THE COUNTRY IS DIFFICULT TO FULFILL BUT THAT THE CHURCH'S EFFORTS MUST CONTINUE, BECAUSE THE HUGE NUMBER OF PARISHIONERS WHO COME TO THE CATHEDRAL EVERY SUNDAY TO EASE THEIR PAINS CANNOT BE ABANDONED.

"A SHEPHERD SHOULD NEVER LEAVE HIS FLOCK, AND, WHEN THERE ARE PROBLEMS, WE WILL CALMLY DEAL WITH THEM, BECAUSE THAT IS PART OF OUR MISSION," HE SAID.

THE PRELATE EXPRESSED HIS CONCERN OVER THE SERIES OF CONTROVERSIES THAT AROSE DURING THE WEEK, SUCH AS THE CHARGES AND THE COUNTERCHARGES. HE SAID THAT THE MOST SERIOUS THING IS THE "CASE OF MSGR ROMERO," WHOSE MEMORY CONTINUES TO INSPIRE MANY AND IS A NIGHTMARE FOR THE MASTERMINDS AND PERPETRATORS OF HIS ABOMINABLE ASSASSINATION.

THESE CHARGES WERE MADE AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL BY FORMER PRESIDENT DUARTE, CURRENT ADMINISTRATION MEMBERS, AND WELL-KNOWN POLITICAL FIGURES. ROSA CHAVEZ REFERRED TO THE CHARGES FILED BY ATTORNEY GENERAL DR MAURICIO ERNESTO COLORADO, WHO LAST WEEK ASKED THE FIRST TREASURY COURT JUDGE TO DRAW UP AN INDICTMENT AGAINST JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, MEMBERS OF HIS FAMILY, AND A CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY LEADER.

THE AUXILIARY BISHOP SAID: "I GREATLY REGRET THE FACT THAT THIS ATMOSPHERE IS ONE OF -- I ACCUSE YOU, YOU ACCUSE ME, AND WE ACCUSE EACH OTHER. THAT IS NO WAY TO MAKE PROGRESS, BECAUSE PEOPLE EXPECT THEIR LEADERS TO BE MORE RESPONSIBLE AND SERIOUS. OTHERWISE, WHAT WILL THOSE OF US WHO ARE UNDERLINGS LEARN? THAT IS WHY I HAVE EXPRESSED THE NEED FOR ALL OF US TO HELP CLEAR THE AIR SO THAT WE CAN ACHIEVE THE PEACE FOR WHICH WE ALL YEARN."

MSGR ROSA CHAVEZ CONGRATULATED ALL JOURNALISTS IN HIS HOMILY AND SAID: "I REMIND ALL JOURNALISTS -- AS POPE JOHN PAUL II ONCE SAID -- THAT NEWS, IF ONE THINKS ABOUT IT, IS NEVER IMPARTIAL, BECAUSE IT AT LEAST INTENTIONALLY AND IMPLICITLY RESPONDS TO IMPORTANT MATTERS. JOURNALISM PROVIDES AN INTIMATE LINK BETWEEN THE NEWS, EDUCATION, AND ESSENTIAL VALUES. ALMOST ALL MEN AND WOMEN WORKING FOR THE PRESS, RADIO, AND TELEVISION MEDIA MUST TRY TO ACCOMPLISH THIS TASK. HOWEVER, EACH DAY THEY NEED COURAGE AND MUST HAVE MUCH LOVE FOR THIS PEOPLE, WHO HAVE SUFFERED GREATLY, SO THAT THEY WILL REMAIN LOYAL TO THE VALUES OF THEIR PROFESSION. THAT IS WHY OUR CONGRATULATION MESSAGE BECOMES A PRAYER FOR THE LORD TO PROTECT THEM AND HELP THEM NOT TO GIVE IN DURING DIFFICULT TIMES."

DEV-MUC3-0326 (BBN)

GUATEMALA CITY, 4 AUG 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] POLICE REPORTED TODAY THAT RENE LOPEZ, AN IMMIGRATION OFFICIAL AND LEADER OF THE RULING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC], WAS SHOT TO DEATH AFTER HE WAS KIDNAPPED BY UNIDENTIFIED MEN.

THE AUTHORITIES DISCLOSED TODAY THAT LOPEZ, WHO WORKED AT THE INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT'S IMMIGRATION DEPARTMENT, WAS KIDNAPPED ON 2 AUGUST AND HIS BODY WAS FOUND IN SOUTHERN GUATEMALA CITY TODAY.

LOPEZ' DEATH IS ONE MORE PDC LEADER MURDERED. DANILO BARILLAS, ANOTHER PDC LEADER, WAS KILLED ON 1 AUGUST, APPARENTLY BY EXTREME RIGHTIST GROUPS.

SO FAR, IT IS NOT KNOWN IF THE TWO KILLINGS ARE CONNECTED BECAUSE THE AUTHORITIES HAVE REMAINED SILENT ABOUT THIS CASE WHICH WAS NOT DISCLOSED UNTIL TODAY.

UNOFFICIAL SOURCES NOTED THAT IT IS BELIEVED THAT THE TWO LEADERS KNEW TOO MANY DETAILS AND POSSIBLY NAMES OF PEOPLE INVOLVED IN COCAINE TRAFFICKING.

HOWEVER, LOPEZ' RELATIVES REJECTED THAT HIS MURDER HAD ANY CONNECTION WITH THE DRUG TRAFFICKING DISCOVERED AT THE AIRPORT THIS WEEK.

SECURITY FORCES FOUND 22 KG OF COCAINE IN A SUITCASE OWNED BY JOSE FERNANDO MINRO NAVAS, AN OFFICIAL OF THE PRESIDENCY'S ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT, ON 1 AUGUST. MINRO WAS CAPTURED AND TURNED OVER TO A COURT.

POLICE SOURCES STATED THAT THEY HAVE CONTINUED THE INVESTIGATIONS TO GET MORE DETAILS OF THE TWO KILLINGS BUT THEY NEITHER DENIED NOR CONFIRMED ANY CONNECTION OF SUSPECTED DRUG TRAFFICKERS WITH THE MURDER OF THE PDC LEADERS.

DEV-MUC3-0328 (BBN)

TEGUCIGALPA, 3 AUG 89 (CADENA AUDIO VIDEO) -- [REPORT] [MIRIAM MERCADO] [EXCERPTS] RAMON CUSTODIO LOPEZ, PRESIDENT OF THE HUMAN RIGHTS DEFENSE COMMITTEE [CODEH] HAS PREDICTED THAT THE TELA SUMMIT WILL BE CHAOTIC BECAUSE, IN HIS OPINION, THE HONDURAN AND SALVADORAN GOVERNMENTS WILL INTERFERE. THE CODEH PRESIDENT ALSO REVEALED THAT THE BATTALION 3-16'S NEW NAME IS THE COUNTERINSURGENCY BATTALION AND ITS COMMANDER IS COLONEL ALBERTO ANDINO BENITEZ. CUSTODIO SAID THIS DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE HE HELD 2 AUGUST.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CUSTODIO] WE HAVE CALLED THIS NEWS CONFERENCE BECAUSE WE WANT TO WARN THE PEOPLE, THE FOREIGN JOURNALISTS WHO ARE HERE, AND THE OTHER CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ABOUT THE ATMOSPHERE OF INSECURITY WHICH AFFLICTS THE HONDURAN PEOPLE.

FIRST OF ALL, WE WILL MENTION THE ASSASSINATIONS WHICH OCCURRED IN JULY AT SAN PEDRO SULA: EDUARDO HERRERA, SALOMON VALLECILLO, AND DR RAMON ROBERTO GARAY. WE BELIEVE THAT THE ASSASSINATIONS WERE PERPETRATED BY PROFESSIONALS SO WE WOULD LIKE A JUDGE TO CALL THE NEW COMMANDER OF BATTALION 3-16 -- NOW CALLED COUNTERINSURGENCY BATTALION -- COLONEL ALBERTO ANDINO BENITEZ TO TESTIFY. THERE ARE REPORTS THAT A MEMBER OF THE 3-16TH BATTALION CONTACTED SALOMON VALLECILLO PRIOR TO HIS DEATH.

LIKEWISE, I WANT TO MENTION HOW THE CITIZENRY IS EXPOSED TO POLICE BRUTALITY. THERE IS THE CASE OF JUSTO PASTOR ESCOBAR SILVA, WHO WAS ASSASSINATED BY A FUSEP [PUBLIC SECURITY FORCES] AGENT WHO IS NOW SERVING A PRISON SENTENCE.

FURTHERMORE, PEOPLE FEEL INSECURE IN THE COUNTRY, AND I WILL MENTION A CASE WHICH OCCURRED 3 WEEKS AGO. DR MARCO ANTONIO BOGRAN WAS TAKEN WITH ALL HIS HOUSEHOLD EMPLOYEES TO THE DNI [DEPARTMENT OF NATIONAL INVESTIGATION] AND HELD FROM 0800 TO 1500. HE WAS NOT ALLOWED TO CALL HIS LAWYER OR HIS RELATIVES, AND HE WAS HELD IN ISOLATION. HE WAS NATURALLY AFRAID THE WORST WOULD HAPPEN. NO ONE EXPLAINED ANYTHING UNTIL THE END. HE WAS TOLD THAT SOMEONE HAD REPORTEDLY MADE A SUBVERSIVE PHONE CALL FROM HIS HOUSE. THIS MEANS THAT HIS TELEPHONE IS BEING ILLEGALLY TAPPED BECAUSE NO ONE HERE HAS THE RIGHT TO CONTROL ANYONE'S CALLS. THE MILITARY MEN IN CHARGE OF HONDUTEL [HONDURAN TELECOMMUNICATIONS ENTERPRISE] ILLEGALLY ABUSE THEIR POWER WHEN THEY HEAR AND CONTROL TELEPHONE CALLS BECAUSE THIS SHOULD BE HANDLED BY THE CIVILIAN AUTHORITIES. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

COLONEL MANUEL ENRIQUE SUAREZ BENAVIDES, CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICE, HAS REACTED TO CUSTODIO LOPEZ' STATEMENT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [COL SUAREZ] I HAVE HEARD PART OF RAMON CUSTODIO'S NEWS CONFERENCE ON CODEH FOREIGN POLICY, AND WE OBSERVED HIS ANIMOSITY TOWARD THE CONTRAS AND HIS AFFECTION FOR THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT IN EL SALVADOR. WE THOUGHT HE ONLY HANDLED HUMAN RIGHTS BUT WE SEE HE ALSO DELVES IN FOREIGN POLICY. HOWEVER, THIS IS NOT THE MAIN ISSUE.

I WANT TO REFER TO THE FACT THAT YEARS AGO WE PUBLICLY PROVED THAT BATTALION 3-16, WHICH HE MENTIONED SO MANY TIMES, HAD BEEN DISMANTLED SO THE UNIT NO LONGER EXISTS. NEVERTHELESS, HE SEEMS TO HAVE FORGOTTEN THIS, OR HE MAY BE INTENTIONALLY FORGETTING THIS. THE UNIT DISAPPEARED BUT THE COUNTERINTELLIGENCE BATTALION HE MENTIONS DOES EXIST AND ITS COMMANDER, WHICH HE MENTIONS, IS A MEMBER OF THE ARMED FORCES. IN OTHER WORDS, HE HAS ABSOLUTELY NOTHING TO DO WITH THE ACTIVITIES THAT BATTALION 3-16 REPORTEDLY CARRIED OUT. IF CUSTODIO WANTS IT, WE CAN SEND HIM A COPY OF THE AGREEMENTS TO DISMANTLE BATTALION 3-16 AND TO APPOINT THE CURRENT COMMANDER OF THE COUNTERINTELLIGENCE BATTALION, WHICH HAS EXISTED FOR MANY YEARS. THAT IS ALL. I WANTED TO CLARIFY THIS AND I HOPE DR CUSTODIO IS MORE OBJECTIVE IN HIS STATEMENTS. I SOMETIMES BELIEVE THAT THE PROBLEM OF BEING ON ONE SIDE [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE MIND.

[REPORTER] COLONEL, WHEN WILL THE ARMED FORCES BE ABLE TO GIVE THE HONDURAN PEOPLE EXACT INFORMATION ON THE LATEST PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN REPORTED MISSING IN OUR COUNTRY?

[COL SUAREZ] EXCUSE ME, I CAN HARDLY HEAR YOU.

[REPORTER] I ASKED: WHEN CAN THE HONDURAN PEOPLE HAVE EXACT INFORMATION ON THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN REPORTED MISSING IN THE COUNTRY?

[COL SUAREZ] LOOK, WE BELIEVE THAT WE WILL SHORTLY, AND I AM TALKING ABOUT A SHORT TIME, HAVE ENOUGH INFORMATION FOR THE HONDURAN PEOPLE ON THE PERSONS YOU HAVE MENTIONED BECAUSE THE INVESTIGATIONS CONTINUE. THE POLICE ARREST PEOPLE BASED ON THE SUSPICION OR HARD, RATIONAL EVIDENCE THAT THEY ARE INVOLVED IN CRIMINAL ACTIONS. I BELIEVE YOU WILL SOON HAVE ENOUGH INFORMATION ON THE PERSONS WHO HAVE BEEN ARRESTED BY THE POLICE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0330 (BBN)

TEGUCIGALPA, 7 AUG 89 (RADIO AMERICA) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [ORTEGA] I BELIEVE THAT PRESIDENT BUSH WILL HAVE TO ACCEPT REALITY, WHICH IS THAT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEOPLES ARE TIRED OF WAR; THEY WANT PEACE. WE CENTRAL AMERICANS ARE THE ONES WHO ARE BEING KILLED, NOT THE U.S. SOLDIERS. THE UNITED STATES HAS THE DUTY TO RESPECT DECISIONS MADE BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEOPLES AND GOVERNMENTS.

[REPORTER] WHAT ARE THE REAL BASES OF THE AGREEMENT REACHED WITH THE NICARAGUAN OPPOSITION?

[ORTEGA] IT IS A DOCUMENT THAT WAS SIGNED BY ALL POLITICAL PARTIES. OBVIOUSLY, I SIGNED IT MYSELF. THE MAIN POINT IN THE DOCUMENT IS THAT WE PROPOSE THE DISMANTLING OF THE CONTRAS. THAT WAS THE FIRST ISSUE WE DISCUSSED. THE DOCUMENT NOTES THAT ONCE THE CONTRAS ARE DISMANTLED, THERE WILL BE AN AMNESTY, AND PRISONERS REMAINING IN NICARAGUA WILL BE RELEASED. WE ALSO STRESSED THAT FOREIGN FORCES SHOULD NOT MEDDLE IN THE NICARAGUAN ELECTION PROCESS; THE CIA, FOR EXAMPLE, HAS BEEN AUTHORIZED TO MEDDLE IN THE NICARAGUAN ELECTION PROCESS; THIS WAS DISCUSSED AT THE U.S. CONGRESS. THEREFORE, WE ARE AGAINST THIS KIND OF ACTIVITY, WHICH SHOWS DISRESPECT FOR NICARAGUAN SOVEREIGNTY.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] CONCERNING [WORDS INDISTINCT]. HOWEVER, IS IT NOT ALSO NECESSARY TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE CONTRAS?

[ORTEGA] WHAT DID YOU SAY? THAT WE MUST TALK TO THE CONTRAS?

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] IT IS ALSO NECESSARY TO TALK TO THE CONTRAS?

[ORTEGA] WELL, WE WILL HAVE TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE CONTRAS TO FIND OUT HOW THEY CAN BE DISLODGED [FROM HONDURAS] AND RETURN TO NICARAGUA; OR WE MUST DISCUSS WHETHER THEY WANT TO STAY HERE IN HONDURAS -- BECAUSE SOME MAY WANT TO STAY IN HONDURAS AND OTHERS MAY WANT TO GO ELSEWHERE, SUCH AS TO THE UNITED STATES. I BELIEVE THAT THE UNITED STATES SHOULD TAKE CARE OF THOSE WHO DO NOT WANT TO STAY IN CENTRAL AMERICA, BECAUSE THE UNITED STATES PROMOTED THE CONTRAS. THE UNITED STATES SHOULD NOT PLACE THIS BURDEN ON HONDURAS OR ON THE OTHER CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES. THEREFORE, WE WILL HAVE TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE CONTRAS TO GET THEM OUT OF HERE, TO GET THEM OUT OF HERE IN AN ORDERLY MANNER AND NOT BY SHOOTING AT THEM.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, THE CONTRAS ARE DEMANDING GUARANTEES.

[ORTEGA] GUARANTEES ALREADY EXIST IN NICARAGUA.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER ORTEGA, DO YOU HELP THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]?

[ORTEGA] WHAT?

[REPORTER] DO YOU PROVIDE ASSISTANCE TO THE FMLN?

[ORTEGA] WE ARE IN FAVOR OF A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] SAID IT HAS EVIDENCE THAT NICARAGUA PROVIDES ASSISTANCE TO THE FMLN. THIS WAS SAID YESTERDAY BY NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER MIGUEL D'ESCOTO.

[ANNOUNCER] THE STATEMENTS BY COMMANDER DANIEL ORTEGA HAVE BEEN INTERRUPTED BECAUSE THE PLANE THAT BROUGHT HIM TO THE AIRPORT IS ABOUT TO TAKE OFF FROM THE TELA AIRPORT. AT THIS TIME, THE HONDURAN FOREIGN MINISTER IS ASKING MR ORTEGA TO GO TO [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE FOREIGN MINISTER IS TRYING TO CONVINCE ORTEGA TO STOP MAKING STATEMENTS, BUT MR ORTEGA SEEMS VERY WILLING TO CONTINUE TO MAKE STATEMENTS TO THE PRESS. AT THIS MOMENT, PRESIDENT ORTEGA CANNOT ANSWER THE QUESTIONS BEING POSED BY LOCAL AND FOREIGN NEWSMEN BECAUSE THE PLANE IS TAKING OFF.

[REPORTER] MR ORTEGA...

[ORTEGA] INTERRUPTING CONCERNING YOUR QUESTION A FEW MINUTES AGO REGARDING THE FMLN. I JUST HELD A MEETING; I JUST HELD A MEETING WITH THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND. THEY ARE TOURING THE AREA, AND I HAVE MET THEM. THEY GAVE ME A LETTER ADDRESSED TO THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS EXPRESSING THEIR WILLINGNESS TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE WITH THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT, USING AS A BASIS THE DIALOGUE THAT THE FMLN HAS HELD WITH THE POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES IN EL SALVADOR. THE FLMN RECENTLY MET WITH THE LEGALLY REGISTERED POLITICAL PARTIES IN EL SALVADOR. THE FMLN HAS MET WITH SOCIAL GROUPS, AND, AFTER THESE TALKS, THEY MADE A SPECIFIC PROPOSAL: TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE TO REACH A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE ENDURING. OUR DESIRE IS TO SUPPORT A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION -- AS ESTABLISHED IN THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENTS - - TO FIND A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THIS KIND OF CENTRAL AMERICAN CONFLICT. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0333 (BBN)

TEGUCIGALPA, 7 AUG 89 (RADIO AMERICA) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [REPORTER] WHAT IS THE PREVAILING ATMOSPHERE NOW?

[ORTEGA] I THINK THAT ALL OF THE PRESIDENTS ARE HOPING THAT AN AGREEMENT WILL BE REACHED. WE HAVE BEEN SERIOUSLY WORKING ON THAT AGREEMENT SO THAT A FINAL AGREEMENT CAN BE ISSUED. WE HAVE PREPARED DOCUMENTS ON WHICH, I WOULD SAY, THERE IS A CERTAIN CONSENSUS--SUCH AS ON THE DOCUMENT ON THE [WORD INDISTINCT] OF THE CONTRAS, THE DOCUMENT ON THE HONDURAN-NICARAGUAN AGREEMENT CONCERNING THE SUIT NICARAGUA HAS FILED BEFORE THE INTERNATIONAL COURT OF JUSTICE, THE SALVADORAN ISSUE, AND OTHER POINTS.

I THINK THERE IS A POLITICAL RESOLVE ON THE PART OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS TO MAKE SURE THAT SOMETHING POSITIVE EMERGES FROM THIS SUMMIT. I AM SURE THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT IS HOPING THAT NOTHING WILL RESULT FROM THIS SUMMIT. I WOULD NOT BE SURPRISED IF THE U.S. GOVERNMENT IS CURRENTLY EXERTING STRONG PRESSURES SO THAT NOTHING WILL COME FROM THIS SUMMIT.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT: WHAT ARE THE PROCEDURES FOR NICARAGUA'S WITHDRAWAL OF ITS SUIT AGAINST HONDURAS?

[ORTEGA] THIS HAS TO BE LINKED TO COMPLETE COMPLIANCE WITH THE PLAN FOR THE CONTRA WITHDRAWAL.

[REPORTER] IN OTHER WORDS, THE CONTRAS MUST FIRST LEAVE?

[ORTEGA] OF COURSE. THAT IS OUR INSURANCE.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, HAS HONDURAS AGREED TO THIS?

[ORTEGA] WE ARE EXCHANGING VIEWPOINTS ON THIS.

[REPORTER] THE SUIT REPRESENTS AN INSURANCE FOR YOU, COMMANDER? WHICH GROUPS HAS THE UNITED STATES BEEN PRESSURING?

[ORTEGA] THE CENTRAL AMERICAN GROUPS. THERE HAVE BEEN DIRECT AND INDIRECT CONTACTS. THE UNITED STATES HAS CONTACTED THE CENTRAL AMERICAN DELEGATIONS IN HOPES THAT NO AGREEMENT WILL BE REACHED. THE AMERICANS CONTINUE TO FAVOR THE PRESENCE OF THE CONTRAS. THE FACT THAT PRESIDENT BUSH MET WITH CONTRA LEADERS ON THE EVE OF THIS CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SUMMIT IS A SLAP IN THE FACE TO THIS MEETING.

[REPORTER] WHEN YOU MENTION THESE PRESSURES, MR PRESIDENT, TO WHICH COUNTRIES ARE YOU REFERRING?

[ORTEGA] ALL OF THEM, WITH THE EXCEPTION OF NICARAGUA. I HAVE NO DOUBTS THAT RIGHT NOW THE UNITED STATES IS EXERTING PRESSURE, BECAUSE IT WANTS TO KILL THIS SUMMIT JUST WHEN WE ARE ABOUT TO REACH AN AGREEMENT. IF NO AGREEMENT IS REACHED AT THIS SUMMIT, THE UNITED STATES WILL BE RESPONSIBLE FOR THAT. [WORDS INDISTINCT] BECAUSE WE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES HAVE SUFFICIENT AUTHORITY AND SUFFICIENT SELF-DETERMINATION AND INDEPENDENCE TO DECIDE OUR OWN ACTIONS.

[REPORTER] AT THIS STAGE, HOW WOULD YOU DESCRIBE THE PRESIDENTS SUMMIT? IS THIS SUMMIT A FAILURE OR A SUCCESS?

[ORTEGA] I THINK IT HAS TO BE A SUCCESS, EVEN IF THE UNITED STATES HAS NOT GIVEN UP TRYING TO MAKE IT FAIL. THIS IS THE TIME, AND I AM SURE THAT IT IS TRYING [WORDS INDISTINCT].

DEV-MUC3-0335 (BBN)

LIMA, 7 AUG 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] INTERIOR MINISTRY SOURCES TODAY REPORTED IN LIMA THAT THREE ALLEGED MEMBERS OF THE TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA) HAVE DIED IN A CLASH WITH THE NATIONAL POLICE (PN). THE GUERRILLAS WERE TRAVELING IN A STOLEN VEHICLE ON 6 AUGUST, WHEN THEY WERE DETECTED BY A PN PATROL IN CHICLAYO PROVINCE. THE PATROL ORDERED THEM TO STOP, BUT THE GUERRILLAS FLED. THE POLICE PATROL GAVE CHASE AND CAUGHT THE GUERRILLAS 15 KM FROM CHICLAYO, ON THE ROAD TO CHONGOYAPE.

A CLASH ENSUED, AND JUAN ZURITA, CESAR ORBEGOZO, AND ERNESTO BENAVIDES WERE KILLED. THE INTERIOR MINISTRY BULLETIN REPORTS THAT THE POLICEMEN SEIZED TWO SUB-MACHINE GUNS, A REVOLVER, AND AN MRTA FLAG FROM THE GUERRILLAS.

THE PRO-GUEVARA MRTA STARTED ITS ARMED FIGHT IN 1984, WHEN IT RIDDLED THE U.S. EMBASSY WITH BULLETS.

THE MRTA HAS ALSO ATTACKED THE CHINESE, SOVIET, SPANISH, AND ARGENTINE EMBASSIES.

IN JANUARY, THE POLICE ARRESTED MRTA'S MAIN LEADER, VICTOR POLAY CAMPOS. AT LEAST 100 MRTA MEMBERS HAVE BEEN KILLED BY THE POLICE THIS YEAR.

POLITICAL VIOLENCE IN PERU, WHICH WAS UNLEASHED BY THE MAOIST SHINING PATH IN 1980, HAS KILLED MORE THAN 15,000 PEOPLE AND CAUSED LOSSES TOTALLING SOME $12 BILLION -- SOME 60 PERCENT OF THE TOTAL PERUVIAN FOREIGN DEBT.

DEV-MUC3-0336 (BBN)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 AUG 89 -- [SPEECH] [CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] I DO NOT SEEK, NOR WILL I SEEK, THE LAURELS OF VICTORY. I DO NOT SEEK HUMILIATING DEFEATS FOR ANYONE. WHAT I SEEK IS PEACE. I SEEK REPRESENTATIVE DEMOCRACY IN OUR HOMELAND. I SEEK TO SOLVE THE SOCIAL PROBLEMS OF OUR PEOPLE BY DEVELOPING AN ECONOMY THAT WILL BENEFIT ALL SALVADORANS.

TO THE LEADERS OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES, A VITAL COMPONENT OF REPRESENTATIVE DEMOCRACY AND OUR NATION'S IDEOLOGICAL PLURALISM, WE WISH TO INVITE YOU TO JOIN US SO THAT TOGETHER WE CAN WORK FOR PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. LET US SET THE PARTY BANNERS ASIDE AND PICK UP OUR NATIONAL FLAG.

TO THE FMLN LEADERS, I REITERATE MY DETERMINATION AND POLITICAL RESOLVE TO WORK FOR PEACE. I AM TRULY INTERESTED IN PUTTING AN END TO THE BLOODY FRATRICIDAL STRUGGLE. I HOPE THE FMLN WILL HEAR THE CALL MADE BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS AND CONTRIBUTE TO STRENGTHEN THE NATIONAL RECONCILIATION AND DEMOCRATIZATION PROCESSES AS ESTABLISHED IN THE ESQUIPULAS II AGREEMENTS. I ALSO HOPE THAT THE FMLN WILL SET ASIDE ITS INTRANSIGENT ATTITUDE AND VOLUNTARILY AGREE TO CEASE ALL HOSTILITIES AND THAT IT WILL DEMONSTRATE ITS PEACEFUL INTENTIONS BY STOPPING ALL TERRORIST ACTIONS AGAINST THE PEOPLE. I HOPE THE FMLN WILL MEET WITH US TO BEGIN THIS PROCESS OF PERMANENT AND FIRM DIALOGUE, WHICH WE ARE WILLING TO BEGIN IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE AGREEMENTS ADOPTED WITHIN THE CONTEXT OF ESQUIPULAS II AT THE RECENT PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT. THIS DIALOGUE SHOULD BE HELD WITHOUT CONDITIONS AND WITHOUT ANY PROPAGANDA.

TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO FOR YEARS HAVE BEEN SUFFERING THE HARD AND SAD CONSEQUENCES OF A WAR AND WHO ARE ANXIOUSLY AWAITING THE ACHIEVEMENT OF PEACE, I ASSURE YOU THAT MY GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO WORK FOR PEACE BY SETTING ASIDE ALL POLITICAL, PERSONAL, OR PARTISAN INTERESTS. I WANT ALL SALVADORANS TO CONTRIBUTE TO ACHIEVING A CIVILIZED END TO THE CONFLICT, AND I WOULD LIKE TO SEE ALL ATTITUDES THAT HINDER THE ACHIEVEMENT OF PEACE SET ASIDE. PEACE MUST NOT BE AN INSTRUMENT FOR AN IDEOLOGICAL OR PARTISAN STRUGGLE. LET US SWITCH THE ROLES. LET US BE THE INSTRUMENTS FOR ACHIEVING PEACE. THE SELFISH ATTITUDE THAT HAS HURT THE HOMELAND DEEPLY MUST BE SET ASIDE, AND WE MUST PLACE THE SACRED INTERESTS OF OUR BELOVED EL SALVADOR ABOVE ALL ELSE.

PEACE CAN ONLY BE ACHIEVED WITH THE HELP OF EVERYONE. WE MUST UNDERSTAND THAT ACHIEVING PEACE WILL BE THE BIGGEST VICTORY OF THE PEOPLE, AND THIS DOES NOT MEAN IDEOLOGICAL SURRENDER. WE ALL HAVE OPPORTUNITIES WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF OUR CONSTITUTION. THE CONSTITUTION GUARANTEES US IDEOLOGICAL PLURALISM AND REPRESENTATIVE DEMOCRACY.

SALVADORAN BROTHERS, LET US PRAY THAT GOD WILL OVERSEE THIS EFFORT FOR PEACE. MAY THE SAVIOR OF THE WORLD GUIDE AND ENLIGHTEN US. THANK YOU AND MAY GOD BLESS YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0338 (BBN)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 AUG 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [ROSSIE CASTILLO] [TEXT] NATIONAL ASSEMBLY DEPUTY MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON SAID TODAY THAT THE POSITION ADOPTED BY EL SALVADOR THROUGH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AT THE SUMMIT IN TELA, HONDURAS, IS POSITIVE BECAUSE EFFORTS ARE BEING MADE TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA. HOWEVER, HE SAID THAT THE POSITION OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WILL ACTUALLY BE VERY CRITICAL NOW. THE FMLN WILL NOT LOOK GOOD INTERNATIONALLY IF IT REJECTS THE DIALOGUE.

HERE IS AN EXCERPT OF D'AUBUISSON'S STATEMENTS, IN WHICH HE ALSO REVEALED THAT COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS HAS OFFERED TO MEDIATE THE DIALOGUE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [D'AUBUISSON, IN PROGRESS] ... FALLACIES. THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME THEY HAVE CLAIMED TO WANT SOMETHING AND ENDED UP DOING SOMETHING DIFFERENT. THEY ARE GOING TO TRY TO IMPROVE THEIR INTERNATIONAL IMAGE AND DO NOT WANT TO LOOK LIKE [WORD INDISTINCT] BEFORE THE LITTLE MANGY-DOGS WHO GO ABOUT PLANTING BOMBS HERE. THEY WANT TO DEMONSTRATE PERHAPS THAT THEY ALWAYS HOLD A HEGEMONIC POSITION HERE AND WILL TRY TO OBTAIN A BETTER NEGOTIATING POSITION FOR THEIR ILLEGAL FORCES, WHICH ARE STILL GOING AROUND [WORD INDISTINCT] AND KILLING PEOPLE [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[CASTILLO] NEVERTHELESS, MAJOR, DO YOU VIEW THIS MEETING AS POSITIVE [WORD INDISTINCT] WITH THE FMLN -- THAT IS, THE DIALOGUE -- NOW THAT SOMETHING TANGIBLE HAS COME OUT OF THE SUMMIT? DO YOU THINK PEACE CAN BE ACHIEVED?

[D'AUBUISSON] THE OBJECTIVE OF ALL SALVADORANS -- AND IN THIS REGARD WE SPEAK FROM THE HEART -- IS TO ACHIEVE PEACE. IF THE FMLN COOPERATES, WE WELCOME ITS COOPERATION. HOWEVER, IF IT DOES NOT COOPERATE, THERE WILL BE FMLN MEMBERS WHO WILL DEMOBILIZE, THE SAME WAY SO MANY PEOPLE FROM THE [WORD INDISTINCT] ARE DESERTING. THESE PEOPLE HAD TO BE GIVEN GUARANTEES. WE WILL SEE LATER IF, AS THEY SAY, THEY ARE TRULY WORKING, OR STRUGGLING, FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE [WORDS INDISTINCT] MORE POSITIVE ACTIONS.

HOWEVER, WE SEE EVERYTHING AS BEING WELL ON THE WAY TO ACHIEVING PEACE IN A SHORT TIME. [END RECORDING]

D'AUBUISSON SAID THAT IF THE FMLN DOES NOT AGREE TO THE DEMOBILIZATION, THE FMLN MEMBERS WILL BE SOLELY RESPONSIBLE IF PEACE IS NOT ACHIEVED. REGARDING THE COMMISSION, HE SAID IT IS ALREADY BEING ORGANIZED AND WILL BEGIN A DIALOGUE SOON.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [D'AUBUISSON, IN PROGRESS] ...A CONTINUOUS DIALOGUE TO FIND SOLUTIONS. THAT IS WHY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI HAS INSTRUCTED THAT IT HAVE NO PRIOR AGENDA BUT THAT IT JUST BEGIN. THEIR FIRST STEP SHOULD BE TO SIT DOWN AT A TABLE TO TALK, TO NEGOTIATE, TO ENGAGE IN DIALOGUE. AND THIS IS TO GO ON CONTINUOUSLY UNTIL SOLUTIONS ARE FOUND AND THEY ACHIEVE SOMETHING TANGIBLE, WHICH IS THE FINAL SOLUTION.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[D'AUBUISSON] WELL, FOR EXAMPLE, COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT ARIAS HAS OFFERED TO ACT AS MEDIATOR OR INTERMEDIARY. HE SAID THAT IF THE COMMISSION GOES TO SAN JOSE, HE WILL TAKE IT UPON HIMSELF TO INVITE THESE GENTLEMEN TOO AND TO GIVE THEM WHATEVER THEY NEED FOR THIS MEETING TO BEGIN. AFTER THAT, THEY THEMSELVES WILL DEVELOP THE MECHANISMS. [END RECORDING]

MAJ D'AUBUISSON SAID THE COMMISSION WILL BE SWORN IN AND WILL MAINTAIN AN ONGOING DIALOGUE WITH THE FMLN REPRESENTATIVES.

COMMENTING ON LEGISLATIVE WORK, HE SAID THAT TODAY THE POLITICAL COMMITTEE WILL MEET TO ELECT THE PRESIDENT OF THE COMMISSION ON CORRUPTION, WHICH HAD BEEN SUBSTANTIALLY NEGLECTED BY DR JAIME VENTURA. THE ONLY CANDIDATE FOR THE PRESIDENCY OF THE COMMISSION ON CORRUPTION IS DEPUTY ROBERTO ANGULO, VICE PRESIDENT AND ACTING PRESIDENT OF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY.

DEV-MUC3-0339 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 7 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [EXCERPTS] [PASSAGE OMITTED] SIMON BOLIVAR AND FRANCISCO DE PAULA SANTANDER GAVE OUR ARMED FORCES THE MISSION OF DEFENDING FREEDOM, INDEPENDENCE, AND DEMOCRACY. THROUGHOUT HISTORY, THE NATIONAL ARMY HAS COMPLIED WITH THAT MANDATE. IT HAS NOT BEEN AN EASY TASK, EVEN LESS SO DURING THE TIMES WE ARE LIVING. VERY FEW NATIONS HAVE HAD TO CONFRONT SIMULTANEOUSLY SO MANY DIFFICULT CHALLENGES. CONFRONTED BY A COMBINATION OF SOURCES OF DISRUPTION, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE NOT LOST THEIR DETERMIANTION AND OPTIMISM, NOR HAVE THEY STOPPED FOR 1 MINUTE TO STRUGGLE FOR THE REESTABLISHMENT OF TRANQUILLITY FOR THE CITIZENS, AND FOR THE PROTECTION OF LIFE, HONOR, AND PROPERTY OF COLOMBIANS.

AS THE VIOLENCE INCREASES, OUR COMMITMENT TO DEMOCRACY AND COLOMBIA IS STRENGTHENED. THE PRICE OF COURAGE AND FIRMNESS HAS BEEN HIGH. MANY SOLDIERS, OFFICERS, AND NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICERS HAVE BEEN KILLED, BUT THEY ARE THE HEROES OF DEMOCRACY. ON THE OCCASION OF ARMY DAY, I SPEAK ON BEHALF OF THE VAST NATIONAL MAJORITY AND CONVEY TO THEIR FAMILIES, FRIENDS, AND FELLOW SOLDIERS OUR MESSAGE OF ENCOURAGEMENT, APPRECIATION, AND HOPE. THEIR EFFORTS HAVE NOT BEEN IN VAIN.

THE BATTLE TO PRESERVE DEMOCRACY AND DEFEAT VIOLENCE CONTINUES. THE DETERMINATION OF COLOMBIANS DOES NOT WEAKEN. OUR ENEMIES ARE ALONE, AS NEVER BEFORE, AND THIS WE OWE TO PERMANENT ACTIONS BY OUR ARMED FORCES.

IN THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN, I OFFERED THE COLOMBIANS A POLICY OF RECONCILIATION BASED ON DEFINED GUIDELINES AND CLEAR PRINCIPLES. THIS WAS THE DEMOCRATIC MANDATE THAT WE RECEIVED FROM THE PEOPLE. NOW, WHEN WE ARE HARVESTING THE RESULTS OF THAT STRATEGY, WE WILL NOT GIVE UP. THE PEACE INITIATIVE HAS SHOWED THAT IT CAN OPERATE AND IT WILL CONTINUE TO BE THE FRAMEWORK WITHIN WHICH WE WILL CONDUCT POLITICAL ACTION FOR NATIONAL RECONCILIATION.

SOME BELIEVE THAT TO PRESERVE DEMOCRACY, IT IS NECESSARY TO LEAVE IT IDLE, AT THE MERCY OF VIOLENCE. OTHERS ARGUE THAT PEACE CAN ONLY BE ACHIEVED IF WE DISMANTLE OUR CAPABILITY TO DEFEND DEMOCRACY. WE DO NOT AGREE. THE GOVERNMENT HAS CONFIRMED THAT STRENGTHENING DEMOCRACY AND THE QUEST FOR PEACE ARE NOT ONLY COMPATIBLE WITH IMPROVING AND STRENGTHENING THE ARMED FORCES, BUT THAT THIS IS INDISPENSABLE FOR ADVANCING THE POLITICAL HANDLING OF VIOLENCE.

EFFICIENT, PROFESSIONAL ARMED FORCES THAT SERVE THE COUNTRY ARE A DEFINITE GUARANTEE OF THE RIGHTS OF CITIZENS AND OF PEACEFUL COEXISTENCE. THAT IS WHY THIS GOVERNMENT HAS MADE A GREAT ADMINISTRATIVE AND FINANCIAL EFFORT TO RETURN TO THE MILITARY INSTITUTIONS COMPLETE FREEDOM OF ACTION.

THIS COMMEMORATION OF THE 170TH ANNIVERSARY OF OUR INDEPENDENCE IS A SUITABLE TIME TO PONDER OUR DUTY TO THE HOMELAND. I AM NOT REFERRING TO DAILY CIVIC DUTIES, WHICH ARE PROPER TO ALL OF US COLOMBIANS, BUT TO SOMETHING MUCH DEEPER -- LOYALTY TO DEMOCRACY AND OUR INSTITUTIONS. DEMOCRACY'S BOUNDARIES ARE BROAD, BUT PRECISE. WHEN VIOLENCE TO A CERTAIN EXTENT IS TOLERATED, MORE VIOLENCE IS CREATED, THERE IS A CONSPIRACY AGAINST PEACE, AND CONFLICTS ARE AGGRAVATED. THE ENTIRE SOCIETY HAS SUFFERED BECAUSE OF THE ACTIVITIES OF THE ENEMIES OF COLOMBIA. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

I CONGRATULATE THE OFFICERS, CIVILIAN PERSONALITIES, SERGEANT AMAYA ALVAREZ, AND PRIVATE MALAMBO TIQUE, WHOSE MERITS WERE ACKNOWLEDGED TODAY IN THE NAME OF THEIR FELLOW COUNTRYMEN AND THE GOVERNMENT. [APPLAUSE] THIS CEREMONY, IN WHICH WE HONOR THE HEROES OF INDEPENDENCE AND THE ARMY, IS A SUITABLE OCCASION TO MAKE KNOWN TO OFFICERS, NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICERS, AND SOLDIERS ALIKE THE NATION'S RECOGNITION OF THEIR COURAGEOUS AND PROFESSIONAL FULFILLMENT OF THEIR DUTIES. WHEN THE ARMED FORCES ACADEMIES PARADE BEFORE US, SO WILL THE YOUNG MEN AND WOMEN WHO HAVE DEVOTED THEIR LIVES TO SERVING THE HOMELAND AND THEIR FELLOW COUNTRYMEN. EVERY HONEST COLOMBIAN SUPPORTS THEM.

SOLDIERS: YOU, WHO WIELD THE NATION'S ARMS, REPRESENT THE BASIC GUARANTEE THAT PRESERVES SOVEREIGNTY, LIBERTY, AND OUR DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS. THANK YOU. [APPLAUSE]

DEV-MUC3-0340 (BBN)

GUATEMALA CITY, 10 AUG 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THREE EXPLOSIONS ROCKED GUATEMALA CITY TODAY, LEAVING AT LEAST ONE DEAD, FIVE WOUNDED, AND VEHICLES AND STORES DAMAGED.

THE MOST SERIOUS INCIDENT WAS CAUSED BY UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS WHO THREW A GRENADE AT A PRIVATELY OWNED PASSENGER BUS ON KILOMETER 6 OF THE ROAD LINKING GUATEMALA CITY WITH PUERTO BARRIOS, ON THE ATLANTIC COAST. ONE PERSON WAS KILLED AND AT LEAST FIVE WERE WOUNDED IN THE ATTACK. THE FATALITY WAS AN UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN.

ANOTHER EXPLOSION TOOK PLACE SIMULTANEOUSLY IN ZONE 5 OF GUATEMALA CITY, IN FRONT OF THE CHURCH OF THE HOLY PRIEST OF ARS, WHOSE PARISH PRIEST, JOSE MARIA RUIZ (FATHER CHEMITA), WAS PREPARING TO SAY MASS.

THREE VEHICLES WERE DAMAGED BY THIS EXPLOSION. THIS WEEK FATHER CHEMITA, FORMER CANDIDATE FOR MAYOR OF GUATEMALA CITY, ACCUSED ALFONSO CABRERA, FORMER FOREIGN MINISTER AND CURRENT SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE RULING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC], OF "HAVING ORDERED" THE KILLING OF PDC LEADER DANILO BARILLAS.

A THIRD EXPLOSION OCCURRED ON THE FIRST FLOOR OF A BUILDING IN GUATEMALA CITY'S ZONE 9. SEVERAL STORES WERE DAMAGED BY THE BLAST.

DEV-MUC3-0341 (BBN)

SANTIAGO, 11 AUG 89 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [REPORT] [ELIANA HENRIQUEZ] [EXCERPTS] PRESIDENT AUGUSTO PINOCHET HAS REQUESTED ALL HIS MINISTERS OF STATE TO RESIGN. THESE RESIGNATIONS WERE TENDERED IN A DOCUMENT SIGNED BY EACH MINISTER AND DELIVERED TO CABINET CHIEF CARLOS CACERES.

THIS INFORMATION WAS DISCLOSED BY MINISTER SECRETARY GENERAL OF GOVERNMENT OSCAR VARGAS, WHO HAS ALSO RESIGNED, AT THE END OF A COUNCIL OF MINISTERS.

VARGAS NOTED THAT THE NEW CABINET WILL BE SWORN IN ON WEDNESDAY, 16 AUGUST, AT 1800.

THE FOLLOWING MINISTERS HAVE RESIGNED IN ORDER TO RUN AS SENATORIAL CANDIDATES DURING THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS: LABOR MINISTER GUILLERMO ARTHUR, WHO PLANS TO REPRESENT THE EIGHTH REGION, AND PUBLIC WORKS MINISTER BRUNO SIEBERT, WHO INTENDS TO REPRESENT THE TENCH REGION.

ECONOMY MINISTER PABLO BARAONA WILL PROBABLY ALSO RUN FOR A CONGRESSIONAL SEAT.

MINISTER VARGAS ALSO SAID THAT DURING THE MEETING THEY HAD DISCUSSED THE PUBLIC ORDER. HE ASSERTED THAT THE COUNTRY IS CALM, WITH THE EXCEPTION OF TERRORIST ACTIONS BY THE LAUTARO MOVEMENT.

DEV-MUC3-0342 (BBN)

LIMA, 13 AUG 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] A SPOKESMAN FOR THE MINERS TODAY REPORTED IN LIMA THAT PERUVIAN SOLDIERS HAVE ARRESTED AT LEAST 22 MINERS, INCLUDING 4 REGIONAL LEADERS, ON THE EVE OF THE MINERS NATIONAL STRIKE, WHICH IS SCHEDULED TO BEGIN ON 14 AUGUST. THERE ARE APPROXIMATELY 100,000 MINERS IN PERU.

THE SPOKESMAN TOLD EFE THAT THE SOLDIERS ARRESTED MINERS AT THE LA OROYA, MOROCOCHA, CASA PALCA, AND AUSTRIA-DUVALZ MINING CAMPS IN THE CENTRAL PART OF THE MOUNTAIN RANGE. IN LIMA, THE POLICE ARE LOOKING FOR THE MAIN LEADERS OF THE MINERS.

THE FEDERATION OF MINERS AND METALWORKERS HAS CALLED A NATIONAL STRIKE FOR 14 AUGUST TO PRESSURE THE COURTS INTO RULING IN FAVOR OF A "SINGLE NATIONAL LIST OF DEMANDS," WHICH WILL ALLOW THE FEDERATION TO REPRESENT ALL PERUVIAN MINERS AT THE DISCUSSIONS OF LABOR AND SALARY ISSUES.

ON FRIDAY, 11 AUGUST, THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT ORDERED ARMY SOLDIERS AND NAVY MARINES TO GUARD MINING CAMPS IN ORDER TO PREVENT POSSIBLE ATTACKS AND SABOTAGE DURING THE STRIKE, THE FIRST THIS YEAR.

TERRORISTS HAVE ATTACKED SEVERAL MINES LATELY AND HAVE KILLED APPROXIMATELY 12 MINERS, INCLUDING SAUL CANTORAL, SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE FEDERATION.

THE MINERS WENT ON STRIKE FOR ALMOST 100 DAYS LAST YEAR. THAT STRIKE CAUSED LOSSES ESTIMATED AT $500 MILLION, ONE-THIRD OF PERU'S OVERALL MINING EXPORTS.

THE STRIKE WILL AFFECT CENTRAL PERUVIAN MINING ENTERPRISE, THE LARGEST STATE-OWNED CORPORATION; THE U.S. COMPANY SOUTHERN PERU COPPER CORPORATION, WHICH EXPLOITS 75 PERCENT OF THE PERUVIAN COPPER; AND THE ILO REFINERY, THE SECOND LARGEST IN PERU.

DEV-MUC3-0343 (BBN)

NO CITY (PERU), NO DATE -- [SPEECH] [GARCIA] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] ARTICLE 5 ADDS: ALL MEN FROM 18 TO 50 YEARS OF AGE AND WOMEN FROM 18 TO 45 YEARS OF AGE ARE OBLIGED TO COMPLY WITH THIS LAW, THUS THIS PERIOD OF LIFE IS CALLED MILITARY AGE. THIS MEANS THAT ALL 18- TO 50-YEAR-OLD PERUVIANS ARE OF MILITARY AGE, AND WE ARE OBLIGED TO COMPLY WITH THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE LAW, IN THE RESERVE.

THEREFORE, ONE NOT ONLY COMPLIES WITH THE MILITARY SERVICE LAW WHEN ONE IS ASSIGNED ON ACTIVE DUTY TO A MILITARY GARRISON FOR 1 OR 2 YEARS, BUT ONE CONTINUES COMPLYING WITH THIS LAW BY REMAINING IN THE RESERVE UNTIL 50 YEARS OF AGE.

ARTICLE 272 OF THE MILITARY SERVICE LAW STATES: MEN FROM 18 TO 50 YEARS OF AGE AND WOMEN BETWEEN 18 AND 45 YEARS OF AGE WHO ARE NOT ON ACTIVE MILITARY SERVICE ALL BELONG TO THE RESERVE, AND THEY MUST COMPLY WITH THE OBLIGATIONS ESTABLISHED BY CLAUSE 4 OF THIS LAW.

IF THE LAW STATES THIS, I THEN ASK ALL PERUVIANS: ARE NOT TERRORISTS -- WHO ARE PART OF THE ARMED FORCES RESERVES AND WHO TAKE ARMS TO ATTACK THE NATIONAL POLICE AND ARMED FORCES -- VIOLATING THE OBLIGATORY MILITARY SERVICE LAW? IS NOT HE, WHO BY VIOLENT MEANS TRIES TO DESTROY THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM OF WHICH THE ARMED FORCES ARE PART, VIOLATING THE MILITARY SERVICE LAW?

THEREFORE, SINCE ARTICLE 282 OF THE CONSTITUTION STATES THAT THOSE WHO VIOLATE THE COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE LAW CAN BE TRIED BY THE MILITARY CODE OF JUSTICE, THEN TERRORISTS CAN BE TRIED BY MILITARY COURTS.

THUS THE IDEA IS THAT ONE LAW, ONE ARTICLE, SHOULD ESTABLISH THAT THE CRIME OF TERRORISM VIOLATES THE MILITARY SERVICE LAW, THEREFORE ENABLING A QUICK AND DRASTIC PUNISHMENT FOR TERRORISTS.

IT WILL THEREFORE NOT BE NECESSARY TO AMMEND THE CONSTITUTION. A CORRECT INTERPRETATION OF THE CONSTITUTION IS ALL THAT WILL BE NEEDED. WE MUST ALSO REMEMBER THAT WHEN THE CURRENT CONSTITUTION WAS APPROVED THERE WAS NO SERIOUS TERRORIST PROBLEM. BESIDES, YOU MUST KNOW THAT TO AMMEND THE CONSTITUTION WE MUST WAIT NEARLY 2 YEARS, AND WE HAVE NO TIME TO WASTE.

MANY PERUVIANS THINK THAT IF MILITARY COURTS TRY TERRORISTS THEY WILL BE SENTENCED TO DEATH. THIS IS FALSE, IT IS NOT CORRECT. THE MILITARY COURTS WILL ONLY RULE SENTENCES IN KEEPING WITH THE LAW, BUT THESE SENTENCES WILL BE APPLIED FIRMLY. THIS MEANS THAT CRIMINALS WILL NOT GO UNPUNISHED.

I ASK ALL PERUVIANS AND ALL INSTITUTIONS TO SUPPORT THIS PROPOSAL. TERRORISTS MUST NOT REMAIN UNPUNISHED. THIS DOES NOT MEAN THAT WE DO NOT TRUST THE CIVILIAN COURTS. THIS MEANS THAT WE MUST SIMPLY INTERPRET THE CONSTITUTION APPROPRIATELY. TERRORISTS REALLY DO VIOLATE THEIR CONDITION AS ARMED FORCES RESERVES WHEN THEY TAKE UP ARMS AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES.

IT IS THEREFORE OUR PURPOSE TO DO THINGS CORRECTLY. THE CONSTITUTION MUST BE INTERPRETED IN FAVOR OF PERU, SINCE IT CANNOT BE INTERPRETED IN FAVOR OF THE TERRORISTS.

I AM SURPRISED THAT ON THE ONE SIDE PEOPLE CRITICIZE THE LITTLE ACTION TAKEN AGAINST TERRORISTS, WHILE ON THE OTHER THEY DO NOT ACCEPT A CONCRETE INITIATIVE LIKE THIS ONE TO PUNISH THEM.

THIS IS THE MOMENT TO RESUME THE DISCUSSION ON THIS SUBJECT BEFORE THE ELECTION CAMPAIGNS MAKE US FORGET THAT WE ARE AT WAR AGAINST TERRORISM. ON THE CONTRARY, IN ORDER TO SAFEGUARD THE ELECTIONS WE MUST QUICKLY MAKE ALL THE IMPORTANT DECISIONS AND APPROVE STRICT PUNISHMENTS THAT WILL ALLOW US TO LIVE IN DEMOCRACY, FREEDOM, PEACE, AND SAFETY. THANK YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0344 (BBN)

LA PAZ, 12 AUG 89 (PRESENCIA) -- [EXCERPT] DEFENSE MINISTER HECTOR HORMACHEA HAS REVEALED THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ASKED TO BE WITHDRAWN FROM THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING BECAUSE THAT MISSION HAS THE DIRECT PARTICIPATION OF THE POLICE.

ORMACHEA EXPLAINED THAT THE ARMED FORCES' ROLE IN DRUG CONTROL WILL BE EVALUATED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND MILITARY CHIEFS BEFORE A FINAL DECISION IS MADE.

ORMACHEA MADE THESE COMMENTS DURING HIS FIRST NEWS CONFERENCE TO TALK ABOUT THE VARIOUS ISSUES RELATED TO HIS MINISTRY.

HE ADDED THAT THE NAVY AND THE AIR FORCE CURRENTLY CARRY OUT A SUPPORT MISSION IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, AS THE ENTIRE TASK IS CARRIED OUT BY THE MOBIL UNITS FOR RURAL AREAS (UMOPAR), WHICH ARE UNDER THE POLICE.

IN HIS FIRST WEEK AS THE NEW MINISTER, ORMACHEA HELD PRELIMINARY TALKS WITH SEVERAL MILITARY CHIEFS TO GET FAMILIAR WITH THE ARMED FORCES' ROLE IN CONTROLLING DRUG TRAFFICKING.

HE SAID: "WE MUST CAREFULLY STUDY AND EVALUATE THE SITUATION TO DETERMINE THE ARMED FORCES' DEGREE OF PARTICIPATION IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING."

HE SAID THAT THE ARMED FORCES WANTED TO WITHDRAW FROM THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING WHEN IT INITIALLY BEGAN, BUT THEY THEN DECIDED TO CARRY OUT A SUPPORT MISSION. HE ADDED: WE ARE GOING TO STUDY THIS AT THE GOVERNMENT LEVEL, WITH THE PRESIDENT MAKING THE FINAL DECISION ON THE ROLE OF THE ARMED FORCES.

ORMACHEA ALSO SAID THAT INTERNAL SECURITY IS CLOSELY LINKED TO HOW THE ARMED FORCES ARE EQUIPPED, BUT ALSO TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE COUNTRY, ESPECIALLY IN THE POOREST ZONES AND BORDER AREAS.

HE SAID THAT THERE HAS BEEN TALK LATELY ABOUT TERRORIST ACTIVITIES, ALTHOUGH THE REPORTS HAVE NOT BEEN VERY CLEAR. THERE WERE APPARENTLY INCURSIONS BY UNIDENTIFIED ARMED GROUPS, MURDER, AND OTHER ACTIVITIES THAT MAY JEOPARDIZE THE COUNTRY'S INTERNAL SECURITY.

ORMACHEA SAID THAT INTERNAL SECURITY AND NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY WILL CONTINUE TO BE THE ARMED FORCES' MAIN CONCERN.

REGARDING THE PRESENCE OF FOREIGN MILITARY ADVISORS INVOLVED IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, ORMAECHEA NOTED THAT "THAT WORK WILL BE USEFUL AS LONG AS IT DOES NOT INTERFERE WITH THE WORK OF BOLIVIAN ORGANIZATIONS."

HE CONCLUDED BY SAYING THAT CHANGING THE PREVIOUS DEFENSE MINISTRY'S POLICY OF ADMINISTRATIVE CENTRALIZATION OF ECONOMIC RESOURCES IS A POSITIVE STEP. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0347 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 17 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIA IS IN UTTER CHAOS TODAY. THE COUNTRY'S MAGISTRATES RESIGNED TODAY TO PROTEST THE MURDER OF COLOMBIAN JUSTICE CARLOS VALENCIA, AND A FEW MINUTES AGO THE ASONAL [NATIONAL ASSOCIATION FOR THE JUDICIAL BRANCH] JUDGES ALSO TENDERED THEIR RESIGNATIONS. MEANWHILE, THE GOVERNMENT IS DESPERATELY ATTEMPTING TO CONVINCE THEM TO GO BACK TO THEIR JOBS.

TODAY, THE 54 MAGISTRATES WHO COMPOSE THE CIVIL, LABOR, AND PENAL COURTS OF THE BOGOTA SUPERIOR TRIBUNAL TENDERED THEIR RESIGNATIONS UNTIL THE GOVERNMENT GUARANTEES THEM SAFETY AND PROTECTION FOR THEIR LIVES SO THAT THEY CAN DISPENSE JUSTICE IN COLOMBIA.

THE MURDER OF JUSTICE CARLOS VALENCIA GARCIA LED THE COLOMBIAN MAGISTRATES TO SUSPEND ALL LEGAL PROCEEDINGS. THE MAGISTRATES OF THE BOGOTA SUPERIOR TRIBUNAL SAID THEY DO NOT WANT TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY BUT ADDED THAT THEY DO NOT WANT TO BE THE NEXT VICTIMS EITHER.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED JUDGE] WE FEEL WE ARE WAGING A USELESS STRUGGLE. WE ARE FIGHTING FOR IDEALS THAT NOBODY SHARES. WHAT WE WANT IS FOR THE COUNTRY TO BEGIN TO SHARE THOSE IDEALS. WHEN THAT HAPPENS, WE, THE COLOMBIAN JUDGES, WILL BE WILLING TO GIVE UP OUR LIVES FOR THOSE IDEALS AS CARLOS VALENCIA GARCIA DID. [END RECORDING]

THE 22,000 JUDICIAL BRANCH EMPLOYEES JOINED THE MAGISTRATES' PROTEST. THE JUDICIAL BRANCH PUBLIC EMPLOYEES ASSOCIATION CALLED FOR AN INDEFINITE STRIKE, BEGINNING TODAY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] THE GOVERNMENT'S PROMISES HAVE BEEN ONLY THAT, PROMISES. THE TRUTH IS THAT THE PLAN TO PROVIDE PROTECTION, ESCORTS, AND ARMORED VEHICLES HAS NOT BEEN IMPLEMENTED.

IN ADDITION, WE BELIEVE THAT TO END THIS WAVE OF MURDERS THE GOVERNMENT MUST SHOW THE POLITICAL RESOLVE TO ERADICATE IT. THE GOVERNMENT MUST CONFRONT THIS PROBLEM BY USING OUR ARMED FORCES WITH DUE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS. AS LONG AS THAT IS NOT DONE, NOT ONLY JUDGES, BUT THE BEST CHILDREN OF COLOMBIA, WILL CONTINUE TO DIE. [END RECORDING]

THE WIFE OF THE MURDERED MAGISTRATE ARRIVED FROM GUATEMALA TODAY FOR THE FUNERAL.

DEV-MUC3-0348 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 18 AUG 89 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] MEDELLIN -- ANTIOQUIA POLICE DEPARTMENT CHIEF WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO WAS MURDERED THIS MORNING ON THIS CITY'S WEST SIDE.

THE GUNMEN FIRED ON THE POLICE COMMANDER WHEN HIS VEHICLE STOPPED FOR A RED LIGHT AT ROAD 80 AND 48TH STREET, NEAR MARTIN RODRIGUEZ VELODROME, A FEW BLOCKS AWAY FROM WHERE THE GOVERNOR OF ANTIOQUIA WAS MURDERED ON 4 JULY.

THE AUTOMATIC WEAPONS FIRE, WHICH LASTED OVER 3 MINUTES, ALSO SERIOUSLY WOUNDED ONE OF THE AGENTS ACCOMPANYING COL QUINTERO.

ACCORDING TO POLICE SOURCES, THE POLICE CHIEF'S WHITE NISSAN PICKUP, WITH LICENSE PLATES ME-7847, WAS INTERCEPTED BY ASSASSINS' GRAY MAZDA, LICENSE PLATES MI-1630.

A CRIMINAL COURT JUSTICE IDENTIFIED THE BODY OF THE POLICE COMMANDER MURDERED THIS MORNING IN SALASAN, ON THIS CITY'S WEST SIDE. THE POLICE CHIEF WAS SHOT IN THE HEAD SEVERAL TIMES.

POLICE UNITS AND SECURITY CORPS AGENTS HAVE REINFORCED STRATEGIC POINTS IN MEDELLIN AND POLICE CHECKPOINTS HAVE BEEN ESTABLISHED IN THE SEARCH FOR THE CRIMINALS.

A METROPOLITAN POLICE OFFICER HAS REPORTED THAT FOR THE PAST WEEK, POLICE CHIEF QUINTERO HAD BEEN WITHOUT A PERSONAL ESCORT. THE POLICE CHIEF HAD EXPLAINED THAT HE DID NOT WANT TO RISK OTHER POLICEMEN'S LIVES. HE DISMISSED HIS PERSONAL ESCORTS, APPOINTING THEM TO OTHER DUTIES.

THE POLICE COMMANDER'S ASSASSINATION HAS CREATED A LOT OF COMMOTION IN COLOMBIAN SOCIETY. ANTIOQUIA GOVERNOR ELENA MONTOYA HAS STATED HER CONCERN OVER THIS NEW EPISODE OF SELECTIVE VIOLENCE AND POINTED OUT THE EFFORTS THAT THE POLICE COMMANDER HAD BEEN MAKING TO PROVIDE SECURITY TO THE CITIZENS OF THIS REGION.

METROPOLITAN POLICE CHIEF ANTONIO SANCHEZ HAS REJECTED THIS NEW ACT OF VIOLENCE AGAINST THE POLICE AS AN INSTITUTION. THE MEDELLIN SECURITY COUNCIL WILL INITIATE A SPECIAL MEETING IN THE NEXT FEW MINUTES TO ANALYZE THE SITUATION.

COMMANDER QUINTERO FOUGHT DRUG-TRAFFICKING AND SUBVERSION IN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT. FROM THE MOMENT HE BECAME ANTIOQUIA POLICE COMMANDER, QUINTERO BECAME KNOWN FOR HIS EXERCISE OF AUTHORITY AND FOR DESIGNING STRATEGIES DESIGNED TO PROVIDE PUBLIC ORDER.

ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS HE PARTICIPATED IN REGIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL MEETINGS WHERE WAYS TO FIGHT CRIME IN ANTIOQUIA WERE DISCUSSED.

LAST WEDNESDAY HE ACCOMPANIED GOVERNOR MONTOYA TO TOLIMA FOR A SECURITY MEETING TO DISCUSS THE SITUATION IN THE REGIONS. AT THAT MEETING, MEASURES WERE ESTABLISHED TO FIGHT SUBVERSION AND COMMON CRIMINALS.

DEV-MUC3-0349 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 18 AUG 89 (EFE) -- [EXCERPT] IT WAS OFFICIALLY REPORTED TODAY THAT 800 COLOMBIAN ARMY AND POLICE MEMBERS WERE TAKEN FROM BOGOTA ON BOARD FOUR PLANES TODAY AND DEPLOYED IN THE CITY OF MEDELLIN TO REINFORCE THE MEDELLIN AUTHORITIES.

A NATIONAL POLICE SOURCE TOLD EFE THAT THE 800 MEN "ARE PART OF A GROUP CHOSEN BY THE POLICE AND ARMY TO COUNTERATTACK CRIME IN MEDELLIN."

THE DEPLOYMENT WAS ORDERED BY THE POLICE AND ARMY HIGH COMMAND AS A RESULT OF THE MURDER OF ANTIOQUIA POLICE CHIEF COLONEL WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO TODAY IN MEDELLIN, COLOMBIA'S SECOND LARGEST CITY.

ACCORDING TO EYE WITNESSES, QUINTERO WAS FIRED AT "INCESSANTLY" IN A DOWNTOWN MEDELLIN STREET AT 0600 LOCAL TIME (1100 GMT) AFTER HIS CAR WAS INTERCEPTED BY ANOTHER VEHICLE FROM WHICH VARIOUS UNIDENTIFIED MEN GOT OUT TO COMMIT THE CRIME.

COL FRANKLIN QUINTERO, CONSIDERED BY HIS SUPERIORS AS AN IMPLACABLE ENEMY OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND ORGANIZED CRIME, WAS KILLED IN THE ACTION.

THE COLOMBIAN DEPUTY POLICE DIRECTOR, GENERAL CARLOS ARTURO CASADIEGO, SAID: "IT IS NO SECRET THAT THE MEDELLIN MAFIA IS RESPONSIBLE FOR ALL THE CRIMES" TAKING PLACE IN THE COUNTRY.

QUINTERO'S MURDER JOINS THAT OF MAGISTRATE CARLOS VALENCIA GARCIA. WHO WAS MURDERED IN BOGOTA ON 16 AUGUST. AT THE TIME OF HIS MURDER, VALENCIA WAS INVESTIGATING THE MEDELLIN CARTEL'S CHIEFS' LINKS.

DEV-MUC3-0350 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 18 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS] [TEXT] FELLOW COUNTRYMEN: I AM ADDRESSING YOU TO EXPLAIN THE MEASURES UNDER THE PROVISIONS OF THE STATE OF SIEGE [MEDIDAS DE ESTADO DE SITIO] WHICH HAVE BEEN ADOPTED AT A TIME WHEN THE NATION HAS JUSTIFIED REASONS TO FEEL ANGRY AND MOVED BY THE SERIOUS ACTIONS OF VIOLENCE THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN RECENT DAYS. UNFORTUNATELY, LUIS CARLOS GALAN, THE LIBERAL PARTY PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL, WAS THE VICTIM OF ANOTHER ATTACK TONIGHT. SENATOR GALAN HAS BEEN TAKEN TO A HOSPITAL. LET US PRAY TO GOD THAT HE WILL RECOVER FROM HIS WOUNDS.

THE CRIMINAL ORGANIZATIONS AND THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS HAVE UNLEASHED A WAVE OF ASSASSINATIONS AND DEATHS. THERE HAVE BEEN ATTACKS AGAINST REPRESENTATIVES AND LEADERS FROM ALL SECTORS OF THE COUNTRY AND FROM ALL INSTITUTIONS. HIGH-RANKING GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, SEVERAL JUDGES, POLITICAL LEADERS, SOLDIERS, CITIZENS, AND PUBLIC OFFICIALS HAVE BEEN THE VICTIMS OF THIS BARBARISM.

VIOLENCE AFFECTS ALL. IT IS NOT AN OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT OR AGAINST JUSTICE; IT IS A WAR AGAINST THE COUNTRY. THEREFORE, THE ENTIRE COUNTRY MUST RESPOND. I CAN UNDERSTAND HOW THE MURDER OF MAGISTRATE CARLOS VALENCIA LED THE JUDGES OF THE REPUBLIC TO PROTEST AND TO REQUEST MORE PROTECTION, BUT FOR THE MAGISTRATES AND JUDGES TO RESIGN ONLY CONTRIBUTES TO WORSENING THE SITUATION WHICH WE MUST ALL SOLVE BY WORKING TOGETHER. THIS IS ALSO EQUIVALENT TO YIELDING TO THE TERRORISTS WHO ARE TRYING TO PARALYZE THE ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE.

TRUE HEROES SUCH AS CARLOS VALENCIA, WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO, AND OTHER JUDGES, POLICEMEN, SOLDIERS, AND BODYGUARDS HAVE PREVENTED THIS BY FULFILLING THEIR DUTIES WITHOUT YIELDING TO INTIMIDATION OR BRIBERY. I INVITE ALL JUDGES OF THE REPUBLIC TO RESUME THEIR WORK. THE GOVERNMENT HAS ADOPTED MORE MEASURES TO PROTECT THEM, AND IT WILL CONTINUE TO RENDER ALL THE COOPERATION THEY REQUIRE AND WHICH IS AVAILABLE. ALL GOOD COLOMBIANS MUST JOIN THE EFFORTS. NO MORE LAMENTATIONS WITHOUT TRUE ACTION OF COOPERATION WITH THE AUTHORITIES.

IT IS NECESSARY THAT ALL FORCES OF THE STATE AND OF SOCIETY -- POLITICAL PARTIES, UNIONS, MEDIA, CIVIC ORGANIZATIONS -- ALL SERVE JUSTICE AND THE STRUGGLE AGAINST CRIME. WE MUST BE PREPARED TO ENDURE MORE SORROW AND SUFFERINGS. ONLY IF ALL COLOMBIA PERSEVERES IN A TRULY STRONG AND SOLID MANNER -- BUT NOT JUST WITH WORDS -- IN THE DIFFICULT BATTLE AGAINST CRIME, WILL WE BE ABLE TO BANISH VIOLENCE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0353 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 19 AUG 89 -- [SPEECH] [BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THAT MEASURE WILL BE COMPLEMENTED WITH A DECREE -- WHICH FALLS UNDER THE PROVISION OF THE STATE OF SIEGE -- ACCORDING TO WHICH THOSE WHO WITH THE EXCUSE OF CARRYING OUT POLITICAL CAMPAIGNS OR OTHER ELECTION ACTIVITIES USE WEAPONS OR THREATEN PEOPLE BY OTHER MEANS TO OBTAIN SUPPORT OR VOTES FOR A SPECIFIC CANDIDATE OR LIST OF CANDIDATES AND ACCORDING TO WHICH THOSE WHO USING THOSE SAME MEANS PREVENT A CITIZEN FROM EXERCISING HIS RIGHT TO VOTE, WILL BE IMPRISONED FOR 3 TO 6 YEARS AND WILL HAVE TO PAY A FINE EQUIVALENT TO 10 TO 50 TIMES THE LEGAL MONTHLY MINIMUM WAGE.

AS FOR THE MEDIA, WHOSE ROLE IS ESSENTIAL IN THE MAINTENANCE OF PUBLIC ORDER IN THE COUNTRY, I WOULD ONLY STATE THAT THE CONSTITUTION GUARANTEES THEM FULL FREEDOM IN TIMES OF PEACE, BUT THEY WILL BE HELD RESPONSIBLE BEFORE THE LAW WHEN THEY ATTACK PEOPLE'S HONOR, SOCIAL ORDER, OR PUBLIC TRANQUILLITY. THE GOVERNMENT WILL THEN ENFORCE THOSE LAWS IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE CONSTITUTION.

BASED ON SPECIAL POWERS, TODAY THE GOVERNMENT ISSUED OTHER DECREES THAT THE NATIONAL CONGRESS APPROVED ON A GOVERNMENT REQUEST. I WILL MENTION ONLY ONE OF THOSE DECREES. THIS DECREE AMENDS OUR PENAL CODE.

THE PUBLIC NAMING OF JURORS WILL BE ELIMINATED. ORGANIZED CRIME TOOK ADVANTAGE OF THAT JURY APPOINTMENT SYSTEM AND AVOIDED THE ACTION OF JUSTICE BY INTIMIDATING JURORS. THE NEW DECREE REDUCES FORMALITIES AND CREATES ROVING JUDGES WHO WILL HAVE AUTHORITY THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, THUS INCREASING THE FLEXIBILITY OF THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM. THOSE JUDGES WILL JUDGE ANY CRIME THAT WILL BE GIVEN SPECIAL IMPORTANCE FOR REASONS OF PUBLIC ORDER.

THESE MEASURES HAVE BEEN CAREFULLY STUDIED. THAT, HOWEVER, DOES NOT MEAN THEY CANNOT BE SUPPLEMENTED IN THE FUTURE IF NECESSARY.

WHEN DRAFTING THESE DECREES WE, AS USUAL, PAID DUE ATTENTION TO THE HONORABLE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE'S DECISIONS SO THAT THE CURRENT DECREES FOLLOW ALONG WITH THE GUIDELINES OF THE CONSTITUTION.

THE THREAT THAT DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND ORGANIZED CRIME REPRESENT JUSTIFIES THE SEVERITY OF THE MEASURES WE HAVE ADOPTED. COLOMBIANS CAN BE SURE WE WILL CONTINUE MAKING ALL THE NECESSARY EFFORTS TO REGAIN TRANQUILLITY IN COLOMBIA. I AM SURE WE WILL OVERCOME THESE DIFFICULTIES. A HANDFUL OF CRIMINALS WILL NOT DEFEAT A UNIFIED NATION THAT IS WILLING TO STRUGGLE AGAINST CRIME.

WE ARE CERTAINLY EXPERIENCING A DIFFICULT TIME. HOWEVER, WE HAVE EXPERIENCED EVEN MORE DIFFICULT SITUATIONS AND COLOMBIA OVERCAME THEM. WE MUST NOT STRAY FROM OUR PATH, BECAUSE THAT IS WHAT THE CRIMINALS WANT. BY FALLING INTO DESPAIR WE WILL BE PLAYING THE TERRORISTS' GAME. IF WE CONTINUE AHEAD FIRMLY AND DECISIVELY, WE WILL HAVE MUCH BETTER RESULTS. INSTEAD OF WASTING OUR TIME IN DISPUTES AND RECIPROCAL REPROACHES, LET US UNITE OUR ACTIONS AGAINST OUR COMMON ENEMY. WE MUST WIN THIS WAR. I AM SURE WE WILL SUCCEED. GOOD EVENING AND SEE YOU SOON.

DEV-MUC3-0358 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 20 AUG 89 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] AFTER THE ASSASSINATION OF LIBERAL LEADER LUIS CARLOS GALAN, THE 4,015 JUDGES OF THE COUNTRY DECIDED TO LIFT THE STRIKE THEY HAD CALLED ON 17 AUGUST, FOLLOWING THE ASSASSINATION OF A MAGISTRATE, AND WITHDREW THEIR RESIGNATIONS.

IT IS NOT THE MOMENT TO GO ON STRIKE OR TO RESIGN, JOSE GABRIEL SALOM, PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME TRIBUNAL OF BOGOTA, STATED. HE AND 47 COLLEAGUES HAD PRESENTED THEIR RESIGNATION LAST FRIDAY TO PROTEST THE ASSASSINATION OF MAGISTRATE CARLOS VALENCIA GARCIA, PRESUMABLY BY PAID ASSASSINS OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS. VALENCIA GARCIA HAD REJECTED THE APPEALS TO EXONERATE PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, KINGPINS OF THE COCAINE TRAFFICKING GROUP OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, FROM THE CHARGE THAT THEY HAD MASTERMINDED THE ASSASSINATION OF JOURNALIST GUILLERMO CANO, DIRECTOR OF THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR, AND JAIME PARDO LEAL, PRESIDENT OF THE OPPOSITION PARTY PATRIOTIC UNION.

ANTONIO SUAREZ, PRESIDENT OF THE JUDICIAL BRANCH PUBLIC EMPLOYEES ASSOCIATION, ANNOUNCED THAT THE STRIKE HAS BEEN CALLED OFF AND THAT NINE JUDGES ARE INVESTIGATING THE ASSASSINATION OF SENATOR GALAN.

THE JUDICIAL BRANCH WILL RESUME ACTIVITIES ON TUESDAY. THE STRIKE OF THE JUDGES, COMPOUNDED BY THE RESIGNATION OF SOME OF THEM, INTERRUPTED THE CONSIDERATION OF THREE CASES. THE STRIKE WAS ALSO CALLED TO FORCE THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO TO ADOPT MEASURES TO PROTECT THE MAGISTRATES WHOSE LIVES HAVE BEEN THREATENED BY ORGANIZED CRIME.

AMONG THE EMERGENCY MEASURES ADOPTED BY THE GOVERNMENT ARE SOME THAT WILL CONTRIBUTE TO HELPING THE JUDICIAL BRANCH TO CONFRONT THE THREAT POSED BY THE DEATH SQUADS OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

DEV-MUC3-0359 (BBN)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [INTERVIEW WITH D'AUBUISSON BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] THIS OFFICIAL TOLD YOU THAT? DOES THIS OFFICIAL, WHOSE NAME YOU DO NOT DISCLOSE, HAVE CREDIBILITY WITH THE GOVERNMENT?

[D'AUBUISSON] ALLOW ME TO RESERVE THE IDENTITY OF THE SOURCE, BUT HE DOES HAVE MUCH CREDIBILITY. HE IS SOMEONE WHO IS VERY FAMILIAR WITH THAT MOVEMENT, AND HE DOES HAVE CREDIBILITY. THE INTERESTING ASPECT OF THIS IS THE WAY THIS BIG MANGY DOG, THIS MR VILLALOBOS, THINKS. IF HE WANTS TO COME HERE AND PARTICIPATE, WE'LL TAKE HIS WORD, AND LET US SEE IF HE WILL REALLY HAVE A LANDSLIDE VICTORY.

[REPORTER] WOULD THERE BE ANY GUARANTEES FOR HIS PARTICIPATION?

[D'AUBUISSON] DIDN'T I JUST TELL YOU THAT THE FIRST MANGY DOGS, UNGO AND ZAMORA, ARE ALREADY HERE? WE DO HAVE THE BEST OF INTENTIONS; THERE IS A WILLINGNESS TO DO THIS. NOW, IF THEY ACTUALLY WANT TO DO IT, THAT IS A DIFFERENT STORY. I AM JUST TELLING YOU ABOUT THE FIRST INDICATIONS WE HAVE HAD, IN ADDITION TO SOME NOTES ON THE ELECTIONS THAT HAVE BEEN SENT BY SOME WHO CLAIM TO BE COMMANDERS. THE OVERALL PICTURE HAS CHANGED SOMEWHAT IN THE LAST FEW YEARS.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THAT CHANGE, MAJOR?

[D'AUBUISSON] IN PRACTICALLY ALL OF THE NOTES THEY [THE FMLN COMMANDERS] HAVE SENT, INCLUDING THE ONES SENT PRIOR TO THE ELECTIONS, THEY SAID THAT IF THE ELECTIONS WERE POSTPONED THEY WOULD PARTICIPATE. THAT IS AN INDICATION THAT THEY DO HAVE PLANS TO JOIN THE PROCESS.

[REPORTER] WHAT DOES THIS MEAN, MAJOR?

[D'AUBUISSON] IT MEANS TWO BASIC THINGS: ONE, THEY ARE LOST. THE OPTION TO SEIZE POWER THROUGH VIOLENT MEANS NO LONGER EXISTS.

[REPORTER] IN OTHER WORDS, THEY ARE LOST IN THE MILITARY FIELD?

[D'AUBUISSON] THEY ARE LOST BOTH IN THE MILITARY FIELD AND IN THE OPTION TO SEIZE POWER THROUGH VIOLENT MEANS. SECOND, THEY NO LONGER HAVE THE SUPPORT, AND WE HAVE BEEN ANALYZING THAT FOR SOME TIME NOW. THERE IS NO LONGER ANY SUPPORT FOR THIS TYPE OF REBEL MOVEMENT, FOR THIS TYPE OF ARMED REBEL MOVEMENT TO SEIZE POWER.

[REPORTER] YOU MEAN SUPPORT FROM THE USSR?

[D'AUBUISSON] THERE IS NO SUPPORT FROM THE COMMUNIST WORLD IN GENERAL. NATURALLY, THIS IS BASED VERY MUCH ON THE SO-CALLED PERESTROYKA. THEREFORE, THEY WILL HAVE TO JOIN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, BECAUSE OTHERWISE THEY ARE GOING TO BE LEFT OUT. IF THEY WANT TO CONTINUE SHOOTING BULLETS JUST FOR THE SAKE OF SHOOTING, THEY ARE GOING TO BE LEFT OUT OF EVERYTHING AND EVERYONE.

[REPORTER] THERE IS MUCH TALK HERE ABOUT FORMING AN INTERNAL OPPOSITION FRONT; I BELIEVE THIS IS PART OF THE "EVERYONE AGAINST ARENA" CAMPAIGN. DO YOU HAVE ANY KNOWLEDGE ABOUT THIS AND THE LINE THIS INTERNAL FRONT MIGHT FOLLOW?

[D'AUBUISSON] WELL, NOT EXACTLY. HOWEVER, IT IS LOGICAL THAT AN INTERNAL POLITICAL FRONT COULD BE FORMED. THAT WOULD BE A POLITICAL PROCESS WITHIN A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS. IT IS ALL RIGHT TO DO THAT. THEY HAVE ALL THE RIGHT IN THE WORLD TO DO THAT.

NOW, THERE ARE SUBVERSIVE THOUGHTS. WE ARE REFERRING TO THOSE BIG MANGY DOGS WHO WANT TO TAKE THE FIRST STEPS IN JOINING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS. ON THE OTHER HAND, THEY ARE SUBVERSIVE INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE DISRUPTING PUBLIC ORDER. IF WHAT THEY WANT IS TO CAUSE HARM AND HINDER THE PROGRAMS PREPARED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI AND HIS CABINET, THEY ARE GOING TO GO AHEAD AND DO IT ANYHOW.

REMEMBER THAT VERY SIMPLE PHRASE I TOLD YOU AT THE BEGINNING. THEY CLAIM THAT IF ARENA FAILS, THEY ARE THE ALTERNATIVE. THAT IS WHAT THE GROUP OF UNGO, ZAMORA, AND ALL THOSE REALLY THINKS. THERE IS ANOTHER GREAT POSSIBILITY, AND THAT IS WHAT IS REALLY GOING TO HAPPEN HERE: ARENA WILL NOT FAIL. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WILL NOT FAIL. HOWEVER, THEY ARE GOING TO TRY ALL THE ILLEGAL, SUBVERSIVE ACTIONS THEY CAN TO MAKE US FAIL. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0360 (BBN)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [INTERVIEW WITH D'AUBUISSON BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [D'AUBUISSON] ONCE THEY FOUND OUT ABOUT THE SITUATION IN THE RURAL AREAS, HARASSMENTS AND ASSASSINATIONS BEGAN SO AS TO GET OUR ATTENTION. THIS WAS BECAUSE THE COMMUNISTS KNOW THAT THE RURAL AREAS HAVE REACTED FAVORABLY. THEY HAVE ALREADY REACHED THE CONCLUSION THAT WE ARE GOING TO BE SUCCESSFUL IN THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE AGRARIAN REFORM, WHICH SHOULD BE PERMANENT. THE AGRARIAN REFORM PROCESS CAN BE MADE IN COMPLIANCE WITH THE LAWS AND THE CONSTITUTION WITHOUT RESORTING TO VIOLENCE. THE AGRARIAN REFORM CAN BE PRODUCTIVE, AND THAT IS OUR GOAL. THE AGRARIAN REFORM IN OUR COUNTRY WILL BE MADE PRODUCTIVE.

[REPORTER] THERE WERE REPORTS THAT PEASANTS WERE CONCERNED BECAUSE SIX CASES HAD BEEN DECIDED IN FAVOR OF THE LANDOWNERS AND THE LANDS WERE LEGALLY TURNED OVER TO THE OWNERS.

[D'AUBUISSON] I DO NOT KNOW IF THERE WERE SIX OR MORE CASES. IF WE LOOK AT IT FROM THE LEGAL POINT OF VIEW, SERIOUS MISTAKES WERE MADE WHEN THE LANDS WERE VIOLENTLY OCCUPIED. MANY LANDS WERE IMPROPERLY OCCUPIED. WE HAVE TO LOOK AT THE POLITICAL ASPECTS OF THIS. WE ARE LOOKING FOR SOLUTIONS FOR THESE PEOPLE. IF THEY CANNOT STAY ON THOSE LANDS, THEY CAN TAKE OTHER LANDS, BECAUSE THERE ARE ABOUT 33 LAND TRACTS THAT HAVE BEEN COMPLETELY ABANDONED. REFUGEES AND ARMY FAMILIES MAY BE BROUGHT TO THOSE REGIONS. EVEN THOSE WHO DISAGREE WITH OUR AGRARIAN REFORM PLAN CAN GO THERE. NO ONE WILL BE ABANDONED.

[REPORTER] WHERE ARE THOSE 33 LAND TRACTS?

[D'AUBUISSON] IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

[REPORTER] IN GENERAL TERMS, AND TO END THIS INTERVIEW, DO YOU BELIEVE THIS 5-YEAR PERIOD WILL BE ONE OF PEACE AND DEVELOPMENT IN EL SALVADOR?

[D'AUBUISSON] YES, AND WE ARE SURE THAT WE WILL WIN THE ELECTIONS IN THE FIRST ROUND IN 1994. IN THIS 5-YEAR PERIOD WE WILL ENJOY THE BENEFITS OF HAVING AN HONEST GOVERNMENT AND OF BEING ABLE TO EXPRESS OURSELVES DEMOCRATICALLY. THERE WILL BE PRODUCTIVITY AND THE PEOPLE OF EL SALVADOR WILL ONCE AGAIN FEEL PROUD OF BEING SALVADORANS. WE WILL NO LONGER NEED OTHERS TO DONATE THINGS TO US BECAUSE WE CAN PRODUCE THEM HERE. WE WILL CONTINUE WORKING TO RESCUE THIS SHIP SO THAT IT CAN SAIL EFFICIENTLY.

[REPORTER] MAJOR, WE WANT TO THANK YOU FOR VISITING US TODAY AND FOR DISCUSSING ALL OF THE ISSUES WE COVERED. IT HAS BEEN INTERESTING TO LISTEN TO YOUR POINTS OF VIEW AND THOSE OF YOUR PARTY REGARDING THE VARIOUS ISSUES.

[D'AUBUISSON] THANK YOU. THIS HAS BEEN AN INTERESTING INTERVIEW. I WILL ALWAYS BE WILLING TO COME BACK HERE AND TALK TO YOU AGAIN.

[REPORTER] THANK YOU, MAJOR, AND WE THANK ALL OUR VIEWERS.

DEV-MUC3-0361 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 21 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, THE ALLEGED "COMPTROLLER" OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS CAPTURED BY COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES TODAY DURING THE RAID ON A FARM IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, IT WAS REPORTED IN BOGOTA.

IT WAS LEARNED THAT THE ARREST OF MARTINEZ ROMERO, THE MOST IMPORTANT ONE SINCE THE ARMY AND POLICE LAUNCHED AN OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIA LAST SATURDAY, OCCURRED ON A FARM NEAR TOLU MUNICIPALITY IN SUCRE DEPARTMENT.

ABOUT 24 PEOPLE WERE ALSO ARRESTED ALONG WITH THE MEDELLIN CARTEL MEMBER. THE CARTEL IS THE LARGEST WORLD COCAINE TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATION, WHICH STAGED A SERIES OF VIOLENT ACTIONS LAST WEEK.

IN FACT, MERCENARIES OF THAT CRIMINAL ORGANIZATION ASSASSINATED IN LESS THAN 48 HOURS, MAGISTRATE CARLOS VALENCIA GARCIA, ANTIOQUIA POLICE COMMANDER COLONEL WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO, AND SENATOR AND PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL LUIS CARLOS GALAN, WHO ACCORDING TO THE POLLS, WAS THE FAVORITE TO SUCCEED VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS AS PRESIDENT.

MARTINEZ ROMERO, ONE OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS MOST WANTED BY THE U.S. DRUG ENFORCEMENT ADMINISTRATION (DEA), HAD MANAGED TO EVADE A PLAN TO CAPTURE HIM IN PANAMA CITY LAST 29 MARCH.

UNOFFICIAL REPORTS IN BOGOTA INDICATE THAT THE WELL-KNOWN MAFIA MEMBER COULD BE THE FIRST TO BE EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES, IN KEEPING WITH THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT'S NEW PROVISIONS ADOPTED IN VIEW OF THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE. THESE PROVISIONS AUTHORIZE THE EXTRADITION OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS TO OTHER COUNTRIES WITHOUT HAVING TO GO THROUGH THE JUSTICE TRIBUNALS.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL REPORTS, MORE THAN 11,000 PEOPLE RELATED TO THE MAFIA HAVE BEEN ARRESTED IN THE INTENSE OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE COLOMBIAN ARMY AND POLICE, IN THE LARGEST OFFENSIVE EVER LAUNCHED BY COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKING BANDS.

THE ACTIONS ARE BEING CARRIED OUT ESPECIALLY IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF ANTIOQUIA, CUNDINAMARCA, AND VALLE DEL CAUCA, WHERE SO-CALLED ELITE PATROLS HAVE TAKEN OVER EXTENSIVE AND SWANK PROPERTIES OWNED BY PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, THE "DRUG LORDS" OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL.

REPORTS TODAY INDICATE THAT ONE OF THE PRIVATE HOMES BELONGING TO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALIAS "THE MEXICAN," WAS RAIDED IN BOGOTA.

DEV-MUC3-0363 (BBN)

GUATEMALA CITY, 21 AUG 89 (PRENSA LIBRE) -- [TEXT] THE STAFF REPORTERS OF THE NEW MAGAZINE POR QUE RESIGNED THEIR POSTS THIS WEEKEND AFTER RECEIVING DEATH THREATS. THE FORMER REPORTERS INDICATED THIS SITUATION COULD MEAN THE MAGAZINE MAY CLOSE THIS WEEK.

THE REPORTER INDICATED THAT THE ANONYMOUS THREATS BEGAN ON 18 AUGUST WHEN THEY WERE ORDERED TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY IN 72 HOURS. THESE NEWSMEN WERE FORCED TO RESIGN THEIR JOBS, BUT OTHER REPORTERS, WHO ALSO RECEIVED THREATENING TELEPHONE CALLS, DID NOT.

THE FORMER REPORTERS INDICATED THAT THIS IS YET ANOTHER ATTACK ON FREEDOM OF INFORMATION AND THOUGHT SINCE 1 AUGUST, WHEN CHRISTIAN DEMOCRAT IDEOLOGUE DANILO BARILLAS, WHO WROTE COLUMNS FOR THE MAGAZINE, WAS MURDERED.

A FEW DAYS AFTER BARRILLA'S MURDER, ROLANDO PINEDA LAM, POR QUE MAGAZINE PUBLISHER AND SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE COMMITTEE FOR THE CREATION OF THE POPULAR ALLIANCE PARTY-5, FOUNDED BY DANILO BARILLAS UNDER THE NAME FCD-5 [CIVIC DEMOCRATIC FRONT], HAD TO GO INTO EXILE.

WE HAVE LEARNED THAT THE MAGAZINE POR QUE BELONGS TO THE TALENTO EMPRESARIAL COMPANY, IS EDITED BY ASOCIACION LIBRO EXITO, INC, AND APPEARS EVERY TUESDAY.

THE EDITORIAL HOUSE DECIDED TO SUSPEND PUBLICATION BECAUSE OF THE DEATH THREATS. SO, IT IS VERY LIKELY THAT THIS NEWS MEDIUM WILL DIE A FEW MONTHS AFTER IT BEGAN.

ACTS OF INTIMIDATION AGAINST THE PRODUCTION AND ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF OF THE AFOREMENTIONED MAGAZINE OCCUR ALMOST SIMULTANEOUSLY WITH CHARGES BY THE GUATEMALAN CHAMBER OF JOURNALISM THAT THE COUNTRY'S INDEPENDENT PRESS IS BEING HARASSED.

DEV-MUC3-0365 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 22 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION: HERE IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT. GLORIA CONGOTTI HAS JUST ARRIVED AT OUR STUDIOS FROM THE DIJIN [DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS] WITH VIDEO CLIPS OF FIVE MEN SUSPECTED OF KILLING LIBERAL PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LUIS CARLOS GALAN SARMIENTO. THEIR NAMES ARE ARMANDO BERNAL ACOSTA, NORBERTO MURILLO CHALATA, PEDRO ZAMBRANO DELGADO, LUIS ALFREDO GONZALEZ CHACON, AND LUIS HASBUN.

THE FIVE SUSPECTS WERE ARRESTED AT 4-A ROAD, NO 1978, IN MEZZANINE 1, BOGOTA, WHERE AN OFFICE SUPPOSEDLY OPERATED. THEY ARE CURRENTLY BEING HELD AT THE DIJIN FACILITIES. ACCORDING TO AUTHORITIES, THEIR FEATURES COINCIDE WITH THE COMPOSITE SKETCH PREPARED BY THE JUDICIAL POLICE BASED ON THE DESCRIPTIONS GIVEN BY WITNESSES.

THE INDIVIDUALS SUSPECTED OF KILLING LUIS CARLOS GALAN SARMIENTO LAST FRIDAY WILL BE TURNED OVER TO THE THIRD PUBLIC ORDER COURT, WHICH WILL BE IN CHARGE OF INVESTIGATING THIS CRIME THAT HAS SHAKEN COLOMBIA AND THE ENTIRE WORLD.

IF ANYONE WHO WAS PRESENT AT THE SOACHA SQUARE FRIDAY NIGHT RECOGNIZES ANYONE OF THESE SUSPECTS, PLEASE CALL DIJIN. OF COURSE, THE NAMES OF THOSE WHO CALL WILL BE KEPT SECRET.

DEV-MUC3-0366 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 22 AUG 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN DEFENSE MINISTRY GAVE THE MEDIA ITS FIRST REPORT ON THE ANTIDRUG OPERATIONS IT HAS CARRIED OUT IN THE COUNTRY AFTER A POLICE COLONEL, A JUDGE, AND CANDIDATE SENATOR LUIS CARLOS GALAN WERE MURDERED LAST WEEK.

THE REPORT INDICATED THAT 817 PROPERTIES IN COLOMBIA HAVE BEEN RAIDED, 10,777 PERSONS HAVE BEEN ARRESTED, AND 678 WEAPONS, AND 4,000 KG OF COCAINE PASTE HAVE BEEN CONFISCATED SINCE FRIDAY, 18 AUGUST.

GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS ALSO CONFISCATED 110 KG OF COCAINE, 1,161 VEHICLES, 30 BOATS, 13 MOTORCYCLES, 42 COMMUNICATION EQUIPMENTS, AND MORE THAN 3,000 CARTRIDGES OF DIFFERENT CALIBERS. IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT 62 PLANES AND 18 HELICOPTERS WERE GROUNDED.

A TOTAL OF 141 PROPERTIES, AS WELL AS 5,222 FARM ANIMALS, SUPPOSEDLY BELONGING TO DRUG TRAFFICKERS, WERE ALSO SEIZED.

THE DEFENSE MINISTRY'S INFORMATION DIRECTOR COLONEL EDUARDO AREVALO, STATED THAT OPERATIONS CONTINUE AND THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL CONTINUE TO SEARCH FOR THE BIG DRUG "CAPOS." ACCORDING TO UNOFFICIAL REPORTS, THE "CAPOS" HAVE ALREADY FLED FROM COLOMBIA BECAUSE OF THE STRONG GOVERNMENT OFFENSIVE AGAINST THEM.

AREVALO STATED, THAT "THE CITIZENS' SUPPORT HAS BEEN DECISIVE IN THE SUCCESS OF THE ARMED FORCES' OPERATIONS" AND THAT HE WAS CONFIDENT THAT THE FLOW OF INFORMATION WOULD ALLOW NEW VICTORIES IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUGS.

MEANWHILE, A HUNDRED AIRCRAFT OF ALL TYPES WERE BEING INSPECTED WITH DOGS TRAINED TO DETECT DRUGS AT THE EL DORADO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT IN BOGOTA TONIGHT. THE CIVIL AERONAUTICS DIRECTORATE HAS ADVISED ALL THE AIRCRAFT OWNERS THAT THEY MUST PROVE THAT THEY DO NOT HAVE ANY LINKS TO DRUG TRAFFICKING WITHIN THE NEXT 7 DAYS.

THE SAME OFFICE HAS REPORTED THAT THE SAME MEASURE WILL BE APPLIED TO OTHER AIRPORTS IN THE COUNTRY IN THE COMING HOURS.

CONCLUDING, THE GOVERNMENT ISSUED A DECREE TONIGHT THAT GOES INTO IMMEDIATE EFFECT. THE DECREE AUTHORIZES MILITARY AND POLICE OFFICIALS TO SUSPEND THE OPERATION OF TELECOMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT THAT OPERATE WITHOUT THE AUTHORIZATION OF THE COMMUNICATIONS MINISTRY. THE EQUIPMENT IS TO BE CONFISCATED AND SENT TO THE SAID MINISTRY.

DEV-MUC3-0367 (BBN)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 23 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] STEPPING UP SURVEILLANCE ALONG THE BORDER WITH COLOMBIA AND PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ' WARNING THAT THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING MUST BE STRENGTHENED ARE VENEZUELA'S VISIBLE REACTIONS TO THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE IN THE NEIGHBORING COUNTRY, WHICH RESULTED IN THE DEATH OF LIBERAL PARTY LEADER LUIS CARLOS GALAN.

MEANWHILE, IT WAS LEARNED THAT EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, RECENTLY ARRESTED IN COLOMBIA AND ONE OF THE LEADERS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ORGANIZATION'S FINANCES, WAS TRYING TO PURCHASE LAND IN VENEZUELA TO EXPAND THE ACTIVITIES OF THE ORGANIZATION.

ACCORDING TO PEREZ, THE ACTIVITIES OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS COULD BE MOVED TO VENEZUELAN TERRITORY. THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT STRESSED THE NEED TO ADOPT STRONG MEASURES AGAINST SUCH A POSSIBILITY. "THE VENEZUELAN PEOPLE MUST UNITE IN THIS BATTLE," THE HEAD OF STATE SAID. HE ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT VENEZUELA WILL SUPPORT COLOMBIA BY STEPPING UP SURVEILLANCE ALONG THE BORDER.

IN THIS SENSE, VENEZUELAN DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL FILMO LOPEZ UZCATEGUI ANNOUNCED THE CREATION OF "TASK FORCES" THAT WILL BE DEPLOYED ALONG VENEZUELA'S WESTERN BORDER. THESE TASK FORCES WILL CARRY OUT INTELLIGENCE ACTIVITIES AND SUPPORT THE MILITARY UNITS STATIONED IN THE AREA.

THE MINISTER REJECTED THE POSSIBILITY OF PARAMILITARY PERSONNEL BEING RECRUITED TO FORM THE "TASK FORCES" AND ADDED THAT INCIDENTS LIKE THE ONE THAT OCCURRED IN EL AMPARO ON THE BORDER WITH COLOMBIA LAST YEAR WHEN A GROUP OF SOLDIERS MURDERED 17 FISHERMEN WILL NOT BE REPEATED.

"WE ARE TRYING TO KEEP DRUG TRAFFICKERS FROM ENTERING THE COUNTRY TO CONTINUE THEIR CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES, THE MINISTER SAID.

ACCORDING TO STATEMENTS MADE BY SOURCES STATIONED ALONG THE COLOMBIAN - VENEZUELAN BORDER, AND CARRIED IN TODAY'S EDITION OF EL NACIONAL, MEDELLIN CARTEL TREASURER MARTINEZ ROMERO WANTED TO BUY LAND IN ZULIA AND TACHIRA, TWO VENEZUELAN STATES, TO EXPAND THE ORGANIZATION'S CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES.

ACCORDING TO ZULIA STATE GOVERNOR ISMAEL ORDAZ, THE SECURITY CORPS HAVE BEEN ALERTED IN LIGHT OF THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKING "CAPOS" MAY HAVE FLED INTO VENEZUELA AS A RESULT OF THE PERSECUTION UNLEASHED IN COLOMBIA FOLLOWING THE MURDER OF LUIS CARLOS GALAN ON 18 AUGUST.

DEV-MUC3-0368 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 23 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT'S STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DRUG CARTELS CONTINUES. THE OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE AUTHORITIES IN MEDELLIN HAVE RESULTED IN 70 RAIDS. HOUSES, FARMS, DISCOTHEQUES, AND APARTMENTS REPORTEDLY OWNED BY PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA HAVE BEEN SEIZED BY THE AUTHORITIES; 921 PERSONS HAVE BEEN ARRESTED, 2 OF WHOM FACE CHARGES THAT MERIT THEIR EXTRADITION.

THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE MILITARY AUTHORITIES AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY HAS BEEN PARTICULARLY EFFECTIVE IN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT. HOURS AFTER LEARNING ABOUT THE MEASURES ADOPTED BY THE GOVERNMENT TO COUNTER DRUG TRAFFICKERS, REGIONAL AUTHORITIES LAUNCHED A LARGE-SCALE PLAN TO CARRY OUT RAIDS AND CONFISCATIONS, AND TO SET UP ROAD BLOCKS.

TWENTY-TWO PROPERTIES -- INCLUDING FARMS, DISCOTHEQUES, BUILDINGS, AND RESTAURANTS -- WERE SEIZED UNDER THE CHARGES THAT THEY WERE OWNED BY MEMBERS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL. THE MOST OUTSTANDING CASES INCLUDE THE MONACO BUILDING -- WHICH WAS ALMOST DESTROYED DURING A DYNAMITE ATTACK LAST YEAR, WAS BEING REPAIRED, AND HAD PRACTICALLY BEEN RESTORED TO ITS FORMER SPLENDOR -- GAMA BUILDING, INTERNATIONAL DISCOTHEQUE, CAMA SUELTA DISCOTHEQUE FORTALEZA DEL LAURO DISCOTHEQUE, AND DON MATEO DISCOTHEQUE, UNDOUBTEDLY THE MOST LUXURIOUS IN THE CITY.

SEVERAL FARMS WERE ALSO SEIZED, INCLUDING EL BIZCOCHO FARM, WHERE SEVERAL WEAPONS CACHES WERE FOUND, AND LAS AGUILAS FARM, BECAUSE THE VALUE OF ITS FURNITURE AND APPLIANCES SURPASS 3 BILLION PESOS. THE MAIN CHARACTERISTIC IN ALL THE CONFISCATED PROPERTIES IS THEIR LUXURY AND ECCENTRICISM, THUS MAKING THEIR TOTAL VALUE INCALCULABLE.

THE AUTHORITIES ALSO SEIZED WEAPONS, VEHICLES, AND COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT. THE FIRST REPORT INDICATES 921 PERSONS WERE ARRESTED BUT THE FIGURE COULD BE HIGHER, GIVEN THE OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT IN RECENT HOURS. THE ARRESTED PERSONS INCLUDE TWO WHO REPORTEDLY FACE ENOUGH CHARGES TO GUARANTEE THEIR EXTRADITION.

MEANWHILE, ANOTHER PERSON HAS BEEN ARRESTED IN CONNECTION WITH INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING OPERATIONS. SHE IS ANA ELENA BEATRIZ RODRIGUEZ, WHO IS THE THIRD EXTRADITABLE PERSON SOUGHT BY U.S. AUTHORITIES IN CONNECTION WITH MONEY LAUNDERING. SHE WAS CAPTURED IN CARTAGENA.

THE COLOMBIAN ARMY'S RAIDS ON PROPERTIES REPORTEDLY OWNED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS STILL CONTINUE. TWO NEW FARMS LOCATED WITHIN THE MOUNTAIN RANGE IN PALMIRA MUNICIPALITY JURISDICTION WERE RECENTLY SEIZED BY THE ARMED FORCES. LA RUIZA FARM, A SYNONYM FOR OSTENTATION AND LUXURY, IS A RECREATION CENTER OWNED, ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORITIES, BY RAMIRO CORREA. PEOPLE VISITING THE FARM COULD ENJOY THE POOLS, SURROUNDED BY LUXURY RUGS, JACUZZIS, A TENNIS COURT, BARS, EXOTICALLY DECORATED BEDROOMS, AND A FOUNTAIN IN THE MIDDLE OF THE LIVING ROOM.

THE AUTHORITIES SEIZED A SIZEABLE AMOUNT OF WEAPONS, COMMUNICATION EQUIPMENT, BULLET-PROOF VESTS, AMMUNITION FOR RIFLES, GRENADES BROUGHT FROM ISRAEL, MILITARY UNIFORMS, AND INFRA-RED SIGHTS -- WHICH NOT EVEN THE ARMY HAS -- AT EL ROSAL FARM, LOCATED IN THE AREA OF POTRERILLOS. THE AUTHORITIES ALSO SEIZED MOTORCYCLES SMUGGLED INTO THE COUNTRY. MOST OF THE VALLEY WAS VISIBLE FROM A LOOKOUT TOWER, PROBABLY FOR SECURITY REASONS OR FOR ENTERTAINMENT PURPOSES. THE MAIN ATTRACTION AT THE FARM WERE TRAINED HIGH- STEPPING COLOMBIAN HORSES. THE OWNERS OF THESE FARMS HAVE YET TO BE ARRESTED, AND THERE IS STILL NO INFORMATION ON THEIR WHEREABOUTS. THE VALUE OF THESE PROPERTIES IS CALCULATED IN MORE THAN 100 BILLION PESOS.

THE AUTHORITIES CONTINUE TO DEAL BLOWS TO THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN ATLANTICO DEPARTMENT. BERNARDO LONDONO QUINTERO, A NATIVE OF PEREIRA AND ACCUSED OF BEING A MEMBER OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS CAPTURED EARLY THIS MORNING NORTH OF BARRANQUILLA. THE AUTHORITIES ARE CURRENTLY INVESTIGATING LONDONO'S ACTIVITIES BECAUSE HE IS APPARENTLY SOUGHT BY THE U.S. AUTHORITIES. FURTHERMORE, THE BARRANQUILLA AUTHORITIES HAVE ARRESTED ALBERTO ORLANDES GAMBOA, A 34-YEAR-OLD NATIVE OF BARRANQUILLA WHO IS CONSIDERED ANOTHER EXTRADITABLE PERSON. THE AUTHORITIES CONFISCATED HIS WINE-COLORED TOYOTA LAND CUISER AND A BROWNING 9-MM PISTOL.S EVERAL RAIDS ARE CURRENTLY UNDER WAY IN NORTHERN BARRANQUILLA AT RESIDENCES PRESUMABLY OWNED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

DEV-MUC3-0370 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 23 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [ANA SOFIA GIRALDO] [TEXT] FORMER GOVERNMENT MINISTER CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO WAS UNANIMOUSLY PROCLAIMED TODAY PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE FOR THE NEW LIBERALISM [MOVEMENT WITHIN THE LIBERAL PARTY].

GAVIRIA, WHO BECAME ONE OF THE MAJOR CONTENDERS FOR THE PRESIDENCY OVERNIGHT, SPOKE TODAY.

GAVIRIA EXPERIENCED ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT MOMENTS OF HIS POLITICAL CAREER WHEN HE WAS NOMINATED CANDIDATE OF THE NEW LIBERALISM MOVEMENT. IT IS ALSO PERHAPS ONE OF THE MOST DIFFICULT TIMES IN HIS PERSONAL LIFE BECAUSE HE RECEIVED THE BANNERS OF LUIS CARLOS GALAN, WHO WAS KILLED LAST FRIDAY. HE SAID THE DEATH OF THE LEADER CANNOT BE USED TO ELIMINATE THE SYSTEM OF CONSULTING WITH THE PEOPLE, WHICH WAS HIS GREATEST POLITICAL ACHIEVEMENT. HE SAID FORMER PRESIDENT JULIO CESAR TURBAY AYALA IS WILLING TO ISSUE SPECIAL A RESOLUTION TO ALLOW THE REGISTRATION OF THE NEW CANDIDACY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GAVIRIA] IF YOU ALL SUPPORT ME IN THIS EFFORT, IN THE MIDST OF THIS GREAT RESPONSIBILITY, IN THE MIDST OF THE CRISIS IN OUR INSTITUTION THAT IS ENDANGERING OUR DEMOCRACY, I AM SURE JUST AS YOU ARE THAT WE ARE GOING TO BE SUCCESSFUL. I AM NOT TALKING ABOUT THE ELECTIONS, BUT I AM TALKING ABOUT MAKING COLOMBIA SUCCESSFUL. LUIS CARLOS GALAN WILL GUIDE US FROM HEAVEN SO THAT WE CAN MAKE COLOMBIA BETTER. [END RECORDING]

HE SAID THAT EVEN THOUGH HE IS AFRAID HE WILL STILL GO OUT TO PUBLIC PLACES TO FIGHT TERRORISM. HE SAID HE IS WILLING TO RESPECT THE RULES OF THE GAME OF THE NEW LIBERALISM. GAVIRIA WILL NOW HAVE FULL AUTHORITY TO APPOINT MEMBERS OF HIS CAMPAIGN.

EVEN THOUGH IT WAS NOT EASY FOR SOME OF GALAN'S FRIENDS TO ACCEPT THE NEW LEADER OF THEIR MOVEMENT, THEY KNOW THAT GALAN IS NO LONGER HERE, AND GAVIRIA IS THE NEW LEADER.

DEV-MUC3-0371 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 24 AUG 89 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] A VIOLENT OFFENSIVE SEEMS TO HAVE BEEN LAUNCHED BY PERSONS WHO ARE BEING SOUGHT THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. SEVERAL EXPLOSIVE DEVICES WERE PLACED AT DIFFERENT SITES IN MEDELLIN [WORDS INDISTINCT] A MESSAGE, WHICH RADIO CARACOL WILL READ FOR ITS LISTENERS:

23 AUGUST 1989 THE EXTRADITABLES AND THE PEOPLE WHOSE PROPERTIES HAVE BEEN CONFISCATED STATE THE FOLLOWING TO THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE:

1. WE HAVE BEEN ASKING THE GOVERNMENT FOR PEACE SINCE THE TALKS IN PANAMA IN 1984. A LOT OF VIOLENCE COULD HAVE BEEN AVOIDED.

2. WE ACCEPTED THE PEACE PLAN PROPOSED BY PRESIDENT BARCO BUT WE RECEIVED NO REPLY FROM THE GOVERNMENT.

3. THE ONLY REPLY WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN REPRESSION, ARBITRARY [WORDS INDISTINCT] UNJUST ARREST OF OUR RELATIVES, LOOTING OF OUR HOUSES.

4. ALL KINDS OF JURIDICAL VIOLATIONS HAVE BEEN PERPETRATED AGAINST US.

5. THE GOVERNMENT HAS BRIBED JUSTICE WITH [WORDS INDISTINCT], DIPLOMATIC SINECURES, AND TRIPS ABROAD.

6. THE ACTIONS OF CONFISCATION ARE NOTHING NEW; THEY HAVE ALWAYS PREVAILED IN OUR COUNTRY. [WORDS INDISTINCT] WERE UNJUSTLY ARRESTED AND IMPRISONED, EVEN THOUGH NO ARREST WARRANTS HAD BEEN ISSUED AGAINST THEM, AND MANY OF OUR PROPERTIES AND POSSESSIONS WERE ARBITRARILY CONFISCATED OR USURPED.

7. COLOMBIAN CITIZENS CHARGED WITH MONEY LAUNDERING HAVE BEEN EXTRADITED AND WILL BE EXTRADITED, ALTHOUGH THIS REPRESENTS A VIOLATION OF COLOMBIAN LAWS.

8. WE ALWAYS WERE, ARE, AND WILL BE WILLING TO ENGAGE IN DIALOGUE BUT WE WILL NOT LOWER OUR GUARD AND WE WILL CONTINUE OUR STRUGGLE AND WIDESPREAD WAR AGAINST TRAITORS AND TURNCOATS.

9. WE DECLARE A WIDESPREAD AND TOTAL WAR ON THE GOVERNMENT, THE INDUSTRIAL AND POLITICAL OLIGARCHY, THE JOURNALISTS WHO HAVE ATTACKED AND MISTREATED US, JUDGES WHO HAVE BEEN BRIBED BY THE GOVERNMENT, THE EXTRADITING MAGISTRATES, THE BUSINESS ORGANIZATION PRESIDENTS, AND ALL THOSE WHO HAVE PERSECUTED US IN THE PAST.

10. WE WILL NOT RESPECT THE FAMILIES OF THOSE WHO HAVE NOT RESPECTED OUR FAMILIES. WE WILL KILL THEM, AND WE WILL BURN AND DESTROY THE OLIGARCHY'S INDUSTRIES, PROPERTIES, AND MANSIONS.

(SIGNED) THE EXTRADITABLES.

DEV-MUC3-0373 (BBN)

GUATEMALA CITY, 24 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] WELL-KNOWN BANKER RAMIRO CASTILLO LOVE WAS MURDERED TODAY BY A GROUP OF UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS WHO RIDDLED HIM WITH MACHINEGUN FIRE AS HE WAS LEAVING HIS RESIDENCE IN AN ELEGANT SUBURB IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF THIS CITY.

ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, APPROXIMATELY SIX UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS BEARING ARMS WENT TO HIS RESIDENCE THIS MORNING WITH THE INTENTION OF ROBBING OR KIDNAPPING CASTILLO. CASTILLO RESISTED, HOWEVER, AND WAS SHOT TO DEATH. THE ATTACKERS ALSO WOUNDED CASTILLO'S SON.

AFTER MURDERING CASTILLO THE ATTACKERS JUMPED INTO ONE OF CASTILLO'S VEHICLES AND FLED.

CASTILLO WAS THE PRESIDENT OF THE BANCO INDUSTRIAL, THE LARGEST PRIVATE BANK IN GUATEMALA.

IT WAS ALSO REPORTED TODAY THAT UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS KIDNAPPED A YOUNG COUPLE, SILVIA AZURDIA AND VICTOR RODRIGUEZ, AS THEY WERE LEAVING THEIR HOME IN GUATEMALA CITY. BOTH AZURDIA AND RODRIGUEZ ARE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS.

AZURDIA IS THE DAUGHTER OF FREDDY AZURDIA, THE DIRECTOR OF A LOCAL RADIO NEWS PROGRAM CALLED "COMANDO INFORMATIVO."

DEV-MUC3-0374 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 24 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] AS A RESULT OF COLOMBIAN PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL LUIS CARLOS GALAN'S MURDER, PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES' SECURITY IN PUBLIC APPEARANCES HAS BECOME A MAJOR ISSUE.

FOLLOWING ARE THE MINIMUM SECURITY MEASURES THAT PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES MUST TAKE INTO ACCOUNT TO PROTECT THEMSELVES AND SAVE THEIR LIVES WHEN ENDANGERED.

FROM NOW ON SUPPORTERS OF ANY PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE MUST UNDERSTAND THAT THEY WILL HAVE TO ABIDE BY THE FOLLOWING SECURITY MEASURES DURING THEIR CANDIDATES' PUBLIC APPEARANCES.

MEASURES FOR CANDIDATES

1. ALL CANDIDATES WILL HAVE TO PLACE THEMSELVES IN THE HANDS OF THEIR GUARDIAN ANGELS, IN OTHER WORDS TO THEIR CHIEF ESCORT. THE CHIEF ESCORT AND THE CANDIDATE WILL JOINTLY PLAN EACH TOUR AND WILL PROGRAM ALL MOVEMENTS IN DETAIL AND FOLLOW THE PROGRAM TO THE LETTER.

THE CANDIDATE MUST INFORM THE CHIEF ESCORT OF HIS AGENDA AND OF ANY THREAT OR INDICATION OF DANGER HE RECEIVES. THE CANDIDATE MUST USE HIS ESCORTS EXCLUSIVELY FOR HIS PROTECTION AND FOR NO OTHER USE.

2. A CANDIDATE'S ESCORTS MUST KNOW THE CANDIDATE'S BLOODTYPE, HIS ILLNESSES, AND WHICH MEDICINE HE TAKES. THE ESCORTS MUST ALSO KNOW THE NAMES OF THE CANDIDATE'S CLOSEST FRIENDS.

3. THE CANDIDATE MUST LEARN WHAT TO DO IN AN EMERGENCY SITUATION. HIS ESCORTS WILL TEACH HIM WHAT TO DO.

4. NO ONE SHOULD BE SURPRISED IF THE CANDIDATES CHANGE THEIR PLANS AT THE LAST MINUTE. THE CANDIDATE MUST NOT FALL INTO A ROUTINE. HE MUST CHANGE ROUTES, SCHEDULES, AND PROGRAMS ALWAYS IN CONSULTATION WITH HIS CHIEF ESCORT.

5. THE CANDIDATE MUST ALWAYS HAVE A DOCTOR IN HIS GROUP.

6. EACH CANDIDATE WILL HAVE TO BEAR AN EXTRA BURDEN. HE WILL HAVE TO WEAR A HEAVY AND SUFFOCATING BULLET-PROOF VEST. SUPPORTERS, PLEASE TAKE THAT INTO ACCOUNT.

7. A PUBLIC RALLY IN AN OPEN PLACE AT NIGHT CAN BE DEADLY FOR YOUR CANDIDATE. PLEASE EXCLUDE ANY SUCH RALLIES FROM YOUR PLANS.

8. SAY NO TO THE USE OF FIRECRACKERS AND POWDER KEGS DURING DEMONSTRATIONS. SUCH THINGS CONFUSE ESCORTS AND SECURITY CORPS.

9. SUPPORTERS, PLEASE UNDERSTAND THAT CROWDS WHO WANT TO SHAKE CANDIDATES' HANDS OR TOUCH THEM CAN BE DEADLY. ESCORTS SHOULD NOT ALLOW SUCH THINGS.

10. CANDIDATES WILL HAVE TO LIMIT THEIR WALKS IN PUBLIC PLACES AND REDUCE THEIR SOCIAL ACTIVITIES TO THE MINIMUM. CANDIDATES WILL VISIT THEIR FRIENDS AT UNUSUAL HOURS.

THIS IS HOW SECURITY WILL BE HANDLED FROM NOW ON. ALL THESE MEASURES HAVE TURNED CANDIDATES INTO MEN WITH LIMITATIONS. THEIR SUPPORTERS MUST UNDERSTAND THEIR CANDIDATES' SITUATION. CANDIDATES ARE MEN UNDER THE DICTATORSHIP OF THEIR GUARDIAN ANGELS WHO LOOK AFTER THEIR SAFETY IN TIMES OF RAGE.

DEV-MUC3-0375 (BBN)

NO CITY (ISRAEL), 25 AUG 89 -- [INTERVIEW WITH NETANYAHU BY FRIEDMAN AND DAN] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [FRIEDMAN] YOU MUST KNOW BETTER THAN I THAT THE ISRAELI GOVERNMENT ITSELF, AND NOT ONLY INDIVIDUAL ISRAELI NATIONALS, ARE ACCUSED OF MAKING SECURITY-RELATED DEALS WITH VARIOUS REGIMES WHICH -- TO THE CIVILIZED WESTERN WORLD, AT LEAST -- APPEAR TO BE OF QUESTIONABLE REPUTE. WHAT ARE THE CRITERIA THAT GUIDE ISRAEL'S ACTIONS AS A STATE AND WHEN ISSUING PERMITS TO PRIVATE COMPANIES TO MAKE DEALS WITH SUCH COUNTRIES?

[NETANYAHU] I WILL NOT GO INTO THE DETAILS OF THE VARIOUS CRITERIA DETERMINED BY THE DEFENSE MINISTRY, WHICH ARE OFTEN RELATED TO OUR OWN DEFENSE ISSUES. ONE CRITERION, HOWEVER, IS CLEAR: WE DO NOT ALLOW COOPERATION WITH ELEMENTS WHICH ARE NOT STATE-AFFILIATED, SUCH AS CARTELS, GROUPS, OR GANGS. ALL THESE ARE OFF LIMITS. THERE IS NO QUESTION ABOUT THAT, AND NO GREY AREAS. THEREFORE, IF THE REPORTS FROM COLOMBIA ARE TRUE, THE PEOPLE ACTED COUNTER TO OUR POLICY AND IN VIOLATION OF THE LAW.

[FRIEDMAN] WHAT ABOUT WORKING WITH OPPOSITION MOVEMENTS TO CERTAIN REGIMES?

[NETANYAHU] I REPEAT: STATE MOVEMENTS ONLY, OR, LET US SAY, STATE REGIMES. THIS IS OUR POLICY. ANY OTHER ACTION RUNS COUNTER TO OUR POLICY.

[DAN] WHEN ISRAELI INVOLVEMENT IN DRUG TRAFFICKING IN COLOMBIA IS MENTIONED, DO YOU KNOW THE NUMBER OF ISRAELIS REFERRED TO? PERHAPS THE STATEMENT IS EXAGGERATED, AND THERE ARE NO MORE THAN ONE OR TWO, PERHAPS THREE ISRAELIS?

[NETANYAHU] THAT IS A GOOD POINT; REPORTS ARE SO OFTEN BLOWN OUT OF PROPORTION. WE SEEM TO HAVE SOME KIND OF REPUTATION WHICH OFTEN LEADS TO EXAGGERATED AND FANTASTIC -- I DO NOT WISH TO USE THE TERM ROMANTIC -- REPORTS IN THIS CONTEXT. IN ANY EVENT, THERE ARE MANY REPORTS, AND WE WOULD LIKE TO GET TO THE CORE OF TRUTH BEHIND THEM. AFTER THAT, WE WILL DECIDE WHAT ACTION WE CAN TAKE. WE MAY TAKE LEGAL STEPS, TAKE AWAY PEOPLE'S PASSPORTS, AND RESORT TO OTHER METHODS.

[FRIEDMAN] IN THE PAST, MR NETANYAHU, YOU BELONGED TO AN ARMY UNIT IN WHICH OUR FINEST YOUNG PEOPLE SERVED. HAVE YOU FOUND FORMER ARMY FRIENDS IN ANY OF THE MENTIONED NAMES?

[NETANYAHU] NO, AND I HOPE NEVER TO FIND ANY.

[DAN] DO YOU UNDERSTAND THE PHENOMENON?

[NETANYAHU] IF IT EXISTS!

[FRIEDMAN] YES, IF IT EXISTS. OUR ENTIRE CONVERSATION IS SUBJECT TO THIS PROVISO, BECAUSE WE HAVE NO SOLID GROUNDS FOR DISCUSSION.

[NETANYAHU] IF IT EXISTS, I THINK IT REFLECTS THE MORAL CORRUPTION OF A FEW INDIVIDUALS. THE STATE CANNOT BE RESPONSIBLE FOR WHAT EACH OF ITS NATIONALS DOES OUTSIDE THE COUNTRY. THESE PEOPLE MAY HAVE SUCCUMBED TO MERCENARY OR OTHER TEMPTATIONS. THE EXPRESSION OF SELLING ONE'S SOUL TO THE DEVIL IS APPROPRIATE IN THEIR CASE.

[FRIEDMAN] DEPUTY FOREIGN MINISTER BINYAMIN NETANYAHU, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.

[NETANYAHU] THANK YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0376 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 25 AUG 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE SINISTER EXTRADITABLES GROUP TODAY THREATENED TO KILL 10 JUDGES FOR EVERY COLOMBIAN WHO IS EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES. THIS IS A WARNING TO THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO WHO HAS ANNOUNCED THAT INDIVIDUALS LINKED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING CAN BE EXTRADITED.

THE CLANDESTINE GROUP, WHICH EARLY THIS MORNING SET FIRE TO THE LLANO GRANDE COUNTRY CLUB IN RIONEGRO MUNICIPALITY, 40 KM NORTH OF MEDELLIN, SENT A LETTER TODAY TO OMAR GARCES, FIRST SUPERIOR COURT JUDGE OF CALI, INFORMING HIM OF THE THREAT TO KILL 10 JUDGES FOR EVERY PERSON EXTRADITED.

GARCES, WHO IS ALSO PRESIDENT OF THE ASSOCIATION OF JUDICIAL OFFICIALS IN VALLE DEL CAUCA DEPARTMENT, SAID THAT THE EXTRADITABLES SENT SEVERAL MESSAGES WITH THE THREAT TO VARIOUS JUDICIAL OFFICES IN THAT AREA OF THE COUNTRY, LOCATED 500 KM FROM BOGOTA.

AS A RESULT OF THE EXTRADITABLES' THREAT, THE JUDGES ARE HOLDING A MEETING TO WEIGH THE SITUATION AND DETERMINE THE VERACITY OF THE WARNING. HOWEVER, THEY DECIDED THEY WILL NOT STOP WORKING.

"THE TIME HAS COME TO UNITE AROUND THE COUNTRY'S FLAG TO RECOVER COLOMBIA'S DIGNITY AND TO PREVENT ITS BAD SONS FROM CONTINUING TO SHAME IT BEFORE THE WORLD," JUDGE GARCES SAID. HE ALSO ASKED FOR PROTECTION FOR HIMSELF AND THE OTHER JUDGES IN THAT AREA OF THE COUNTRY.

DEV-MUC3-0378 (BBN)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (TCS TELEVISION) -- [INTERVIEW WITH CRISTIANI BY KOBERG] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] WHEN MUCH TERRORIST VIOLENCE IS CREATED AND WHEN MUCH STREET VIOLENCE IS CREATED, EVERYONE IS ADVERSELY AFFECTED; WE BELIEVE THE ARMED FORCES HAVE AN OBLIGATION TO PREVENT THIS FROM HAPPENING. WE BELIEVE THAT WHEN IT PREVENTS VIOLENCE, IT IS DOING A MORE PROFESSIONAL JOB THAN IF IT ALLOWED IT TO TAKE PLACE, BECAUSE ONCE THE VIOLENCE GETS STARTED, THE CONSEQUENCES OF THEIR ACTIONS MAY BE A LOT MORE UNFORTUNATE. WE BELIEVE THAT THE POLICY OF TRYING TO PREVENT VIOLENT PLANS BEFORE THEY ARE CARRIED OUT IS SOMETHING THAT HAS PRODUCED GOOD RESULTS.

OF COURSE, THE PEOPLE SUSPECTED BY THE ARMED FORCES OF SUPPORTING THE FMLN PLANS ARE ARRESTED AND TURNED OVER TO THE JUDGE ONCE THE EVIDENCE IS GATHERED. I CAN TELL YOU THAT THIS IS VERY DIFFICULT. UNFORTUNATELY MANY OF THOSE WHO ARE ARRESTED ARE LATER RELEASED. MANY OF THEM TURN OUT TO BE INNOCENT BECAUSE SUSPICIONS MAY TURN OUT TO BE FALSE AND THE JUDGE IS THERE TO PREVENT MISTAKES FROM BEING COMMITTED. HOWEVER, THE ARMED FORCES ARE ACTING WITHIN A LEGAL FRAMEWORK.

THERE ARE CASES SUCH AS MR MASARIEGO. WHEN HE WAS RELEASED, IT WAS CONFIRMED THAT THERE WAS ABSOLUTELY NOTHING WRONG WITH HIM, AND WE HAVE HERE DOCUMENTS PROVING THAT. HOWEVER, HE TOURED THE UNITED STATES TO SHOW OFF HIS BURNT KNEE AND TO SAY THAT HE HAD BEEN TORTURED HERE IN EL SALVADOR. IT HAD BEEN PROVEN THAT THERE WAS ABSOLUTELY NOTHING WRONG WITH HIM WHEN HE WAS RELEASED. THE LEFT WANTS TO DISCREDIT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES ABROAD. HOWEVER, I DO NO BELIEVE THE LEFT HAS BEEN SUCCESSFUL.

[KOBERG] MR PRESIDENT, AN ANALYST WHO MET WITH US A SHORT TIME AGO GAVE HIS OPINION ON THE POSSIBILITY OF A DIALOGUE AND ITS RESULTS. HE WAS NOT VERY OPTIMISTIC AND HE SAID THAT THERE WERE SEVERAL POINTS THAT COULD BECOME OBSTACLES TO THE DIALOGUE. ONE OF THEM WAS THE ECONOMIC MEASURES. HE SAID THAT THE FMLN COULD NOT HOLD NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE GOVERNMENT AS LONG AS THE GOVERNMENT MAINTAINED THE ECONOMIC MEASURES IT WAS IMPLEMENTING. WE HAVE LEARNED FROM THE FMLN COMMUNIQUES, WHICH ALWAYS TALK ABOUT THE NEED TO KEEP IMPLEMENTING THE AGRARIAN REFORM PROCESS AND OTHER SERIES OF POINTS CONCERNING THE ECONOMIC MEASURES. I WOULD LIKE TO ASK YOU, WITHIN THIS FRAMEWORK, WHAT CAN THE GOVERNMENT NEGOTIATE OR WHAT DOES THE GOVERNMENT UNDERSTAND BY NEGOTIATION? COULD THERE BE POSSIBLE NEGOTIATION ON THE ECONOMIC POLICY?

[CRISTIANI] I BELIEVE THE WORD NEGOTIATION HERE IN OUR COUNTRY NO LONGER HAS THAT GENERIC MEANING GIVEN BY THE DICTIONARY. THIS WORD HAS BEEN MANIPULATED BY LEFTIST FORCES IN THE SENSE THAT TO NEGOTIATE IS TO ACCEPT WHAT THE FMLN WANTS. ACCORDING TO THE LEFT, THAT IS WHAT NEGOTIATING MEANS. I BELIEVE THE WORD NEGOTIATION HAS A GENERIC MEANING. A NEGOTIATION IS TO TRY TO FIND JOINT AGREEMENTS TO SOLVE A PROBLEM AND THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE BEEN PROPOSING. WE HAVE SOUGHT AGREEMENTS ON THE LARGEST NUMBER OF POINTS POSSIBLE. LOGICALLY, NOT ALL POINTS WILL BE ACCEPTED BY THE OTHER SIDE AND WE BELIEVE THE FMLN IS MAKING A MISTAKE WHEN IT THINKS IT WILL NEGOTIATE ITS ECONOMIC, POLITICAL, OR SOCIAL PLATFORM WITH THE GOVERNMENT. THE FMLN MUST UNDERSTAND THAT THEY HAVE TO NEGOTIATE THEIR PLANS FOR THE COUNTRY WITH THE PEOPLE. THAT IS DONE BY POLITICAL CAMPAIGNS AND BY SHOWING THEIR PROPOSALS TO THE PUBLIC. IF THE PEOPLE ARE CONVINCED THAT THEIR PROPOSALS ARE BEST, THEY WILL GET THE VOTES AND THEY WILL HAVE THE RIGHT TO IMPLEMENT THEIR PROGRAMS AND THEIR POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND SOCIAL PROGRAMS.

IN THIS CASE, UNFORTUNATELY THEY DID NOT PARTICIPATE; IT WAS OUR PARTY PLATFORM THAT WAS CHOSEN BY THE PEOPLE. THIS GIVES THE GOVERNMENT THE RIGHT TO IMPLEMENT WHAT THE MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE ASK OF THEM.

WE DO NOT THINK THE FMLN SHOULD OPPOSE THIS OFFERING. THE FMLN REFUSES TO TALK WITH THE GOVERNMENT AND KEEPS LOOKING FOR EXCUSES AND SETTING CONDITIONS, SUCH AS DEMANDING THAT THE GOVERNMENT DECLARE ITSELF TEMPORARY BEFORE ANY TALKS ARE CONSIDERED. THEY KNOW THEY ARE ASKING THE IMPOSSIBLE. THEIR TRUE PURPOSE IS TO REFUSE TO TALK SERIOUSLY, WHICH THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WANTS THEM TO DO. LORENA, I DO NOT THINK WE SHOULD CONFUSE THE VARIOUS FACTORS INVOLVED. HOLDING A DIALOGUE IS NOT EASY, AS POINTED OUT BY THIS ANALYST, WHOSE NAME I DO NOT KNOW. THE SITUATION IS NOT EASY TO RESOLVE. THIS PROCESS COULD WELL LAST MANY MONTHS OR EVEN YEARS. IT IS NECESSRY TO START NOW WITH A DIALOGUE IN WHICH BOTH SIDES BEGIN TO DISCUSS, NOT WHAT THEY CANNOT AGREE ON, BUT WHAT WE CAN AGREE ON. WE SHOULD BEGIN BY TRYING TO ELIMINATE THE VIOLENCE THAT PREVAILS IN THE COUNTRY. IF THEY FIND THEY CANNOT AGREE ON SOME OF THE GOVERNMENT PROPOSALS, THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD ALSO CONSIDER AN ALTERNATIVE STANCE. THE FMLN KEEPS SAYING THAT THERE ARE NO PROPER CONDITIONS FOR TALKING. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0379 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 25 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] LAST MINUTE REPORT: IN CONFUSING EVENTS, POLICE LIEUTENANT ALFREDO CORREA AND ONE PRIVATE WERE KILLED IN VALLE DEPARTMENT. NO FURTHER INFORMATION ON THIS INCIDENT HAS BEEN MADE AVAILABLE, OTHER THAN THAT AUTHORITIES ARE INVESTIGATING THE EVENT.

IT HAS ALSO BEEN REPORTED THAT 10TH ARMY BRIGADE MEMBERS FOUND AND CONFISCATED 2 METRIC TONS OF HIGH-GRADE COCAINE AT LA MONEDA FARM IN LECHI, CAUCASIA, AT THE BORDER BETWEEN ANTIOQUIA AND CORDOBA DEPARTMENTS. THE DRUG WAS FOUND IN SEALED WATERPROOF PACKAGES IN UNDERGROUND TUNNELS. THIS MAKES AUTHORITIES BELIEVE THE DRUG WAS READY TO BE AIR DROPPED OVER THE SEA TO BE PICKED UP BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS. IN ADDITION, A LARGE NUMBER OF ARMS, A SIZABLE AMOUNT OF AMMUNITION, AS WELL AS AUTOMOBILES AND RADIO SETS WERE CONFISCATED. THE DRUG WAS SET ON FIRE IN THE PRESENCE OF JUDGES AND MILITARY AUTHORITIES. A CLANDESTINE LANDING STRIP WAS ALSO DESTROYED.

ARSON SEEMS TO BE THE NEW CRIMINAL STYLE USED IN ANTIOQUIA. IN LESS THAN 24 HOURS, FOUR FARMS HAVE BEEN SET ON FIRE. THREE OF THESE FARMS, LOCATED NEAR MEDELLIN, ARE OWNED BY POLITICAL AND INDUSTRIAL LEADERS EDGAR GUTIERREZ CASTRO, IGNACIO VELEZ ESCOBAR, AND AUGUSTO LOPEZ. THE MOST RECENT OF THESE INCIDENTS OCCURRED AT THE LLANO GRANDE COUNTRY CLUB EARLY THIS MORNING. SEVERAL ARMED MEN SHOWED UP AT THE SITE AND SET THE CLUB ON FIRE AFTER THREATENING AND BEATING UP THE WATCHMEN. THE AMOUNT OF THE LOSSES HAS NOT YET BEEN DETERMINED. THE MANAGER DID NOT ALLOW REPORTERS INTO THE PLACE. IT WAS REPORTED, HOWEVER, THAT THE ATTACKERS IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES AS EXTRADITABLES WHO SAID THE ACTION WAS BEING TAKEN IN REPRISAL FOR THE GOVERNMENT ACTIONS AGAINST THEM. THE ARMED MEN LEFT THE PLACE SHOUTING THAT THEIR REACTION HAS JUST BEGUN AND THAT THEIR STRUGGLE WILL CONTINUE. FURTHER DAMAGE TO THE CLUB AND THE LOSS OF HUMAN LIFE WERE PREVENTED BY WORKERS WHO REACTED PROMPTLY.

THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN MEASURES TO COUNTERACT THESE ACTIONS. THE ARMY THIS AFTERNOON WILL RECEIVE THE INITIAL U.S. TACTICAL SUPPORT AS PART OF THE NEW ANTITERRORIST OFFENSIVE, GOVERNMENT SOURCES HAVE REPORTED. U.S. MILITARY CARGO PLANES WILL FLY TO COLOMBIA ARMED TWIN-TURBINE BELL-212 HELICOPTERS. IN ADDITION, THE PENTAGON WILL SHIP RADIO COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT. THE HELICOPTERS WILL BE FLOWN BY COLOMBIAN MILITARY CREWS, U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT SOURCES SAID IN WASHINGTON. FOR THE TIME BEING, BOTH GEORGE BUSH'S ADMINISTRATION AND VIRGILIO BARCO'S GOVERNMENT ARE NOT CONSIDERING THE PRESENCE OF U.S. MILITARY MEN IN COLOMBIA.

OVER THE PAST 72 HOURS, THE ARMY RAIDED FIVE FARMS, ONE HOME, AND A BAR-RESTAURANT OWNED BY GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, CAMILO ZAPATA, AND PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA. THE RAIDS WERE CONDUCTED BY 13TH BRIGADE TROOPS IN CHIA, PACHO, AND BOGOTA. THIS FARM, KNOWN AS EL CASTILLO DE MARROQUIN, OWNED BY ZAPATA AND ESTIMATED TO BE WORTH MORE THAN 100 BILLION PESOS, WAS RAIDED ON WEDNESDAY AFTERNOON. ACCORDING TO THE ARMY, THIS VERITABLE FORTRESS, LOCATED ON THE EL COMUN BRIDGE, WAS MANAGED BY RETIRED POLICE MAJOR ALVARO TOVAR TOVAR. LUXURIOUS CARS, A GOLD-ORNAMENTED CHAPEL, A SWIMMING POOL FITTED WITH A HEATING SYSTEM, 15 STABLES WITH FINE HORSES, A TENNIS COURT, AND THE IMPRESSIVE CASTLE ALL MAKE UP A FARM WORTH MILLIONS. EXTENSIVE GARDENS, LONG TRAILS, AND AN ATTRACTIVE LAKE COMPLEMENT THE WONDERFUL NATURAL LANDSCAPE OF THE REAL ESTATE RIGHT BY THE BOGOTA NORTHERN FREEWAY. THERE ARE EXOTIC ADORNMENTS ON THE WALLS. FOR INSTANCE, THERE IS A BOTERO PAINTING WORTH 4 MILLION PESOS. IN ONE ROOM, THERE WERE MANY ELECTRIC APPLIANCES AND A FULL RADIO COMMUNICATIONS SET. THE EXORBITANT WEALTH IS INDICATED BY EVEN A WITCHCRAFT ROOM. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0381 (BBN)

CLANDESTINE, 25 AUG 89 (RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THIS IS RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI REPORTING A NEW HONDURAN ARMY RAID INTO SALVADORAN TERRITORY. WE ALSO ALERT THE HONDURAN PEOPLE AND THE CENTRAL AMERICAN COMMUNITY TO THIS INCURSION. HONDURAN PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA HOYO HAS VIOLATED THE TELA AGREEMENTS.

AT 1400 ON 24 AUGUST, A HONDURAN ARMY PATROL ENTERED 3 KM INSIDE SALVADORAN TERRITORY AT EL MONO HAMLET IN NAHUATERIQUE JURISDICTION, MORAZAN DEPARTMENT. A FEW DAYS AGO, OTHER SALVADORAN ARMY PATROLS ENTERED LAS ARADAS HAMLET IN NAHUATERIQUE. WE REMIND YOU THAT IN THE PAST FEW DAYS WE HAVE BEEN REPORTING THESE RAIDS BY HONDURAN TROOPS IN LAS FILAS BORDER AREA IN WESTERN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT. THERE HAVE ALSO BEEN RAIDS IN ARCATAO, WHERE HONDURAN TROOPS HAVE RANSACKED SCHOOLS, THREATENED TEACHERS, REPRESSED AREA RESIDENTS, SET FIRES, STOLE VILLAGERS' PROPERTY, AND KIDNAPPED SOME CITIZENS.

WE REPEAT OUR WARNING TO THE HONDURAN TROOPS, ESPECIALLY TO THE HONDURAN ARMY HIGH COMMAND AND GOVERNMENT. WE WILL NOT PERMIT MORE RAIDS AND OUTRAGES AGAINST CIVILIANS IN OUR TERRITORY. [WORDS INDISTINCT] OUR UNITS WILL ATTACK THE HONDURAN TROOPS. AZCONA HOYO, YOU HAVE BEEN WARNED. WE URGE THE HONDURAN PEOPLE TO TAKE ACTION AND DEMAND RESPECT FOR SALVADORAN SOVEREIGNTY BECAUSE THIS MEDDLING BY THE HONDURAN ARMY AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN OUR CONFLICT IS OUR CONCERN [WORDS INDISTINCT]. HONDURAN TROOPS, IN COMPLICITY WITH THE SALVADORAN ARMY, CARRY OUT ALL SORTS OF OUTRAGES.

DEV-MUC3-0384 (BBN)

BRIDGETOWN (BARBADOS), 24 AUG 89 (CANA) -- [TEXT] WASHINGTON, D.C.--THE BAHAMAS GOVERNMENT IS SUPPORTING COLOMBIA'S FIGHT ON ILLEGAL DRUG TRAFFICKING. "THERE ARE LESSONS TO BE LEARNED FROM THE RECENT EVENTS IN COLOMBIA. WE APPLAUD THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT FOR THE BOLD STEPS HE IS TAKING, BUT WE MUST SHOW THE CARTELS THAT HE IS NOT ALONE," BAHAMAS' FOREIGN MINISTER CHARLES CARTER SAID.

THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS STEPPED UP THE FIGHT AGAINST THE TRAFFICKERS FOLLOWING THE KILLING OF A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE. CARTER SAID THAT "ALL OF US IN THIS HEMISPHERE" MUST SHOW THE DRUG DEALERS THEY ARE "PART OF THE WAR".

THE BAHAMAS WANTS TO HOST A MEETING THIS YEAR OF LEADERS OF THE HEMISPHERE TO DEFINE A COMPREHENSIVE STRATEGY FOR WAGING AN ALL OUT WAR ON THE PRODUCTION, PROCESSING, SHIPMENT, DISTRIBUTION AND USE OF ILLEGAL DRUGS. CARTER TOLD CANA THAT RECENT EVENTS IN COLOMBIA DEMONSTRATED THE NEED FOR A WELL PLANNED, COORDINATED AND IMPLEMENTED PROGRAM WHICH WOULD TACKLE ALL ASPECTS OF THE DRUG PROBLEM. HE SAID HIS COUNTRY HOPED SUCH A SUMMIT COULD BE HELD BEFORE THE END OF THIS YEAR.

THE FOREIGN MINISTER TOLD CANA THAT HIS COUNTRY HAD INDICATED TO THE UNITED STATES IN JANUARY A WILLINGNESS TO HOST THE SUMMIT BUT, TO DATE, THERE WAS NO RESPONSE FROM THE UNITED STATES ADMINISTRATION. "WE DISCUSSED THE IDEA OF THE SUMMIT AT THE CARICOM (CARIBBEAN COMMUNITY) FOREIGN MINISTERS MEETING, THE HEADS OF GOVERNMENT MEETING, AT THE ORGANIZATION OF AMERICAN STATES (OAS) AND WE INFORMED THE UNITED STATES BY DIPLOMATIC NOTE IN JANUARY OF OUR DESIRE TO HOST THE MEETING BUT SO FAR THE UNITED STATES HAS NOT RESPONDED. WHETHER WE WOULD ULTIMATELY GO AHEAD WITH IT I'M NOT SURE," CARTER EXPLAINED.

CARTER WAS AGAINST USING UNITED STATES TROOPS IN LATIN AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN IN THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUGS, POINT OUT THAT "THE DEMOCRATIC TRADITIONS IN SOME OF OUR COUNTRIES WOULD BE THREATENED IF WE WERE TO RESORT TO THE USE OF FORCE." HE SAID ARRANGEMENTS SUCH AS ONE BETWEEN HIS COUNTRY AND THE UNITED STATES FOR JOINT POLICING COULD EXTENDED TO INVOLVE OTHER COUNTRIES IN THE HEMISPHERE.

THE FOREIGN MINISTER SAID THAT THREE QUARTERS OF THE DRUGS PRODUCED ARE CONSUMED IN NORTH AMERICA. "WE ARE NOT THE MARKETS. COUNTRIES LIKE THE BAHAMAS, JAMAICA, TRINIDAD, CUBA AND BARBADOS ARE ONLY USED BY THE DRUG LORDS TO REACH THE 3 BILLION DOLLAR UNITED STATES MARKET," HE REMARKED. "WE AREN'T REALLY THE TARGET AND THEREFORE WE MUST FOCUS ON THE QUESTION OF DEMAND. AND WE IN CARICOM, AND SPECIFICALLY IN THE BAHAMAS, ARE READY TO BE PART OF THE SOLUTION TO THE UNITED STATES DRUG PROBLEM."

CARTER SAID AMONG THE BENEFITS OF SUCH A SUMMIT WOULD BE "A JUDICIAL ATMOSPHERE" THAT WOULD LET THE DRUG BARONS, DEALERS AND USERS "KNOW THAT THEY ARE CRIMINALS WHEREVER THEY ARE OR WHEREVER THEY GO."

DEV-MUC3-0385 (BBN)

HAVANA (CUBA), 22 AUG 89 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [COMMENTARY] [MANOLO ORTEGA] [TEXT] THE FULL SCOPE OF THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE AND DEATH THAT HAS SWAMPED COLOMBIA OVER THE PAST SEVERAL YEARS IS NOW BEGINNING TO BE ASSESSED. LATIN AMERICA AND OTHER PARTS OF THE WORLD HAVE REMAINED ON THE SIDELINES OF THAT SOUTH AMERICAN COUNTRY'S DOMESTIC STRIFE, WHERE HUMAN LIFE IS ALMOST WORTHLESS. VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ HIT THE NAIL ON THE HEAD WHEN HE TOLD COLOMBIAN RADIO CARACOL THAT WE MAY NOT BE DOING WHAT WE MUST CONCERNING CURRENT DEVELOPMENTS IN COLOMBIA. CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ IS CONCERNED THAT SOME NATIONS MAY BE GETTING USED TO LIVNG IN A CLIMATE OF COLLECTIVE INTIMIDATION.

DAILY EVENTS OCCUR IN COLOMBIA AMID A CLIMATE OF NATIONAL UNCERTAINTY. BANDS OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE BUILT AN EMPIRE OF DIRTY MONEY AND BLOODTHIRSTY MAFIAS IN DEATHLY COMPLICITY WITH THE MILITARY DEPLOYMENT OF 140 PARAMILITARY GROUPS. YEARS AGO, WHEN THESE GROUPS ANNOUNCED THEIR GUNS WERE AIMED AT PROGRESSIVE AND LEFTIST PERSONALITIES, THEY OPERATED WITH THE UNSPOKEN COMPLICITY OF MANY SECTORS, INCLUDING THE GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, FOR SOME TIME NOW, THE MURDER VICTIMS HAVE BEEN LEFTISTS, LIBERALS, CONSERVATIVES, AND EVEN POLITICALLY INDEPENDENT PERSONS WHO OPPOSE THE CHAOS CREATED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS, LANDOWNERS, SOME OFFICERS, AND PARAMILITARY GROUPS. LUIS CARLOS GALAN, 46, PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL, LIBERAL SENATOR, LAWYER, AND NEWSMEN IS THE LATEST VICTIM OF THIS DEATHLY SPIRIAL. HIS REMAINS [29-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] LUIS CARLOS GALAN. DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE SHOWN THEIR HIT LIST IS NEVERENDING. THEY ALSO BRING TO THE FORE THE POWER AND SCOPE OF THE DIRTY WAR THESE PEOPLE BEGAN IN THE COUNTRY AMID THE GOVERNMENT'S INACTION.

MANY WONDER HOW THE PARAMILITARY TOP COMMAND CAN GO UNPUNISHED, CONSIDERING THAT ITS CHIEF LEADERS HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED, BECAUSE MORE OFTEN THAN NOT THE KILLERS DO VERY LITTLE TO COVER THEIR TRACKS. LOOKING AHEAD, THE COLOMBIAN ELECTORAL PROCESS THAT WILL CONCLUDE IN NEXT YEAR'S ELECTIONS HAS BEEN DEALT A HEAVY BLOW WITH GALAN'S MURDER. THE REMAINING PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES WILL HAVE TO CONDUCT THEIR POLITICAL CAMPAIGN SURROUNDED BY ARMIES OF BODYGUARDS, AN ARRANGEMENT WIDELY USED IN COLOMBIA BY POLITICIANS, LABOR LEADERS, JUDGES, ARTISTS, AND MINOR OFFICIALS. PERPLEXITY OVER WHAT HAPPENED IN COLOMBIA IS ONE OF THE INITIAL REACTIONS IN LATIN AMERICA. LUIS CARLOS GALAN'S MURDER ALSO CALLS FOR CONDEMNATION. PERHAPS IN THE FUTURE IT MAY HELP MAKE THE CONTINENT MEDITATE ON WHETHER OR NOT IT IS ADVISABLE TO BE INDIFFERENT TO THE COLLECTIVE INTIMIDATION THAT PREVAILS IN COLOMBIA.

DEV-MUC3-0388 (BBN)

CLANDESTINE, 27 AUG 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] 1. ON SUNDAY 20 AUGUST, EIGHT FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] DISABLED WAR COMRADES OCCUPIED THE [SAN SALVADOR METROPOLITAN] CATHEDRAL, WHERE THEY REMAIN STILL TO PROTEST THE VIOLATIONS BY THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] GOVERNMENT OF INTERNATIONAL LAW AS WELL AS NON-COMPLIANCE TO THE COMMITMENTS MADE WHEN THE RELEASE AND EXCHANGE OF COLONEL [OMAR NAPOLEON] AVALOS WAS NEGOTIATED IN PANAMA [IN 1987].

2. THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND GREETS THE DISABLED COMRADES AND CONGRATULATES THEM ON DEMANDING THAT THEY BE ALLOWED TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY AND OBTAIN ADEQUATE MEDICAL ATTENTION. THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND ALSO CALLS ON THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO OFFER SOLIDARITY AND SUPPORT FOR THE JUST DEMANDS OF THE WAR DISABLED. WE RECOGNIZE AND ENCOURAGE THE HUMANITARIAN ASSISTANCE THAT MSGR ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS IS GIVING IN FINDING A JUST SOLUTION TO THIS PROBLEM DESPITE THE GOVERNMENT HINDERING HIS WORK AS A MEDIATOR IN SOLVING THE CONFLICT.

3. ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS, THE ARMED FORCES HAS ASSAULTED FMLN HOSPITALS, CAPTURED, TORTURED, AND MURDERED MEDICAL STAFF AND PATIENTS. ALSO, THEY HAVE CAPTURED, TORTURED, AND MURDERED DISABLED PERSONS IN VARIOUS CIRCUMSTANCES. THIS BEHAVIOR IS IN SHARP CONTRAST WITH THE FMLN'S STRICT RESPECT FOR THE HOSPITALS, MEDICAL STAFF, AS WELL AS THE ARMED FORCES' DISABLED AND WOUNDED PERSONNEL, ALTHOUGH THEY ARE VULNERABLE TARGETS OF OUR ACTIONS. THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND REITERATES THIS POLICY OF PRINCIPLES AND DEMANDS THE SAME BEHAVIOR FROM THE ARMED FORCES.

4. FOLLOWING THE OCCUPATION OF THE CATHEDRAL BY THE DISABLED, [PRESIDENT ALFREDO] CRISTIANI IS TRYING TO MAKE THE CASE AN OBJECT OF NEGOTIATION, DEMANDING CERTAIN ACTIONS OF THE FMLN. THIS ATTITUDE BY THE ARENA GOVERNMENT MIGHT MAKE THE PROBLEM MORE COMPLEX AND MAKE US REVERT TO CIRCUMSTANCES WE HAD ALREADY SURPASSED. THE DEPARTURE FROM THE COUNTRY OF THE DISABLED IS A RIGHT THAT THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD RESPECT, AND THIS CANNOT BE CONSIDERED AN ISSUE THAT CAN BE USED FOR NEGOTIATIONS OR BLACKMAIL.

WE ARE SURE THAT THIS JUST DEMAND WHICH HAS LED THE DISABLED COMRADES TO STAY AT THE CATHEDRAL UNTIL THEY AND THEIR COMRADES CAN LEAVE THE COUNTRY WILL BE SUPPORTED BY ALL OF OUR PEOPLE, WHILE INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY WILL LEAVE IT CLEARLY ESTABLISHED THAT CRISTIANI, ARENA, AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE ACTING IN AN UNJUST AND INCORRECT MANNER. [SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, 26 AUGUST 1989.

DEV-MUC3-0389 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 28 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [GLADYS VARGAS] [TEXT] TERRORISM CONTINUES IN MEDELLIN. THE METROPOLITAN POLICE THIS MORNING DEFUSED FIVE BOMBS AND ARRESTED FIVE SUSPECTS. DURING THE OPERATION, THE POLICE RECOVERED SEWING MACHINES [MAQUINAS DE CORSAR] WORTH 25 MILLION PESOS. A VEHICLE AND A MOTORCYCLE WERE CONFISCATED.

FOUR POLICE AGENTS FROM THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] BOYACA COMMAND KIDNAPPED BY THE SO-CALLED ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION [ELN] WERE RELEASED ON 27 AUGUST AT 1800 IN GRENADA, EASTERN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT. THE POLICE AGENTS WERE KIDNAPPED ON 14 AUGUST. POLICE AGENTS JESUS BERNARDO BUSTOS, MIGUEL ANGEL GARCIA, JAIRO VARGAS, AND ESTEBAN GALVIZ WERE RETURNING TO TAMA AFTER PARTICIPATING IN THE NATIONAL POLICE ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATIONS WHEN THEY WERE KIDNAPPED ON THE MEDELLIN-BOGOTA HIGHWAY.

THE RELEASED POLICEMEN HAVE NOT SPOKEN TO THEIR SUPERIORS YET AND THEREFORE COULD NOT TALK TO THE MEDIA. THE ELN REPORTED THAT IT TREATED THE POLICEMEN WELL AND THAT THIS RELEASE IS AN ACTION IN FAVOR OF A MORE HUMANIZED WAR, WHICH IS A SLOGAN THESE GUERRILLAS HAVE PROCLAIMED IN THE PAST 5 YEARS. SHORTLY BEFORE THE RELEASE OF THESE POLICEMEN, THE ELN KIDNAPPED ELIECER DE JESUS ACEVEDO OLARTE, THE MAYOR OF ZARAGOZA MUNICIPALITY, IN ANTOQUIA DEPARTMENT.

DEV-MUC3-0391 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 28 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] COMBINED ARMY AND POLICE FORCES HAVE RAIDED AN OFFICE IN DOWNTOWN BOGOTA THAT APPARENTLY SERVED AS THE "FINANCIAL HEADQUARTERS" OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKING GROUP HEADED BY GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, THE SECOND MOST IMPORTANT MEDELLIN CARTEL BOSS. THIS ANNOUNCEMENT WAS MADE TODAY BY THE COLOMBIAN DEFENSE MINISTRY.

IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT THE AUTHORITIES DISCOVERED THE NUMBERS OF THE BANK ACCOUNTS THE DRUG TRAFFICKER HAS IN COLOMBIA AND ABROAD. THE AUTHORITIES CONFISCATED 30 SOPHISTICATED COMPUTERS, TELEFAX, AND OTHER ELECTRONIC EQUIPMENT. THIS HAS BEEN ANOTHER SEVERE SETBACK FOR RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ONE OF THE MAFIA BOSSES MOST WANTED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.

RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALIAS THE MEXICAN, IS CONSIDERED TO BE THE RIGHT-HAND MAN OF PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, THE MEDELLIN CARTEL'S TOP BOSS. GACHA'S GROUP HAS SUFFERED MANY LOSSES DUE TO THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE GOVERNMENT AGAINST COCAINE TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATIONS OPERATING IN COLOMBIA. OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS, ELITE ARMY TROOPS HAVE SEIZED SEVERAL LARGE FARMS OWNED BY RODRIGUEZ GACHA IN THE TOWN OF PACHO, AS WELL AS LUXURIOUS RESIDENCES IN BOGOTA. A SON OF RODRIGUEZ GACHA, FREDDY RODRIGUEZ CELADES, AND THE GROUP'S "CHIEF OF FINANCES," FERNANDO GALEANO BERRIO--WHO IS WANTED BY THE U.S. AUTHORITIES--ARE BEING HELD BY COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES.

HOWEVER, DESPITE THE "WAR" THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECLARED ON THE DRUG TRAFFICKING GANGS, A SUPERIOR COURT HAS REVOKED A WARRANT FOR THE ARREST OF ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, RODRIGUEZ GACHA, AND OTHER PERSONS LINKED TO MASSACRES CARRIED OUT BY RIGHTIST MILITARY GROUPS BEING TRAINED BY ISRAELI, BRITISH, U.S., AND WEST GERMAN MERCENARIES, ACCORDING TO THE INVESTIGATIONS.

THE RULING WAS MADE KNOWN YESTERDAY. TODAY THE COUNTRY IS STILL AMAZED, CONSIDERING THAT THERE IS ENOUGH EVIDENCE TO PROVE THAT THE MAFIA LEADERS MASTERMINDED THE MASSACRES, AS REPORTED BY JUSTICE MARIA ELENA DIAZ, WHO WAS SHOT TO DEATH LAST MONTH, EVIDENTLY AS A REPRISAL FOR HAVING STATED THIS OPINION.

THE ARREST WARRANT ALSO INCLUDED LUIS RUBIO ROJAS, A FORMER MAYOR OF THE TOWN OF PUERTO BOYACA, AN OPERATIONS CENTER OF RIGHTIST PARAMILITARY ELEMENTS, AND SEVERAL ARMY DETACHMENT ELEMENTS WHO REPORTEDLY PROMOTE TERRORIST SQUADRONS.

IT HAS BEEN FULLY ESTABLISHED THAT ARMED ULTRA-RIGHTIST GROUPS HAVE BEEN TRAINED BY FOREIGN MERCENARIES, INCLUDING JAIR KLEIN, A FORMER ISRAELI ARMY COLONEL WHO COMMANDED HIS COUNTRY'S ANTITERRORIST CORPS SEVERAL YEARS AGO.

DEV-MUC3-0393 (BBN)

MOSCOW (USSR), 28 AUG 89 -- [TEXT] IN VIEW OF THE RECENT INCIDENTS AT TOBALABA AIRPORT, THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF CHILE [PCCH] HAS ISSUED THE FOLLOWING COMMUNIQUE:

THE DICTATORSHIP INTENDS TO USE STILL UNCLEAR INCIDENTS THAT TOOK PLACE A FEW DAYS AGO AT TOBALABA AIRPORT TO CREATE A CLIMATE OF PROVOCATION AND ALARM WITH THE PURPOSE OF DISRUPTING THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE POLITICAL PROCESS THAT SHOULD LEAD TO A DEMOCRATIC VICTORY ON 14 DECEMBER.

PINOCHET'S OPEN INTERVENTION IN THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE ELECTORAL PROCESS REMAINED CLEAR IN HIS 23 AUGUST SPEECH AND WAS RECENTLY DENOUNCED BY OPPOSITION LEADER PATRICIO AYLWIN AND BY ALL OPPOSITION POLITICAL FORCES.

THE DECLARATION ISSUED BY THE NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER, CNI -- AN ORGANIZATION THAT FOR MANY YEARS HAS SHAMEFULLY VIOLATED THE MOST BASIC RIGHTS OF THE CHILEAN PEOPLE BY USING THE MOST CRUEL AND INHUMAN FORMS OF TERROR AND VIOLENCE AGAINST CHILEAN DEMOCRATS AND WHOSE DISSOLUTION HAS BEEN PROPOSED EVEN BY THE GOVERNMENT'S CANDIDATE HERNAN BUCHI -- INTENDS TO MISGUIDE THE PEOPLE BY ONCE AGAIN TRYING TO IMPLICATE THE PCCH IN AN INCIDENT IN WHICH IT HAD NO PARTICIPATION WHATSOEVER.

THE CNI DECLARATION, EXPRESSLY ORDERED BY AUTHORITIES OF THE REGIME, GOES TO THE EXTREME OF INFAMOUSLY MANIPULATING FAMILY TIES TO ATTACK OUR GENERAL SECRETARY, COMRADE VOLODIA TEITELBOIM.

THE REGIME SEEKS TO CREATE A CLIMATE OF TERROR AND INTIMIDATION IN ORDER TO IMPOSE THE ANTIDEMOCRATIC DEMANDS RECENTLY MADE BY PINOCHET.

TO THIS END, AND AS PINOCHET HIMSELF HAS STATED, THE REGIME IS WILLING EVEN TO RESORT TO FORCE ONCE AGAIN. PART OF THIS PLAN IS THE MURDER OF LUIS VARGAS, WHO WAS ARRESTED AND TORTURED BY THE CNI AND LATER THROWN OUT OF A FIFTH- FLOOR WINDOW OF THE MILITARY COURT BUILDING AFTER BEING FALSELY CHARGED WITH HAVING AN ARSENAL IN HIS HOME; THE SCANDALOUS COURT DECISION THAT LEAVES UNPUNISHED THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE INHUMAN DEATH OF RODRIGO ROJAS DENEGRI AND THE SERIOUS INJURY OF CARMEN GLORIA QUINTANA; THE SHAMEFUL SUPREME COURT DECISION CLEARING THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE HORRIBLE CRIMES AGAINST 10 CHILEANS IN LATE 1976; THE REGIME'S INTENTION TO IMPOSE A NEW AMNESTY LAW TO LEAVE THOUSANDS OF CASES OF VIOLATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS IN THE PAST 16 YEARS UNPUNISHED; THE ARREST AND INCOMMUNICADO DETENTION OF 13 PEOPLE, AMONG THEM A PREGNANT WOMAN ALLEGEDLY INVOLVED IN THE INCIDENTS AT THE TOBALABA AIRPORT AND FOR WHOSE PHYSICAL AND PSYCHOLOGICAL INTEGRITY WE FEAR.

THIS IS THE CONSEQUENCE OF PINOCHET, THE CNI, AND THE CIRCLES CLOSE TO THE DICTATORSHIP'S DESPAIR IN VIEW OF THE PROGRESS MADE BY THE DEMOCRATIC STRUGGLE AND THE GROWING UNITY OF ALL OPOSITION FORCES AROUND A SINGLE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE AND A COMMON PLATFORM DESIGNED TO DEMOCRATIZE THE COUNTRY.

AS ALWAYS WHEN IT FEELS THREATENED, THE DICTATORSHIP HAS DECIDED TO DIVIDE AND CONFUSE THE OPPOSITION FORCES.

WE APPEAL TO ALL DEMOCRATS TO COME TOGETHER EVEN MORE FIRMLY SO THE LEVEL OF UNITY ACHIEVED BY THE OPPOSITION SECTOR WILL NOT ALLOW SUCH MANEUVERS TO JEOPARDIZE THE RESOLUTE PROGRESS TOWARD THE MUCH DESIRED DEMOCRACY AND FREEDOM FOR OUR PEOPLE.

WE ALSO URGE THAT THIS PROVOCATION BE DENOUNCED BY DOUBLING EFFORTS TO OVERWHELMINGLY DEFEAT THE DICTATORSHIP ON 14 DECEMBER, THUS TAKING A DECISIVE STEP IN THE STRUGGLE TO DEFINITIVELY OUST THIS REGIME OF HATRED, DEATH, AND PAIN.

SIGNED: AMERICO ZORRILLA, JAIME INSUNZA, AND CARLOS MOLINAS FOR THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF CHILE.

DEV-MUC3-0394 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 29 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] SEVEN POWERFUL BOMBS WERE SET OFF IN BOGOTA AND MEDELLIN EARLY THIS MORNING IN WHAT SEEMS TO BE THE CONTINUATION OF THE "WAR" DECLARED BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN REPRISAL FOR THE MAJOR BLOWS THEY HAVE BEEN DEALT BY THE AUTHORITIES IN VARIOUS AREAS OF COLOMBIA.

ACCORDING TO THE INITIAL POLICE REPORTS, SIX BOMBS EXPLODED IN MEDELLIN, THE COUNTRY'S SECOND-LARGEST CITY, WHERE THE RESPONSE FROM THE DRUG DEALERS HAS BEEN MORE STRONGLY FELT IN RECENT DAYS.

THE BOMBS WERE PLACED IN LIQUOR STORES WHERE, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL ESTIMATES, THE DAMAGE IS EXTENSIVE.

MEDELLIN WAS THE FIRST CITY HIT BY THE DRUG CARTEL'S "COUNTERATTACK" AFTER THE SO-CALLED "EXTRADITABLES" ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE IN WHICH THEY VOWED TO WAGE A "WAR" ON THE GOVERNMENT, JUDGES, BUSINESSMEN, AND JOURNALISTS NATIONWIDE. THE EXTRADITABLES ARE DRUG TRAFFICKERS SOUGHT BY U.S. COURTS.

ON SUNDAY, NINE BOMBS EXPLODED AND COMPLETELY DESTROYED SEVERAL STATE-OWNED BANKS.

MEANWHILE, ANOTHER BOMB EXPLODED IN BOGOTA IN FRONT OF A TRAVEL AGENCY, BUT THE EXTENT OF THE DAMAGE HAS YET TO BE REPORTED.

THE INTENSE OFFENSIVE BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO'S ADMINISTRATION BEGAN 2 WEEKS AGO IN THE WAKE OF A NUMBER OF CRIMINAL ATTACKS THAT CLAIMED THE LIVES OF PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL LUIS CARLOS GALAN, A HIGH-RANKING POLICE OFFICER, AND A JUDGE.

THE POLICE REPORTED TODAY THAT FOR THE FIRST TIME, COMBINED ARMY AND POLICE FORCES RAIDED SEVERAL PROPERTIES OWNED BY HERNANDO SUAREZ BURGOS, [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE RULING LIBERAL PARTY, IN SOUTHWESTERN NARINO DEPARTMENT.

UNITS OF THE ELITE FORCES, THE MAIN ONES INVOLVED IN THE OPERATIONS, ALSO RAIDED THE PRIVATE RESIDENCE OF BUSINESSMAN EDGARDO BARROS, PRESIDENT OF THE SPORTING SOCCER CLUB OF CALI.

POLICE SPOKESMEN ALSO REPORTED TODAY THAT MORE THAN 7,000 PEOPLE WHO HAD BEEN ARRESTED SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE OFFENSIVE WERE RELEASED WHEN IT WAS FULLY PROVEN THEY HAD NO LINKS WITH THE DRUG MAFIAS.

MEANWHILE, APPROXIMATELY 4,000 PEOPLE REMAIN IN CUSTODY AWAITING JUDICIAL RULINGS.

DEV-MUC3-0396 (BBN)

JERUSALEM (ISRAEL), 29 AUG 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH ENERGY AND INFRASTRUCTURE MINISTER MOSHE SHAHAL BY HAYIM HECHT] [EXCERPT] BEFORE ADDRESSING THE ISSUE OF COLOMBIA, MINISTER SHAHAL POINTED OUT: I DO NOT KNOW ABOUT ANY CARTELS IN COLOMBIA, NOR DID I MEET ANY CATTLE BREEDERS [REFERENCE TO THE PROFESSION CLAIMED [BEGIN RECORDING] [SHAHAL] WE HAVE AN EXCELLENT RELATIONSHIP WITH COLOMBIA IN SEVERAL VERY CONCRETE SPHERES. THESE INCLUDE THE PURCHASE OF COAL, FOR WHICH WE SIGNED A 4-YEAR CONTRACT DURING MY VISIT THERE ABOUT A YEAR AGO. THAT CONTRACT HAS BEEN FULFILLED TO THE SATISFACTION OF BOTH SIDES. THE COLOMBIAN COAL IS EXCELLENT, AS IS THE PRICE WE PAY FOR IT. WE ARE A VERY GOOD CUSTOMER, AND THE RELATIONS BETWEEN US ARE VERY CLOSE. [END RECORDING]

BY THE WAY, THE TRADE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES WAS FORMULATED BY THE LADY IN THE NEWS, MONICA DE GREIFF, WHO WAS THE ENERGY MINISTRY DIRECTOR GENERAL DURING MINISTER SHAHAL'S VISIT TO COLUMBIA. AT PRESENT SHE IS BOGOTA'S JUSTICE MINISTER, AND IS HIDING IN THE UNITED STATES FROM THE DRUG CARTEL'S ASSASSINATION THREATS.

MINISTER SHAHAL STRESSED THAT IN HIS MEETINGS WITH THE ADMINISTRATION HEADS IN COLOMBIA, THE LATTER HAD LAVISHED PRAISE ON THE ASSISTANCE EXTENDED BY OUR DEFENSE SECTOR TO COLOMBIA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SHAHAL] IT IS ABSOLUTELY TRUE. ISRAEL TRAINED COLOMBIAN DEFENSE ESTABLISHMENT ELEMENTS; THIS WAS DONE IN THE CUSTOMARY WAY AND WITH THE APPROVAL OF THE DEFENSE MINISTER. COLOMBIA BOUGHT SECURITY PRODUCTS FROM ISRAEL, SUCH AS THE KFIR PLANES, WHICH WERE THE OTHER SIDE OF THE COAL PURCHASE. ON THE DAY I MET WITH THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT HE SIGNED AN ORDER APPROVING THE PURCHASE OF THE KFIR PLANES BY THE COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE. A DAY LATER WE SIGNED THE COAL AGREEMENT. THE TOTAL VALUE OF THE DEAL WAS ABOUT $200 TO $250 MILLION FOR EACH SIDE. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0397 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 29 AUG 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] FIVE HUNDRED COLOMBIAN JUDGES HAVE ANNOUNCED THEIR "JOINT RESIGNATION" IN PROTEST OF THE ABOLITION OF THE JURY, WHICH MAKES THE JUDGES FULLY RESPONSIBLE FOR A SENTENCE. THE JUDGES HAVE ALSO COMPLAINED THAT THEY DO NOT HAVE ENOUGH OFFICIAL PROTECTION.

THE JUDICIAL BRANCH NATIONAL ASSOCIATION [ASOCIACION NACIONAL DEL PODER JUDICIAL] (ASONAL) REPORTED TODAY THAT THE GOVERNMENT DECISION -- WHICH BECAME EFFECTIVE ON 28 AUGUST -- "REPRESENTS A GRAVE DANGER FOR THE JUDGES, BECAUSE THEY ARE FULLY RESPONSIBLE FOR DECLARING A PERSON GUILTY AND CONDEMNING THE CULPRITS."

A GROUP OF LITIGANT LAWYERS ALSO ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT THEY WILL NOT PARTICIPATE IN PUBLIC HEARINGS UNTIL THE REINSTATEMENT OF THE JURY, WHOSE ABOLITION THEY CONSIDER UNCONSTITUTIONAL.

ASONAL SECRETARY GENERAL ORLANDO MORALES TOLD EFE THAT THE JOINT RESIGNATION INVOLVES 550 JUDGES IN BOGOTA AND CUNDINAMARCA, THE DEPARTMENT IN WHICH THE COUNTRY'S CAPITAL IS LOCATED.

THE RESIGNATION COULD BE ANNOUNCED DURING THE WEEKEND AS A "CONTINUATION" OF THE 16 AUGUST STRIKE, WHEN 4,600 JUDGES DEMANDED MORE PROTECTION TO DO THEIR WORK, MORALES ADDED.

MORE THAN 200 OFFICIALS HAVE BEEN MURDERED SINCE THE COLOMBIAN JUSTICE SYSTEM BEGAN ITS STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DRUG LORDS IN 1981.

THREE JUDGES HAVE BEEN MURDERED SO FAR THIS YEAR. THEY WERE IN CHARGE OF LAWSUITS AGAINST THE MOST SOUGHT AFTER DRUG TRAFFICKING LEADERS IN THE COUNTRY. THE LAWSUITS WERE LATER SUSPENDED.

COLOMBIAN JUSTICE MINISTER MONICA DE GREIFF TRAVELED TO THE UNITED STATES ON 25 AUGUST TO REQUEST $2.5 MILLION IN AID TO GUARANTEE THE PROTECTION OF COLOMBIAN JUDGES AND THEIR RELATIVES.

THE MINISTER AND HER 3-YEAR-OLD SON HAVE BEEN THREATENED BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIAS.

DEV-MUC3-0398 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 29 AUG 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN DEFENSE MINISTRY IN BOGOTA CONFIRMED TODAY THAT AT LEAST THREE-FOURTHS OF THE 10,797 PEOPLE ARRESTED AFTER SENATOR LUIS CARLOS GALAN'S MURDER ON 18 AUGUST HAVE BEEN RELEASED.

THE RELEASES TOOK PLACE AS THE PREVENTIVE ARREST DEADLINES ESTABLISHED IN THE STATE OF SIEGE DECREES ISSUED ON 25 AUGUST BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO'S LIBERAL GOVERNMENT BEGAN TO EXPIRE.

COLONEL EDUARDO AREVALO, PRESS DIRECTOR FOR THE DEFENSE MINISTRY, TOLD AFP THAT THE AUTHORITIES COULD ONLY DETAIN SUSPECTS FOR 7 WORKING DAYS.

IT IS QUITE DIFFERENT WHEN ARRESTS ARE MADE ON SPECIFIC DRUG TRAFFICKING CHARGES, HE EXPLAINED.

"THERE ARE NO EXACT FIGURES REGARDING THE PERSONS RELEASED, BUT I CAN ASSURE YOU THAT AT LEAST THREE-FOURTHS OF THE DETAINEES ARE INVOLVED," COL AREVALO SAID.

THAT PROPORTION OF THE ALMOST 10,797 DETENTIONS MADE DURING THE OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY AGAINST COMMON CRIMINALS AND PRESUMED ACCOMPLICES OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIAS, LEADS TO THE ASSUMPTION THAT APPROXIMATELY 3,500 PEOPLE REMAIN IN CUSTODY AT THE JAILS, POLICE INSPECTION OFFICES, AND OTHER BRANCHES.

THE LEGAL SITUATION OF THESE INDIVIDUALS WILL BE ESTABLISHED AS THEIR TERMS EXPIRE IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE LAW, AREVALO SAID.

AREVALO EXPLAINED TO AFP THAT THERE HAVE BEEN A FEW DIFFICULTIES REGARDING THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN DETAINED AND ARRESTED, ADDING THAT THE DIFFICULTIES STEM FROM THE WORK STOPPAGE IN THE JUDICIAL BRANCH IN PROTEST OVER THE ASSASSINATION OF JUSTICE CARLOS VALENCIA IN BOGOTA.

HE SAID THAT AMONG THE DETAINEES ARE THREE INDIVIDUALS WHO COULD BE EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES.

ONE OF THE EXTRADITABLES IS EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, CAPTURED WHILE HE WAS VACATIONING ON HIS FARM IN TOLU, A VILLAGE IN THE NORTHWESTERN PROVINCE OF SUCRE ON THE CARIBBEAN COAST, APPROXIMATELY 750 KM FROM BOGOTA, AND HIS TRANSFER TO THE UNITED STATES COULD COME AT ANY MOMENT.

THE PROCEDURES FOR MARTINEZ ROMERO'S EXTRADITION WERE CARRIED OUT UNEVENTFULLY AFTER THE U.S. EMBASSY MADE THE REQUEST. HOWEVER, IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT HIS EXTRADITION MAY BE POSTPONED FOR A FEW DAYS BECAUSE THE SUPREME COURT SUSPENDED THE DEADLINES FOR THE ELECTION OF JUSTICES AT 27 HIGHER COURTS.

THE SUPREME COURT'S CONSTITUTIONAL CHAMBER AND THE ATTORNEY GENERAL HAVE 10 WORKING DAYS TO STATE THEIR POSITIONS REGARDING THE LEGALITY OF THE EXECUTIVE DECREES, WITHOUT WHICH THE GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE TO ABSTAIN FROM AUTHORIZING FUTURE EXTRADITIONS.

"WE MUST NOT ACT HASTILY BECAUSE WE DO NOT WANT TO MAKE ERRORS. SOME OF THE EXTRADITABLES MAY BE INNOCENT," COMMUNICATIONS MINISTER CARLOS LEMUS TOLD AFP.

DEV-MUC3-0399 (BBN)

BOGOTA, 30 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] THE RESIGNATIONS OF THREE OF THE JUDGES IN CHARGE OF INVESTIGATING THE MURDERS OF THE GOVERNOR OF ANTIOQUIA, ANOTHER JUDGE, AND THE ANTIOQUIA POLICE COMMANDER, WERE ANNOUNCED TODAY. MOREOVER, TWO OF THE JUDGES LEFT COLOMBIA.

MEANWHILE, ALMOST 4,000 MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE AND THE MEDELLIN SECURITY FORCES WILL PATROL THE METROPOLITAN AREA THROUGHOUT THE NIGHT. REVENUE GUARDS [CARABINEROS], GOES [SPECIAL OPERATIONS GROUP] AGENTS, MEMBERS OF THE CITIZEN ORDER DEPARTMENT [DEPARTAMENTO DE ORDEN CIUDADANO], AND TRAFFIC POLICEMEN WILL BE ON ALERT.

AMONG THE MEASURES PLANNED BY THE METROPOLITAN POLICE FOR THE CURFEW THAT BEGINS TONIGHT IN MEDELLIN ARE THE INSTALLATION OF 18 CHECKPOINTS STRATEGICALLY LOCATED AT THE METROPOLITAN AREA'S LEADING ENTRANCES AND EXITS. THREE HUNDRED AND FIFTY POLICEMEN WILL GUARD THE CHECKPOINTS AND CONDUCT SEARCHES. THEY WILL WORK AROUND-THE- CLOCK SEARCHING VEHICLES AND INDIVIDUALS TRAVELING IN THOSE AREAS. THE NINE PERMANENT AND NINE MOBILE CHECKPOINTS WILL BE USEFUL IN LOCATING WEAPONS, EXPLOSIVES, DRUGS, CRIMINALS, AND STOLEN VEHICLES. SEVERAL OF THE CHECKPOINTS WILL BE REINFORCED WITH ARMORED ANTIRIOT VEHICLES IN ANTICIPATION OF CLASHES.

DEV-MUC3-0403 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 30 AUG 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE POLICE REPORTED THAT CATTLEMAN LIBERTO GUTIERREZ MARQUEZ, THE ALLEGED FRONT MAN OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL AND BROTHER OF A FORMER COLOMBIAN ATTORNEY GENERAL, WAS FOUND MURDERED TODAY APPROXIMATELY 500 KM NORTHWEST OF BOGOTA.

THE SOURCE SAID THAT LIBERTO GUTIERREZ HAD RECENTLY DISAPPEARED AND APPARENTLY HAD BEEN KIDNAPPED BY MAOIST PEOPLE'S LIBERATION ARMY (EPL) GUERRILLAS, BUT THIS WAS NOT CONFIRMED.

GUTIERREZ' CORPSE WAS FOUND TODAY IN AYAPEL MUNICIPALITY, CORDOBA DEPARTMENT, APPROXIMATELY 500 KM NORTHWEST OF BOGOTA, BUT THE DATE OF HIS DEATH IS NOT KNOWN.

LIBERTO GUTIERREZ OWNED A FARM NEXT TO THE NOW CONFISCATED NAPOLES FARM, WHICH BELONGED TO PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, CONSIDERED THE MEDELLIN CARTEL LEADER.

GUTIERREZ' FARM, LOCATED IN PUERTO TRIUNFO, A ZONE IN MAGDALENA MEDIO, ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, HAD A LANDING STRIP IN WHICH A "TURBOCOMMANDER 2000" -- STOLEN BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS FROM A COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE BASE (FAC) IN BOGOTA -- HAD LANDED ON 2 MARCH 1988.

FAC FIGHTER PLANES CHASED THE THIEVES UP TO LIBERDO GUTIERREZ' FARM AND BOMBED BOTH THE AIRCRAFT AND THE LANDING STRIP, AS WELL AS THE NAPOLES FARM, KILLING A COOK WHO WORKED IN ESCOBAR'S HOUSE.

AS A RESULT OF THE INCIDENT IT WAS DISCOVERED THAT THE OWNER OF THE FARM AND LANDING STRIP USED BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WAS ALSO THE BROTHER OF ALFREDO GUTIERREZ, WHO WAS APPOINTED ATTORNEY GENERAL OF COLOMBIA FOLLOWING THE MURDER OF CARLOS MAURO HOYOS ON 25 JANUARY 1988.

BECAUSE OF THE SUSPICION THAT HIS BROTHER WAS A FRONT MAN FOR PABLO ESCOBAR, ATTORNEY GENERAL ALFREDO GUTIERREZ RESIGNED ON 28 MARCH 1988, 2 MONTHS AFTER ASSUMING HIS POST.

THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S RESIGNATION OCCURRED DURING A GENERAL OFFENSIVE IN MEDELLIN AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS, FOLLOWING HOYOS' MURDER, DURING WHICH FARMS WERE RAIDED AND ARSENALS AND DOCUMENTS CONFISCATED.

DEV-MUC3-0404 (LANG SYS INC)

MADRID (SPAIN), 31 AUG 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] WE NOW HAVE SOME STATEMENTS MADE EXCLUSIVELY TO MADRID RADIO BY A FORMER MEMBER OF THE CHILEAN SECRET POLICE. JOSE MANUEL MARTIN MEDEM REPORTS:

[MARTIN MEDEM] THE EXILES FROM CHILE, ARGENTINA, AND URUGUAY REPEATEDLY STATED THAT WHILE THERE WERE MILITARY DICTATORSHIPS IN THEIR COUNTRIES, THE ARMED FORCES OF THE SOUTHERN HALF OF LATIN AMERICA ACTED JOINTLLY, WITHOUT RESPECTING BORDERS, IN REPRESSION. IN THIS WAY, THEY WERE ABLE TO KIDNAP AN EXILE FROM WHERE HE HAD TAKEN REFUGE AND MAKE HIM RETURN TO THE COUNTRY OF ORIGIN, WHERE MANY WERE TORTURED AND MURDERED. OUR COLLEAGUE, JAVIER GONZALEZ, HAS NOW MANAGED A WITNESS REPORT THAT CONFIRMS THESE ACCUSATIONS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GONZALEZ] A FORMER MEMBER OF DINA [NATIONAL INTELLEGENCE DIRECTORATE], THE CHILEAN SECRET SERVICE UNDER PINOCHET, HAS ASKED REQUESTED POLITICAL ASYLUM IN SPAIN. HE IS JUAN JOSE SOTO VARGAS, WHO WORKED IN THE DINA CITIZENS' INTELLIGENCE BRIGADE. HE HAS TURNED AWAY FROM THE REGIME, ALTHOUGH HE MAINTAINED HIS IDEOLOGICAL STANCE. SOTO VARGAS, A DOCTOR BY PROFESSION AND A PASTOR OF AN EVANGELICAL CHURCH, HAS MADE EXCLUSIVE STATEMENTS TO MADRID RADIO IN WHICH HE CONFIRMS POLICE COOPERATION BETWEEN THE REGION'S MILITARY GOVERNMENTS DURING THE PERIOD OF STATE TERRORISM.

[SOTO VARGAS] WE, IN THE CHILEAN EMBASSY, WORKED WITH THE ARGENTINE FEDERAL POLICE AND WITH THE ARGENTINE ARMED FORCES IN THE FIGHT AGAINST SUBVERSION IN 1976 AND SHORTLY BEFORE ISABEL MARTINEZ DE PERON LEFT POWER. WE ALSO WORKED JOINTLY WITH THE SECURITY FORCES OF URAGUAY, PARAGUAY, AND BRAZIL. I WORKED IN THE CHILEAN EMBASSY IN BRAZIL WITH THE AGREEMENT OF THE NATIONAL INFORMATION SERVICE OF THE BRAZILIAN CENTRAL AGENCY. WELL, RELATIONS WERE THE BEST AND THIS WAS SIMPLY BECAUSE THE SOUTH AMERICAN ARMED FORCES, AT TO INSTALL ITSELF IN SOUTH AMERICA OR TO IMPOSE ITSELF THROUGH GUERRILLA TACTICS AND VIOLENCE.

[GONZALEZ] SOTO VARGAS HAS ALREADY REQUESTED POLITICAL ASYLUM IN OTHER EUROPEAN COUNTRIES, WHICH HE HAS HAD TO LEAVE FOR DIFFERENT REASONS. HE SAYS THAT HE DID NOT TORTURE OR KILL ANYONE AND THAT THINGS LIKE THIS DID NOT HAPPEN IN CHILE. HOWEVER, HE ADMITS THAT GENERAL CARLOS PRATS, THE HEAD OF THE ARMY UNDER PRESIDENT ALLENDE, WAS ASSASSINATED IN BUENOS AIRES UNDER ORDERS OF THE PINOCHET GOVERNMENT.

[SOTO VARGAS] THERE IS PROOF, EVEN JUDICIAL PROOF, THAT THERE WAS PARTICIPATION BY HIGH-RANKING MEMBERS OF THE CHILEAN ARMY WHO WERE ORDERED TO CARRY OUT ASSASSINATIONS. FOR EXAMPLE, WHEN I WORKED IN THE MILITARY SECTION OF THE CHILEAN EMBASSY IN ARGENTINA, GEN VICTOR HUGO BARRIERA BARRIERA OF THE ARMY INTELLIGENCE SERVICE AN THERE WAS TALK IN THE CHILEAN EMBASSY THAT THE CHILEAN HIGH-RANKING OFFICER HAD ORDERED THE PHYSICAL EXTERMINATION OF PRATS. [AS HEARD] [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0409 (LANG SYS INC)

RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL), 31 AUG 89 (O GLOBO) -- [TEXT] TABATINGA (AMAZONAS STATE) -- IN TABATINGA, 1,700 KM FROM MANAUS, POLICE, WITH THE SUPPORT OF THE BRAZILIAN ARMY AND THE SOUTHERN UNIFIED COMMAND (EAST OF COLOMBIA, YESTERDAY BEGAN AN OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS OF THE MEDELLIN AND CALI CARTELS. ROMEU TUMA, DIRECTOR GENERAL OF THE FEDERAL POLICE DEPARTMENT, PLANNED THE POLICE ACTION IN A MEETING WITH GENERAL AUGUSTO RODRIGUES ARANGO OF THE SOUTHERN UNIFIED COMMAND AND COLONEL LUIS FERNANDO GUZMAN VASQUEZ OF ARMY HEADQUARTERS IN LETICIA, COLOMBIA.

TUMA SAID THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS LEFT MEDELLIN AND CALI IN SMALL AIRPLANES, PROBABLY WITH FALSE DOCUMENTS, TO GO TO MANAUS, WHERE THEY WOULD PREPARE TO LEAVE FOR EUROPE AND THE UNITED STATES. ALL THE HOTELS OF MANAUS ARE UNDER STRICT SURVEILLANCE.

THE FIRST ATTEMPTS BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS TO ENTER BRAZIL WERE DISCOVERED WHEN THE POLICE FOUND THREE IMPORTED CARS. THE CARS, WHICH ARE LUXURY MODELS MADE IN THE UNITED STATES AND JAPAN, ARE INCLUDED IN A LIST OF 26 CARS SENT TO THE FEDERAL POLICE BY THE COLOMBIAN JUSTICE MINISTRY. THE CARS WERE LEFT BY AN UNIDENTIFIED COLOMBIAN AT A CAR WASH IN TABATINGA. AS THE CARS WERE NOT PICKED UP BY THEIR OWNERS FOR SEVERAL DAYS, THE OWNER OF THE CAR WASH REMOVED THE CARS'S TIRES AND CALLED THE FEDERAL POLICE, WHO TOOK THE CARS TO POLICE FACILITIES YESTERDAY.

TUMA BELIEVES THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE PLANNING TO STAY IN BRAZIL AFTER THE MURDER OF SEVERAL COLOMBIAN OFFICIALS, BUT IN THE FACE OF THE OFFENSIVE MOUNTED BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, THEY DECIDED TO MOVE ON.

TUMA ALREADY HAS THE WARRANT FOR THE ARREST OF 12 MEMBERS OF THE MEDELLIN AND CALI CARTELS FROM THE COLOMBIAN JUSTICE MINISTRY. GENERAL RODRIGUES ARANGO SAID THAT THE BRAZILIAN BORDER WITH COLOMBIA IS WELL GUARDED BY BRAZILIAN ARMY TROOPS.

DEV-MUC3-0411 (LANG SYS INC)

SAN SALVADOR, 29 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] RICALDONE INSTITUTE DIRECTOR FATHER GIUSSEPPE CORO PROTESTED TODAY THE MURDER OF A YOUNG MECHANICS STUDENT AND LATER ATTEMPTS TO INVOLVE THE INSTITUTE IN ILLEGAL ACTIVITIES IN THIS COUNTRY, WHICH IS AT WAR. THE RICALDONE INSITUTE IS ONE OF SEVERAL IMPORTANT SCHOOLS RUN BY SALESIAN PRIESTS IN EL SALVADOR.

FATHER CORO STATED DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE THAT STUDENT MIGUEL ERNESTO MIRANDA REINA, 18, "WHO WAS THE BEST MECHANICS STUDENT IN THE INSTITUTE,' WAS DESPICABLY AND COWARDLY SHOT IN THE BACK WHEN HE WAS ABOUT TO APPROACH HIS HOUSE IN WESTERN SAN SALVADOR ON 22 AUGUST. FATHER CORO ACCUSED THE "ATLACATL" BATTALION SOLDIERS, PARTICULARLY AN OFFICER, "A LIEUTENANT, SERGEANT, OR WHOMEVER," WHO LATER ATTEMPTED TO DISTORT THE EVENT BY STATING THAT THE YOUNG STUDENT WAS A "REBEL" BECAUSE HE WORE REBEL BOOTS AND HAD A REBEL BOOK.

THE SALESIAN PRIEST, WHO HAS LIVED IN THIS CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY FOR THE PAST 16 YEARS, SAID THAT THE STUDENT WAS RETURNING HOME AFTER WORKING ON HIS THESIS AS HE WAS TO GRADUATE THIS YEAR. THE STUDENT WORE THE SCHOOL'S UNIFORM, HAD HIS IDENTIFICATION PAPERS, AND CARRIED A BOOK ON RELIGION THAT SHOWED JESUS CHRIST WITH A BEARD ON ITS COVER.

FATHER CORO STATED THAT SINCE IT WAS NOT ENOUGH TO KILL AN INNOCENT YOUNG MAN WHO WAS AN HONOR STUDENT, THE SOLDIERS HAD STARTED TO KEEP A WATCH ON THE INSTITUTE, TO STOP STUDENTS TO HARRASS THEM MENTALLY BY ASKING THEM IF THEY KNEW MIRANDA REINA, TO PLACE A CHECKPOINT IN FRONT OF THE MURDERED STUDENT'S HOME, AND OTHER SIMILAR MEASURES. HE ADDED THAT IF THESE MEASURES ARE NOT STOPPED, THE SALESIAN COMMUNITY IN EL SALVADOR WILL PROTEST TO THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND.

FATHER CORO STATED THAT THE SALESIAN COMMUNITY FEELS AFFECTED BY THESE ACTIONS AS THEIR SCHOOLS HAVE ALWAYS EDUCATED THE YOUNG SO THAT THEY CAN EARN A LIVILIHOOD AND THAT THESE MEASURES -- POSSIBLY ORDERED BY MID-LEVEL COMMANDERS -- HINDER THEIR ACTIVITIES AND CAUSES INSTABILITY IN THE STUDENT BODY THAT DOES NOT PROMOTE EDUCATIONAL ADVANCEMENT.

DEV-MUC3-0413 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 2 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [EXCERPTS] THERE HAS BEEN A TERRORIST ATTACK AGAINST EL ESPECTADOR NEWSPAPER IN WESTERN BOGOTA. YOLANDA GOMEZ AND J.J. PINILLA REPORT. [PINILLA] ACCORDING TO A REPORT WE RECEIVED A FEW MINUTES AGO FROM THE FIRE STATION, A TRUCK BOMB EXPLODED INSIDE A GAS STATION NEXT TO THE EL ESPECTADOR NEWSPAPER INSTALLATIONS, WHICH IS VERY CLOSE TO THE BOGOTA CUSTOMS OFFICE. THE BLAST CAUSED GREAT DAMAGE, AND ONE OR TWO BUSES WERE TOTALLY DESTROYED. IT IS ESTIMATED THAT THE LOSSES AMOUNT TO SEVERAL MILLIONS [CURRENCY NOT SPECIFIED].

[GOMEZ] THERE IS A LARGE DEPLOYMENT OF POLICE, FIREMEN, AND AMBULANCES HERE ON 68TH AVENUE NEAR THE EL ESPECTADOR INSTALLATIONS. ACCORDING TO THE PRELIMINARY REPORTS, IT SEEMS SOME PEOPLE WERE INJURED INSIDE THE EL ESPECTADOR BUILDING BECAUSE SOME WINDOWS WERE BROKEN DUE TO THE BLAST.

ANNOUNCER THAT IS CORRECT YOLANDA, WE HAVE LEARNED THERE ARE AT LEAST THREE INJURED INSIDE THE EL ESPECTADOR INSTALLATIONS DUE TO THE BOMB EXPLOSION. AS YOU REPORTED, THE POLICE HAVE CONFIRMED A BOMB EXPLODED INSIDE A VEHICLE PARKED AT A GAS STATION NEXT TO THE EL ESPECTADOR NEWSPAPER INSTALLATIONS. PLEASE CONTINUE.

[GOMEZ] THE BOMB EXPLODED AT THE GAS STATION ON 68TH AVENUE. THE GAS STATION IS TOTALLY DESTROYED, NOTHING REMAINS OF THE GAS STATION, NOT EVEN THE GAS STATION BILLBOARD.

[ANNOUNCER] WE HAVE CALLED LUCIA DE OJEDA AT THE BOGOTA RED CROSS. THIS IS RADIO CADENA NACIONAL. COULD YOU PLEASE TELL US ABOUT THE NAMES AND THE CONDITION OF THE INJURED TAKEN TO THE RED CROSS.

[OJEDA] EIGHT OR NINE PEOPLE HAVE ARRIVED AT THE RED CROSS--WE DO NOT HAVE THE EXACT NUMBER--INCLUDING A WOMAN. THERE IS ONE DEAD PERSON WHO HAS NOT BEEN IDENTIFIED SINCE HE HAS NO IDENTIFICATION PAPERS.

[ANNOUNCER] SO ONE PERSON HAS DIED.

[OJEDA] AMONG THE INJURED HERE ARE HERIBERTO LOPEZ GONZALEZ, 53; JAIME ORLANDO SUAREZ, 24; NORALBA BELTRAN, 23; GLORIA CARRANZA, 25; LEON ALVARO VITORINO, 32; DANIEL MANTILLA, 26; MARITZA MARTINEZ, 38; GLADYS PAEZ; PEDRO ORTIZ, ABEL PORTILLO, AND CARMEN ROSA GUTIERREZ.

[ANNOUNCER] YOU SAID THERE IS ONE DEAD PERSON. HAD HE DIED BEFORE HE ARRIVED AT THE RED CROSS OR DID HE DIE AT THE RED CROSS.

[OJEDA] HE IS A YOUNG MAN, WHO HAS NO IDENTIFICATION PAPERS.

[ANNOUNCER] DO YOU HAVE ANY REPORTS ON THE INJURED?

[OJEDA] THEY ARE BADLY INJURED. SOME ARE SLIGHTLY INJURED BUT THERE ARE OTHERS BADLY INJURED.

THANK YOU MRS OJEDA.

DEV-MUC3-0414 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 2 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [REPORT] [BERTA LUCIA CEVALLOS] [TEXT] THE SO-CALLED EXTRADITABLES HAVE CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK ON THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR FACILITIES IN BOGOTA THIS MORNING. EL ESPECTADOR PRESIDENT LUIS GABRIEL CANO SAID HE RECEIVED THE PHONE CALL IN WHICH THE GROUP CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK.

MEANWHILE, THERE IS CONFIRMATION OF AN ATTACK ON A PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CANO FAMILY IN ISLAS DEL ROSARIO.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CANO] THEY [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] BURNED A FEW VACATION CABINS AT A SMALL ISLET I OWN ON ROSARIO ISLAND.

[UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] HAVE YOU CALCULATED THE LOSSES CAUSED BY THE ATTACK ON ROSARIO ISLAND?

[CANO] NO, I DO NOT HAVE SPECIFIC DATA YET, BECAUSE I HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO COMMUNICATE WITH THE PEOPLE THERE. FORTUNATELY, THE WATCHMAN ON THE PROPERTY WAS UNHARMED. I WAS PLEASED TO KNOW THAT, BECAUSE I WAS AFRAID FOR HIM. PROPERTY CAN BE REPLACED, BUT HUMAN LIVES CANNOT. [END RECORDING]

WHILE THE LOSSES CAUSED ON EL ESPECTADOR WERE BEING ESTIMATED, VARIOUS PHONE CALLS WERE RECEIVED AT THE NEWSPAPER REGARDING THE DYNAMITE ATTACK.

ON 3 SEPTEMBER A REDUCED VERSION OF EL ESPECTADOR NEWSPAPER WILL CIRCULATE. APPROXIMATELY 250,000 COPIES OF EL ESPECTADOR WILL CIRCULATE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CANO] WE ARE MAKING HUGE EFFORTS TO CIRCULATE TOMORROW. EVEN IF TOMORROW'S ISSUE OF OUR NEWSPAPER HAS ONLY TWO OR FOUR PAGES, EL ESPECTADOR WILL CIRCULATE ON 3 SEPTEMBER AND WILL CONTINUE TO CIRCULATE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0415 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 2 SEP 89 (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] BOGOTA INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2 BROADCASTS A SERIES OF REPORTS, TOTALING ABOUT 10 MINUTES, ON THE 2 SEPTEMBER BOMB ATTACK CARRIED OUT AGAINST THE FACILITIES OF THE BOGOTA NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR.

THE FIRST REPORT BEGINS BY SAYING THAT THE FACILITIES OF THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR WERE THE "TARGET OF A BRUTAL TERRORIST ATTACK IN WHICH MANY INNOCENT PEOPLE WERE INJURED." THE REPORT ADDS THAT "TODAY A TRUCK BOMB CARRYING ALMOST 200 KG OF DYNAMITE WENT OFF AT A LARGE GAS STATION LOCATED NEXT TO THE FACILITIES OF THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR. THE ATTACK IS ONE OF THE MOST SERIOUS TERRORIST ATTACKS CONDUCTED IN BOGOTA IN THE LAST FEW MONTHS."

THE NEXT REPORT SAYS THAT "TODAY'S EXPLOSION CAUSED A TRUE HOSPITAL EMERGENCY IN BOGOTA. ONE PERSON WAS KILLED AND 86 OTHERS INJURED, INCLUDING 6 WHO WERE SERIOUSLY INJURED AS A RESULT OF THE ATTACK."

THE REPORT STATES THAT "THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR WAS VIRTUALLY PARALYZED TODAY, ALTHOUGH ITS DIRECTORS SAID THAT IT WILL CIRCULATE TOMORROW NO MATTER WHAT. HERNANDO SANTOS, CHIEF EDITOR OF THE COLOMBIAN NEWSPAPER EL TIEMPO, EVEN OFFERED WORKSHOPS AND ROTARY PRESSES TO ASSEMBLE AND PRINT EL ESPECTADOR IF THAT WERE NECESSARY."

THE REPORT CONTINUES THAT "LOSSES OF OVER 200 MILLION PESOS OCCURRED AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION IN WESTERN BOGOTA THIS MORNING. THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR FACILITIES WERE LEFT AS IF THEY HAD BEEN BOMBED." THE REPORT ADDS THAT MOST OF THE INTERIOR WAS "VISIBLY" DESTROYED AND THAT THERE ARE CRACKS IN THE OUTER AND INNER WALLS OF THE BUILDING.

THE REPORT INCLUDES RECORDED STATEMENTS BY EL ESPECTADOR GENERAL MANAGER ALFONSO CANO WHO STATES THAT "EL ESPECTADOR HAS FOLLOWED A SPECIFIC LINE FOR THE LAST 102 YEARS. THAT LINE WILL NOT CHANGE BECAUSE WE WERE THE TARGETS OF A BOMB ATTACK OR BECAUSE ITS REPORTERS ARE KILLED. WE WILL CIRCULATE TOMORROW EVEN IF WE PRINT A 2-PAGE NEWSPAPER."

FINALLY, THE REPORT CONCLUDES BY SAYING THAT "IN A FEW MINUTES THE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR DIRECTORS WILL ISSUE A COMMUNIQUE ON THE ATTACK IN WHICH THEY WILL EXPRESS THEIR REJECTION OF THESE TERRORIST ATTACKS."

DEV-MUC3-0416 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 2 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING "CAPOS," THOSE "EXTRADITABLE" TO THE UNITED STATES, "ARE IN COLOMBIA; THEY HAVE NOT SOUGHT REFUGE ABROAD," NATIONAL POLICE CHIEF GENERAL MIGUEL GOMEZ PADILLA TOLD THE PRESS TODAY.

"I AM SURE THAT THEY ARE IN COLOMBIAN TERRITORY. WE HAVE EVIDENCE TO THAT EFFECT," THE GENERAL SAID, ADDING THAT THE POLICE "HAVE AN ENTIRE UNIT READY TO BE TAKEN TO ANY POINT OF THE COUNTRY AT A MOMENT'S NOTICE" SHOULD ANY OF THE "CAPOS" BE FOUND.

SOME OF THE 12 "EXTRADITABLES" -- JORGE LUIS, JUAN DAVID, FABIO OCHOA, PABLO ESCOBAR, GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, AND GILBERTO RODRIGUEZ OREJUELA -- HAVE BEEN POINTED OUT AS BEING THE KINGPINS OF THE CALI AND MEDELLIN NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING GROUPS. THEY ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR EXPORTING 80 PERCENT OF THE COCAINE USED IN THE UNITED STATES.

ALTHOUGH HE ADMITTED THAT THE POLICE DO NOT HAVE "EXACT INFORMATION," GEN GOMEZ PADILLA POINTED OUT THAT MANY OF THE DOCUMENTS SEIZED IN THE LAST 2 WEEKS FROM THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATIONS-- INVENTORIES, ACCOUNTS, AND PROPERTY TITLES--"ALLOW US TO PROGRESS IN OUR CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING NETWORKS."

THE POLICE CHIEF ADDED THAT "THE POLICE ARE CAREFULLY EVALUATING THE DOCUMENTS SEIZED. NO POLITICAL OR PUBLIC FIGURE HAS BEEN FOUND TO BE INVOLVED WITH NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING AS A RESULT OF THESE PAPERS," HE SAID, BUT HE ADMITTED THAT BRIBERY IS ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT "ELEMENTS OF DESTABILIZATION" THAT THE MULTIMILLIONAIRE COCAINE MAFIAS USE.

GEN GOMEZ PADILLA ADMITTED THAT THE POLICE DEPARTMENT HAS ALSO BEEN THE VICTIM OF BRIBERY CASES. "THANK GOD THERE ARE ONLY A FEW CASES, JUST FOUR OR FIVE," BUT THESE HAVE BEEN DETECTED IN TIME AND THOSE FOUND HAVE BEEN PUNISHED.

HE ALSO SAID THAT "WE HAVE HAD SOME EXEMPLARY MEN WHO HAVE GIVEN THEIR LIVES FOR THEIR PROFESSIONAL WORK."

IN THE LAST 3 YEARS, 1,300 POLICEMEN HAVE BEEN KILLED WHILE WORKING ON CASES RELATED TO NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING, GOMEZ PADILLA REPORTED. HE ALSO ADMITTED HE HIMSELF HAS RECEIVED DEATH THREATS.

MIGUEL GOMEZ PADILLA STRESSED BEFORE THE FOREIGN PRESS THAT "COLOMBIA IS A SOVEREIGN NATION THAT HAS A VERY QUALIFIED AND PROFESSIONAL ARMED FORCES," AND THAT IN ORDER TO FIGHT NARCOTICS TERRORISM "WE DO NOT NEED FOREIGN FORCES."

WITH THIS REMARK, GEN GOMEZ AGAIN REJECTED THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE UNITED STATES MIGHT SEND TROOPS TO FIGHT THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING GROUPS IN COLOMBIAN TERRITORY.

"THE FACT WE NEED EQUIPMENT AND TECHNOLOGICAL SUPPORT IS SOMETHING ELSE," THE POLICE CHIEF SAID, ADDING THAT "WE WELCOME ANY AMOUNT OF MONEY."

GOMEZ PADILLA POINTED OUT THAT "AS NEVER BEFORE, THE ARMY, THE SECRET AGENTS, AND THE POLICE ARE TRULY COMITTED TO THE STRUGGLE AND HAVE ASSIGNED 80,000 UNITS TO FIGHT DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY AGAINST NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING."

AS OF 18 AUGUST, WHEN THE GOVERNMENT LAUNCHED ITS MOST RECENT OFFENSIVE AGAINST NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING AND ADOPTED MEASURES THAT INCLUDED EXTRADITON, THE PRODUCTION AND MARKETING OF COCAINE "HAS NEARLY STOPPED," GOMEZ PADILLA SAID.

THE GENERAL STATED THAT THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS ARE SEEKING NEW MARKETING ROUTES AND NEW BORDER AREAS TO INSTALL THE COCAINE REFINING LABORATORIES.

HE ADDED THE COLOMBIAN TOPOGRAPHY -- MOUNTAINOUS AND WITH VERY DENSE JUNGLES -- CONCEALS THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS AND THEIR INSTALLATIONS, "BUT SOONER OR LATER WE ARE GOING TO FIND THEM; THEY CANNOT HIDE FOREVER."

DEV-MUC3-0417 (LANG SYS INC)

TAIPEI (TAIWAN), 4 SEP 89 (CNA) -- [TEXT] THE PRESIDENTS OF THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA AND THE REPUBLIC OF GUATEMALA JOINTLY DENOUNCED TERRORISTS AND DRUG-PUSHERS AS "TWO MAJOR POLLUTIONS OF THE WORLD" MONDAY.

IN A JOINT COMMUNIQUE THEY SIGNED BEFORE GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT MARCO VINICIO CEREZO AREVALO CONCLUDED HIS SIX-DAY VISIT HERE, THE TWO HEADS OF STATE REITERATED THEIR DETERMINATION TO PROMOTE WORLD PEACE AND INTERNATIONAL CO-PROSPERITY.

PRESIDENT CEREZO AND PRESIDENT LI TENG-HUI SIGNED ON THE COMMUNIQUE IN TAIPEI MONDAY MORNING. THE GUATEMALAN PRESIDENTIAL ENTOURAGE LEFT FOR HOME IN THE AFTERNOON.

THE COMMUNIQUE SAID THE WORLD COUNTRIES SHOULD RESPECT EACH OTHER'S NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY, RESPECT THEIR PEOPLE'S FREEDOM OF CHOICE, AND REFRAIN FROM INTEFERING WITH DOMESTIC AFFAIRS OF OTHER COUNTRIES.

EVERY COUNTRY'S FOREIGN POLICY SHOULD ALSO BE GOVERNED BY THE PRINCIPLES OF PEACEFUL SOLUTIONS TO DISPUTES, NOT INVADING OTHERS' TERRITORIES, AND RESPECTING THE SOVEREIGNTY OF NATURAL RESOURCES OF INDIVIDUAL COUNTRIES, SAID THE COMMUNIQUE.

CEREZO AND LI EXPRESSED CONCERN OVER ARMAMENTS AND INTERNATIONAL DISPUTES WHICH MIGHT AGGRAVATE TENSION IN THE WORLD.

THEY ALSO "STRONGLY DENOUNCED" ALL TERRORIST ACTIONS AND PLANTING AND PUSHING OF DRUGS, SAYING THE TWO ARE "MAJOR POLLUTIONS OF THE WORLD."

THE TWO PRESIDENTS POINTED OUT THAT PEACE EFFORTS REAFFIRMED BY FIVE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS IN THREE RECENT SUMMITS TO PROMOTE MUTUAL RESPECT AND PEACEFUL CO-EXISTENCE ARE "EXTREMELY IMPORTANT."

THE ROC AND GUATEMALAN PRESIDENTS SAID THEY WERE SATISFIED WITH THE SUCCESSFUL DEVELOPMENT OF BILATERAL TIES, REAFFIRMING THEIR RESOLUTE DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE AND STRENGTHEN VARIOUS COOPERATIVE PROGRAMS BETWEEN THE TWO NATIONS.

THEIR JOINT REVIEW OF IMPLEMENTATION OF VARIOUS TREATIES AND ACCORDS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES CONCLUDED THAT THESE BILATERAL AGREEMENTS HAVE FORMED A BROAD BASE FOR THEM TO CONSOLIDATE THEIR RESPECTIVE DEMOCRATIC DEVELOPMENT, ACCORDING TO THE COMMUNIQUE.

PRESIDENT CEREZO THANKED PRESIDENT LI FOR THE ROC'S FINANCIAL, AGRICULTURAL, INDUSTRIAL AND TECHNOLOGICAL ASSISTANCES TO GUATEMALA. THE TWO SAID THESE COOPERATIVE PROJECTS SHOULD CONTINUE.

THE TWO HEADS OF STATE ALSO EXPRESSED SATISFACTION OVER INCREASING EXCHANGES OF VISITS BY GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS WHICH HAVE SUCCESSFULLY PROMOTED ECONOMIC COOPERATION BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES.

THEY AGREED THAT SUCH EXCHANGES AND ECONOMIC COOPERATION SHOULD CONTINUE IN ORDER TO BOOST MUTUAL FRIENDSHIP AND BENEFIT THEIR PEOPLES.

RECOGNIZING CULTURAL AND SPORTS EXCHANGES' CONTRIBUTION TO CONSOLIDATING BILATERAL FRIENDSHIP AND PROMOTING PEACE, THE TWO PRESIDENTS AGREED TO STRENGTHEN THE EXCHANGES BY INCREASING INVITATIONS AND QUOTA FOR SCHOLARSHIPS.

CEREZO IN THE MEANTIME CORDIALLY INVITED PRESIDENT LI TO VISIT GUATEMALA. THE LATTER ACCEPTED THE INVITATION WITH GREAT PLEASURE, AND ASKED THEIR STAFFS TO ARRANGE THE DETAILS.

DURING HIS STAY HERE, CEREZO HAS BEEN WARMLY AND COURTEOUSLY WELCOMED AND TREATED. HE HAS ALSO BEEN CONFERRED AN ODER OF THE HIGHEST HONOR TO A CIVILIAN LEADER. BEFORE HIS DEPARTURE, HE GAVE A PRESS CONFERENCE TO TALK ABOUT HIS VISIT.

DEV-MUC3-0420 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 4 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] A C-123 HERCULES PLANE HAS BEEN DYNAMITED IN MONTERIA. ACCORDING TO THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY], THE AIRPLANE BELONGS TO THE DRUG ENFORCEMENT AGENCY. THE PLANE HAD BEEN FLYING TO CALI LAST WEEK, BUT IT HAD TO LAND AT THE LOS GARZONES AIRPORT, LOCATED 10 MINUTES FROM MONTERIA, AFTER DEVELOPING MECHANICAL DIFFICULTIES.

THE C-123 HERCULES PLANE WAS DYNAMITED BY DRUG TRAFFICKING GANGS AS IT SAT IN A DARK SECTION OF THE LOS GARZONES AIRPORT OF MONTERIA. AIRPORT SOURCES SAID THE GRAY PLANE HAD BEEN IN ROUTE TO CALI LAST WEEK, BUT ITS CREW HAD TO LEAVE IT IN MONTERIA BECAUSE OF ITS MECHANICAL DEFECTS. THE POWERFUL DYNAMITE CHARGE WAS PLACED UNDERNEATH THE PLANE. THE EXPLOSION DESTROYED A LARGE PART OF THE CABIN, INSTRUMENT PANEL, AND CONTROLS. THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED DURING A HEAVY DOWNPOUR. THE AUTHORITIES REPORTED THAT THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES.

THE AIRPLANE WAS UNDER SPECIAL PROTECTION, BUT THE GUARDS WERE INSIDE THE AIRPORT WHEN THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED. ONLY THE AIRPORT PERSONNEL AND CIVIL AERONAUTICS WATCHMEN WERE AT THE TERMINAL WHEN THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED.

DEV-MUC3-0421 (LANG SYS INC)

MOSCOW (USSR), NO DATE -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] FULLY AWARE OF OUR RESPONSIBILITY AND THE MAGNITUDE OF THE CHALLENGE, THE PCCH AND THE LEFTIST SECTOR, AS PART OF THE OPPOSITION, WILL SPARE NO SACRIFICE TO SECURE AN IMPORTANT VICTORY BY ELECTING PATRICIO AYLWIN PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND ESTABLISHING A DECISIVE MAJORITY IN CONGRESS FOR THE OPPOSITION, INCLUDING THE UNITED LEFT AND THE PAIS [BROAD PARTY OF THE SOCIALIST LEFT].

IN OUR OPINION, SAID VOLODIA TEITELBOIM, THIS IS NOT JUST AN ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN. WE DO NOT SEE IT AS SEPARATE FROM THE SOCIAL MOBILIZATION CARRIED OUT BY PEOPLE BURDENED BY HUNDREDS OF DAILY PROBLEMS, A MOBILIZATION TO RECOVER THEIR RIGHTS TO FOOD, JOBS, HEALTH, HOUSING, AND EDUCATION -- TO A WAY OF LIFE WORTHY OF HUMAN BEINGS.

FIVE OR SIX MILLION HUNGRY AND POOR CHILEANS IS A SCANDAL, AND THEY DESERVE A SHARE OF THE WEALTH OF THOSE WHO TOOK OVER THE COUNTRY'S GOVERNMENT.

WE NEED TO DEMAND AND DEFEND THE RESPECT FOR LIFE THAT HAS NOT BEEN GUARANTEED DURING THESE PAST 16 YEARS IN OUR FATHERLAND. A SINGLE DAY DOES NOT GO BY WITHOUT A DEFENDER OF FREEDOM BECOMING A VICTIM OF THE REGIME'S REPRESSIVE APPARATUS.

THE COMMUNIST REPRESENTATIVE ADDED: WE WANT PEACE FOR CHILE. WE WANT THE DEADLY VIOLENCE AND TERRORISM UNLEASHED ON 11 SEPTEMBER 1973 TO END ONCE AND FOR ALL.

THE CHILEAN DILEMMA CONTINUES TO BE DEMOCRACY OR DICTATORSHIP, LIBERTY OR TYRANNY, PERPETUATION IN POWER OR A NEW LIFE. VOLODIA TEITELBOIM HAS INDEED MADE A CALL TO GET ORGANIZED, TO UNITE, AND TO CONVINCE. THE PERPETUATION OF POWER IS NOW CALLED HERNAN BUCHI. WE MUST ALL UNITE TO DEFEAT PINOCHET. BUCHI IS HIS MAN.

TEITELBOIM POINTED OUT THAT THE PEOPLE DID NOT MAKE A MISTAKE. THEY JUST HAD TO CHANGE A LETTER OF BUCHI'S PROPAGANDISTIC SLOGANS TO RESTORE THE TRUTH: BUCHI IS NOT THE MAN; RATHER, HE REPRESENTS HUNGER.

IN ITS 15TH CONGRESS THE PCCH MADE A CALL TO DEFEAT THE MINISTER WHO HAS MADE MILLIONS OF PEOPLE POOR, THE MINISTER WHO HAS NOW BECOME A DEMAGOGUE AND IS PROMISING THE MOON AND AN UNREALISTIC WORLD FOR THE PEOPLE; THAT IS, THE MINISTER WHO IS PROMISING EVERYTHING HE FAILED TO ACCOMPLISH IN HIS YEARS AS MINISTER.

BUCHI'S INSINCERE PROMISES ARE SURPASSED ONLY BY ANOTHER TALKATIVE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF THE REGIME: MR ERRAZURIZ.

VOLODIA TEITELBOIM THEN ADDED: IN ORDER TO GUARANTEE THE VICTORY OF DEMOCRACY, IT IS NECESSARY TO ORGANIZE THE UNITED FORCES OF ALL THOSE WHO HOPE FOR LIBERTY.

WE HEREBY CALL FOR THE CREATION OF MILLIONS OF COMMANDOS FOR DEMOCRACY AND BROAD COMMITTEES ACROSS THE COUNTRY TO DISPLAY INITIATIVES, ENCOURAGE IMAGINATION, AND FORM CARAVANS OF PEOPLE WHO WILL GIVE EXPLANATIONS FROM DOOR TO DOOR AND FROM PERSON TO PERSON, IMPLEMENTING A FERVENT AND OVERWHELMING DYNAMIC CAPABLE OF CHANGING CHILE ON 14 DECEMBER 1989.

OUR PEOPLE HAVE ALWAYS PLAYED AN OUTSTANDING ROLE IN THE CRUCIAL CROSSROADS OF THE 20TH CENTURY. THEY ARE PLAYING IT NOW, FIGHTING WHOLEHEARTEDLY, CONVINCED THAT THE VICTORY OF DEMOCRACY WILL REPRESENT A SIGNIFICANT STEP TOWARD RESPECTING HUMAN RIGHTS, AN EMPHATIC AND RIGHTEOUS NO TO IMPUNITY, AND A SUBSTANTIVE YES TO LIBERTY FOR ALL POLITICAL PRISONERS AND TO THE DISSOLUTION OF THE CNI [NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER].

THE OUTSTANDING COMMUNIST LEADER AND INTELLECTUAL SAID THAT THESE ARE DAYS FOR GENEROSITY AND SPIRITUAL GRANDEUR. SEEKING DEMOCRACY, WE ARE SHAKING HANDS WITH ALL THOSE WITH WHOM WE HAVE HAD DISAGREEMENTS IN THE PAST. WE WANT TO EMPHASIZE THIS. ALTHOUGH WE ARE MOTIVATED BY DIFFERENT POLITICAL CONCEPTS, THIS IS A CREATIVE TIME FOR A COMMON DENOMINATOR, JOINT ACTIONS, AND FOR EVERYONE TO LEND A HAND.

IF THE OPPOSITION MARCHES UNITED TOWARD 14 DECEMBER, IT WILL ACHIEVE A OVERWHELMING VICTORY THAT WILL BE REGISTERED IN CHILEAN HISTORY AS A GOLDEN DATE OF EXTRAORDINARY SIGNIFICANCE.

SUCH A VICTORY WILL FINALLY RESTORE A RIGHT THAT HAS REPEATEDLY BEEN REQUESTED AND VIOLATED: THE RIGHT TO REJOICE AND TO TRUST IN THE FUTURE WITH THE CERTAINTY THAT NO ONE WILL SLIP UNNOTICED THROUGH THE SHADOWS OF THE NIGHT TO KILL A CHILEAN WITH IMPUNITY.

THE PEOPLE, ADDED VOLODIA TEITELBOIM, ARE BEGINNING TO PAINT THE WALLS WITH A SLOGAN: THE PEOPLE WIN, THE DICTATORSHIP IS OVER. THE DICTATORSHIP WILL END AND THE PEOPLE WILL WIN.

IF WE WIN IN 14 DECEMBER AND DOUBTLESSLY WE WILL, AND IF WE -- ALWAYS ACTING IN UNISON -- IMMEDIATELY SPOIL PINOCHET'S PLANS, WE WILL [WORD INDISTINCT] THEN THE PRESIDENT OF THE PRESIDENT OR THE PERPETUAL BOSS.

THE TOP LEADER OF CHILEAN COMMUNISTS WARNED THAT THE DANGERS AND DIFFICULTIES DEMAND THAT WE REMAIN ALERT AND WORK EVEN HARDER. WE MUST BURY ALL ATTEMPTS BY THE GENERAL AND HIS FAITHFULS TO STOP OR REVERSE CHILE'S PROGRESS TOWARD NEW HORIZONS.

VOLODIA TEITELBOIM POINTED OUT THAT PATRICIO AYLWIN, DURING A MEETING AT THE OPENING CEREMONY FOR THE CHRISTIAN LEFT PARTY OFFICES, EXPRESSED HIS DESIRE TO BE ABLE TO IMPLEMENT A TRULY DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT THAT WILL MAKE ALL CHILEANS ACTIVE AGAIN IN DEMOCRATIC LIFE. THIS PURPOSE REFLECTS THE SENTIMENTS OF A VAST MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE WHO WANT TO TURN THE BLOODY PAGE OF THE DICTATORSHIP AND PUT AN END TO POLITICAL AND SOCIAL NEGLECT AND TO THE DIVISIONS BETWEEN HUMANS, BETWEEN PARIAHS AND PRIVILEGED ONES, AND BETWEEN FIRST-CLASS, SECOND-CLASS, OR THIRD-CLASS PEOPLE, WHERE SOME ENJOY EVERY RIGHT WHILE OTHERS ARE DENIED EVEN THE RIGHT TO LIVE.

IN HIS SPEECH OVER A PARTIAL RADIO NETWORK, THE PCCH SECRETARY GENERAL SAID: WE DREAM ABOUT AND STRIVE FOR A CHILE WITHOUT MISSING PEOPLE, WITHOUT EXECUTED PEOPLE, WITHOUT BURNED YOUTHS, WITHOUT POLITICAL PRISONERS, WITHOUT EXILES -- A FATHERLAND OF EQUALS AMONG EQUALS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0423 (LANG SYS INC)

MEDELLIN, 4 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A NEW TERRORIST ACTION SHOOK MEDELLIN IN NORTHWESTERN COLOMBIA THIS EVENING WHEN TWO MEN RIDING ON A MOTORCYCLE THREW AN EXPLOSIVE DEVICE AT A POLICE POST LOCATED IN THE EXCLUSIVE SUBURB OF EL POBLADO. MIRACULOUSLY, THE THREE POLICEMEN AND TWO CIVILIANS WHO WERE INSIDE ESCAPED INJURY.

THE POST, KNOWN AS AN IMMEDIATE ATTENTION CENTER (CAI), WHICH PLAYS THE ROLE OF A POLICE CONTROL POST, WAS DESTROYED BY THE EXPLOSION OF THE DEVICE.

THREE POLICEMEN AND TWO CIVILIANS WERE INSIDE THE POST, WHICH WAS NOT FULLY OPERATIONAL BECAUSE IT HAD NOT BEEN COMPLETELY BUILT, BUT MANAGED TO ESCAPE.

ONE OF THE POLICEMEN TOLD AFP THAT THEY SAW TWO MEN ON A MOTORCYCLE SWIFTLY PASSING BY THE CAI AND THEN THROWING A RED PLASTIC BAG.

THE THREE POLICEMEN AND THE TWO CIVILIANS MANAGED TO RUN A FEW METERS DOWN THE STREET BEFORE THE DEVICE EXPLODED.

ALTHOUGH THE DEVICE'S POWER HAS YET TO BE ESTABLISHED BY EXPERTS, THE DETONATION WAS STRONG ENOUGH TO DESTROY THE STRUCTURE, MEASURING APPROXIMATELY 11 SQUARE METERS.

PRECISELY 1 MONTH AGO THE SAME CAI HAD BEEN DESTROYED WHEN ITS WALLS WERE BEING CONSTRUCTED.

A WOMAN WHO PASSED THROUGH THE AREA AT THE TIME OF THE ATTACK WAS NOT INJURED EITHER, EVEN THOUGH HER VEHICLE SUSTAINED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE, PARTICULARLY THE WINDOWS, WHICH WERE DESTROYED.

THE NEW TERRORIST ACTION OCCURRED 12 HOURS AFTER A MAN WAS INVOLVED IN A SPECTACULAR SHOOT-OUT AT THE JOSE MARIA CORDOBA AIRPORT IN MEDELLIN, WHERE THE GUNMAN AND A YOUNG MAN DIED AND 10 PERSONS WERE WOUNDED, INCLUDING THREE POLICEMEN.

THE CAI'S DESTRUCTION OCCURRED 4 HOURS AFTER THE BEGINNING OF THE CURFEW, IMPOSED BY MAYOR JUAN GOMEZ MARTINEZ 6 DAYS AGO IN AN ATTEMPT TO CURTAIL THE TERRORIST ACTIONS WHICH HAVE SHAKEN THE CITY, BIRTHPLACE OF THE MEDELLIN DRUG CARTEL.

DEV-MUC3-0425 (LANG SYS INC)

SANTIAGO, 5 SEP 89 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [EXCERPTS] POLICE SOURCES HAVE CONFIRMED THAT JECAR ANTONIO NEGHME CRISTI, 28, POLITICAL LEADER OF THE MOVEMENT OF THE REVOLUTIONARY LEFT, MIR, DIED INSTANTLY LAST NIGHT WHEN HE WAS HIT BY 12 BULLETS FIRED FROM 2 DIFFERENT WEAPONS IN AN ATTACK THAT OCCURED WHILE HE WAS WALKING HOME FROM HIS PARTY OFFICE.

SOME DOCUMENTS WERE FOUND AT THE SCENE OF THE CRIME. ONE OF THE LEAFLETS FOUND STATED: KILLED FOR BETRAYING THE REVOLUTIONARY STRUGGLE AND THE PEOPLE. YELLOW AND BOURGEOIS [AS HEARD].

ACCORDING TO THE INVESTIGATORS, NEGHME'S BODY RECEIVED 18 BULLET WOUNDS, CAUSED BY 12 DIRECT HITS. THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT BY A GROUP OF ARMED INDIVIDUALS IN A MOVING CAR. NOTHING IS KNOWN ABOUT THE ATTACKERS.

CARABINEROS PERSONNEL WENT TO THE SCENE OF THE CRIME AFTER RECEIVING A TELEPHONE CALL. HOMICIDE EXPERTS FROM THE CIVILIAN POLICE ARRIVED A LITTLE LATER. THEY IMMEDIATELY CONDUCTED THE APPROPRIATE INVESTIGATIONS WHERE THE MIR SPOKESMAN WAS GUNNED DOWN. NEGHME WAS KILLED SOME 50 METERS FROM THE BERNARDO O'HIGGINS PROMENADE, AT 10 WEST BULNES STREET. THE STREET IS POORLY ILLUMINATED. IT IS BELIEVED THAT THERE WERE NO EYEWITNESSES OF THE CRIME.

ACCORDING TO POLICE SOURCES, TWO AUTOMATIC WEAPONS WERE USED; ONE A 7.65-MM AND THE OTHER A 9-MM. THE POLICE ADDED THAT NEGHME WAS NOT CARRYING A WEAPON. A BRIEFCASE FOUND NEAR HIS BODY CONTAINED SOME SPEECHES AND A BOOK ON CHILEAN HISTORY.

DEV-MUC3-0426 (LANG SYS INC)

SAN SALVADOR, 5 SEP 89 (REUTER) -- [REPORT] [RICHARD JACOBSEN] [TEXT] A SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT COMMISSION WILL MEET WITH LEFTIST REBELS BEFORE 15 SEPTEMBER IN A PRELIMINARY DIALOGUE TO END ALMOST 10 YEARS OF CIVIL WAR, IT WAS REPORTED TODAY BY A HIGH-RANKING OFFICIAL.

PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI WILL ANNOUNCE ON 7 SEPTEMBER THE CREATION OF A COMMISSION AND THE DATE AND PLACE OF THE TALKS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) REPRESENTATIVES, IT WAS STATED BY COMMUNICATIONS MINISTER MAURICIO SANDOVAL.

"THE MEETING WILL BE HELD BEFORE 15 SEPTEMBER," SANDOVAL TOLD REUTER.

SANDOVAL'S STATEMENTS WERE GIVEN AFTER FMLN COMMANDER ANA GUADALUPE MARTINEZ SAID TODAY IN MEXICO CITY THAT THE REBELS HAD ACCEPTED A GOVERNMENT PROPOSAL TO HOLD TALKS BEFORE 15 SEPTEMBER, THE ANNIVERSARY OF EL SALVADOR'S INDEPENDENCE.

"WE THINK THAT THE MEETING COULD BE HELD IN MEXICO CITY, AND ON 7 SEPTEMBER WE WILL ANNOUNCE A SERIES OF MEASURES TO FACILITATE THE DIALOGUE" -- THE FIRST BETWEEN CRISTIANI'S RIGHT-WING GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN, MARTINEZ SAID IN A NEWS CONFERENCE.

SHE DID NOT RULE OUT THE DECLARATION OF AN UNILATERAL CEASE-FIRE. "PERHAPS YES, PERHAPS NO," MARTINEZ ANSWERED WHEN ASKED ABOUT IT.

SANDOVAL SAID THAT THE TALKS COULD BE HELD IN COSTA RICA OR MEXICO.

"IT IS ALMOST SURE THAT THE TALKS WILL BE HELD IN MEXICO," HE SAID.

SANDOVAL SAID THAT THE PROGRESS ACHIEVED TOWARD THE TALKS WAS PROOF OF THE PLEDGE ASSUMED BY THE GOVERNMENT WHICH WAS SWORN IN ON 1 JUNE TO SOLVE A CONFLICT WHICH HAS COST EL SALVADOR MORE THAN 70,000 LIVES.

"SPECIFIC STEPS ARE BEING TAKEN IN THE SEARCH FOR PEACE," HE SAID.

GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS HAVE EMPHASIZED THAT THE FIRST ROUND OF TALKS WILL PROBABLY PREPARE THE GROUNDWORK FOR FUTURE, MORE SUBSTANTIAL, TALKS.

SANDOVAL DID NOT SAY WHO WOULD COMPRISE THE GOVERNMENT'S DIALOGUE COMMISSION BUT OFFICIALS HAD PREVIOUSLY SAID THAT THE ARMED FORCES AND THE CHURCH WOULD NOT BE REPRESENTED -- A PREVIOUS FMLN DEMAND.

"WE ACCEPT THAT THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION THAT WILL ATTEND THE DIALOGUE BE COMPOSED AS THE GOVERNMENT WANTS," COMMANDER MARTINEZ SAID TODAY. "WE BELIEVE IT IS NEGATIVE FOR THE ARMY NOT TO PARTICIPATE IN A DIALOGUE WHERE THE WAR WILL BE DISCUSSED. IT WILL BE A MISTAKE FOR THE MILITARY NOT TO ATTEND THE MEETING."

VICE PRESIDENT FRANCISCO MERINO TOLD REPORTERS ON 4 SEPTEMBER THAT THE ARMED FORCES -- AND THE OPPOSITION POLITICAL PARTIES -- WOULD BE INCLUDED IN WHAT HE DESCRIBED AS A "SUPPORT COMMISSION" THAT WOULD PLAY AN ADVISORY ROLE IN THE TALKS.

THREE ROUNDS OF TALKS BETWEEN THE FMLN AND PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE'S CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT, WHICH CONCLUDED ITS TERM ON 1 JUNE, FAILED TO ACHIEVE PROGRESS TOWARD THE SOLUTION OF A CIVIL WAR.

TODAY'S ANNOUNCEMENT OF A PEACE DIALOGUE OCCURRED AMID FIERCE CLASHES BETWEEN GOVERNMENT TROOPS AND REBELS IN SEVERAL PARTS OF EL SALVADOR.

A MAJOR CLASH OCCURRED IN EASTERN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT, WHERE THE REBELS KILLED 14 SOLDIERS AND 2 OFFICERS.

THE ARMED FORCES ALSO SAID THEY HAD CAUSED "NUMEROUS" REBEL CASUALTIES DURING A CLASH WHICH OCCURRED NEAR CHILANGA, BUT THEY FAILED TO PROVIDE EXACT FIGURES.

DEV-MUC3-0427 (LANG SYS INC)

SAN SALVADOR, 4 SEP 89 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] COLONEL ORLANDO MONTANO, DEPUTY MINISTER OF DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY, GAVE ASSURANCES TODAY THAT THE ARMED FORCES WILL ESTABLISH A TRUCE ON 14 AND 15 SEPTEMBER, AS REQUESTED BY THE PERMANENT DIALOGUE COMMITTEE, AND THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS PLEDGED TO RESPECT IT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MONTANO] THE NATIONAL DIALOGUE COMMITTEE'S PROPOSAL IS A GOOD ONE AND THE ARMED FORCES APPLAUDS IT, AND IS IN A POSITION TO ACCEPT IT, AS LONG AS THE FMLN ALSO COMPLIES WITH IT. [END RECORDING]

SPEAKING AT A NEWS CONFERENCE, COL MONTANO SAID THAT THE MAIMED FMLN FIGHTERS' PRESENCE AT THE METROPOLITAN CATHEDRAL IS AN INDICATION THAT FMLN LEADERS ABANDON THEIR FIGHTERS WHEN THEY CEASE TO BE USEFUL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MONTANO] I BELIEVE THAT IF THE FMLN WANTED TO SEND THOSE PEOPLE ABROAD, AS THEY HAVE DONE IN THE PAST, THEY COULD VERY WELL HAVE DONE SO. THEY HAVE THE FIGHTERS AT THE CATHEDRAL FOR PROPAGANDA PURPOSES, AND TO GIVE THE IMPRESSION THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS INHUMANE. I HAVE EVEN READ AND HEARD STATEMENTS BY FMLN ALLIES WHO SAY THAT THE SITUATION OF THE MAIMED CANNOT BE NEGOTIATED FOR HUMANITARIAN REASONS. HOWEVER, DID THEY DISPLAY HUMANENESS WHEN THEY BURNED BUSES, LEFT THE PEOPLE WITHOUT ELECTRICITY, OR DESTROYED SO MANY THINGS THAT BENEFIT THE PUBLIC? [END RECORDING]

REFERRING TO THE HOMILY DELIVERED YESTERDAY BY MONSIGNOR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, AUXILIARY BISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, WHO ACCUSED THE AIR FORCE OF BOMBING THE SANTA ELENA CHURCH IN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, COL MONTANO SAID THAT SOME LEFTIST CLERGYMEN DISTORT THE FACTS FOR PROPAGANDA PURPOSES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MONTANO] WITH THEIR HUMANITARIAN IMAGE, THEY OFTEN OPPOSE THE SEARCH FOR PEACE, THEY OPPOSE THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIZATION AND, IN FACT, THEY OFTEN PLAY UP TO THE FMLN. IN REALITY THEIR ATTACKS AND DISPARAGING REMARKS ABOUT THE ARMED FORCES ARE UNFAIR. THEY BLAME THE ARMY FOR THINGS IT IS NOT GUILTY OF OR RESPONSIBLE FOR. [END RECORDING]

TO CONCLUDE, THE MILITARY OFFICER SAID THE ARMY IS CARRYING OUT AN OPERATION TO ENSURE SAFETY DURING THE INDEPENDENCE FESTIVITIES.

DEV-MUC3-0428 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 5 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] PUBLIC ORDER JUDGES WILL BEGIN WORKING OUT OF THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] HEADQUARTERS. THIS IS PART OF THE PROTECTIVE MEASURES THE AUTHORITIES ARE IMPLEMENTING TO PREVENT COLOMBIAN JUDGES FROM BEING MURDERED. FURTHERMORE, SECURITY MEASURES AT COURT ENTRANCES CAN BE NOTED, EVEN SUCH IMPLAUSIBLE MEASURES AS THIS: ALL PEOPLE WHO BEAR WEAPONS MUST TURN THEM IN AT THE ENTRANCE IN EXCHANGE FOR A PIECE OF CARDBOARD.

ALL THESE WEAPONS BELONG TO PEOPLE VISITING THE PALO QUEMADO COURTS. ON SOME DAYS, THERE CAN BE AS MANY AS 100 DIFFERENT CALIBER WEAPONS LYING ON THE TABLE. THEY ARE IDENTIFIED BY SIMPLE, EASILY FORGED PIECES OF CARDBOARD. THIS IS ONE OF THE SECURITY MEASURES USED TO PROTECT JUDGES WORKING HERE. ARMED POLICEMEN CARRY OUT BODY SEARCHES ON VISITORS AND CHECK OUT THE SURROUNDING AREAS, BUT THE JUDGES ARE STILL NERVOUS.

JUDGES WITH THE MOST RESPONSIBILITIES -- PUBLIC ORDER JUDGES -- YEARN FOR SEVERE RESTRICTIONS SUCH AS THOSE THAT PROTECT ITALIAN JUDGES, WHO CONVENE IN SECURE BUNKERS THAT PROTECT THEM FROM DANGER, BOTH TO THEM AND THEIR FAMILIES. LACKING THOSE FACILITIES, COLOMBIAN JUDGES HAVE ACCEPTED THE OFFER MADE BY THE DAS DIRECTOR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ORLANDO MORALES, JUDICIAL BRANCH NATIONAL ASSOCIATION SECRETARY] PUBLIC ORDER JUDGES ARE GOING TO WORK OUT OF THE DAS OFFICES.

[REPORTER] DO YOU KNOW WHEN?

[MORALES] BEGINNING NEXT WEEK, I BELIEVE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0429 (LANG SYS INC)

SAN SALVADOR, 5 SEP 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AFFIRMED TODAY THAT MANY OF THE SALVADORAN REFUGEES IN HONDURAS ARE LINKED TO THE GUERRILLAS BUT THAT HE WILL MAKE A "GOOD WILL" GESTURE TO HAVE APPROXIMATELY 3,800 OF THEM REPATRIATED.

"THE GOVERNMENT IS MAKING A GOOD WILL GESTURE BY ACCEPTING THE REPATRIATION OF THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS WHILE KNOWING THAT MANY OF THEM ARE RELATIVES OF CRIMINAL TERRORISTS (GUERRILLAS), SAID SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT AND INTERIOR MINISTER FRANCISCO MERINO.

THE GOVERNMENTS OF EL SALVADOR AND HONDURAS AND THE UN HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR REFUGEES ARE PREPARING THE RETURN OF THESE SALVADORANS WHO FLED TO HONDURAS AT THE BEGINNING OF THIS DECADE TO ESCAPE FROM THE ARMED CONFLICT.

MERINO STATED: "WE WANT THEM TO UNDERSTAND THAT IF AT ANY GIVEN MOMENT THERE WAS A JUSTIFICATION FOR RESORTING TO VIOLENCE, NOW, 10 YEARS LATER, THERE IS NO JUSTIFICATION AT ALL AND THE MOMENT HAS COME FOR BEGINNING A NORMAL LIFE."

ACCORDING TO THE VICE PRESIDENT, THE FACT THAT THERE ARE NO MALES AMONG THESE REFUGEES IS EVIDENCE THAT THEY HAVE LINKS WITH THE GUERRILLAS.

ALTHOUGH WE DID NOT FIND MEN OF OVER 13 YEARS OF AGE, THERE WERE MANY PREGNANT WOMEN," MERINO TOLD THE PRESS.

THE GOVERNMENT SELECTED SETTLEMENT AREAS FOR THE REPATRIATED, WHERE IT WILL GIVE THEM MEDICAL AND EDUCATIONAL ASSISTANCE AND A FUNCTIONING INFRASTRUCTURE.

FOR THEIR PART, THE REFUGEES HAVE ASKED TO BE ALLOWED TO RETURN TO THEIR PLACES OF ORIGIN, IN WAR-TORN AREAS IN THE NORTHERN PART OF CHALATENANGO, SAN MIGUEL, AND MORAZAN DEPARTMENTS, OR IN LA UNION DEPARTMENT.

"TO SEND THEM THERE," MERINO SAID, "WOULD BE TO CONDEMN THEM TO PERMANENT UNDERDEVELOPMENT. THEY WANT TO RETURN TO PLACES THAT DO NOT PROVIDE WHAT IS NEEDED FOR DEVELOPMENT OR FOR A NORMAL LIFE."

THE CHRISTIAN COMMITTEE FOR DISPLACED SALVADORANS, WHICH CLAIMS TO REPRESENT THE REFUGEES, HAS ACCUSED THE GOVERNMENT OF WANTING TO SEND THE REPATRIATED TO "CONCENTRATION CAMPS GUARDED BY THE ARMED FORCES."

DEV-MUC3-0430 (LANG SYS INC)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 5 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE EXTENSIVE BORDER SHARED BY VENEZUELA AND COLOMBIA IS TODAY, MORE THAN EVER, THE CAUSE OF CONCERN FOR THE CARACAS GOVERNMENT. THE OFFENSIVE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING ORDERED BY PRESIDENT BARCO IS VIEWED BY LOCAL COMMENTATORS AS A DANGEROUS THREAT TO VENEZUELA DUE TO ITS PROXIMITY TO COLOMBIA, WITH WHOM VENEZUELA SHARES OVER 2,000 KM.

THE BORDER WITH COLOMBIA HAS ALWAYS BEEN A CAUSE OF CONCERN FOR VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENTS. ON SEVERAL OCASSIONS VENEZUELA HAD TO FACE RAIDS INTO ITS TERRITORY, AS WELL AS THE KIDNAPPING OF STOCKBREEDERS, SMUGGLING OF GOODS, AND DRUG TRAFFICKING BY COLOMBIAN GUERRILLAS AND CRIMINALS. THE WAR DECLARED BY THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT ON THE MEDELLIN CARTEL OPENS UP THE POSSIBILITY THAT MANY OF THE DRUG CHIEFTAINS, AND PERHAPS SOME DRUG KINGPINS, MAY SEEK REFUGE IN VENEZUELAN TERRITORY.

VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ WARNED THAT IF DRUG TRAFFICKERS ATTEMPT TO TRANSFER THEIR INDUSTRIES TO VENEZUELA THEY WILL HAVE TO "FACE VENEZUELAN JUSTICE, AND CERTAINLY EXTRADITION TRIALS." THE STATES OF ZULIA, TACHIRA, AND APURE --IN WESTERN VENEZUELA -- BORDER COLOMBIAN TERRITORY AND HAVE BEEN THE SCENE OF DRUG TRAFFICKING OPERATIONS MANY TIMES. IN THE PAST FEW DAYS VENEZUELAN SECURITY FORCES HAVE INCREASED VIGILANCE AT THE MAIN BORDER POSTS BECAUSE OF RUMORS THAT DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE BEGUN MOVING TO VENEZUELA.

GOVERNOR OF ZULIA STATE ISMAEL ORDAZ CONFIRMED TO NEWSMEN THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS INTENSIFIED CONTROL AND VIGILANCE MEASURES AT THE BORDER WITH COLOMBIA. HE NOTED THERE IS BROAD COOPERATION BETWEEN THE VENEZUELAN AND COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

DURING A RADIO PROGRAM ON MONDAY, 4 SEPTEMBER, JOURNALIST JOSE VICENTE RANGEL, FORMER MOVEMENT TOWARD SOCIALISM PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, MAINTAINED THAT IT IS NOT AT THIS TIME THAT DRUG TRAFFICKERS ARE ATTEMPTING TO ENTER VENEZUELA BECAUSE THEY ENTERED A LONG TIME AGO. RANGEL MAINTAINED THAT VENEZUELA ANNUALLY SERVES AS A BRIDGE FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING WORTH SOME $20 BILLION. FURTHERMORE, HE SAID, THE EXPENSIVE VENEZUELAN ELECTORAL CAMPAIGNS HAVE ALSO RECEIVED RESOURCES OBTAINED FROM DRUG TRAFFICKING.

THE FIGURES GIVEN BY RANGEL ARE EQUIVALENT TO 66 PERCENT OF THE VENEZUELAN FOREIGN DEBT, WHICH AMOUNTS TO SOME $30 MILLION THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS CURRENTLY TRYING TO RENEGOTIATE. MOREOVER, RANGEL SAID, DURING THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN THAT CONCLUDED WITH THE ELECTION OF CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ IN DECEMBER 1988, POLITICAL PARTIES INVESTED SOME 5 BILLION BOLIVARES (SOME $135 MILLION) IN PROPAGANDA. THIS FIGURE IS EXCESSIVE IF ONE TAKES INTO ACCOUNT THAT, AS ESTABLISHED BY THE LAW, THE STATE ONLY CONTRIBUTES 100 MILLION BOLIVARES ($2.7 MILLION) FOR THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGNS HELD EVERY 5 YEARS.

RANGEL ADDED THAT THE POSSIBLE TRANSFER OF COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKING OPERATION CENTERS TO VENEZUELA IS VERY WORRYING IF ONE TAKES INTO ACCOUNT THAT VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS HAVE OPENLY ADMITTED THE LACK OF VIGILANCE AT THE BORDERS. HOWEVER, WHILE COLOMBIA IS ATTEMPTING, PERHAPS BELATEDLY, NOT TO YIELD TO THE ECONOMIC POWER AND VIOLENCE OF DRUGS, THERE SEEMS TO BE NO AWARENESS IN VENEZUELA ABOUT THE GRAVE DANGER POSED BY THE ALLEGED CHANGE OF ADDRESS WHICH, ACCORDING TO SOME REPORTS, IS BEING PLANNED BY COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

DEV-MUC3-0431 (LANG SYS INC)

LIMA, NO DATE (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [SPEECH] [GARCIA] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] IT IS CLEAR THAT NEO-LIBERALISM IS THE IDEOLOGY OF THE NORTH. IF IN THE PAST LIBERALISM WAS A FACTOR THAT PROMOTED PROGRESS AND INDEPENDENCE IN LATIN AMERICA, NEO- LIBERALISM IS NOW THE STATE IDEOLOGY OF THE MORE POWERFUL NATIONS. IT IS AN AUTHORITARIAN IDEOLOGY THAT DOES NOT QUESTION ALL TYPES OF STATES, BUT ONLY THE STATES OF THE SOUTH. UNDER THE GUISE OF ELIMINATING BUREAUCRACY AND PROMOTING EFFICIENCY, NEO-LIBERALISM WANTS TO DESTROY THE STATE TO ELIMINATE ANY RESISTANCE TO THE HEGEMONY OF THE WORLD MARKET.

WE SHOULD NOT PLAY THAT GAME. IDEOLOGICAL NONALIGNMENT SHOULD THEREFORE REDEFINE THE STATE AND DEFEND ITS STRENGTH IN OUR COUNTRIES.

WHEN I SAY STATE I AM NOT REFERRING MERELY TO THE INDIVIDUAL STATES THAT EVERY ONE OF US REPRESENTS. I AM REFERRING TO AN ACCORD THAT OUR STATES SHOULD REACH IN EACH REGION. WE MUST RECOGNIZE THAT WE ARE UNITED IN CONTINENTAL BLOCS. WE MUST PROMOTE OUR REGIONAL ECONOMY.

ONLY THROUGH REGIONAL INITIATIVES WILL WE HAVE POWER IN THE CURRENT PROCESS OF RESTRUCTURING THE MARKET. IT IS THEREFORE IMPERATIVE TO CALL -- IN EACH CONTINENT -- MORE FREQUENT AND REGULAR MEETINGS OF OUR MOVEMENT. WE MUST ORGANIZE THE NONALIGNED MOVEMENT ON A CONTINENTAL BASIS TO STRENGTHEN IT IN ALL PLACES.

MANY HAVE COME TO THIS MEETING TO PROPOSE AN ADMINISTRATIVE STRUCTURE FOR OUR MOVEMENT TO INSURE ITS CONTINUITY. THIS CAN BE VIEWED AS A SUGGESTION. IT IS A LOT MORE IMPORTANT, THOUGH, TO RECOGNIZE THE EXISTENCE OF REGIONAL DIFFERENCES AND TO CREATE INTERMEDIATE NONALIGNED MOVEMENT ORGANIZATIONS WHEREVER POSSIBLE. THESE INTERMEDIATE ORGANIZATIONS SHOULD STRENGTHEN THE PRINCIPLES OF THE MOVEMENT IN EACH REGION, THUS EXPANDING ITS POWER.

ALTHOUGH IT'S TAKEN SOMETIME, I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE ALREADY ADOPTED THIS APPROACH IN LATIN AMERICA THROUGH THE CREATION OF THE POLITICAL CONSULTATION MECHANISM OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT, WHICH GIVES COMMON ANSWERS TO THE ECONOMIC CRISIS AND TO POLITICAL INTERVENTION.

MR PRESIDENT, IN HONORING OUR FOUNDERS -- TITO, NEHRU, AND NASSER -- I SHOULD STRESS THE ETHICAL SIGNIFICANCE OF NONALIGNMENT. WITHOUT THE POWER OF NUCLEAR BOMBS OR MONEY, WE HAVE UPHELD THE MORAL VALUES OF MANKIND TO HELP IT TO CONTINUE TO STRUGGLE IN ALL FIELDS.

THEREFORE, OUR MOVEMENT CANNOT REMAIN INDIFFERENT TO THE VERY SERIOUS PROBLEM OF DRUG TRAFFICKING AND DRUG ADDICTION, WHICH HAS SPREAD AROUND THE WORLD.

IT IS TRUE THAT THIS IS ESSENTIALLY A PROBLEM THAT AFFECTS RICH COUNTRIES, BECAUSE DRUG ADDICTION REFLECTS THE MOST REFINED STAGE OF CONSUMPTION, THE CONSUMPTION OF INSATISFACTION. YET IT IS ALSO TRUE THAT WE, AS DRUG PRODUCERS OR DEALERS, ARE INVOLUNTARY PARTNERS. LIKE NEO- LIBERALISM, DRUG TRAFFICKING HAS PERVERSELY TRIED TO TAKE OVER.

DRUG TRAFFICKING IS ALSO A FORM OF HEGEMONY BY THE LARGE RICH MARKETS, WHICH ARE THEREBY DISTORTING AND CORRUPTING OUR SOCIETY. DRUG TRAFFICKING ALSO SEEKS TO DESTROY STATES, AS IT IS NOW DOING IN COLOMBIA.

I BELIEVE WE SHOULD RAISE THE BANNER OF MANKIND'S MORAL VALUES; WE SHOULD TELL THE RICH THAT EVEN IF THEY IGNORE OUR CLAIMS FOR JUSTICE, WE WILL NOT IGNORE THEIR YOUTH AND THEIR CHILDREN, WHO MUST BE DEFENDED FROM DRUG ADDICTION.

THE U.S. PRESIDENT WILL FORMULATE A PROPOSAL ON THE SUBJECT TOMORROW, AND WE HOPE IT WILL BE AN ALL-ENCOMPASSING PROPOSAL.

THE PROBLEM IS NOT JUST OVER HELICOPTERS AN AMMUNITION. IT INVOLVES AN ACCORD BETWEEN THE UNITED STATES AND EUROPE, ON ONE SIDE, AND THE COUNTRIES THAT ARE DIRECTLY INVOLVED ON THE OTHER.

THE PRODUCTION OF DRUGS, IN PARTICULAR, CALLS FOR STRUCTURAL TREATMENT, WITHOUT WHICH ANY MILITARY AID WILL BE INSUFFICIENT.

OUR MOVEMENT MUST ADOPT A STRONG STAND AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING AND UNDERTAKE JOINT MEASURES TO ERADICATE IT. THE NONALIGNED MOVEMENT MUST ALSO ADOPT A STRONG STAND AGAINST TERRORISM, PARTICULARLY WHEN IT IS LINKED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING, AS IN PERU.

FAITHFUL TO ITS MORAL PRINCIPLES, THE NONALIGNED MOVEMENT SHOULD STRONGLY REJECT DRUG ADDICTION AND DEATH. THIS WILL SHOW THAT OUR NATIONS' RESPECT FOR HUMAN DIGNITY IS AS STRONG AS THAT OF THE MOST DEVELOPED COUNTRIES.

MR PRESIDENT: WE CAME TO THIS SUMMIT FROM PERU TO REITERATE OUR FAITH IN NONALIGNMENT, OUR ANTI-IMPERIALIST POSITION AGAINST COLONIALISM AND INTERVENTIONISM, AND OUR DECISION TO SIDE WITH THE NATIONS STRUGGLING FOR FREEDOM AND JUSTICE. WE CAME TO DEFEND IDEOLOGICAL NONALIGNMENT. WE CAME TO DEMAND FINANCIAL DISARMAMENT AND THE RECOGNITION OF THE MARKET VALUE OF THE DEBT. WE ARE HERE TO REITERATE OUR ALLEGIANCE TO THE IMMORTAL PRINCIPLES THAT WE UNITED BEHIND 28 YEARS AGO.

I SALUTE THE NATIONS OF THE NONALIGNED MOVEMENT. THANK YOU VERY MUCH. [APPLAUSE]

DEV-MUC3-0432 (LANG SYS INC)

MEDELLIN, 5 SEP 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] A RADIO STATION NEWSMAN HAS REPORTED THAT AN ALLEGED SPOKESMAN FOR "THE EXTRADITABLES," A GROUP THAT CLAIMS TO BE LINKED TO THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE BURNING OF A RESTAURANT TODAY AND A 5 SEPTEMBER SHARPSHOOTER ATTACK AT THE LOCAL AIRPORT.

A NEWSMAN FROM RADIO CARACOL OF MEDELLIN REPORTED RECEIVING A TELEPHONE CALL FROM A MEMBER OF THE EXTRADITABLES CLAIMING RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE BURNING OF A COUNTRYSIDE RESTRAURANT. THE CALLER JUSTIFIED THIS ACTION BY SAYING THAT THE RESTARANTS' OWNERS PAID HOMAGE TO A MILITARY LEADER.

MEDELLIN, WHICH IS THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS' TRADING HEADQUARTERS IN COLOMBIA, WAS HIT BY A WAVE OF THREATS THAT TURNED OUT TO BE NOTHING BUT FALSE ALARMS THAT NEVERTHELESS PROMPTED THE POLICE TO CONSTANTLY PATROL THE CITY AND EVACUATE SHOPPING CENTERS IN SEARCH OF NONEXISTENT BOMBS.

WORKERS SAID THAT THE RESTAURANT, WHOSE OWNER WAS A FOLLOWER OF RECENTLY ASSASSINATED PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LUIS CARLOS GALAN, WAS TORCHED BY RIFLE-TOTING YOUTHS.

THEY LOCKED FOUR WORKERS IN AN OFFICE UNTIL THE FIRE STARTED. THE RESTAURANT SUFFERED 20 MILLION PESOS ($50,000) IN LOSES.

HE ALSO SAID THAT THE EXTRADITABLES ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR AN ATTACK ON 5 SEPTEMBER IN WHICH A MAN DRESSED IN COMBAT GEAR FIRED AN AUTOMATIC RIFLE AT INDUSTRIALISTS AND BUSINESSMEN AT THE MEDELLIN AIRPORT.

THE SHARPSHOOTER, WHO WAS SHOT BY POLICEMEN, MANAGED TO KILL 1 PERSON AND WOUND 12 OTHERS. THE ANONYMOUS CALLER GAVE NO EXPLANATION FOR THE ATTACK, A CARACOL NEWSMAN TOLD REUTER.

TWO WEEKS AGO THE EXTRADITABLES DECLARED "TOTAL WAR" AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO AFTER HE LAUNCHED A CAMPAIGN TO REPRESS THE DRUG BARONS IN WHICH 11,000 INDIVIDUALS WERE ARRESTED AND MILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN PROPERTY OWNED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE CONFISCATED.

DEV-MUC3-0433 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 6 SEP 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE POLICE REPORTED TODAY THAT U.S. JOURNALIST BERNARDETTE PARDO, WHO WAS SENT TO COLOMBIA BY THE SPANISH-SPEAKING UNIVISION TELEVISION NETWORK TO COVER THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT'S "WAR" AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS, WAS INJURED LAST NIGHT DURING AN ATTACK IN MEDELLILN.

IT WAS LEARNED THAT PARDO WAS IN A RESTAURANT IN MEDELLIN ACCOMPANIED BY CAMERAMAN CARLOS CORRALES AND COLOMBIAN MOVIE ACTOR JORGE SAENZ WHEN A MEDIUM-INTENSITY BOMB EXPLODED IN THE ESTABLISHMENT.

PARDO, OF CUBAN ORIGIN, SUFFERED FRACTURES IN HER CLAVICLE AND RIGHT SHOULDER BLADE AND WOUNDS IN HER NECK. SHE IS CURRENTLY AT A HOSPITAL IN MEDELLIN. CORRALES WAS INJURED BY SPLINTERS IN VARIOUS PARTS OF HIS BODY.

THE POLICE REPORTED THAT THE ATTACK WAS APPARENTLY CARRIED OUT BY A COUPLE THAT WAS SITTING AT A TABLE CLOSE TO THE JOURNALISTS. ACCORDING TO REPORTS, A WOMAN WENT TO THE RESTROOM, THEN LEFT IN A HURRY FOLLOWED BY THE MAN, WHO WAS ACCOMPANYING HER, SHORTLY BEFORE THE EXPLOSION.

ON THE NIGHT OF 3 SEPTEMBER UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS PLACED TWO BOMBS IN A PARKING LOT AND GARDEN OF A MEDELLIN HOTEL WHERE SEVERAL FOREIGN JOURNALISTS WERE STAYING. THE JOURNALISTS ARRIVED IN COLOMBIA A FEW DAYS AGO TO COVER THE INTENSIFICATION OF THE GOVERNMENT'S STRUGGLE AGAINST NARCOTICS-TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATIONS.

ALTHOUGH NO ONE WAS INJURED IN THAT INCIDENT, IT WAS CLEAR THAT THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, THE LARGEST DRUG-TRAFFICKING RING IN THE WORLD, HAD DECLARED AN ALL-OUT "WAR" AGAINST FOREIGN JOURNALISTS WHO REMAIN COLOMBIA.

LIKEWISE, COLOMBIAN JOURNALISTS WERE THREATENED A FEW DAYS AFTER THE GOVERNMENT'S OFFENSIVE BEGAN, IN REPRISAL FOR THE HARD BLOWS DEALT TO THE DRUG CARTEL, IN THE PAST 3 WEEKS.

IN A STATEMENT FOR A FRENCH NEWSPAPER, PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, THE MEDELLIN CARTEL'S MAIN "CAPO" SAID THAT JOURNALISTS AND JUDGES "WILL PAY THE CONSEQUENCES" OF THE GOVERNMENT'S STRUGGLE, WHICH HAS RESULTED IN HUNDREDS OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS ARRESTED AND NUMEROUS PROPERTIES OWNED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS CONFISCATED.

THE ATTACK AGAINST THE UNIVISION JOURNALISTS OCCURRED SIMULTANEOUSLY WITH AN ANNOUNCEMENT BY THE POLICE IN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT -- THE CAPITAL OF WHICH IS MEDELLIN -- OF THE ARREST OF FOUR DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHOSE EXTRADITION MAY HAVE BEEN REQUESTED BY THE UNITED STATES.

THE NAMES OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE NOT DISCLOSED TO THE PRESS. HOWEVER, IT WAS LEARNED THAT THEIR ARREST TOOK PLACE DURING INTENSIVE OPERATIONS WHICH TOOK PLACE IN THIS CITY DURING THE PAST FEW HOURS AS A RESULT OF WHICH 21 MERCENARIES OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL HAVE FALLEN.

MEMBERS OF THE SAME NARCOTICS-TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATION DETONATED TWO BOMBS IN FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS AND SET A RESTAURANT ON FIRE IN MEDELLIN, POLICE SPOKESMEN REPORTED.

DEV-MUC3-0436 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 6 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIA AND THE WORLD RECEIVED WITH OPTIMISM THE BUSH ANTIDRUG PLAN. THE U.S. PRESIDENT ANNOUNCED CONTROLS AND PUNISHMENTS FOR THOSE WHO USE DRUGS. HE ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT $8 BILLION HAS BEEN ALLOTED FOR THIS PLAN, WHICH INCLUDES REHABILITATION AND PREVENTION PROGRAMS. THE MEASURES HAVE BEEN CRITICIZED. HOWEVER, THE BUSH PLAN BRINGS HOPE IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG USAGE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSH] THIS IS A COCAINE BY-PRODUCT CALLED CRACK WHICH WAS CONFISCATED A FEW DAYS AGO BY POLICEMEN AT A PARK IN FRONT OF THE WHITE HOUSE. IT COULD HAVE BEEN HEROIN OR PCP. IT LOOKS LIKE CANDY, BUT THIS IS TURNING OUR CITIES INTO BATTLEFIELDS AND IS KILLING OUR CHILDREN. [END RECORDING]

THIS IS HOW PRESIDENT BUSH BEGAN HIS SPEECH, IN WHICH HE DELIVERED HIS PLAN TO U.S. CITIZENS ON FIGHTING DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THE HUGE NUMBER OF DRUG USERS MADE THE GOVERNMENT INCREASE THE $2 BILLION BUDGET LAST YEAR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSH] AS YOU CAN SEE ON THIS CHART, IN 1985 THE GOVERNMENT ESTIMATED THAT 23 MILLION U.S. CITIZENS WERE USING DRUGS ON A CASUAL BASIS; THAT IS, AT LEAST ONCE DURING THE PAST MONTH. LAST YEAR, THIS FIGURE DROPPED BY OVER 1/3, WHICH MEANS THAT 9 MILLION U.S. CITIZENS HAVE CEASED BEING OCCASIONAL DRUG USERS. ALTHOUGH THE OVERALL COCAINE USAGE HAS DROPPED, THE FREQUENT USE OF COCAINE HAS ALMOST DOUBLED IN THE PAST FEW YEARS. THESE ARE THE CASUAL COCAINE USERS, THOSE WHO CONSUME CRACK, AND WHO REPRESENT THE MOST SERIOUS AND URGENT PROBLEM. [END RECORDING]

PRESIDENT BUSH'S ADVISERS SAID THE PRESIDENT IS AWARE OF THE DIFFICULTIES OF THE PLAN, HOWEVER HE BELIEVES THIS IS THE FIRST STEP IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUGS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSH] TODAY, I SENT THIS DOCUMENT. OUR FIRST NATIONAL STRATEGY ON DRUG CONTROL. I SENT IT TO THE CONGRESS. [END RECORDING]

BUSH BELIEVES THAT WITH THIS FORMULA HE WILL DEFEAT DRUG USAGE IN HIS COUNTRY, DESPITE CRITICISM FROM SOME U.S. CONGRESSMEN.

DEV-MUC3-0437 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 6 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [EXCERPT] THE MEDELLIN CARTEL REACTED WITH A CAMPAIGN OF ATTACKS TO U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH'S ANTIDRUG PROGRAM. AS OF THIS MORNING THE SPEECH HAD NOT ELICITED ANY OFFICIAL COMMENT ON THE PART OF THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENCY.

ONLY COMMUNICATIONS MINISTER CARLOS ELMOS STATED IN VERY GENERAL TERMS THAT THE PROBLEM CONTINUES TO BE "FUNDAMENTALLY THAT OF THE CONSUMPTION IN THE UNITED STATES," WHICH HE ADDED MUST "PUNISH THE CONSUMERS."

SHORTLY AFTER PRESIDENT BUSH'S SPEECH, A WAVE OF ATTACKS SHOOK MEDELLIN, THE GENERAL HEADQUARTERS OF THE COUNTRY'S PRINCIPAL DRUG TRAFFICKERS. ACCORDING TO A POLICE REPORT ISSUED TODAY 11 PERSONS, INCLUDING 2 NEWSMEN, WERE WOUNDED IN THE ATTACKS.

THE BOGOTA NEWSPAPERS DEDICATED THEIR MAIN HEADLINES THIS MORNING TO THE U.S. PRESIDENT'S SPEECH. IN GENERAL THEY COMPARED HIS SPEECH TO A DECLARATION OF WAR: "BUSH WAGES WAR (EL ESPECTADOR), "BUSH DECLARES WAR" (EL SIGLO), "8 BILLION AGAINST DRUGS" (EL TIEMPO).

THE NEWSPAPERS DID NOT DEDICATE ANY EDITORIAL TO BUSH'S SPEECH, BUT LIMITED THEMSELVES TO PUBLISHING EXCERPTS OF HIS SPEECH, TAKING SPECIAL NOTE OF THE 5-YEAR $2 BILLION AID PLAN FOR COLOMBIA, PERU, AND BOLIVIA.

THE COLOMBIAN TELEVISION STATIONS, WHICH HAD ANNOUNCED THAT THEY WOULD CARRY A LIVE BROADCAST OF THE OVERALL ANTIDRUG PLAN, FINALLY ENDED UP ONLY TRANSMITTING EXCERPTS OF THE SPEECH ON A DELAYED BASIS, WITHOUT EXPLAINING THE REASON FOR THE CHANGE OF PLANS.

ONLY CARACOL RADIO REBROADCAST THE TEXT OF PRESIDENT BUSH'S SPEECH ON A DELAYED BASIS WITH A SIMULTANEOUS SPANISH TRANSLATION.

DESPITE THE CURFEW IMPLEMENTED 1 WEEK AGO IN MEDELLIN AND THE MAJOR MILITARY PRESENCE IN THE COUNTRY'S SECOND LARGEST CITY, TWO BANK BRANCHES AND A RESTAURANT WERE BLOWN UP WHILE A RESTAURANT WAS BURNED.

DEV-MUC3-0438 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 6 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] THIS STATION HAS JUST CONFIRMED THAT EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, REPORTED TO BE THE FINANCIAL WIZARD OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES TODAY.

IN A FEW HOURS, AN ATLANTA, GEORGIA COURT WILL RECEIVE MARTINEZ, WHO HAS BEEN EXTRADITED BY THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT AFTER HE WAS INDICTED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT ON CHARGES THAT HE LAUNDERED $1.1 BILLION. INCLUDING MARTINEZ, 15 COLOMBIANS HAVE BEEN EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES, 14 OF THEM DURING THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT'S TENURE, WHILE THE EXTRADITION TREATY WITH THE UNITED STATES WAS IN FORCE.

THE FIRST EXTRADITION WAS EFFECTED ON THE SAME GROUNDS AS THAT SERVING TO JUSTIFY THIS MEASURE TOWARD MARTINEZ-- MONEY LAUNDERING. AFTER BOTERO [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED], THE MOST FAMOUS CASES WERE THOSE OF CARLOS LEHDER, WHOSE EXTRADITION WAS ARRANGED FOR IN LESS THAN 24 HOURS. WHEN THE SUPREME COURT DECLARED THE TREATY UNENFORCEABLE, EXTRADITIONS WERE SUSPENDED UNTIL TODAY, WHEN A NEW INSTRUMENT WAS UTILIZED. THIS INSTRUMENT WAS ANNOUNCED BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO THE SAME NIGHT PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL LUIS CARLOS GALAN WAS MURDERED. THIS IS AN ADMINISTRATIVE RECOURSE THAT EMPOWERS THE PRESIDENT TO MAKE ALL DECISIONS.

DEV-MUC3-0439 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 6 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] LUZ AMPARO GOMEZ SERNA, A 29-YEAR-OLD WOMAN FROM CALI, WAS MURDERED AT 1620 THIS AFTERNOON. THE LA GRAN COLOMBIA UNIVERSITY LAWYER HAD JUST LEFT A FRUIT STAND IN THE POLO CLUB NEIGHBORHOOD IN NORTHERN BOGOTA AND WAS GETTING INTO A RENAULT STATION WAGON DRIVEN BY HER BROTHER, WILLIAM, WHEN A YOUNG MAN APPROACHED HER AND SHOT HER THREE TIMES IN THE HEAD WITH A 9-MM GUN. THE KILLER, A YOUNG MAN, ESCAPED IN A GREEN SAMURAI CAMPER THAT WAS WAITING FOR HIM A FEW BLOCKS FROM THE SITE OF THE MURDER.

ACCORDING TO LUZ AMPARO GOMEZ SERNA'S FAMILY, SHE HAD NEVER BEEN THREATENED. UNTIL A FEW MONTHS AGO, SHE WORKED AT THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR THE NATIONAL AND JUDICIAL POLICE AND SHE HAD SPECIALIZED ABROAD IN CRIMINAL PROCEDURES. SHE WAS CURRENTLY THE LAWYER FOR EMERALD DEALER ANGEL GAITAIN MAECHA AND WAS DEFENSE ATTORNEY IN THE CASE OF THE EL PORTAL APARTMENTS IN NORTHERN BOGOTA.

SHE WAS MARRIED AND HAD NO CHILDREN. HER HUSBAND, JAIME CASTRO, IS CURRENTLY IN SPAIN. A CRIMINAL COURT JUDGE HAS ORDERED A CORONER'S REPORT.

DEV-MUC3-0442 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 7 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] A 20-KG BOMB WENT OFF AT A BRANCH OF THE CENTRAL MORTAGE BANK LOCATED IN THE BELEN NEIGHBORHOOD OF THE CITY OF MEDELLIN LAST NIGHT, ONLY 2 HOURS BEFORE THE CURFEW WENT INTO EFFECT.

ON THIS OCCASION, THE TERRORISTS' TARGET WAS A BRANCH OF THE CENTRAL MORTGAGE BANK LOCATED IN THE BELEN NEIGHBORHOOD. ACCORDING TO BOMB EXPERTS WHO WORK FOR THE MEDELLIN METROPOLITAN POLICE, THE DYNAMITE CHARGE, WHICH PARTIALLY DESTROYED THE BANK FACILITIES, WEIGHED 20 KG. FORTUNATELY, NO ONE WAS KILLED OR WOUNDED IN THIS ATTACK.

WHILE THIS WAS HAPPENING, ANOTHER DYNAMITE CHARGE WAS DEFUSED AT THE SOCIAL SAVINGS BANK IN ITAHUI.

ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORITIES' REPORT, THE TERRORIST ATTACKS CARRIED OUT IN MEDELLIN OVER THE PAST 12 DAYS HAVE KILLED 2 PEOPLE AND WOUNDED AT LEAST 20 OTHERS, INCLUDING JOURNALIST BERNARDETT PARDO OF UNIVISION NETWORK, WHO, ALONG WITH HER CAMERAMAN, WITNESSED THE EXPLOSION OF A BOMB AS THEY WERE HAVING DINNER AT A RESTAURANT.

THE PROPERTY DAMAGE CAUSED BY ALL THE BOMB ATTACKS IN MEDELLIN ADD UP TO APPROXIMATELY 300 MILLION PESOS. EIGHT PEOPLE HAVE BEEN ARRESTED AND CHARGED WITH TERRORIST ACTIVITIES.

DURING THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE IN MEDELLIN, THE AUTHORITIES HAVE DEFUSED 14 BOMBS AND CONFISCATED 5 ROCKETS.

DEV-MUC3-0453 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 9 SEP 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN DEFENSE MINISTRY SPOKESMEN REPORTED TODAY THAT ARMY TROOPS DEALT A HARSH BLOW TO THE MEDELLIN DRUG CARTEL OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS. THE ARMY TROOPS SEIZED FIVE FARMS OWNED BY GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, THE SECOND MOST IMPORTANT MEDELLIN DRUG CARTEL CHIEF.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL REPORTS, THE TROOPS ARRIVED AT A RURAL AREA IN CENTRAL BOYACA PORT MUNICIPALITY AND RAIDED FIVE FARMS WHICH, ACCORDING TO PRELIMINARY EVIDENCE, WERE USED BY THE MAFIA TO TRAIN RIGHTIST PARAMILITARY GROUPS.

ACCORDING TO SECRET POLICE INVESTIGATIONS, THE PARAMILITARY SQUADS WERE FORMED BY THE MEDELLIN CARTEL TO PROTECT ITS INTERESTS. THE MEMBERS OF THOSE SQUADS WERE TRAINED BY ISRAELI MERCENARIES HEADED BY FORMER LT COL JAIR KLEIN.

IT WAS REPORTED THAT SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE COLOMBIAN OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE NARCO-CRIMINAL GROUPS 3 WEEKS AGO, JOINT ARMY AND POLICE TROOPS HAVE SEIZED 15 FARMS AND SEVERAL URBAN HOUSES OWNED BY GONZALEZ GACHA.

FREDDY RODRIGUEZ CELADES, 17, SON OF RODRIGUEZ GACHA, IS STILL UNDER ARREST, AFTER HAVING BEEN CAPTURED BY THE AUTHORITIES ALONG WITH OTHER DRUG TRAFFICKERS DURING AN OPERATION AGAINST ONE OF THE FARMS OWNED BY THE MAFIA LEADER.

MEANWHILE, IT WAS LEARNED TODAY THAT FERNANDO GALEANO BERRIO, SUSPECTED TO BE RODRIGUEZ GACHA'S FINANCE CHIEF, WHO WAS ARRESTED A FEW DAYS AGO, WAS RELEASED BY A CRIMINAL JUDGE.

GALEANO BERRIO LEFT HIS CELL ON THURSDAY, 7 SEPTEMBER, ALTHOUGH HE IS ONE OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHOSE EXTRADITION HAS BEEN REQUESTED BY THE UNITED STATES AND DESPITE BEING CHARGED WITH THE MURDER OF SEVERAL LEFTIST POLITICAL LEADERS.

ACCORDING TO INVESTIGATIONS, GALEANO WAS IN CHARGE OF HANDLING RODRIGUEZ GACHA'S FINANCES. THUS, THE POSSIBILITY THAT GALEANO WORKED CLOSELY WITH EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, MEDELLIN DRUG CARTEL FINANCE CHIEF, IS NOT RULED OUT. MARTINEZ ROMERO WAS EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES ON WEDNESDAY, 6 SEPTEMBER.

REPORTS PUBLISHED BY THE BOGOTA MORNING NEWSPAPER EL TIEMPO INDICATE THAT THE AUTHORITIES HAVE CONFISCATED 50 VEHICLES OWNED BY DRUG BARON RODRIGUEZ GACHA.

ACCORDING TO THE DOCUMENTS FOUND AT THE MEDELLIN CARTEL ACCOUNTING OFFICE, WHICH OPERATED IN THE MIDDLE OF DOWNTOWN BOGOTA, RODRIGUEZ GACHA COULD OWN APPROXIMATELY 400 VEHICLES, MANY OF THEM ARMORED VEHICLES OR VEHICLES WITH POWERFUL RADIO COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT.

SIMILARLY, THE ARMY SEIZED A FARM OWNED BY PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA IN BOYACA PORT MUNICIPALITY. ESCOBAR IS CONSIDERED THE WORLD'S BIGGEST DRUG TRAFFICKER.

MILITARY SPOKESMEN SAID THAT ONE OF THE MANY MAFIA SCHOOLS FOR GUNMEN OPERATED AT THAT FARM. THOSE GUNMEN ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MASSACRES OF PEASANTS WHO WORKED IN THE NORTHWESTERN BANANA REGION OF URABA.

THE OPERATIONS AGAINST ESCOBAR GAVIRIA CONTINUED YESTERDAY WHEN THE GROUP OF MERCENARIES WHO SERVED AS ESCORTS FOR ESCOBAR GAVIRIA'S WIFE, MARIA VICTORIA HENAO, WAS BROKEN UP.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS, CLOSE AIDS OF THE CAPO WERE MEMBERS OF A CRIMINAL GROUP CALLED "LOVE FOR MEDELLIN." THIS GROUP IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MURDERS OF SEVERAL PROSTITUTES, HOMOSEXUALS, AND BEGGARS.

IT WAS ALSO KNOWN THAT THE MEMBERS OF THE AFOREMENTIONED GROUP PLACED A CAR BOMB ACROSS FROM THE MEDELLIN TELEPHONE COMPANY, INJURING FIVE PEDESTRIANS AND CAUSING MILLIONS OF PESOS IN PROPERTY DAMAGE.

THE DYNAMITE ATTACKS, WHICH HAVE BECOME THE MAFIA RESPONSE TO THE GOVERNMENT'S HEAVY OFFENSIVE, CONTINUED TODAY WHEN AN EXPLOSIVE DEVICE WENT OFF AT A PRIVATE FACTORY LOCATED IN NORTHWESTERN ITAGUI MUNICIPALITY.

DEV-MUC3-0454 (LANG SYS INC)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 3 SEP 89 (THE NEWS) -- [ARTICLE] [FELIX ARCINIEGA] [TEXT] AN EMERGENCY MEETING OF ATTORNEY GENERALS AND OTHER TOP OFFICIALS FROM NINE LATIN AMERICAN NATIONS TOOK PLACE IN MEXICO CITY TO ESTABLISH A "COMMON FRONT" AND PROTECT ONE ANOTHER AGAINST TAKEOVER EFFORTS BY DISPLACED DRUG BARONS AND THEIR ARMED MAFIAS.

NAMED THE SEVENTH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE FOR DRUG CONTROL, IT WAS HELD AUG 29-31 HERE, AND REPRESENTATIVES PRAISED COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES FOR THEIR IMMEDIATE REPRISAL AGAINST DRUG LORDS AND THEIR MAFIAS.

ARGENTINA, CHILE, COLOMBIA, EL SALVADOR, GUATEMALA PERU, COSTA RICA, BRAZIL AND OTHERS ALL EXPRESSED THE SAME APPREHENSION, INVASION BY DISPLACED COLOMBIAN DRUG DEALERS.

THE UNITED STATES, ATTENDING UNOFFICIALLY, REPORTEDLY DID NOT SAY MUCH BUT IMMEDIATELY DISPATCHED 65 MILLION DOLLARS WORTH OF SOPHISTICATED MILITARY HARDWARE DELIVERED FRIDAY TO COLOMBIA BY TWO ENORMOUS C-130'S. HERE, MAFIA WARLORDS OPENLY THREATENED TO CARRY OUT THEIR TERRORIST BOMBINGS AND KILLINGS "IN BROAD DAYLIGHT TO SHOW WE CANNOT BE STOPPED."

MEXICAN ATTORNEY GENERAL ENRIQUE ALVAREZ DEL CASTILLO CONGRATULATED THOSE IN ATTENDANCE AND OFFERED THE EXPERIENCE MEXICO HAD ACQUIRED DURING 10 YEARS OF AN AGGRESSIVE DRUG WAR.

BESIDES MORAL SUPPORT, MEXICO UNDERLINED THE NEED FOR COORDINATED EFFORTS IN LAWS AND ACTION. FIRST, THAT COURTS HAND DOWN STIFF SENTENCES; SECOND, THAT NO BAIL BE GRANTED IN DRUG TRIALS; THIRD, THAT ALL PROPERTY DERIVED FROM DRUG PROFITS BE CONFISCATED AND LEGALLY USED TO DEFRAY COSTS OF COMBATTING DRUG TRAFFIC.

IN THE FINAL RESOLUTION, THE NINE NATIONS ACCEPTED TO EXCHANGE INFORMATION, COORDINATE ALL ACTIVITIES JOINTLY - BUT CARRY THEM OUT SEPARATELY BECAUSE OF THE DELICATE ISSUE OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY - COMPLETE COOPERATION IN ALL AREAS AND TO REGARD THE DRUG EFFORT AS AN INTERNATIONAL PROBLEM WHERE PRODUCER, DEALER AND USER MUST ALL BE COMBATTED.

ON FRIDAY, BRAZIL AND COLOMBIA AGREED TO JOINTLY PROTECTING THEIR BORDERS TO KEEP DRUG DEALERS OUT AND AWAY FROM THOSE THAT HAVE BECOME A SERIOUS PROBLEM IN BRAZIL.

THIS COOPERATION IS BEING SOUGHT FOR ALL CASES WHERE THERE MAY BE DANGER. AND SECRETLY, EVERY NATION IS FEARFUL OF WHAT A CONCENTRATED ATTACK BY THE NARCOTIC MAFIA AND THE TERRORISM, POLITICAL AND DE FACTO, DRUG LORDS CAN BUY WITH THEIR ENORMOUS WEALTH.

DEV-MUC3-0457 (LANG SYS INC)

GUATEMALA CITY, 10 SEP 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] TWO POLICEMEN WERE INJURED AND 13 BUSINESS ESTABLISHMENTS WERE DESTROYED AS THE RESULT OF TWO TERRORIST ATTACKS LAST NIGHT IN THE GUATEMALAN CAPITAL.

GUATEMALA CITY FIRE DEPARTMENT SPOKESMEN REPORTED THAT THE BOMBS WENT OFF AT APPROXIMATELY 0400 GMT ON 10 SEPTEMBER IN A RESIDENTIAL AREA IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF THE CITY.

THE SOURCES ADDED THAT THE FIRST BOMB EXPLODED IN A PUBLIC BUILDING, INJURING 2 POLICEMEN AND DESTROYING 13 BUSINESS ESTABLISHMENTS. HOWEVER, THE AMOUNT OF DAMAGE HAS NOT YET BEEN DETERMINED.

THE SOURCES ALSO SAID THAT UNDIDENTIFIED MEN HURLED A GRENADE AT THE "CAMINO REAL" HOTEL, TO THE SOUTH OF THE CAPITAL, BUT WHEN IT EXPLODED IT ONLY MADE A HOLE IN THE GROUND.

THIS WEEK DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL HECTOR ALEJANDRO GRAMAJO ACCUSED ARMY DISSIDENTS, EXTREME RIGHT-WINGERS, AND PRIVATE ENTERPRISES OF BEING DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE GUATEMALAN TERRORIST ACTS.

IN LESS THAN 1 MONTH, 11 LEADERS OF THE ASSOCIATION OF UNIVERSITY STUDENTS HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED BY UNIDENTIFIED MEN. THE POLICE HAVE SAID THEY HAVE CLUES CONCERNING THE STUDENTS' WHEREABOUTS, BUT HAVE NOT DISCLOSED THEM.

DEV-MUC3-0459 (LANG SYS INC)

BOGOTA, 10 SEP 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS TODAY BROKE INTO A FARM OWNED BY CARLOS OSSA, MANAGER OF THE COLOMBIAN INSTITUTE OF AGRARIAN REFORM (INCORA), KILLED A WATCHMAN, AND SET FIRE TO THE FARM. AUTHORITIES VIEW THIS ACTION AS A CONTINUATION OF TERRORISM BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN THE COUNTRY.

THE INCIDENT OCCURRED IN SEVILLA MUNICIPALITY (370 KM FROM BOGOTA), WHERE APPROXIMATELY FIVE INDIVIDUALS SHOT TO DEATH A WATCHMAN WHO TRIED TO PREVENT THEM FROM ENTERING THE FARM.

AFTER THE 18 AUGUST ASSASSINATION OF SENATOR AND PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LUIS CARLOS GALAN, THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT ORDERED A RELENTLESS OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE DRUG MAFIAS, WHICH HAVE REACTED BY CARRYING OUT BOMB ATTACKS AND THREATING TO KILL OFFICIALS, JUDGES, BUSINESSMEN, AND JOURNALISTS.

AS INCORA MANAGER, OSSA HAS LAUNCHED AN INTENSE CAMPAIGN TO CONFISCATE LAND OWNED BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND DISTRIBUTE IT TO PEASANTS AS PART OF THE AGRARIAN REFORM BEING CARRIED OUT BY THE ADMINISTRATION OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO.

"WE ARE NOT RULING OUT THAT THE CRIMINALS ARE TAKING REPRISALS AGAINST OSSA AND ALL THE OFFICIALS WHO REJECT THE ACTIVITIES BY THOSE CRIMINALS," A POLICE SPOKESMAN TOLD DPA.

IN ANOTHER ACTION ATTRIBUTED TO THE MAFIAS, SEVERAL MEN LAST NIGHT WOUNDED A WATCHMAN AT AN APARTMENT BUILDING WHERE MARIA VICTORIA GALAN, THE SISTER OF GALAN, LIVES. ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL REPORT, THEY WERE PLANNING TO ATTACK HER.

THE RESOLUTE ACTION OF WATCHMAN JAVIER VELASCO PREVENTED THE GUNMEN, WHO WERE RIDING MOTORCYCLES, FROM ENTERING MRS GALAN'S APARTMENT.

MEANWHILE, MEMBERS OF THE ARMY, POLICE, AND SECURITY FORCES CONTINUED TO PATROL THE COLOMBIAN CITIES TO PREVENT TERRORIST ACTIONS BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHO HAVE THREATENED TO KILL 10 COLOMBIAN JUDGES FOR EVERY MAFIA CHIEF WHO IS EXTRADITED.

THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT LAST NIGHT AUTHORIZED THE EXTRADITION OF ELENA BEATRIZ ZUNIGA RODRIGUEZ, ACCUSED BY THE U.S. AUTHORITIES OF SMUGGLING COCAINE. THIS BRINGS TO TWO THE NUMBER OF COLOMBIANS WHOSE EXTRADITION IS AUTHORIZED IN LESS THAN A WEEK. EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, SUSPECTED "FINANCE CHIEF" OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS SENT TO THE UNITED STATES ON WEDNESDAY.

THE BOMBINGS HAVE MAINLY AFFECTED BOGOTA AND MEDELLIN, WHERE AUTHORITIES HAVE IMPLEMENTED UNPRECEDENTED SECURITY MEASURES TO PREVENT TERRORIST ACTIONS.

A POLICE SPOKESMAN SAID THAT SECURITY HAS BEEN REINFORCED IN TERMINALS, GOVERNMENT BUILDINGS, MEDIA OFFICES, AND AQUEDUCTS OF THE MAIN CITIES BECAUSE OF CONSTANT THREATS THAT THE MAFIAS WILL BLOW UP THOSE LOCATIONS.

MANY RESIDENTS OF BOGOTA HAVE BEEN COMMENTING ON RUMORS THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS PLAN TO PLACE TOXIC SUBSTANCES IN THE AQUEDUCT OF THIS CITY OF 6 MILLION PEOPLE. THE RUMOR HAS NEITHER BEEN DENIED NOR CONFIRMED BY AUTHORITIES.

DEV-MUC3-0463 (LANG SYS INC)

MEDELLIN, 11 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PABLO PELAEZ GONZALES, 45, A FORMER MAYOR OF MEDELLIN, WAS MURDERED TODAY BY GUNMEN WHO FIRED SEVEN SHOTS AT HIM, SAID MEDICAL SOURCES AT GENERAL HOSPITAL, WHERE THE VICTIM WAS TAKEN AFTER THE ATTACK.

PELAEZ GONZALEZ WAS INTERCEPTED BY SEVERAL UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS WHILE ENROUTE TO HIS OFFICE FROM HIS HOME IN THE EL POBLADO NEIGHBORHOOD IN SOUTHERN MEDELLIN, COLOMBIA'S SECOND LARGEST CITY, WHERE A CURFEW HAS BEEN IN EFFECT SINCE 30 AUGUST.

THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE AT APPROXIMATELY 0845 (1345 GMT) WHEN, ACCORDING TO WITNESSES, AT LEAST THREE UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS FIRED FROM VARIOUS ANGLES AT PELAEZ' VEHICLE.

THE DRIVER OF THE VEHICLE, WHOM AUTHORITIES HAVE NOT YET IDENTIFIED, WAS ALSO KILLED IN THE ATTACK.

PELAEZ GONZALEZ HAD PRESIDED OVER A "SESSION FOR PEACE" ON 18 AUGUST IN MEDELLIN, WHICH IS CONSIDERED ONE OF THE MOST VIOLENT CITIES IN THE WORLD.

ON THAT VERY DAY, COLONEL WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO OF THE POLICE FORCE IN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, WHOSE CAPITAL IS MEDELLIN, WAS MURDERED.

PELAEZ GONZALEZ WAS MAYOR OF MEDELLIN BETWEEN 3 MAY 1984 AND THE END OF 1985, AND WAS CURRENTLY THE PRESIDENT OF THE "TIN PLATE AND LAMINATING COMPANY" (HOLASA).

THE AUTHORITIES HAVE ATTRIBUTED THE MURDER TO THE DRUG MAFIAS, WHO ON 24 AUGUST ANNOUNCED A COUNTEROFFENSIVE TO THE GOVERNMENT MEASURES, WHICH ARE A DECLARATION OF "TOTAL WAR" AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

ON 24 AUGUST, AFTER A NUMBER OF ATTACKS, THE "EXTRADITABLES," THE ARMED BRANCH OF THE "MEDELLIN CARTEL," WHO, WITH THE CALI CARTEL ARE CONSIDERED THE WORLD'S LEADING COCAINE PRODUCERS AND DISTRIBUTORS, SAID THAT THEY WOULD RESPOND TO THE WAR WITH ATTACKS ON "POLITICIANS, JUDGES, JUSTICES, UNION AND COMPANY PRESIDENTS, JOURNALISTS, AND THE OLIGARCHY."

MEDELLIN, 200 KM TO THE NORTHWEST OF BOGOTA, HAS BEEN BESET BY A WAVE OF VIOLENCE UNLEASHED BY THE DRUG CARTELS, WHICH OVER THE PAST 3 WEEKS HAVE CARRIED OUT OVER 30 BOMB ATTACKS THAT HAVE LEFT MANY PEOPLE INJURED AND CAUSED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE.

DEV-MUC3-0466 (LANG SYS INC)

VIENNA (AUSTRIA), 12 SEP 89 (DER STANDARD) -- [TEXT] "NONE OF US WANTED THE WAR. NOW THAT WE STARTED IT, WE HAVE TO WIN IT." WITH THESE WORDS MARGARET J. ANSTEE, DIRECTOR GENERAL OF THE UN OFFICE IN VIENNA, OPENED THE SECOND INTERREGIONAL MEETING OF THE HEADS OF NATIONAL DRUG LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCIES (HONLEA) IN VIENNA ON MONDAY [11 SEPTEMBER].

THE CONFERENCE, WHICH IS SCHEDULED TO LAST UNTIL FRIDAY, FOCUSES ON INTERNATIONAL TRENDS AND STRATEGIES IN THE FIGHT AGAINST THE ILLEGAL NARCOTICS TRADE, AS WELL AS THE DRAWING UP OF A FIRST "POSITIVE BALANCE SHEET" SINCE THE VIENNA HONLEA MEETING OF 1986, AND THE 1987 INTERNATIONAL NARCOTICS CONFERENCE. SPECIAL EMPHASIS WILL BE PUT ON THE RECENT DEVELOPMENTS IN COLOMBIA AND ALL OTHER PARTS OF LATIN AMERICA.

"WITH ITS FIGHT AGAINST THE ILLEGAL NARCOTICS TRADE, COLOMBIA HAS ASSURED ITSELF A PLACE IN THE HISTORY OF THE WORLD WAR AGAINST DRUGS," ANSTEE SAID. THIS "BATTLE" IS NOT AN ISOLATED PROBLEM OF AN INDIVIDUAL STATE, BUT A CONCERN OF THE WHOLE WORLD, SHE SAID.

"EVEN THE MURDER OF A COLOMBIAN JUDGE, POLICE HEAD, OR POLITICIAN, WHO WAS TRYING HARD TO BRING DRUG DEALERS TO COURT, IS NOT MERELY AN ATTACK AGAINST HIS PERSON AND HIS FAMILY, NOT ONLY ONE AGAINST THE LAWS AND THE GOVERNMENT BUT ALSO AN ASSAULT AGAINST US ALL, THE UN OFFICIAL SAID.

SHE EMPHASIZED THAT IT IS NOW PARTICULARLY IMPORTANT TO ENSURE THAT THE ANTI-DRUG CONVENTION, WHICH WAS CONCLUDED IN 1988 AND, UP TO NOW, SIGNED BY 71 STATES, TRANSLATES INTO CONCRETE STEPS AS SOON AS POSSIBLE -- EVEN BEFORE THE PROTRACTED RATIFICATION PROCEDURE IS CONCLUDED.

JAVIER CUELLO TREJO, THE MEXICAN WHO WAS ELECTED CHAIRMAN OF THE CONFERENCE BY ACCLAMATION, SAID: "THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUGS IS NOT ONLY OF ENORMOUS IMPORTANCE FOR LAWS AND GOVERNMENTS BUT ALSO FOR THE SURVIVAL OF THE ENTIRE MANKIND. WITHOUT ANY EXCEPTION, WE AND OUR PEOPLES ARE VICTIMS OF THOSE PEOPLE WHO LIVE FROM SUPPRESSING OTHER PEOPLE."

THE SITUATION IN THE SPHERES OF THE NARCOTICS TRADE AND CONSUMPTION HAS DRAMATICALLY DETERIORATED EVERYWHERE IN THE WORLD DURING THE PAST 3 YEARS, CHRISTOPH HARSDORF, HEAD OF THE FRG DELEGATION, NOTED AT THE PERIPHERY OF THE UN CONFERENCE.

DEV-MUC3-0468 (LANG SYS INC)

SAN JOSE (COSTA RICA), 12 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION OF GUATEMALA [CDH] CHARGED HERE TODAY THE "SHARED RESPONSIBILITY" OF PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO AND THE SECRET SERVICE OF THE ARMY (G-2) IN THE DEATH OF FOUR UNIVERSITY STUDENTS, WHOSE BRUTALLY MUTILATED BODIES WERE FOUND ON 10 SEPTEMBER IN A GUATEMALA CITY SUBURB.

THE FINDING COMES IN THE MIDDLE OF A WAVE OF KIDNAPPINGS, KILLINGS, AND DYNAMITE ATTACKS WHICH WERE UNLEASHED STARTING IN MID-JULY AND WHICH HAS SHOCKED THE GUATEMALANS. THE WHEREABOUTS OF SEVEN OTHER STUDENTS, KIDNAPPED BY ALLEGED DEATH SQUADS, REMAIN UNKNOWN. THESE SQUADS HAVE BEEN ON THE RAMPAGE SINCE 23 AUGUST.

IN A COMMUNIQUE TO VARIOUS POLITICAL, TRADE UNION, AND HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANIZATIONS, THE CHDG BRANCH IN SAN JOSE REQUESTED "URGENTLY" THE SENDING OF MESSAGES TO THE GUATEMALAN EMBASSIES, GOVERNMENT, AND ARMY CONDEMNING THE "IMPUNITY" OF THE DEATH SQUADS.

TWO OF THE MURDERED VICTIMS -- SILVIA AZURDIA AND HER HUSBAND VICTOR HUGO RODRIGUEZ -- WERE ABDUCTED BY EIGHT MEN IN CIVILIAN CLOTHES BEFORE WITNESSES WHO EVEN PROVIDED THE AUTHORITIES WITH THE LICENSE PLATE NUMBERS OF THE TWO VEHICLES USED BY THE KIDNAPPERS.

THE CDHG EXPRESSED "DEEP CONCERN OVER THESE EVENTS WHICH REFLECT A TOTAL LACK OF POLITICAL WILLINGNESS" ON THE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT TO END REPRESSION AGAINST THE PEOPLE.

ACCORDING TO HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, GUATEMALA HOLDS A RECORD IN THE HEMISPHERE, 40,000 MISSING PERSONS IN THE LAST 20 YEARS.

ON 11 SEPTEMBER, IT WAS OFFICIALLY REPORTED THAT THE MUTILATED AND BULLET-RIDDLED BODIES OF THREE MORE UNIDENTIFIED GUATEMALANS WERE FOUND.

ONE OF THE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS KILLED LAST WEEKEND WAS CARLOS HUMBERTO CABRERA, WHO HAD RETURNED TO GUATEMALA AFTER SEVERAL YEARS OF EXILE TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE GUARANTEES ANNOUNCED BY THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT TO REPATRIATE HOME ANY GUATEMALAN WHO WISHED TO COME, THE LOCAL PRESS REPORTED TODAY.

ON THE OTHER HAND, HUMBERTO CHUTA, A BROTHER OF ONE OF THE VICTIMS, STATED THAT "IT SEEMS THAT WE ARE GOING TO LIVE ALL OUR LIVES AS IF WE WERE DOGS." HE REQUESTED CEREZO "DO WHATEVER IS NECESSARY TO INVESTIGATE THE SITUATION, IF HE IS NOT RESPONSIBLE FOR WHAT HAPPENED."

DEV-MUC3-0469 (LANG SYS INC)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] SINCE A MINE IS A WEAPON OF A MILITARY NATURE AND SINCE ITS USE HAS INCREASED IN THE PAST FEW YEARS THROUGHOUT VARIOUS UNPOPULATED AREAS OF THE COUNTRY WHERE MINE FIELDS HAVE BEEN PLANTED, THE SWEEPING OF THIS TYPE OF WEAPON WILL NECESSARILY HAVE TO BE DONE GRADUALLY FOR TECHNICAL AND OPERATIONAL REASONS. THEREFORE, THE MEASURES TO BE ADOPTED TO SUSPEND THEIR USE WILL BE:

1. END THE MANUFACTURING OF BOOBY TRAPS.

2. END TO THE PLANTING OF NEW MINE FIELDS.

3. IMMEDIATE REMOVAL OF ALL MINES PLANTED IN AREAS OF HIGH RISK FOR THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND MARKING OF THOSE AREAS THAT, FOR TECHNICAL REASONS -- LOSS OF MAP OF THE MINED AREAS -- CANNOT BE SWEPT IMMEDIATELY.

4. GRADUAL SWEEPING OF THE MINE FIELDS LOCATED IN AREAS OF LOW RISK FOR THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND MARKING OF SITES WHERE, FOR TECHNICAL REASONS, THE MINES CANNOT BE REMOVED.

5. THIS ORDER DOES NOT INCLUDE THE CLAYMORE MINES USED IN THE AMBUSH OF SOLDIERS.

WE WILL COORDINATE THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THESE MEASURES WITH HUMANITARIAN AID ORGANIZATIONS AND THE PEOPLE THEMSELVES.

LIKEWISE, WE EXPECT THE ARMY TO SWEEP THE MINE FIELDS THAT SURROUND THE GARRISONS AND FIXED MILITARY POSTS LOCATED IN HEAVILY POPULATED AREAS. THESE MINES ARE CONSTANTLY HARMING THE PEOPLE OR THEIR DOMESTIC ANIMALS.

LIKEWISE, THE ARMY MUST CEASE ALL BOMBING AND SHELLING OF CIVILIAN TARGETS.

FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

EL SALVADOR, 11 SEPTEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0471 (LANG SYS INC)

LIMA, 12 SEP 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [TEXT] FOREIGN MINISTER GUILLERMO LARCO COX TODAY LABELED THE U.S. AID TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING IN SOUTH AMERICA AS MEAGER. HE SAID THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT SHOULD RECONSIDER THE AID GIVEN TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LARCO] I UNDERSTAND THE U.S. GOVERNMENT APPROPRIATED AN AMOUNT WITHOUT PREVIOUS STUDY AND WITHOUT CONSULTING WITH THE COUNTRIES INVOLVED. IF THAT IS TRUE, THE U.S. AID CAN JUSTIFIABLY BE CALLED RIDICULOUS.

[REPORTER] WHAT CONTACTS HAVE YOU HAD WITH THE U.S. GOVERNMENT TO EXPLAIN THAT THE RESOURCES APPROPRIATED TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING ARE NOT ENOUGH?

[LARCO] THE CONTACTS WILL BE MADE DURING THE MEETINGS TO BE HELD BY THE PRESIDENTS OF BOLIVIA, COLOMBIA, AND PERU WITH U.S. PRESIDENT BUSH. THE TALKS THERE WILL BE FRANK AND THE MISTAKES MADE CAN THEN BE CORRECTED.

[REPORTER] COLOMBIA IS FACING A SERIOUS PROBLEM IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. WHAT ACTION IS THE FOREIGN MINISTRY TAKING TO SUPPORT COLOMBIA?

[LARCO] THE PRESIDENT IS THE ONE WHO RUNS INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS, AND PRESIDENT GARCIA'S DECISION TO VISIT PRESIDENT BARCO AND TO HONOR ASSASSINATED SENATOR GALAN SHOWS THE PRESIDENT'S SUPPORT FOR COLOMBIA AND THE DIRECTION OF THE FOREIGN MINISTRY'S ACTIVITIES. IN ADDITION TO THAT, WE ARE WORKING WITH THE COLOMBIAN AND BOLIVIAN FOREIGN MINISTRIES TO PREPARE AN AGENDA AS A BASIS FOR A TRIPARTITE MEETING, AS A FIRST STAGE BEFORE THE MEETING WITH PRESIDENT BUSH. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0472 (LANG SYS INC)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 13 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] REBEL COMMANDER SHAFIK HANDAL IN THE MEXICAN CAPITAL TODAY SAID THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS HAVE PROPOSED NINE POINTS "THAT REFLECT THE ASPIRATIONS OF THE ENTIRE NATION" TO THE REPRESENTATIVES OF THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT.

HANDAL POINTED OUT THAT THEY WILL BE STUDIED TODAY AND TOMORROW DURING MEETINGS HERE BETWEEN REPRESENTATIVES OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) AND A SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DELEGATION.

THE NINE POINTS REVEALED BY THE GUERRILLA COMMANDER ARE:

1. BEGINNING OF A PROCESS TO INTRODUCE AMENDMENTS TO THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM AGREED UPON BY CONSENSUS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND OPPOSITION PARTIES.

2. JOINT ACCORD ON MEASURES TO ENSURE THE END OF ALL FORMS OF REPRESSION AND FULL RESPECT FOR DEMOCRATIC LIBERTIES THAT WOULD BE VERIFIED BY THE UNITED NATIONS AND OAS.

3. PACT TO CONTINUE HONEST JUDICIAL PROCESS GUARANTEEING THE DETERMINATION OF RESPONSIBILITIES AND PUNISHMENT OF THOSE WHO ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF MONSIGNOR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO AND ALL THOSE INVOLVED IN DEATH SQUADS.

4. ACCORD TO DISSOLVE THE ECONOMIC STRUCTURE THAT CAUSES POLITICAL AND SOCIAL CONFRONTATION THROUGH THE MAINTENANCE OF REFORMS PROMOTED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, WHO PRECEDED CRISTIANI.

5. PACT ON MEASURES FOR SELF-MONITORING AND PROFESSIONALIZATION OF THE ARMED FORCES.

6. COMMITMENT FROM THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT THAT IT WILL SUBMIT ACCORDS ON CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS THAT COULD EMERGE FROM THIS DIALOGUE THAT BEGINS TODAY FOR APPROVAL BY THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY.

7. ACCORD TO ADVANCE LEGISLATIVE AND MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS TO BRING ABOUT CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS AS SOON AS POSSIBLE AND ACCELERATE AN END TO THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR.

8. MUTUAL GUARANTEES FOR THE OPERATION AND SETTLEMENT OF FORCES THAT WILL GUARANTEE RESPECT FOR A CEASE-FIRE WITHOUT THIS IMPLYING A VIOLATION OF THE NATIONAL TERRITORY.

9. INITIAL STEPS FOR THE INCORPORATION OF THE FMLN INTO SALVADORAN POLITICAL LIFE.

AS FOR THIS LATTER POINT, HANDAL SAID THAT THE FMLN MUST BECOME A POLITICAL PARTY BY REGISTERING ITS FOLLOWERS AND ESTABLISHING A RAPPORT WITH THE MEDIA.

HE POINTED OUT THAT THIS GUERRILLA GROUP HAS ESTABLISHED A "NO LATER THAN 15 NOVEMBER" DEADLINE TO ACHIEVE A CEASE-FIRE ACCORD.

DEV-MUC3-0473 (LANG SYS INC)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 13 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] WITH MODERATE OPTIMISM, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS OPENED A DIALOGUE IN MEXICO CITY TODAY TO ESTABLISH PEACE IN EL SALVADOR, WITH A SPECTACULAR PRIOR ANNOUNCEMENT BY THE INSURGENTS THAT THEY ARE PREPARED TO DECLARE A DEFINITIVE CEASE-FIRE AND BECOME A POLITICAL PARTY.

THIS PROPOSAL -- WHICH ENTAILS A DECISION TO LAY DOWN ARMS IF CERTAIN PRIOR CONDITIONS ARE MET -- DID NOT MEET WITH A MATCHING PROPOSAL FROM THE GOVERNMENT. THE DISCUSSIONS ARE TAKING PLACE IN A MODERN BUILDING BELONGING TO THE SOCIAL SECURITY ADMINISTRATION IN A RESIDENTIAL DISTRICT IN THE SOUTHERN SECTION OF MEXICO CITY.

COMMANDER MIGUEL SAENZ OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) SAID DURING A RECESS THAT "THE GOVERNMENT'S COMMISSION DID NOT BRING ANY SUBSTANTIVE PROPOSAL."

ALL THE MEN WERE WEARING COATS AND TIE, WHEREAS THE FEMALE FMLN COMMANDERS WERE IN VERY FORMAL ATTIRE.

THE MEETING IS TAKING PLACE IN A 10-SQUARE-METER ROOM IN WHICH THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATES AND GUERRILLAS SIT FACE-TO-FACE, WITH THE MODERATORS AT THE HEAD OF THE TABLE. THE ROOM HAS AN ANNEX TO WHICH THE NEGOTIATORS WITHDRAW DURING RECESSES TO ANALYZE THE OTHER SIDE'S POSITIONS.

MSGR ROMEO TOBAR ASTORGA, WHO IS THE MODERATOR OF THE MEETING AND PRESIDENT OF THE SALVADORAN EPISCOPAL CONFERENCE, HAD ASSERTED BEFORE THE START OF THE MEETING THAT HE COULD SEE A WILLINGNESS ON BOTH SIDES "TO END A WAR THAT HAS CAUSED MANY VICTIMS."

"ALTHOUGH I AM NOT A MARXIST, BECAUSE THAT IDEOLOGY IS ATHEISTIC AND MATERIALISTIC, I AM CONVINCED THAT IT IS URGENT THAT THIS DIALOGUE LEAD TO THE PEACE WE LONG FOR," HE ALSO SAID.

SAENZ, WHO ALSO SOUNDED OPTIMISTIC BUT CAUTIOUS, SAID DURING A BRIEF TALK WITH NEWSMEN THAT PROCEDURES FOR THIS AND SUBSEQUENT MEETINGS ARE UNDER DISCUSSION, AND TIMETABLES, STAGES, AND SITES SHOULD RESULT FROM THEM.

SHORTLY BEFORE THE MEETING BEGAN, OSCAR SANTAMARIA, WHO IS THE JUSTICE MINISTER AND ONE OF THE OFFICIAL DELEGATES, ASSERTED THAT "THERE IS UTMOST WILLINGNESS TO ACHIEVE PEACE" ON THE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT.

IN ADDITION TO SANTAMARIA, THE OTHER MEMBERS OF THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION ARE PRESIDENCY MINISTER JUAN MARTINEZ, POET DAVID ESCOBAR, AND ADVISERS HECTOR CONTRERAS AND ABELARDO TORRES. TOBAR ASTORGA IS ACCOMPANIED BY MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, AUXILIARY BISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR.

BESIDES SAENZ, THE FMLN IS REPRESENTED BY COMMANDERS SHAFIK HANDAL, SALVADOR SAMAYOA, ANA GUADALUPE MARTINEZ, MERCEDES LETONA, MARIO ROJAS, AND DANIEL LOPEZ.

AT 1045 (1645 GMT), 1 HOUR BEFORE THE MEETING BEGAN, THE FMLN RELEASED ITS PROPOSAL TO THE PRESS, WHICH INCLUDES A CEASE-FIRE ON 15 NOVEMBER, A DEFINITIVE END TO THE HOSTILITIES ON 31 JANUARY, AND THE INCORPORATION OF ITS LEADERS AND ACTIVISTS INTO THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL LIFE THROUGH A POLITICAL PARTY.

THE CONDITIONS DEMANDED BY THE FMLN INCLUDE REFORMS TO THE JUDICIAL SYSTEMS, AN END TO ALL MANNER OF REPRESSION, THE PURGING AND PROFESSIONALIZATION OF THE ARMED FORCES, THE FULL EXERCISE OF FREEDOMS (VERIFIED BY THE UN AND THE OAS), THE REORGANIZATION OF THE ELECTORAL SYSTEM, THE HOLDING OF THE 1991 LEGISLATIVE AND MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS AHEAD OF SCHEDULE, AND AN INVESTIGATION INTO THE ASSASSINATION OF MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO.

THE FIRST STEP THE FMLN WOULD TAKE ONCE THE CEASE-FIRE IS IN PLACE WOULD BE TO LEGALIZE THE STATUS OF ITS MILITANTS AND ITS MEDIA. "THIS STEP INVOLVES RISKS, BUT WE ARE WILLING TO TAKE THEM," THE GUERRILLA DELEGATES SAID.

THE TALKS WERE CONTINUING EARLY IN THE AFTERNOON WITHOUT ACCESS TO THE PRESS AND AMID A DISCREET SECURITY MEASURE ESTABLISHED BY THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT -- JUST A COUPLE OF MEN WITH "WALKIE-TALKIES" AND DISGUISED WEAPONS.

SAVE FOR AN UNFORESEEN OBSTACLE, THE MEETING IS SCHEDULED TO CONTINUE TOMORROW, THURSDAY.

DEV-MUC3-0478 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 14 SEP 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT AND THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19) HAVE POSTPONED SIGNING A PEACE AGREEMENT BUT HAVE NOT BROKEN OFF THE NEGOTIATIONS, AN M-19 SPOKESMAN ANNOUNCED TODAY.

RAFAEL PARDO RUEDA, PRESIDENTIAL ADVISER FOR PEACE AFFAIRS, ANNOUNCED THAT AFTER THE TALKS ON 13 SEPTEMBER IN SANTO DOMINGO (400 KM SOUTHWEST OF BOGOTA), THE AGREEMENT FOR THE M-19 TO DEMOBILIZE AND RETURN TO POLITICAL LIFE WAS POSTPONED.

IN STATEMENTS BY TELEPHONE TO REUTER FROM SANTO DOMINGO, HIPOLITO BLANCO, A RANKING M-19 SPOKESMAN, SAID "WE HOPE TO HOLD ANOTHER MEETING SOON; THE TOPICS WE MUST AGREE UPON ARE COMPLEX AND WE MUST TAKE TIME TO ANALYZE THEM."

BLANCO POINTED OUT THAT "YESTERDAY'S MEETING WAS CHARACTERIZED BY CORDIALITY," BUT "THE MECHANISMS TO BROADEN DEMOCRACY IN THE COUNTRY AND DEMOBILIZATION" ARE ISSUES THAT MUST STILL BE STUDIED IN-DEPTH.

BLANCO ADMITTED THAT ONE OF THE SUBJECTS BEING CONSIDERED IS A PARDON FOR M-19 MEMBERS, INCLUDING THOSE WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE VIOLENT OCCUPATION OF THE JUSTICE PALACE IN NOVEMBER 1985, WHEN APPROXIMATELY 100 PEOPLE WERE KILLED.

THE M-19 IS ONE OF SIX ACTIVE GUERRILLA GROUPS IN COLOMBIA AND THE ONE THAT HAS MADE THE GREATEST PROGRESS IN PEACE TALKS WITH THE GOVERNMENT.

THE GROUP IS NATIONALIST IN IDEOLOGY. IT HAS 1,000 ARMED MEN, IS BEST KNOWN FOR ITS SPECTACULAR OPERATIONS, AND MAY WELL BECOME THE FIRST COLOMBIAN GUERRILLA GROUP TO LAY DOWN THEIR ARMS INDEFINITELY.

THE GOVERNMENT AND THE M-19 SIGNED A PEACE AGREEMENT ON 17 MARCH AND OPENED TALKS IN MAY WITH POLITICAL AND SOCIAL SECTORS CALLED "WORKING TABLES."

THE INITIAL RESULTS OF THE "WORKING TABLES" -- WHICH ENDED THE FIRST WEEK OF JULY -- WILL BE PRESENTED TO CONGRESS AND THE PRESIDENCY IN ORDER FOR THEM TO BE TRANSFORMED INTO CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS, LAWS, OR DECREES.

SOME OF THE REFORMS DEAL WITH THE REPRESENTATION OF MINORITY GROUPS IN CONGRESS AND MECHANISMS FOR THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE GUERRILLAS.

OTHER GUERRILLA ORGANIZATIONS WILL PROBABLY MEET WITH THE GOVERNMENT THIS MONTH TO SPEED UP THE PEACEMAKING PROCESS.

THE ONLY GUERRILLA GROUP THAT HAS STAYED AWAY FROM THE PEACE PROCESS IS THE CASTROITE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY, WHICH CEASED BOMBING PIPELINES ON 25 AUGUST, BUT HAS CONTINUED ITS GUERRILLA OPERATIONS.

ACCORDING TO MILITARY ESTIMATES, THE SIX INSURGENT GROUPS IN COLOMBIA HAVE A TOTAL OF APPROXIMATELY 7,000 ARMED MEN.

DEV-MUC3-0479 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 14 SEP 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN SECRET POLICE SOURCES REPORTED THAT THE ALLEDGED DRUG TRAFFICKERS BERNARDO PELAEZ ROLDAN AND GUILLERMO BUENO DELGADO WERE ARRESTED TODAY. APPARENTLY, THE UNITED STATES HAS REQUESTED THAT THESE MEN BE EXTRADITED TO RESPOND TO CHARGES AGAINST THEM IN THAT COUNTRY.

IT WAS REPORTED THAT PELAEZ ROLDAN WAS ARRESTED IN BOGOTA AND IS CHARGED BY A COURT IN DETROIT OF CONSPIRACY TO DISTRIBUTE COCAINE IN THE UNITED STATES.

BUENO DELGADO WAS ARRESTED BY THE POLICE ON SAN ANDRES ISLAND IN THE CARIBBEAN AND WAS IMMEDIATELY TRANSFERRED TO BOGOTA AND HANDED OVER TO JUDICIAL AUTHORITIES.

ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY, DAS, SPOKESMEN SAID THAT REQUESTS FOR EXTRADITION OF THE SUSPECTED DRUG LORD HAVE BEEN RECEIVED FROM FLORIDA AND CALIFORNIA COURTS, WHERE HE HAS BEEN CHARGED WITH SMUGGLING AT LEAST 5,000 KG OF COCAINE INTO THE UNITED STATES AND LAUNDERING DOLLARS OBTAINED AS A RESULT OF THIS ILLEGAL ACTIVITY.

LAST WEEK, THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT EXTRADITED THE ALLEDGED "FINANCIAL HEAD" OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL TO THE UNITED STATES. HE IS EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO AND HAS TO ANSWER CHARGES IN AN ATLANTA COURT OF "LAUNDERING" MORE THAN $1.2 BILLION THROUGH A PANAMANIAN BANK.

THE DRUG-TRAFFICKING MAFIAS HAVE THREATENED TO MURDER 10 JUDGES FOR EACH COLOMBIAN EXTRADITED TO ANOTHER COUNTRY, AND THIS THREAT HAS THE WHOLE COUNTRY TENSE AND ANXIOUS.

THERE ARE RUMORS CIRCULATING IN SEVERAL CITIES THAT NARCOCRIMINAL ORGANIZATIONS ARE PREPARING AN OPERATION CALLED "BLACK SEPTEMBER" THAT WILL BE IMPLEMENTED NEXT WEEKEND BY POISONING WATER SUPPLIES AND ATTACKING COMMERCIAL CENTERS AND NIGHT CLUBS.

DEV-MUC3-0481 (UMASS)

HAVANA (CUBA), 14 SEP 89 (RADIO RELOJ NETWORK) -- [TEXT] THE REBELS' DECISION TO EXPRESS THEIR WILLINGNESS TO ABANDON THE ARMED STRUGGLE AND MAKE OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FLMN] OF EL SALVADOR A LEGAL PARTY, FAR FROM WEAKENING THE GUERRILLA, STRENGTHENS ITS REVOLUTIONARY POSITION. A COMMENTARY WRITTEN BY RITA CEBALLOS FROM PRENSA LATINA NOTES THAT IN ADDITION OF BEING DECISIVE IN THE ACHIEVEMENT OF A DRASTIC INTERNAL CHANGE, THE PROPOSAL MADE BY THE GUERRILLA IS A POLITICAL BLOW TO THE SALVADORAN EXTREME RIGHT.

PRENSA LATINA ADDS THAT THE DISARMAMENT AND PEACE OFFER GIVES SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI A SITUATION HE HAS TO RESOLVE IN THE INTERNATIONAL AREA. NO MATTER WHAT THE OFFICIAL RESPONSE IS DURING THE CONSULTATION SESSIONS BEING HELD IN MEXICO BETWEEN THE EXTREME RIGHT'S NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE AND REPRESENTATIVES OF THE FLMN, THE SALVADORAN REACTIONARIES WILL NOT BENEFIT. THE FLMN SAID IN THE MEETING IN MEXICO THAT EITHER THE REGIME ACCEPTS THE CONDITIONS SUGGESTED BY THE GUERRILLA OR PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI ANNOUNCES HE FAVORS A WAR HE CANNOT WIN.

THE GUERRILLA PROPOSES THE TOTAL CEASE OF HOSTILITIES BEFORE 31 JANUARY, END OF THE REPRESSION, SELF-CLEANING OF THE ARMY, AND THE RESTRUCTURING OF THE MUNICIPAL AND ELECTORAL SYSTEM, AMONG OTHER PROPOSALS. PRENSA LATINA COMMENTS THAT THE SWIFTNESS WITH WHICH THE GUERRILLA CHIEFS PRESENTED THEIR PROPOSALS AND THEIR CONTENTS LEFT CRISTIANI'S CABINET AT THE DEFENSIVE AS WELL AS ITS MANEUVERS TO DISARM THE REVOLUTIONARIES. THE AGREEMENT OF ARENA, THE ULTRA-RIGHT RULING PARTY, TO TALK WITH THE GUERRILLA OPENS A POSSIBILITY FOR PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. WE WILL HAVE TO WAIT AND SEE.

DEV-MUC3-0483 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 14 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [REPORT] [HERNANDO CORRAL] [TEXT] THE THIRD PUBLIC JUDGE ISSUED ARREST WARRANTS FOR NORBERTO HERNANDEZ ROMERO AND RAFAEL RIVERA ALARCON AND CHARGED THEM WITH PARTICIPATING IN THE MURDER OF LIBERAL PARTY LEADER LUIS CARLOS GALAN SARMIENTO. THE SAME JUDGE ISSUED AN ARREST WARRANT FOR JAIME DE JESUS VALENCIA MARTINEZ AND CHARGED HIM WITH BEING THE MASTERMIND OF THE CRIME. THESE THREE PERSONS HAVE NOT BEEN ARRESTED AND ARE BEING SOUGHT THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

LUIS ALFREDO GONZALEZ CHACON, PEDRO ZAMBRANO DELGADO, NORBERTO MURRILLO CHALARCA, ARMANDO BERNAL ACOSTA, HECTOR MANUEL ZEPEDA QUINTERO, AND ALBERTO JUBIS HASZVUMB WERE ARRESTED A FEW DAYS AGO IN BOGOTA AND CHARGED WITH BEING ACCOMPLICES TO THE CRIME. THE THIRD CIVIL JUDGE ALSO DECIDED TO RELEASE LUIS FELIPE TORRES, THE MAN WHO CARRIED A POSTER AND A HAT AT THE MURDER SCENE AND WHO WAS INITIALLY ACCUSED OF HAVING PARTICIPATED IN THE CRIME.

IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT JAIME DE JESUS VALENCIA MARTINEZ, THE ALLEGED MASTERMIND OF THE CRIME, OFFERED 50 MILLION PESOS TO POLICE OFFICIALS IN AN ATTEMPT TO OBTAIN THE RELEASE OF SIX PERSONS WHO HAD BEEN ARRESTED IN A LUXURY APARTMENT IN BOGOTA. VALENCIA IS ALSO CHARGED WITH BEING THE OWNER OF THE MACHINEGUN THAT WAS FOUND IN THE APARTMENT IN WHICH THE SIX SUSPECTS WERE ARRESTED.

THE DEFENSE CLAIMS THAT THERE IS A SWORN STATEMENT BY FORMER MINISTER CARLOS OBANDO VELASCO THAT CERTIFIES THAT HE WAS WITH JUBIS HAZVUMB ON THE DAY GALAN WAS KILLED. THE LAWYERS ALSO CLAIM THAT GALAN SARMIENTO WAS KILLED BY AN UZI SUBMACHINEGUN AND THAT THE ONE FOUND AT THE APARTMENT WHERE THE SIX SUSPECTS WERE ARRESTED WAS AN INGRAM. BALLISTIC TEST RESULTS HAVE NOT YET BEEN REVEALED. THE DEFENSE LAWYERS HAVE APPEALED THE COURT DECISION, AND NOW THE COURT WILL HAVE TO DECIDE IF THE DECISION ISSUED BY THE THIRD PUBLIC JUDGE IS TO STAND.

DEV-MUC3-0484 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 14 SEP 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE FRG EMBASSY IN BOGOTA TODAY REJECTED A REPORT THAT SOME OF ITS OFFICIALS ARE LINKED TO THE POWERFUL DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIAS THAT OPERATE IN COLOMBIA.

THE REPORT WAS PUBLISHED IN THE GERMAN WEEKLY "WELT AM SONNTAG," WHICH BASED ITS INFORMATION ON FEDERAL INVESTIGATIONS OFFICE SOURCES WHO STATED THAT SOME OFFICIALS IN THE DIPLOMATIC MISSION ASSIGNED TO BOGOTA ARE LINKED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING AND HAVE PARTICIPATED IN THE OPERATIONS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, THE BIGGEST DRUG TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATION IN THE WORLD.

AN FRG EMBASSY SPOKESMAN WHO WAS QUESTIONED BY DPA SAID: "WE KNOW NOTHING ABOUT A MISSION MEMBER WHO HAS BEEN LINKED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING."

ACCORDING TO THE GERMAN PUBLICATION, APPROXIMATELY $20 MILLION OBTAINED BY THE MEDELLIN CARTEL FOR THEIR ILLEGAL ACTIVITIES HAVE BEEN TRANSFERRED FROM BANKS IN COLOMBIA TO FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS IN PANAMA AND LUXEMBOURG.

LAST WEEK, THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT, WHICH HAS DECLARED "WAR" ON THE COCAINE GANGS, EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, THE ALLEGED "FINANCIAL HEAD" OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL. ROMERO IS ACCUSED OF BEING THE "BRAIN" BEHIND THE CARTEL'S MONEY-LAUNDERING OPERATIONS.

AT PRESENT, MARTINEZ ROMERO IS BEING CHARGED AT AN ATLANTA COURT FOR ALLEGEDLY LAUNDERING MORE THAN $1.2 BILLION IN THE BANCO DE OCCIDENTE DE PANAMA. ACCORDING TO "WELT AM SONNTAG," THIS BANK SENT THE DRUG TRAFFICKING FUNDS TO THE DEUTSCH-SUEDAMERIKANISCHE BANK.

THE DRUG TRAFFICKER'S EXTRADITION HAS CAUSED TENSION AND ANXIETY IN COLOMBIA BECAUSE THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE WHEREIN THEY THREATENED TO KILL 10 JUDGES FOR EACH COLOMBIAN SENT TO ANOTHER COUNTRY.

THE FRG EMBASSY SPOKESMAN ADDED THAT THE ALLEGED LINKS OF EMBASSY OFFICIALS WITH THE MAFIA "WERE INVENTED BY A NEWS AGENCY -- NOT DPA -- THAT WROTE THE INFORMATION IN BONN." THE INFORMATION WAS LATER PUBLISHED BY "WELT AM SONNTAG," WHICH, THE SPOKESMAN SAID, WAS A NEWSPAPER "THAT WAS NOT VERY IMPORTANT."

SO FAR, THE "WAR" BEING CARRIED OUT BY COLOMBIAN OFFICIALS HAS LED TO THE CAPTURE OF SEVERAL PEOPLE WHO ARE CONNECTED TO THE DRUG CARTEL AND THE CONFISCATION OF NUMEROUS PROPERTIES BELONGING TO THE "CAPOS" PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, THE BIGGEST MAFIOSOS IN THE WORLD, ACCORDING TO WASHINGTON AND BOGOTA.

DEV-MUC3-0485 (UMASS)

GUATEMALA CITY, NO DATE (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE SETTING OF EXPLOSIVE DEVICES AND THE KIDNAPPINGS ARE AN ATTEMPT BY SOME TO GIVE THE GOVERNMENT JUSTIFICATION FOR USING A STRONG HAND, PRESIDENT CEREZO SAID. THE PRESIDENT STRESSED THAT THE BOMBS AND THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] OF CANDIDATES IS THE WORK OF TERRORISTS. REPORTING THAT THE RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS WILL BE PRESENTED IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS, CEREZO AREVALO URGED CITIZENS TO HELP IN THE EFFORTS TO CONTROL VIOLENCE.

[CEREZO] "FIRST, WE NEED THE PEOPLE'S WILLINGNESS TO HELP, WHICH IMPLIES HAVING THE COURAGE TO PASS ON INFORMATION TO THE GOVERNMENT, BECAUSE PEOPLE FEAR REPRISALS FROM CRIMINALS. HOWEVER, IF WE ARE NOT ALL UNITED TO FIGHT CRIME AND TERRORISM, WE GUATEMALANS WILL CERTAINLY BE AFFECTED SERIOUSLY IN THE FUTURE BY THIS KIND OF VIOLENCE, WHICH SEEMS TO BE SPREADING THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, AS WE HAVE SAID IN THE PAST.

"SECOND, I HAVE NOTICED THAT SOME SECTORS HAVE TURNED TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY BY REQUESTING THAT HUMAN RIGHTS GROUP REPRESENTATIVES BE SENT HERE, AS IF THE GOVERNMENT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. PEOPLE ARE AWARE THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT RESPONSIBLE, YET THEY HOLD THE GOVERNMENT RESPONSIBLE. I BELIEVE THAT WHAT WE SHOULD DO IS TURN TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY -- THE GOVERNMENT WILL DO THIS -- SO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY CAN HELP US CONTROL TERRORISM.

"THIRD, I MUST RECOGNIZE THAT ONE OF THE PARTIES, THE UNION OF THE NATIONAL CENTER, HAS ADOPTED A POSITIVE ATTITUDE BY MAKING SUGGESTIONS TO THE GOVERNMENT ON HOW TO CONTROL CRIME. WE ARE GOING TO STUDY THEIR PROPOSALS. WE BELIEVE THAT ALTHOUGH THE PROPOSALS COME FROM AN OPPOSITION PARTY, WE SHOULD ANALYZE THEM. WE URGE ALL SECTORS IN GUATEMALAN SOCIETY NOT TO SIMPLY ADOPT THE EASY ATTITUDE OF ACCUSING THE GOVERNMENT. WE SHOULD INSTEAD ADOPT THE ATTITUDE OF REJECTING CRIME."

REGARDING THE PROPOSALS HE WILL MAKE DURING HIS UPCOMING VISIT TO THE UN HEARDQUARTERS AND THE RECENT ATTACKS IN GUATEMALA, WHICH HE SAID ARE AIMED AT DESTROYING THE ACCOMPLISHMENTS ACHIEVED DURING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, CEREZO AREVALO ADDED:

[CEREZO] "AMONG THE ISSUES WE ARE GOING TO POINT OUT IS THAT, AT THIS MOMENT, GUATEMALA IS THE TARGET OF AN ATTEMP TO UNDERMINE THE CONSOLIDATION OF DEMOCRACY. WE ARE GOING TO NEED THE HELP OF DEMOCRACIES THAT ARE FRIENDS OF GUATEMALA, BUT NOT IN THE CAPACITY OF JUDGES. WE ARE GOING TO NEED TOTAL SUPPORT TO CONTROL A DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL TERRORIST OFFENSIVE THAT IS TAKING PLACE IN THE COUNTRY AND THAT SEEKS TO DESTROY THE REPUBLIC."

THERE ARE PEOPLE INTERESTED IN HAVING THE LARGE NUMBER OF REFUGEES WHO HAVE RETURNED TO THE COUNTRY SINCE CEREZO WAS SWORN IN LEAVE THE COUNTRY AGAIN TO DISCREDIT GUATEMALA, PRESIDENT CEREZO SAID.

[CEREZO] "DURING 3 AND 1/2 YEARS OF DEMOCRACY, IN WHICH WE IMPLEMENTED PLANS AND GUARANTEED THE RIGHTS OF ALL CITIZENS, GUATEMALA BEGAN TO WELCOME ALL KINDS OF PEOPLE: REFUGEES -- GUATEMALANS WHO HAVE BEEN LIVING IN EXILE FOR YEARS IN MEXICO AND OTHER COUNTRIES; PEOPLE WHO HAD BEEN THREATENED AND WHO WERE LIVING IN COSTA RICA AND WHO HAVE RETURNED. WE DO NOT EVEN KNOW WHERE THESE PEOPLE WORK BECAUSE, FOR US, THEY ARE GUATEMALANS WHO HAVE RETURNED. HOWEVER, WE ARE BEGINNING TO RECEIVE REPORTS FROM THEM. THEY HAVE TOLD US THEY ARE BEING SYSTEMATICALLY THREATENED OVER THE TELEPHONE. WHO KNOWS WHERE THESE PEOPLE ARE OR HOW THEY GOT THEIR TELEPHONE NUMBERS? HOW IS THIS DONE? THERE ARE PEOPLE INTERESTED IN HAVING THESE FORMER REFUGEES LEAVE THE COUNTRY TO AGAIN REPORT THAT WE ARE VIOLATING HUMAN RIGHTS IN GUATEMALA TO CREATE A CLIMATE OF INTERNATIONAL ISOLATION. I WOULD SAY WE ARE BEING AFFECTED BY TWO TRENDS THAT ARE FIGHTING AGAINST GUATEMALAN DEMOCRACY." [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0486 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 15 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE [FAC] COMMANDOS AND PILOTS TODAY RECEIVED ORDERS TO STAND READY TO TAKE OFF, INTERCEPT, CAPTURE, OR SHOOT DOWN UNIDENTIFIED OR HOSTILE AIRCRAFT FLYING OVER THE NATION'S TERRITORY. THE GOVERNMENT ADOPTED THESE MEASURES IN CONNECTION WITH THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. HERE IS A REPORT BY AMPARO MONTON:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MONTON] THE ORDER WAS ISSUED BY THE COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE COMMANDS, WHICH ALSO DECIDED TO USE GROUND-TO-AIR MISSILES AND OTHER WEAPONS ABOARD FAC AIRCRAFT. ACCORDING TO THE INSTRUCTIONS MANUAL SENT TO ALL AIR BASES, ORDERS ARE GIVEN TO CAPTURE, DESTROY, OR SHOOT DOWN PLANES IN 11 INSTANCES, WHICH INCLUDE THE FOLLOWING: WHEN PLANES FLY OVER FORBIDDEN OR RESTRICTED AREAS; IN THE EVENT OF UNAUTHORIZED LANDINGS; WHEN THE [WORD INDISTINCT] DO NOT ESTABLISH RADIO CONTACT WITH THE INTERCEPTOR PLANE FLYING OVER THEM; WHEN AIRCRAFT LAND IN PLACES NOT AUTHORIZED BY THE CIVIL AERONAUTICS OFFICE; WHEN THEY LAND ON CLANDESTINE AIRSTRIPS.

INSTRUCTIONS WERE ALSO ISSUED TO ALL AIR COMMANDS TO KEEP TWO ARMORED AIRCRAFT ON ALERT AT ALL TIMES EITHER ON THE GROUND OR IN THE AIR. THE ONLY EVENT IN WHICH THE SHOOTING DOWN OF A HOSTILE AIRCRAFT MUST NOT BE CONSIDERED IS WHEN SUCH AN ACTION WOULD ENDANGER INNOCENT PEOPLE OR OCCUPIED BUILDINGS.

IN ADDITION, THE FAC COMMAND DIVIDED THE PROCEDURE INTO FOUR PHASES, NAMELY: DETECTION, IDENTIFICATION, INTERCEPTION, AND DESTRUCTION. THESE MEASURES WILL APPLY TO ALL SUSPICIOUS-LOOKING AIRCRAFT, INCLUDING PLANES OF COLOMBIAN OR FOREIGN REGISTRY. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0489 (UMASS)

MOSCOW (USSR), NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [VEDENYAPIN] DURING THE LAST 3 WEEKS IN COLOMBIA, YOU KNOW, A REAL WAR HAS BEEN GOING ON, A WAR BEING WAGED BY THE GOVERNMENT ON THE DRUGS MAFIA. IN BOGOTA, MEDELLIN, CALI, AND OTHER TOWNS SHOTS ARE HEARD, BOMBS EXPLODE, BLOOD IS FLOWING, AND MORE AND MORE OFTEN WE HEAR THE WORDS THE MEDELLIN CARTEL. THIS IS THE HEART OF THE COLOMBIAN MAFIA. WHAT IS IT? HOW DID IT FORM? WITH THIS QUESTION I TURN TO YOU, YURIY NIKOLAYEVICH. INCIDENTALLY, I KNOW YOU HAVE BEEN IN MEDELLIN.

[ISAYEV] YES, WHILE WORKING IN LATIN AMERICA AS A CORRESPONDENT FOR USSR STATE TELEVISION AND RADIO I WAS ABLE TO VISIT MEDELLIN ONCE. THERE WAS A SEMINAR THERE ON THE PROBLEMS OF CENTRAL AMERICA. OUTWARDLY IT IS A VERY ATTRACTIVE TOWN, VERY GREEN, SITUATED ON A PLAIN, AND IT IS CALLED ETERNALLY BLOSSOMING. AFTER SEVERAL HOURS IN MEDELLIN BURSTS OF SUBMACHINEGUN FIRE RANG OUT SUDDENLY IN THE STREETS AND I UNDERSTOOD THEN THAT I WAS IN THE CENTER OF THE COCAINE MAFIA. TWO CLANS OF BANDITS WERE EXCHANGING FIRE AND PASSERS-BY LITERALLY HAD TO RUN AWAY FROM THE SCENE OF EVENTS AS FAST AS THEY COULD.

LOCAL COLLEAGUES SHOWED ME A HUGE DISTRICT CONSISTING OF LUXURIOUS VILLAS WHERE THE GODFATHERS OF THE COLOMBIA DRUG MAFIA LIVE. IT IS DIFFICULT TO EVEN APPROACH THESE HOUSES: THEY ARE SURROUNDED BY BARBED WIRE AND THERE ARE VIDEO CAMERAS AND WATCH TOWERS. IF YOU DECIDE TO GO FAIRLY CLOSE THE GUARDS WILL OPEN FIRE WITHOUR WARNING. I WAS ALSO ABLE TO SEE A NINETEENTH-CENTURY CASTLE, A RARE AND EXTREMELY BEAUTIFUL BUILDING, A GENUINE ARCHITECTURAL MONUMENT. THIS CASTLE BELONGS TO ONE OF THE HEADS OF THE MAFIA, CARLOS LEHDER.

[VEDENYAPIN] YES, YURIY NIKOLAEVICH, BUT HOW WAS THE MEDELLIN CARTEL FORMED? SOME INFORMATION ON ITS HISTORY, IF YOU COULD.

[ISAYEV] BY RIGHTS THE FOUNDER OF THE CARTEL IS CONSIDERED TO BE CARLOS ENRIQUE LEHDER, WHO WAS ABLE TO UNITE THE COCAINE MAFIA OF COLOMBIA AROUND HIM AT THE BEGINNING OF THE SEVENTIES. A FEW WORDS ABOUT LEHDER HIMSELF: HE IS A DESPERATE EXTREMIST WHO HOLDS NOTHING SACRED. HE HAS HUNDREDS OF HUMAN LIVES ON HIS CONSCIENCE. IT IS NOT FOR NOTHING THAT HIS FRIENDS GAVE HIM AT VARIOUS TIMES THE NICK NAMES RUM ROBIN HOOD, THE DRUGS BARON, AND SO ON. CARLOS LEHDER IS DISTINGUISHED FOR HIS AUDACITY AND A RESTLESS DISPOSITION. TOGETHER WITH HIM OTHER COLOMBIAN FAMILIES HAVE BEEN OCCUPIED IN THIS ADVANTAGEOUS BUSINESS, NAMELY THE OCHOA AND ESCOBAR FAMILIES. AT THE END OF THE EIGHTIES [AS HEARD] A COCAINE WAR BEGAN BETWEEN THESE THREE CLANS. LATER, HOWEVER, THEY CAME TO AN AGREEMENT AND THE MEDELLIN CARTEL WAS FORMED

[VEDENYAPIN] IN THE PRESS MANY REPORTS HAVE APPEARED STATING THAT LITERALLY BILLIONS OF DOLLARS PASS THROUGH THE HANDS OF THE CARTEL. IS THIS TRUE?

[ISAYEV] THE CARTEL'S ANNUAL INCOME, AS THE PRESS CLAIMS, IS $8 BILLION. TO SKETCH THE SCALE OF COCAINE OPERATIONS I WILL REMIND YOU THAT IN 1984, FOR EXAMPLE, THE CARTEL BIGWIGS PROPOSED TO THE GOVERNMENT TO CLEAR COLOMBIA'S ENTIRE FOREIGN DEBT WITHIN A WEEK -- AND I WILL REMIND YOU THAT THIS IS $9 BILLION -- IF THE GOVERNMENT WOULD RELEASE MAFIA MEMBERS WHO HAD BEEN ARRESTED. NOT VERY LONG AGO A WEST GERMAN MAGAZINE PUBLISHED A LIST OF THE RICHEST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD AND ONE OF THE HEADS OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL -- JORGE OCHOA -- IS BY NO MEANS LAST ON THAT LIST. I WOULD LIKE TO MENTION ANOTHER CASE THAT CHARACTERIZES THE DIMENSIONS OF THE DRUG MAFIA'S MEANS. FOUR YEARS AGO IT CAME TO LIGHT THAT THE CARTEL HAD TAKEN PART IN NEGOTIATIONS ON BUYING A WHOLE CONSIGNMENT OF SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES, SEVERAL MILITARY HELICOPTERS, AND OTHER MODERN WEAPONS.

[VEDENYAPIN] HOW IS THIS LETHAL ARSENAL USED?

[ISAYEV] IT IS COMPLETELY NATURAL THAT THE CARTEL COULD NOT EXIST WITHOUT A COMPLETE ARMY OF MERCENARY KILLERS AND INFORMANTS WHO HAVE PENETRATED INTO LITERALLY ALL SPHERES OF THE COLOMBIAN ECONOMY, PARLIAMENT, AND THE ARMY. THE MAIN TARGET OF THE MAFIOSI ARE PROGRESSIVE POLITICIANS, WHO IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER THREATEN THE DRUGS BUSINESS. I WILL REMIND YOU THAT THE SAME CARLOS LEHDER IN 1984 ORGANIZED THE ASSASSINATION OF LARA BONILLA, THE COLOMBIAN MINISTER OF JUSTICE. IN 1986 GUILLERMO CANO, THE DIRECTOR OF THE PROGRESSIVE NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR WAS MURDERED, AND IT WAS BASICALLY AFTER THIS MUDER THAT THE HUNT FOR LEHDER BEGAN. IN THE SAME YEAR HE WAS ARRESTED AND HANDED OVER TO U.S. JUSTICE, WHICH SENTENCED HIM TO LIFE IMPRISONMENT. IT SHOULD ALSO BE NOTED THAT THERE EXISTS AN AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE U.S. AND COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENTS ON THE EXTRADITION OF ESPECIALLY DANGEROUS CRIMINALS.

[VEDENYAPIN] IF WE TAKE THE PRESENT WAR -- IT CANNOT BE CALLED ANYTHING ELSE -- WHAT WERE ITS IMMEDIATE CAUSES? [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0490 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 17 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] TWO BOMBS EXPLODED A FEW MINUTES AGO IN THE CHAPINERO NEIGHBORHOOD IN BOGOTA. THE EXPLOSION TOOK PLACE IN A BRANCH OFFICE OF THE COLMENA CORPORATION ON 59TH STREET AND 9TH AVENUE. THIS NEW TERRORIST ACTION HAS LEFT A TOLL OF 1 PERSON WOUNDED AND MATERIAL DAMAGE TO OVER 20 STORES IN THE AREA.

UNFORTUNATELY, A NEW TERRORIST ACTION HAS TAKEN PLACE IN THE CAPITAL CITY OF THE REPUBLIC. THE FIRST EXPLOSION OCCURRED ON 59TH STREET, BETWEEN 13TH AND 7TH AVENUES. THE SECOND EXPLOSION TOOK PLACE AT A BANK BRANCH ON 60TH STREET AND 7TH AVENUE. THE FIRST EXPLOSION, AS YOU CAN NOW SEE, WENT OFF AT THE CONAVI [NATIONAL SAVINGS AND HOUSING CORPORATION] BRANCH, CLOSE TO THE OFFICES OF THE SOCIAL SAVINGS FUND. THIS BANK WAS COMPLETELY DESTROYED. WE NOW SEE THE WORK BEING DONE BY THE BOGOTA FIRE DEPARTMENT.

AN OPERATION IS BEING CONDUCTED ON 60TH STREET AND 7TH AVENUE, WHERE THE SECOND BOMB EXPLODED. ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORITIES, NO ONE WAS HURT IN THIS NEW TERRORIST ACTION.

DEV-MUC3-0491 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 17 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN POLICE REPORTED THAT A HOMEMADE ROCKET WAS LAUNCHED AT THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE U.S. EMBASSY IN BOGOTA THIS EVENING. NO INJURIES OR DAMAGE WERE REPORTED.

THE ROCKET PARTIALLY PERFORATED ONE OF THE WALLS OF THE EMBASSY, BUT DID NOT EXPLODE.

THE ALREADY TIGHT SECURITY SURROUNDING THE EMBASSY SINCE THE WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFIC WAS DECLARED WAS STEPPED UP IMMEDIATELY AND TRAFFIC AND PEDESTRIANS WERE KEPT OUT OF THE AREA.

THIS ATTACKED FOLLOWED THE TWO DYNAMITE EXPLOSIONS THAT OCCURRED EARLY SUNDAY EVENING IN THE NORTHERN AREA OF BOGOTA WHERE ONE PERSON WAS SLIGHTLY INJURED AND APPROXIMATELY 30 LOCALS WERE DAMAGED.

DURING THE BELISARIO BETACUR ADMINISTRATION (1982 - 1986), WHEN SEVERAL COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES, THE U.S. EMBASSY WAS ATTACKED IN A SIMILAR MANNER. NO INJURIES WERE REPORTED DURING THAT ATTACK. LATER, HOWEVER, A BOMB EXPLODED IN THE EMBASSY'S PARKING LOT KILLING A COLOMBIAN WOMAN WHO WAS STANDING IN LINE TO GET A VISA.

LIKE IN OTHER ATTACKS OF THIS KIND REPORTED OVER THE PAST FEW WEEKS IN BOGOTA AND IN OTHER CITIES, NO ORGANIZATION HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS ATTACK; HOWEVER, THE PRESS AND THE AUTHORITIES ARE BLAMING PERSONS IN THE SERVICE OF THE DRUG LORDS.

DEV-MUC3-0492 (UMASS)

DHAKA (BANGLADESH), 9 SEP 89 (THE BANGLADESH OBSERVER) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH HAS DECLARED HIS COUNTRY'S WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN A DRAMATIC MANNER, COMMITTING A MASSIVE FUND OF $7.86 BILLION FOR THE PROGRAMME, PROVIDING INCREASED POWERS TO LAW-ENFORCEMENT AGENCIES AND EVEN OFFERING SUBSTANTIAL FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO OTHER COUNTRIES, ESPECIALLY IN LATIN AMERICA, FIGHTING THIS MENACE. TO DEAL WITH WHAT HE CALLED, "AMERICA'S TOUGHEST DOMESTIC TEST IN DECADES" DURING HIS STERN ADDRESS ON TUESDAY, THE US LEADER HAS GIVEN A NEW BOOST TO THE CONTINUING INTERNATIONAL CRUSADE AGAINST NARCOTICS.

THIS NEW INITIATIVE WILL BE WARMLY WELCOMED BY THE WORLD COMMUNITY, MOST OF ALL BY LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES, ESPECIALLY COLOMBIA WHICH IS FIGHTING A DESPERATE BATTLE AGAINST COCAINE BARONS. THE NEWS FROM BOGOTA IS SIMPLY FRIGHTENING. IN THE COUNTRY'S LONG WAR AGAINST DRUG DEALERS, NOTHING LIKE WHAT IS HAPPENING NOW -- THE MERCILESS KILLING OF SECURITY OFFICERS AND THEIR RELATIVES -- HAS EVER HAPPENED BEFORE. SHOULD COLOMBIA LOSE THIS WAR AGAINST COCAINE BARONS, DRUG LORDS IN OTHER LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES WILL FLEX THEIR MUSCLES TOO. TO PUT IT PLAINLY, COLOMBIA CANNOT AFFORD TO LOSE THIS WAR. BUT WHETHER SHE WINS OR LOSSES THIS BATTLE DEPENDS ON WHAT ASSISTANCE THE UNITED STATES CAN PROVIDE TO THIS LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRY.

HERE, COLOMBIA FACES DIFFICULT OPTIONS. WHILE SHE HAS ACCEPTED SOME LOGISTIC SUPPORT, SUCH AS HELICOPTERS, FROM WASHINGTON, SHE MAINTAINS HERE OPPOSITION TO THE USE OF US TROOPS IN TACKLING WHAT SHE RIGHTLY REGARDS AS A DOMESTIC CRISIS. THE STATEMENT BY MR BUSH ON WEDNESDAY HAS SO FAR MADE NO DIFFERENCE TO THIS OPPOSITION. THE PROBLEM FACING BOGOTA IS, WHILE AN INCREASE IN THE LOGISTIC SUPPORT FROM US WOULD HELP, THE GOVERNMENT CANNOT OVERNIGHT RAISE THE STRENGTH OF ITS ANI-NARCOTIC SECURITY FORCES. WITH THE FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE OFFERED BY THE UNITED STATES, BOGOTA CAN, OF COURSE, BUY ARMS FOR USE AGAINST DRUG BARONS. BUT THE BATTLE WILL STILL BE HARD AND LONG.

IN FIGHTING THIS RELENTLESS BATTLE AGAINST COCAINE DEALERS, COLOMBIA HAS MADE ONE PERFECTLY VALID POINT, MORE THAN ONCE. TRUE, IT IS THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE GOVERNMENT OF COLOMBIA TO WIN ITS INTERNAL WAR, WITH ALL THE HELP THAT WASHINGTON CAN PROVIDE. BUT THE REAL BATTLE AGAINST DRUG DEALERS MUST BE FOUGHT WITHIN THE UNITED STATES, ON THE STREETS OF NEW YORK, WASHINGTON, CHICAGO AND ALL OTHER CITIES. THIS IS THE MARKET FOR THE COCAINE BARONS OF COLOMBIA OR FOR THE DRUGS PRODUCED IN THE INFAMOUS GOLDEN TRIANGLE IN ASIA. AND IT IS ALSO WITHIN THE UNITED STATES WHERE ALL THE CHANNELS OF DISTRIBUTION, SOME CONTROLLED BY US CITIZENS, THRIVE UNDER THE EYES OF THE US LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCIES. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MAY ASK IF ENOUGH HAS BEEN DONE TO DEAL WITH THIS PROBLEM AT THE US END.

THIS STATEMENT BY MR BUSH SUGGESTS THAT HIS ADMINISTRATION HAS RECOGNISED THIS BASIC PROBLEM AND WANTS TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT. A MAJOR PORTION OF THE FUNDING SUPPORT FOR THE ANTI-DRUG WAR WILL BE USED IN STRENGTHENING THE LAW-ENFORCEMENT AGENCIES WITHIN THE UNITED STATES. BUT QUESTIONS HAVE BEEN RAISED BY MEMBERS OF THE US CONGRESS WHETHER THE PRESIDENT HAS GONE FAR ENOUGH IN THAT DIRECTION. IN FACT, THERE IS SOME DISAPPOINTMENT THAT THE PRESIDENT'S PLAN HAS NOT BEEN "BOLD ENOUGH" EITHER. WHILE ONE MUST ADMIT THAT THE US CONGRESSMEN ARE USED TO MAKING SUCH CRITICISMS AGAINST THE ADMINISTRATION ON PROBLEM ON WHICH THEY THEMSELVES RARELY OFFER ANY NEW INITIATIVE, ONE HOPES THAT THE US ADMINISTRATION WILL KEEP ITS NEWLY-UNVEILED ANTI-DRUG PLAN UNDER CONSTANT SCRUTINY AND ENSURE THAT THE BATTLE THAT COLOMBIA IS BEING URGED TO WIN AT ALL COSTS IS NOT LOST WITHIN THE UNITED STATES.

DEV-MUC3-0495 (UMASS)

HAVANA (CUBA), NO DATE (CUBAVISION TELEVISION) -- [SPEECH] [CASTRO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] I BELIEVE THAT MANY HAVE BEEN PREPARING THEMSELVES DURING THE LAST YEARS. WHATEVER COURSE HISTORY MAY TAKE IN THE FUTURE, WE KNOW THAT HUNDREDS UPON HUNDREDS HAVE PREPARED THEMSELVES, AND WE KNOW THAT IN THEIR WISDOM THE CHILEAN PEOPLE WILL NOT ALLOW SUCH A SAD HISTORY TO BE REPEATED, BE WHENEVER IT MAY. [APPLAUSE]

WE HAVE NOT SOWN IN THE DESERT OR PLOWED AT SEA. THESE PAST 16 YEARS REPRESENT AN EXPERIENCE WHOSE VALUE IS VIRTUALLY IMPOSSIBLE TO ASSESS. IT IS CLEAR THAT IMPORTANT STEPS FORWARD HAVE BEEN TAKEN. IT IS CLEAR THAT THE PLEBISCITE WAS UNQUESTIONABLY A STEP FORWARD. I REMEMBER THE DAY WE UNVEILED ALLENDE'S BUST AT THE HOSPITAL. I EXPRESSED THE CERTAINTY THAT THE CHILEAN PEOPLE WOULD VOTE AGAINST PINOCHET, DESPITE PINOCHET'S RESOURCES AND THE PSYCHOLOGICAL WARFARE AND TERRORIST METHODS THAT WERE USED TO INTIMIDATE THE MASSES. IT WOULD BE IMPOSSIBLE FOR A PEOPLE TO FORGET THE MANY CRIMES AND MONSTROSITIES THAT HAVE BEEN COMMITTED. IT IS IMPOSSIBLE.

IN EFFECT, THE PLEBISCITE WAS A HARSH BLOW FOR PINOCHET. I THINK ALSO THAT THE ELECTIONS WILL BE AN EXTREMELY HARSH BLOW, PERHAPS AN IRREVERSIBLE BLOW, TO PINOCHET. HOWEVER, IT IS A FACT THAT NOBODY CAN ASSERT HERE THAT PINOCHET'S DEFEAT IN THE ELECTION WILL BE THE SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEM OF THE DICTATORSHIP IN CHILE. I AM NOT TALKING ABOUT A REVOLUTION. I THINK IT WOULD BE UNNECESSARY. THERE WOULD BE NO SENSE IN TALKING HERE ABOUT A REVOLUTION [WORD INDISTINCT] A STAGE ABOVE THE DEMOCRATIC OPENING. WE ARE TALKING ABOUT A DEMOCRATIC OPENING, BUT THE ELECTORAL VICTORY DOES NOT ENTAIL A SOLID DEMOCRATIC OPENING YET. HOWEVER, IN OUR OPINION IT WILL UNDOUBTEDLY REPRESENT ANOTHER VERY IMPORTANT STEP FORWARD.

PINOCHET WILL TRY TO STAY ON AS HEAD OF THE ARMY AND AS HEAD OF THE ARMED FORCES. WE COULD ALMOST SAY THAT HE WILL STAY ON AS A SORT OF SENTINEL, A POWER ON WHICH THE COUNTRY'S DESTINY WOULD CONTINUE TO HANG FOR SOME TIME TO COME. WHETHER HE CAN REALLY FULFILL THE GOALS HE HAS SET FOR HIMSELF REMAINS TO BE SEEN. HOWEVER, I AM CERTAIN HE WILL NOT GIVE UP POWER WITHOUT A STRUGGLE. ONLY THE CHILEAN PEOPLE CAN MAKE THIS AN IRREVERSIBLE STRUGGLE TO ACHIEVE A TRUE AND FULL DEMOCRATIC OPENING, AN OPENING WITHOUT ALL OF THE LIMITATIONS THAT THE REGIME HAS WRITTEN INTO ITS CONSTITUTION, WHICH GRANTS HIM ALL OF THESE RIGHTS -- TO BE A SENATOR FOR LIFE, AND, IF MY MEMORY DOES NOT FAIL ME, TO SERVE AS CHIEF OF THE ARMY FOR AN ADDITIONAL 8 YEARS. LOOK AT HIS HARANGUES. HIS HARANGUES ARE STILL AGGRESSIVE, HAUGHTY, AND THREATENING. WE HEAR WARNINGS. WE HEAR APPEALS TO THE ARMY TO REMAIN UNITED, BECAUSE HE WILL UNDOUBTEDLY TRY TO PERPETUATE HIMSELF.

I THINK HE WILL BE MORE AND MORE CORNERED BY THE CHILEAN PEOPLE, BECAUSE A NEW STAGE WILL BEGIN AFTER THE ELECTIONS. IT IS INEVITABLE THAT THE PEOPLE WILL PARTICIPATE TO A MUCH GREATER EXTENT. THEY WILL INEVITABLY HAVE A MUCH GREATER POSSIBILITY OF EXPRESSING THEMSELVES, OF ACTING, OF MOBILIZING, OF THINKING ABOUT WHAT IS ESSENTIAL AT THE MOMENT AND NOT ABOUT SHARES OF POWER. I THINK THEY HAVE TO BE...[CHANGES THOUGHT] THAT THIS IS REALLY AN ADMIRABLE TEST OF PATRIOTIC AND REVOLUTIONARY FEELING FOR THOSE WHO ARE NOT RIGHTISTS, FOR THOSE WHO ARE NOT CONSERVATIVES, FOR THOSE WHO ARE NOT EVEN IN THE CENTER BUT ON THE LEFT, AND WELL TO THE LEFT: TO GO TO THE POLLS AND TO VOTE, FORGETTING WHICH PARTY IT WAS THAT PUT FORWARD THE CANDIDATE FOR PRESIDENT, OR WHAT THE CANDIDATE'S POLITICAL THINKING IS, JUST THINKING OF CHILE, ONLY THINKING OF CHILE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0497 (UMASS)

HAVANA (CUBA), 16 SEP 89 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [COMMENTARY] [MANOLO ORTEGA] [TEXT] FOR THE FIRST TIME IN VIRTUALLY 10 YEARS OF ARMED CONFLICT, WHICH HAS CLAIMED ALMOST 70,000 LIVES, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND GUERRILLAS SIGNED AN AGREEMENT RECENTLY IN MEXICO CITY. THIS COULD MARK THE BEGINNING OF AN UNPRECEDENTED PATH OF PEACE FOR THAT CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY.

AFTER 2 DAYS OF TALKS, FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REPRESENTATIVES AND SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DELEGATES AGREED TO ESTABLISH A PERMANENT DIALOGUE TO SECURE A DEFINITE CEASE-FIRE. ON 16 AND 17 OCTOBER, THE COSTA RICAN CAPITAL WILL HOST THE MEETING BETWEEN THE NEGOTIATING PARTIES. THE EVENT WILL BE ATTENDED BY TWO REPRESENTATIVES OF THE CATHOLIC CHURCH AS MEDIATORS FOR THE SALVADORAN EPISCOPAL CONFERENCE. UN AND OAS REPRESENTATIVES WILL BE INVITED TO ATTEND AS WITNESSES.

ASIDE FROM MATTERS OF PROCEDURE, IT IS WORTHWHILE TO SAY THAT, IN ADDITION TO BEING DECISIVE IN ACHIEVING A SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN INTERNAL CRISIS, THE REBELS' RECENT PEACE INITIATIVE WAS A STRONG BLOW TO THE RULING ULTRA-RIGHTIST SECTOR. THE REBELS' WILLINGNESS TO END HOSTILITIES AND TURN THE FMLN INTO A POLITICAL PARTY PLACED BEFORE PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI THE DECISION OF CONTINUING THE WAR OR OPTING FOR PEACE.

AS OF THAT MOMENT, AND IN VIEW OF THE IMPORTANCE ASSIGNED TO THE TALKS BY THE INTERNATIONAL MEDIA AND ANALYSTS, INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION KEPT ABREAST OF THE DIALOGUE, WHICH IS SO VITAL FOR EL SALVADOR AND FOR CENTRAL AMERICA. FOR THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA], THE PROPOSALS WERE CLEARLY DEFINED TO AGREE ON A TOTAL CEASE-FIRE BEFORE 31 JANUARY, TO END THE REPRESSION, TO CONDUCT A PURGE IN THE ARMY, AND TO REORGANIZE THE JUDICIAL AND ELECTORAL SYSTEM.

ALTHOUGH DETAILS WERE NOT GIVEN ON HOW THE ISSUES WILL BE HANDLED, THE FACT REMAINS THAT DISCUSSIONS BETWEEN THE TWO PARTIES WILL BEGIN IN ONLY A MONTH. IT MEANS THAT THE VEILED GOVERNMENT INTENTION TO DELAY THE TALKS AND CONTINUE THE WAR, WHICH IT CANNOT WIN IN ANY EVENT, HAS FAILED. WE MIGHT EVEN ADD THAT THE ARENA GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN ON THE DEFENSIVE FROM THE BEGINNING, ESPECIALLY FOLLOWING THE TELA SUMMIT WHICH APPEALED TO THE SALVADORAN AUTHORITIES TO HOLD DIALOGUE AS SOON AS POSSIBLE WITH THE REBELS. PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S ATTEMPT TO SECURE THE FORCEFUL DEMOBILIZATION OF THE GUERRILLAS AND HIS ATTEMPT TO COMPARE THESE FORCES WITH THE NICARAGUAN COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES ALSO FAILED.

THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT'S POSITION AND ITS WILLINGNESS TO SECURE A DEFINITIVE PEACE AGREEMENT WILL BE IN EVIDENCE AT THE NEXT MEETINGS. MEANWHILE, THE PROSPECTS FOR ACHIEVING PEACE IN THE COUNTRY APPEAR TO BE FAVORABLE.

DEV-MUC3-0498 (UMASS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 20 SEP 89 (TASS) -- [TEXT] THE CENTRAL AMERICAN MASS MEDIA HAS REGARDED THE INTENTION OF SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TO CONTINUE NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE EXISTING CONSTITUTION AS A DEVIATION FROM RECENT AGREEMENTS WITH THE REBELS.

THE INTENTION IS OUTLINED IN A STATEMENT MADE BY THE PRESIDENT IN REPSONSE TO THE REBEL PROPOSAL TO GIVE UP THE ARMED STRUGGLE AND JOIN THE POLITICAL LIFE IF THE ARMY CLEANS UP ITS RANKS, IF REPRESSIONS ARE STOPPED, ELECTIONS TO MUNICIPAL AND LEGISLATIVE BODIES ARE HELD EARLIER THAN 1991 AND IF THE ELECTION SYSTEM IS REFORMED.

ACCORDING TO THE SALVADORAN MASS MEDIA, THIS PACKAGE OF PROPOSALS WILL BE DOMINATE THE FMLN TALKS WITH THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IN COSTA RICA IN OCTOBER.

AT THE SAME TIME, THE SALVADORAN POLICE HAVE STAGED ANOTHER ACT OF VIOLENCE IN SAN SALVADOR. SPECIAL POLICE UNITS DISPERSED A DEMONSTRATION ORGANISED BY THE FEDERATION OF SALVADORAN TRADE UNIONS IN PROTEST AGAINST THE ARREST OF 12 ACTIVISTS OF WORKERS' AND PEASANT ORGANISATIONS. ABOUT 100 DEMONSTRATORS SHELTERED IN A CATHEDRAL. BUT, THE POLICE SMASHED THE CATHEDRAL'S WINDOWS AND SHOT TEAR GAS INTO THE BUILDING. POLICEMEN ALSO OPENED FIRE AND ARMY HELICOPTERS CIRCLED OVER THE CATHEDRAL.

DESPITE THE FACT THAT MANY PEOPLE INSIDE WERE WOUNDED, THE POLICE DID NOT ALLOW RED CROSS REPRESENTATIVES TO APPROACH THE CATHEDRAL, AS DEMONSTRATORS DEMANDED.

ABOUT 60 DEMONSTRATORS WERE FIRST BRUTALLY BEATEN AND THEN ARRESTED, THE SAN SALVADORAN MASS MEDIA SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0499 (UMASS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 10 SEP 89 (MOSCOW) -- [REPORT] [LEONID LEVCHENKO] [TEXT] A U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE SPOKESMAN HAS INDICATED THAT WASHINGTON PROPOSES TO CONTINUE HELPING THE SALVADORAN REGIME UNTIL THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] COMBATANTS SURRENDER THEIR ARMS.

THE TIMING OF THIS STATEMENT IS REMARKABLE. LET US RECALL THAT LESS THAN 1 WEEK AGO REPRESENTATIVES OF THE REBEL FORCES AND THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT MET IN MEXICO, THUS LAUNCHING A DIALOGUE AIMED AT A NATIONAL RECONCILIATION. THE PARTIES AGREED TO CONTINUE THESE TALKS IN COSTA RICA ON 16 AND 17 OCTOBER, HOWEVER, EVEN THE FIRST ROUND OF TALKS IN MEXICO SHOWED THAT CONTINUING THE WAR WAS POINTLESS BECAUSE NEITHER OF THE PARTIES IS CAPABLE OF MILITARY DEFEATING THE OTHER. THUS, THE ONLY POSSIBLE VICTORY FOR ALL IS THE VICTORY OF COMMON SENSE. THIS CAN BE ACHIEVED ONLY THROUGH NATIONAL DIALOGUE. THE REBELS HAVE CORRECTLY MADE IT CLEAR THAT NO PRECONDITIONS CAN BE SET FOR CONTINUING DIALOGUE, AND LESS STILL CAN IT BE DEMANDED THAT THE FMLN COMBATANTS SHOULD UNILATERALLY SURRENDER THEIR ARMS.

IT SHOULD BE NOTED THIS DEMAND IS BEING MADE WHILE THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS GETTING CONSIDERABLE MILITARY AID FROM THE UNITED STATES AND, ACCORDING TO THE DEPARTMENT OF STATE SPOKESMAN, IT HAS NO PLANS TO DISCONTINUE THIS AID.

THE SALVADORAN MILITARY IS USING U.S.-MADE WEAPONS ONLY AGAINST THE REBELS AND NOT AGAINST ANY FOREIGN ENEMY. IT IS WELL KNOWN THAT THROUGHOUT THE 10 YEARS OF CIVIL WAR IN EL SALVADOR, THE UNITED STATES HAS SUPPLIED ALMOST $4 BILLION WORTH OF MILITARY AND NONMILITARY AID TO THAT COUNTRY. THANKS TO THIS ASSISTANCE, 70,000 SALVADORANS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND OVER 1 MILLION PEOPLE HAVE HAD TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY TO SAVE THEIR LIVES.

WE CAN SEE THAT ADDITIONAL U.S. MILITARY AID WILL INFLICT FURTHER UNTOLD SUFFERING AND MISFORTUNES ON THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. PUTTING AN END TO THIS ASSISTANCE AND TO ANY FURTHER INTERFERENCE IN SALVADORAN DOMESTIC AFFAIRS WOULD HELP DISPEL MUTUAL DISTRUST AND WOULD CREATE IN THE COUNTRY AN ATMOSPHERE FAVORABLE TO NATIONAL DIALOGUE. WASHINGTON'S DEMANDS THAT THE REBELS SHOULD SURRENDER THEIR ARMS AS A PRECONDITION FOR WASHINGTON TO RECONSIDER THE ISSUE OF MILITARY AID TO THE SALVADORAN REGIME REPRESENTS, AS FAR AS I AM CONCERNED, UNACCEPTABLE INTERFERENCE IN EL SALVADOR'S DOMESTIC AFFAIRS.

UNDOUBTEDLY, THE PROCESS OF NATIONAL RECONCILIATION MUST TAKE PLACE FREE OF ANY FOREIGN INTERFERENCE WHATSOEVER. I WOULD LIKE TO QUOTE JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, A REBEL LEADER, WHO TOLD THE NEW YORK TIMES THAT THE END OF U.S. MILITARY AID TO THE SALVADORAN REGIME WOULD LEAD TO AN IMMEDIATE END TO THE WAR.

DEV-MUC3-0500 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A HELICOPTER WAS DAMAGED, A REBEL WAS KILLED, AND TWO OTHERS WERE WOUNDED IN HEAVY CLASHES IN THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE COUNTRY, THE SALVADORAN ARMY REPORTED TODAY.

THE OFFICIAL BULLETIN REPORTS THAT A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REBEL WAS KILLED AND TWO OTHERS WERE WOUNDED TODAY IN CLASHES IN DULCE NOMBRE DE MARIA, AND NUEVA CONCEPCION, IN THE NORTHERN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

THE PRESS COMMITTEE OF THE ARMED FORCES (COPREFA) REPORTED THAT THE GUERRILLA'S ANTIAIRCRAFT FIRE ON 19 SEPTEMBER DAMAGED A U.S.- MADE UH-1H AIR FORCE HELICOPTER AS IT WAS EVACUATING A WOUNDED SOLDIER NEAR SAN JOSE GUAYABAL, 30 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR. THE ARMED CLASHES TOOK PLACE AMID THE FMLN 10-DAY UNILATERAL TRUCE DECREED BY THE FMLN ON 13 SEPTEMBER, WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE DIALOGUE HELD LAST WEEK IN MEXICO CITY BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE INSURGENTS.

MEANWHILE, AT LEAST THREE VILLAGES IN THE GUAZAPA HILL AREA, 25 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, TODAY REMAINED WITHOUT ELECTRICITY DUE TO THE INTENSE CLASHES WHICH LASTED UNTIL DAYBREAK.

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ONLY ADMITTED THAT A SOLDIER HAS BEEN KILLED IN THESE CLASHES AND THAT A HELICOPTER HAS BEEN DAMAGED. THE ARMY CLAIMS IT HAS INFLICTED SEVERAL CASUALTIES ON THE REBELS, BUT THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES IS STILL UNKNOWN.

ACCORDING TO CIVILIAN SOURCES IN THE ZONE, SEVERAL HELICOPTERS AND AN AIRPLANE ON 19 SEPTEMBER AND TODAY AT DAYBREAK BOMBED ALLEGED REBEL POSITIONS IN THE FOOTHILLS OF GUAZAPA HILL.

DEV-MUC3-0501 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 21 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] AN ESCALATION IN TERRORIST ACTS AFFECTED THE CAPITAL AND RESULTED IN ONE PERSON WOUNDED AND UNDETERMINED LARGE PROPERTY LOSSES.

NINE POWERFUL BOMBS EXPLODED ALMOST SIMULTANEOUSLY AT 0315 THIS MORNING AT EIGHT POLITICAL PARTIES' OFFICES AND A BRANCH OF THE SOCIAL SAVINGS ASSOCIATION.

ACCORDING TO AUTHORITIES, THE BOMBS WENT OFF AT THE POLITICAL OFFICE OF SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE COUNCILMAN DIEGO PARDO COPEL AT NO. 1810 ON 34TH STREET, THE POLITICAL OFFICES OF BOGOTA DISTRICT COUNCILMAN RICAURTE LOZANA VALDERRAMA AT NO. 2228 ON 37TH STREET AND NO. 2163 ON 34TH AVENUE, THE POLITICAL OFFICE OF SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE COUNCILMAN FRANCISCO FANADOR CABRERA LOCATED AT NO. 1824 ON 32D AVENUE, A LIBERAL PARTY OFFICE LOCATED AT NO. 1866 ON 36TH STREET, A LIBERAL PARTY REGISTRATION OFFICE LOCATED AT NO. 1976 28TH AVENUE, AN INDEPENDENT CONSERVATIVE PARTY OFFICE AT NO. 2326 37TH STREET, THE POLITICAL OFFICE OF MIGUEL SANTAMARIA DAVILA AT NO. 4136 28TH AVENUE, AND AT A BRANCH OF THE SOCIAL SAVINGS ASSOCIATION AT NO. 5119 ON 86TH STREET.

THE DETONATIONS SHOOK TEUSAQUILLO NEIGHBORHOOD, AND ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL REPORTS, THE AUTHORITIES FELT COMPELLED TO INCREASE SECURITY MEASURES.

THE WOUNDED PERSON WAS IDENTIFIED AS IRMA DE PUENTES, WHO WAS QUICKLY TREATED AT A CLINIC AND RELEASED BECAUSE SHE HAD ONLY A MINOR WOUND IN THE LEG.

DEV-MUC3-0502 (UMASS)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 22 SEP 89 (REUTER) -- [ARTICLE] [PAUL IREDALE] [TEXT] ACCORDING TO WESTERN DIPLOMATS, COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE MOVED TO GUATEMALA IN SEARCH OF NEW SUPPLY ROUTES, BRINGING INSTABILITY TO A COUNTRY THAT IS EXPERIENCING A WAVE OF VIOLENCE FROM VARIOUS SECTORS.

THE DIPLOMATS BELIEVE THAT UP TO 200 COLOMBIANS LINKED TO THE MEDELLIN AND CALI CARTELS ARE NOW OPERATING IN GUATEMALA AND THAT ABOUT 500 KG OF COCAINE PASS EVERY WEEK THROUGH THE COUNTRY, ESSENTIALLY ENROUTE TO THE U.S. MARKET.

THE INCREASING DRUG TRAFFICKING ACTIVITY COINCIDES WITH A NEW WAVE OF KIDNAPPINGS, BOMBINGS, AND MURDERS IN GUATEMALA, AWAKENING FEARS THAT THE COUNTRY WILL RETURN TO THE VIOLENCE PREVALENT AT THE BEGINNING OF THE DECADE, WHEN THOUSANDS WERE KILLED BY DEATH SQUADS DURING MILITARY REGIMES.

SINCE AUGUST, A PROMINENT POLITICIAN, A WELL-KNOWN BANKER, AND AT LEAST FIVE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS HAVE BEEN MURDERED. SEVERAL BOMBS HAVE EXPLODED IN THE CAPITAL IN RECENT MONTHS AND STUDENTS AND HUMAN RIGHTS ACTIVISTS ARE MISSING.

"ALL OF THIS VIOLENCE CANNOT BE BLAMED ON A [WORDS INDISTINCT], BUT THE INCREASE OF DRUG TRAFFICKING IS CLEARLY AN ADDITIONAL CONCERN."

IN ADDITION TO THE COCAINE, WHICH THE DIPLOMATS SAY IS TAKEN TO THE UNITED STATES ABOARD LIGHT PLANES OR IN AUTOMOBILES THROUGH MEXICO AND TEXAS, U.S. OFFICIALS HAVE REPORTED AN INCREASE IN OPIUM PRODUCTION IN GUATEMALA. ACCORDING TO ESTIMATES, THE NUMBER OF HECTARES PLANTED WENT FROM 225 IN 1985 TO 1,500 THIS YEAR.

THERE ARE INSISTENT RUMORS THAT BANKER RAMIRO CASTILLO LOVE WAS MURDERED OUTSIDE HIS HOUSE ON 25 AUGUST BECAUSE HE REFUSED TO LAUNDER DRUG MONEY. THERE IS OPEN TALK IN THE CAPITAL ABOUT IMPORTANT POLITICIANS BEING LINKED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING.

NEVERTHELESS, THE DIPLOMATS SAY THAT THERE IS NO EVIDENCE TO BACK SUCH SPECULATION AND THEY ADD THAT IT IS VERY LIKELY THAT SEVERAL INTERESTS ARE WORKING TO DESTABILIZE THE COUNTRY'S FRAGILE DEMOCRACY.

"IT SEEMS AS IF SEVERAL STRINGS ARE BEING PULLED AT THE SAME TIME," A DIPLOMAT SAID.

WHILE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO HAS GIVEN GUATEMALA A RESPITE, AFTER DECADES OF MILITARY REGIMES DURING WHICH IT IS BELIEVED THAT MORE THAN 100,000 PEOPLE WERE KILLED AS A RESULT OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE, IT IS ESTIMATED THAT APPROXIMATELY 1,200 LEFTIST GUERRILLAS ARE STILL FIGHTING IN THE MOUNTAINS.

FURTHERMORE, THE COUNTRY HAS FACED TWO COUP ATTEMPTS SINCE DEMOCRACY WAS RESTORED IN 1986.

THE ULTRA-RIGHT-WING, WITH ITS TIES TO THE LAND-OWNING OLIGARCHY, CONTINUES TO BE A POWERFUL FORCE IN THE COUNTRY. IT HAS BLOCKED A MAJORITY OF REFORMS THAT CEREZO HAS TRIED TO INTRODUCE AND, ACCORDING TO THE GENERAL CONSENSUS, IT HAS PROMOTED DISCONTENT AMONG THE ARMED FORCES' MID-LEVEL OFFICERS.

"THE ULTRA-RIGHT-WING IS UNDOUBTEDLY BEHIND PART OF THE VIOLENCE," SAID A DIPLOMAT. "IT COULD BE TRYING TO FORCE THE GOVERNMENT TO OVERREACT OR CAUSE THE ARMY TO GET INVOLVED."

AS IF TO CONFIRM THIS, A POLICE ARREST WARRANT HAS BEEN ISSUED AGAINST FORMER PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LIONEL SISNIEGA, A NOTED POLITICIAN WHO LEANS TO THE RIGHT AND HAS BEEN INVOLVED IN COUP ATTEMPTS SINCE 1954, ON CHARGES OF HEADING A GROUP RESPONSIBLE FOR MUCH OF THE VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY.

DIPLOMATS HAVE ALSO POINTED TO THE RESURGENCE OF ACTIVITIES BY LEFT-WING GUERRILLAS WHO HAVE BEEN STRUGGLING TO TOPPLE SUCCESSIVE GOVERNMENTS OVER THE PAST 2 DECADES.

"NOWADAYS THEY ARE USING MUCH MORE OBVIOUS TACTICS, ERECTING BARRICADES ON HIGHWAYS AND OCCUPYING SMALL TOWNS NEAR THE CAPITAL," ONE DIPLOMAT SAID.

FEAR THAT THE VIOLENCE OF THE SEVENTIES WILL RETURN MAY ALSO CONTRIBUTE TOWARD A RESURGENCE IN THE NUMBER OF ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS THAT CROSS OVER TO MEXICO.

MEXICAN AUTHORITIES SAY THAT THE NUMBER OF UNDOCUMENTED CENTRAL AMERICANS DEPORTED TO GUATEMALA HAS DOUBLED OVER THE PAST FEW MONTHS.

THE DIPLOMATS FEEL THAT CEREZO'S GOVERNMENT WILL WEATHER THE VIOLENCE AND PASS IT ONTO HIS SUCCESSOR AFTER THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS SCHEDULED FOR NOVEMBER 1990.

"PERHAPS THE SITUATION IS THE RESULT OF THE PREPARATION FOR ELECTIONS IN GUATEMALA," A DIPLOMAT SAID. "THINGS WILL PROBABLY WORSEN NEXT YEAR."

DEV-MUC3-0505 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 22 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [REPORT] [CARLOS MARIO MARQUEZ] [TEXT] A FEW MINUTES AGO, DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS ANNOUNCED THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE WILLING TO STUDY THE POSSIBILITY OF A TROOP REDUCTION IF AN AGREEMENT IS REACHED WITH THE LEFTIST REBELS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT. GENERAL LARIOS MADE THESE STATEMENTS TO FOUR DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL MEDIA REPORTERS. HERE ARE EXCERPTS OF GENERAL LARIOS' STATEMENTS WHEN HE ANNOUNCED THAT THE ARMED FORCES WOULD CONSIDER A REDUCTION IN TROOPS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LARIOS] [IN PROGRESS] ... WHEN IT INVOLVES DAMAGING THE INSTITUTION -- IN THIS CASE THE ARMED FORCES -- WE MUST UNDERSTAND THAT WE WERE NOT BORN ON A WHIM, OR BY HAPPENSTANCE OR ACCIDENT. WE ARE A CONSTITUTIONAL INSTITUTION AND THE CONSTITUTION HAS ESTABLISHED CLEAR TASKS FOR US. THUS, OUR INSTITUTION IS AUTHENTIC AND LEGAL.

BECAUSE OF THIS, THE CONCEPT OR CRITERIA OF A REDUCTION IN ARMED FORCES PERSONNEL CAN BE MANAGED IF IT IS BASED ON VERY PARTICULAR AND SPECIFIC TERMS. IF, FOR EXAMPLE, WE REACH A POLITICAL AGREEMENT WITH THE TERRORIST FORCES FOR THEIR PEACEFUL RETURN TO THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC LIFE, THEN THIS WOULD MEAN THE END OF THE ARMED CONFLICT. IT WOULD ALSO MEAN THAT WE, AS THE COUNTRY'S ARMED FORCES, WOULD HAVE TO STUDY AND RECONSIDER THE NEED FOR THE NUMBER OF TROOPS THAT WE PRESENTLY HAVE AVAILABLE TO CONFRONT AN IMPOSED SITUATION, AN AGGRESSION OF A MARXIST-LENINIST NATURE. IF AN AGREEMENT IN THIS SENSE IS REACHED, WE WOULD BE WILLING TO ANALYZE THE INSTITUTION'S INTERNAL SITUATION TO DETERMINE THE AMOUNT OF HUMAN RESOURCES NEEDED TO COMPLY WITH OUR CONSTITUTIONAL RESPONSIBILITY. [END RECORDING]

THOSE WERE STATEMENTS BY THE DEFENSE MINISTER AT NOON. HE ANNOUNCED THAT THE ARMED FORCES WOULD BE WILLING TO STUDY A REDUCTION IN FORCES IF AN AGREEMENT IS REACHED BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND REBEL COMMISSIONS AT THE MEETING TO BE HELD IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, ON 16 AND 17 OCTOBER. GENERAL LARIOS SAID THAT PEACE WILL BE ATTAINED BEFORE THE ESTABLISHED DATE IF THE REBELS SHOW THEIR GOOD WILL TO END THE ARMED CONFLICT IN OUR COUNTRY. THIS WAS LAST MINUTE NEWS. THIS IS THE FIRST TIME A DEFENSE MINISTER HAS MADE SUCH AN ANNOUNCEMENT IN THE PAST 9 YEARS.

DEV-MUC3-0507 (UMASS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 18 SEP 89 (PRENSA LIBRE) -- [TEXT] ARMY SPOKESMAN COLONEL LUIS ARTURO ISAACS HAS SAID THAT POSSESSION OF WAR MATERIEL DESIGNATED FOR THE EXCLUSIVE USE OF THE MILITARY MAKES LIONEL SISNIEGA OTERO A TERRORIST. HOWEVER, COL ISAAC DID NOT CONFIRM WHETHER SISNIEGA WAS INVOLVED IN THE TERRORIST ATTACK THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN THE PAST FEW WEEKS.

INVESTIGATIONS HAVE CONFIRMED THAT IT WAS LIONEL SISNIEGA OTERO WH SUPPLIED THE GRENADES TO THOSE WHO ARE NOW UNDER ARREST. ONCE ARRESTED, SISNIEGA WILL HAVE TO EXPLAIN TO THE COURT WHY HE HAD THE WEAPONS, COL ISAACS ADDED.

COL ISAACS CONFIRMED THAT MILITARY INTELLIGENCE IS INVESTIGATING HOW AND FROM WHERE SISNIEGA OTERO OBTAINED THE WAR MATERIEL.

THE MILITARY SPOKESMAN SAID THE POSSESSION OF WAR MATERIEL BY CIVILIANS IS PROHIBITED AND PUNISHABLE BY LAW. IN THIS RESPECT, CIVILIAN PROTECTION SYSTEM AUTHORITIES SHOULD DEEPEN THEIR INVESTIGATIONS AND THE COURTS SHOULD BE STRICTER.

ASKED ABOUT THE SURPRISING AND SUDDEN MANNER IN WHICH CAPTAIN LIONEL SISNIEGA CORDERO, SON OF SISNIEGA OTERO, WAS SENT OUT OF THE COUNTRY, COL ISAACS SAID THAT IT HAD BEEN DONE FOR HIS PERSONAL SAFETY, SINCE ANY EXTREMIST FACTION COULD TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE SITUATION TO TRY TO HARM HIM.

ISAACS CONFIRMED THAT CAPT SISNIEGA OTERO WAS APPOINTED MILITARY ATTACHE AT THE GUATEMALAN EMBASSY IN VENEZUELA AND THAT FILLING THIS POSITION IS PART OF THE SOLDIER'S DUTY.

WHEN ASKED WHETHER CAPT SISNIEGA CORDERO COULD HAVE SUPPLIED THE WEAPONS TO HIS FATHER, COL ISAACS REJECTED THE POSSIBILITY, ADDING THAT EVERY OFFICER KNOWS PERFECTLY WELL THAT KEEPING WAR MATERIEL AT HOME IS FORBIDDEN AND IN VIOLATION OF ARMED FORCES DIRECTIVES.

POSSESSION OF WEAPONS IS A MISDEMEANOR AND NOT A FELONY, COL ISAAC SAID. AS AN EXAMPLE, HE SAID HE HAS A "GALIL" WHICH HE KEEPS AT HIS OFFICE, ALTHOUGH HE CARRIES HIS HANDGUN WHEREVER HE GOES.

HOWEVER, HE SAID THE POSSIBILITY IS BEING INVESTIGATED, ALTHOUGH H CONSIDERS IT FAR-FETCHED. AS A RULE THE ARMY PROTECTS ITS MEMBERS, AN THIS IS PRECISELY WHY CAPT SISNIEGA CORDERO WAS GIVEN DIPLOMATIC STATUS AND SENT TO VENEZUELA.

ON ANOTHER SUBJECT, COL ISAACS SAID HE HAD NO KNOWLEDGE OF A GUERRILLA ATTACK ON THE ACATENENGO DETACHMENT, POINTING OUT THAT THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY (URNG) MAKES FALSE CLAIMS THAT DO NOT CORRESPOND WITH REALITY.

THERE HAVE BEEN PERSISTENT RUMORS OF A RECENT SUBVERSIVE GROUP ATTACK ON THE ACATENANGO DETACHMENT DURING WHICH MANY CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED.

DEV-MUC3-0510 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 22 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A DISTRIBUTION AGENCY OF THE BOGOTA NEWSPAPER EL ESPECTADOR AND THE OFFICE OF THE MORNING NEWSPAPER EL SIGLO WERE THE TARGETS OF TERRORIST ATTACKS TONIGHT WHICH LEFT ONE POLICEMAN SLIGHTLY INJURED AND CAUSED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE, THE AUTHORITIES HAVE REPORTED.

IN THE FIRST ATTACK, A 5-KG DYNAMITE CHARGE EXPLODED IN A BRANCH OF EL ESPECTADOR IN THE SUBURB OF NORMANDIA IN THE WESTERN PART OF BOGOTA.

A SECURITY GUARD WAS INJURED BY THE SHATTERED GLASS CAUSED BY THE IMPACT OF THE EXPLOSION.

ALTHOUGH THE NEWSPAPER OFFICE WAS NOT SERIOUSLY DAMAGED, SOME 10 HOMES NEARBY WERE.

THE PRINCIPAL OFFICE OF EL ESPECTADOR, A NEWSPAPER WHICH HAS MAINTAINED A HARDLINE POSITION ON DRUG TRAFFICKING AND WHOSE DIRECTOR WAS ASSASSINATED IN DECEMBER 1986, WAS THE TARGET OF A VIOLENT CAR BOMB ATTACK 20 DAYS AGO.

IN ANOTHER TERRORIST ACTION, SEVERAL MEN IN A VEHICLE OPENED FIRE ON THE OFFICES OF THE NEWSPAPER EL SIGLO, BUT NOBODY WAS INJURED.

THIS IS THE SECOND ATTACK OF THIS KIND AGAINST THE NEWSPAPER IN THE PAST FEW DAYS. THE DIRECTOR OF THE NEWSPAPER IS FORMER PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE ALVARO GOMEZ.

IN VIEW OF THE INCREASED DYNAMITE ATTACKS SINCE 21 SEPTEMBER, WHEN NINE POLITICAL OFFICES AND THREE BANK BRANCHES WERE ATTACKED, THE ARMY AND POLICE HAVE INCREASED VIGILANCE IN BOGOTA.

DEV-MUC3-0511 (UMASS)

KINGSTON (JAMAICA), 23 SEP 89 (CANA) -- [TEXT] SECURITY AT THE COLOMBIAN EMBASSY IN KINGSTON HAS BEEN TIGHTENED FOLLOWING A BOMB THREAT ON MONDAY [18 SEPTEMBER], THE GLEANER NEWSPAPER REPORTED.

SINCE MONDAY, THERE HAS BEEN AN INCREASED PRESENCE OF UNIFORMED POLICEMEN ON GUARD OUTSIDE AND INSIDE THE XEROX BUILDING WHERE THE COLOMBIAN EMBASSY HAS ITS OFFICES.

REPRESENTATIVES OF THE COLOMBIAN EMBASSY WERE UNWILLING TO TALK TO CANA, BUT THE GLEANER REPORTED THAT MINISTER OF NATIONAL SECURITY K.D. KNIGHT HAD CONFIRMED THAT THREATS HAD BEEN MADE AGAINST THE EMBASSY AND THAT THE NECESSARY PRECAUTIONS HAD BEEN PUT IN PLACE. HE SAID THERE WAS NO NEED FOR ALARM. KNIGHT SAID THAT THE EMBASSY HAD RECEIVED A THREATENING NOTE AND THAT THE MINISTRY HAD ALSO RECEIVED ONE THROUGH A "CHANNEL", BUT GAVE NO DETAILS.

SINCE TAKING OFFICE, THE MANLEY GOVERNMENT HAS EXPRESSED ITS FIRM COMMITMENT TO STAMP OUT DRUG ABUSE AND DRUG TRAFFICKING. JAMAICA IS SAID TO BE A TRANSSHIPMENT POINT FOR DRUGS SHIPPED FROM SOME LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES TO THE UNITED STATES.

THE NATIONAL SECURITY MINISTER, HOWEVER, SAID THAT FROM ALL INDICATIONS THE ACTION WAS A "TOTALLY INTERNAL ONE" AND THERE WAS NO OBVIOUS CONNECTIONS WITH THE DRUG WAR BETWEEN THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT AND THE MEDELLIN DRUG CARTEL. "WE ARE LOOKING AT THE MATTER WITH ALL SERIOUSNESS, BUT PRESENT INDICATIONS SHOW THAT WE DO NOT NEED TO BE ALARMED AND ADDITIONAL SECURITY MEASURES HAVE ALREADY BEEN PUT IN PLACE", HE SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0513 (UMASS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 22 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A HIGH-RANKING MILITARY SOURCE CLOSE TO VINICIO CEREZO'S GOVERNMENT SUGGESTED TODAY THAT "THE OFFICERS OF THE MOUNTAIN" [ODEM], A SECRET MILITARY ORGANIZATION THAT CONDUCTED TWO FAILED COUPS IN THE LAST YEAR AND A HALF, MAY BE INVOLVED IN THE WAVE OF TERRORIST EXPLOSIONS, ABDUCTIONS, AND POLITICAL MURDERS THAT HAS BEEN SCOURGING GUATEMALA OVER THE LAST 2 MONTHS.

THE MILITARY SOURCE, WHO MADE STATEMENTS TO AFP ON THE CONDITION THAT HIS IDENTITY WAS NOT REVEALED, SAID THAT "THOSE GENTLEMEN (ODEM) HAVE BECOME THE NUMBER ONE ENEMY" OF CEREZO'S GOVERNMENT.

THE SOURCE ADDED THAT "THE COUNTRY IS AGAIN FACING CERTAIN THREATS, INCLUDING THAT OF THOSE GENTLEMEN."

THUS FAR, NOBODY KNOWS FOR SURE WHO THE MEMBERS OF THE ORGANIZATION ARE, ALTHOUGH SOME MEDIA SOURECES CLAIM THEY ARE "VERY POWERFUL AND WELL ORGANIZED."

AMID THE TERRORIST ACTIVITY THAT HAS BEEN SHAKING GUATEMALA OVER THE LAST 2 MONTHS, "ODEM" HAS BEEN MARKING ITS INCREASING PRESENCE THROUGH FREQUENT COMMUNIQUES RELEASED CLANDESTINELY IN GUATEMALA CITY. IN THE COMMUNIQUES, IT LAUNCHES HARSH ATTACKS ON THE CURRENT GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT.

IN ONE OF THEIR MOST RECENT COMMUNIQUES, WHICH THEY CIRCULATED IN GUATEMALA CITY LAST WEEK, THE REBEL MILITARY MEN SAY: "WE WILL NOT STOP UNTIL WE CHANGE THIS SYSTEM OF ANARCHY, CORRUPTION, AND DRUG TRAFFICKING.

ACCORDING TO AN OFFICIAL ARMY SPOKESMAN, THE SEDITIOUS MILITARYMEN "ARE OFFICERS WHO WERE REMOVED FROM POWER IN THE LAST FEW YEARS AND LOST ALL THEIR LEADERSHIP IN THE BARRACKS. THEIR RESENTMENT IS BEING MANIPULATED BY POLITICAL, CONSERVATIVE FORCES.

"THEY ARE MANIPULATED BY PEOPLE OF THE EXTREME RIGHT, IN OTHER WORDS, BY POLITICAL CRIMINALS WHO WANT TO RETURN TO POWER TO REGAIN THEIR PAST PRIVILEGES." THIS WAS STATED TODAY BY ONE OF THE MILITRAY OFFICERS WHO LINKED THE THE ODEM TO THE ESCALATION OF TERRORISM IN THE COUNTRY.

THE SAME SOURCE ADMITTED THAT THE SUSPECTED MILITARY TERRORISTS COULD HAVE "SUPPORTERS" WITHIN THE ARMY, BUT ADDED THAT "THE UNITY" OF THE GUATEMALAN ARMED FORCES IS NOT THREATENED BY THEM.

IN THEIR FREQUENT COMMUNIQUES, ODEM IDENTIFIES ITSELF AS "PATRIOTS WHO OPPOSE THE COMMUNIST AND CORRUPT SYSTEM THEY [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] WANT TO IMPOSE ON US THROUGH THE CURRENT POLICY IMPLEMENTED BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKING CLIQUE IN POWER."

DEV-MUC3-0515 (UMASS)

QUITO, 14 SEP 89 (EL COMERCIO) -- [TEXT] THE ECUADORAN POLICE DEALT A HARSH BLOW TO DRUG TRAFFICKING WHEN IT CAPTURED JUAN HERNANDO GONZALEZ AND GERMAN BELANDRIA, TWO DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHO WORKED FOR THE COLOMBIAN CARTELS.

ACTING GOVERNMENT MINISTER LUIS FELIX LOPEZ SAID THE TWO COLOMBIANS WERE ARRESTED IN TAISHA, IN THE CENTRAL EASTERN REGION, WHEN THEIR AIRPLANE VIOLATED ECUADOR'S AIR SPACE.

THE AIRPLANE, A LUXURY CESSNA 210 TWIN-MOTOR AIRCRAFT WITH A COLOMBIAN REGISTRATION, WAS FORCED TO LAND BY THE ECUADORAN ARMED FORCES.

ACCORDING TO ECUADOR RADIO, THE AIRCRAFT MADE AN EMERGENCY LANDING IN THE AREA OF BUFFO IN PASTAZA PROVINCE. THE RADIO ADDED THAT THE AIRPLANE, NAMED CENTURION, IS WHITE AND HAS THE REGISTRATION NUMBER H-K-27-29.

ONCE THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE ARRESTED THEY WERE BROUGHT TO QUITO AND DEPORTED TO COLOMBIA, WHERE THEY WILL BE TRIED.

ACTING MINISTER LOPEZ SAID THAT THE EVENT OCCURRED IN TAISHA AT 1000 ON 14 SEPTEMBER. THE AIRCRAFT, WHICH WAS FLYING OVER ECUADORAN TERRITORY TOWARD AN UNKNOWN DESTINATION, IS NOW IN CUSTODY OF THE ECUADORAN ARMED FORCES AT THE TAISHA AIRPORT.

THE TWO TRAFFICKERS HAD $336,000 IN THEIR POSSESSION.

LOPEZ SAID THAT THE ECUADORAN GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO STOP THE INFILTRATION OF FOREIGNERS, PARTICULARLY THOSE INVOLVED IN DRUG TRAFFICKING ACTIVITIES.

THE ARREST OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS WAS COORDINATED BY THE MINISTRY OF DEFENSE AND THE POLICE.

GONZALEZ AND BELANDRIA ARE PRESUMABLY LINKED WITH DRUG TRAFFICKING ACTIVITIES, GIVEN THE LARGE AMOUNT OF MONEY THEY CARRIED AND THE FACT THAT THEY WERE CLANDESTINELY FLYING OVER ECUADORAN TERRITORY.

IT IS PRESUMED THAT THE AIRCRAFT WAS COVERING THE CALI-PUERTO ASIS-LETICIA (COLOMBIA) ROUTE.

DEV-MUC3-0516 (UMASS)

CLANDESTINE, 22 SEP 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THE U.S. SENATORS HAVE MADE A MISTAKE. THEY HAD A GREAT DEBATE TO [WORDS INDISTINCT] A SIGN SHOWING THEIR WILLINGNESS TO HELP SUPPORT THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, THEY VOTED IN FAVOR OF CONTINUING WITH THE MILITARY AID [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THEY APPROVED AID THAT WILL BE INVESTED IN WAR, WHICH WE BELIEVE IS NOT A SIGN OF PEACE. THERE WERE TWO POSITIONS AT THE SENATE: THOSE WHO ADVOCATED THAT THE AID BE DIVIDED IN THREE PACKAGES TO CONTINUE THE DELIVERY OF THE LAST PORTION OF THE AID TO THE GOVERNMENT AMID THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, AND THOSE WHO WANTED TO GIVE UNCONDITIONAL AID TO CRISTIANI, A POSITION BASICALLY DEFENDED BY CHRISTOPHER DODD. SENATOR DODD HIMSELF SAID THIS AID IS ALLEGEDLY TO ENCOURAGE CRISTIANI BECAUSE HE IS ACCOMPLISHING WHAT THE UNITED STATES HAS BEEN TRYING TO ACCOMPLISH IN THE PAST 10 YEARS.

HOWEVER, THE U.S. SENATORS MADE A MISTAKE. THEY VOTED FOR THE UNCONDITIONAL AID WHICH ACTUALLY ENCOURAGES THE MILITARY MEN AND THE HARDLINERS IN ARENA [NATIONALISTIC REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] WHO ARE BLOCKING THE POLITICAL SOLUTION OF THE CONFLICT AND WHO UNREASONABLY PROMOTE THE CONTINUATION OF THE WAR. THIS IS NOT A SIGN FOR THE MODERATES. THE VOTING FOR UNCONDITIONAL AID IS INTERPRETED BY THE FASCISTS, THE WARMONGERING, THE ARENA [WORDS INDISTINCT] AS A BLANK CHECK TO CONTINUE WITH THE ADVENTURE OF WAR. THIS WAS THE TIME FOR U.S. DEMOCRATS AND REPUBLICANS TO SUPPORT WITH THEIR VOTING THE REGIONAL EFFORT AND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S EFFORT TO ATTAIN PEACE IN EL SALVADOR.

THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS TAKEN UNMISTAKABLE STEPS THAT EXPRESS ITS WILLINGNESS TO HELP ATTAIN PEACE. HOWEVER, IT SEEMS THE U.S. SENATORS ARE MISINFORMED ABOUT EVENTS IN EL SALVADOR: THE INCREASE IN HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS, THE ARRESTS, THE BOMBINGS, THE WAR PARADES, AND THE HARASSMENT OF THE PRESS. IN SUM, THESE ARE WAR ACTIONS AMID A NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL DEMAND FOR NEGOTIATIONS TO ATTAIN PEACE.

THE U.S. SENATORS MADE A MISTAKE. WAR ACTIONS IN EL SALVADOR ARE CONTRARY TO THE EXPECTATIONS OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND CLEARLY COME FROM THE [WORDS INDISTINCT], THE ARENA HARDLINERS. THEY ALSO ALSO FROM THE U.S. SENATORS WHO VOTED IN FAVOR OF THE UNCONDITIONAL AID. THEREFORE, THE U.S. SENATORS GAVE A SIGN [WORDS INDISTINCT] ARE ENCOURAGING THE WAR WITH THIS BLANK CHECK TO THE ARENA GOVERNMENT.

DEV-MUC3-0517 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 23 SEP 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [MAURICIO FUNES] [TEXT] SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT FRANCISCO MERINO STATED TODAY THAT THE MILITARY ASPECTS OF THE AGREEMENTS THAT THE GOVERNMENT MAY REDUCTIONS. ACCORDING TO THE VICE PRESIDENT, AN EFFECTIVE CEASEFIRE AGREEMENT WITH THE FMLN MUST ALSO INCLUDE THE CONTROL OF VIOLENT ACTIONS BY MASS ORGANIZATIONS IN EL SALVADOR. MERINO MADE REFERENCE TO THE DOUBTS THAT CERTAIN MILITARY COMMAND SECTORS HAVE ABOUT THE FMLN'S PROPOSAL. HE SAID THAT THESE DOUBTS ARE PRESENT, MAINLY BECAUSE THE REBELS HAVE NOT KEPT THEIR PUBLIC PROMISES CONCERNING MILITARY ACTIONS IN THE PAST. HOWEVER, THE OFFICIAL COMMENTED THAT, IN THE LONG RUN, A CEASEFIRE AGREEMENT WOULD LEAD TO NEGOTIATIONS ON IMPORTANT ISSUES, SUCH AS MILITARY TROOP REDUCTIONS, THAT MUST BE ACCEPTED BY THE ARMED FORCES. LET US HEAR VICE PRESIDENT MERINO:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] WE CANNOT IGNORE THAT THE FMLN AND EVEN THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT HAVE MADE PROMISES THAT THEY NEVER KEPT. THE ARMED FORCES ARE A PERMANENT INSTITUTION AND THEY HAVE PREVIOUSLY SUFFERED THE NONCOMPLIANCE OF AGREEMENTS THAT HAD BEEN MADE BY THE PREVIOUS GOVERNMENT WITH THE FMLN. NOW, THE LACK OF TRUST MUST BE OVERCOME WITH SPECIFIC ACTIONS IN THE FUTURE. HERE, WE HAVE SOMETHING THAT MUST BE CLEARLY APPRECIATED. THE GOVERNMENT IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. THE ARMED FORCES ARE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT; THEY ARE AN INSTITUTION. PRESIDENT CRISTIANI IS THE GENERAL COMMANDER OF THE ARMED FORCES. THUS, THE ARMED FORCES' POSITION IS ALSO INCLUDED IN PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S STATEMENTS. [END RECORDING]

ACCORDING TO MERINO, COMMENTARIES THAT HAVE BEEN MADE BY SEVERAL MILITARY COMMANDERS ARE TO BE UNDERSTOOD AS COMMENTARIES OUTSIDE ANY AGREEMENT THAT THE GOVERNMENT MAY REACH WITH THE REBELS. ON THE SAME SUBJECT, THE VICE PRESIDENT ALSO COMMENTED THAT IT IS NECESSARY FOR THE GUERRILLAS TO CHANGE THEIR MILITARY BEHAVIOR, AS THEY HAVE TO SHOW THAT THEY REALLY WANT TO START A PROGRESSIVE WAR DE-ESCALATION PROCESS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] THE EFFECTIVENESS AND TOTALITY WITH WHICH THE FMLN STOPS HOSTILITIES; CEASES ITS ACTS OF SABOTAGE AGAINST ELECTRICITY, COMMUNICATIONS, AND PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION FACILITIES; AND STOPS THE USE OF MINES WILL DETERMINE THE LEVEL OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY'S OFFENSIVE ACTIONS. THIS IS LOGICAL, AS WHEN THERE IS NO AGGRESSION, THERE CAN BE NO ACTION TO COUNTER IT. [END RECORDING]

MERINO SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT PROPOSAL INCLUDES AN AGREEMENT FOR THE FMLN TO DRASTICALLY DECREASE STREET VIOLENCE IN EL SALVADOR, SUCH AS THE VIOLENCE PROMOTED BY MASS ORGANIZATIONS RECENTLY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] HOSTILITIES ARE NOT ONLY THOSE ACTIONS THAT INCLUDE THE USE OF MILTARY FORCE, SUCH AS MINES, BOMBS, AND SO ON. THEY ALSO INCLUDE FMLN MASS ORGANIZATION ACTIONS THAT ARE CARRIED OUT MAINLY IN SAN SALVADOR AND ARE CREATING A CERTAIN DEGREE OF DESTABILIZATION. IT IS A KIND OF URBAN TERRORISM, AS THESE GROUPS ARE DISTORTING THE RIGHT TO PROTEST OR THE RIGHT OF EXPRESSION. THESE ORGANIZATIONS ARE NO LONGER ONLY CARRYING A MESSAGE, BUT HAVE STARTED TO DESTROY AND DAMAGE PRIVATE PROPERTY AND PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION, AND THREATEN THE CITIZENS' INTEGRITY. THUS, YOU SEE HERE A DIRECT RELATIONSHIP WHICH DEMANDS THAT THE FMLN MILITARY ACTIONS AND CEASEFIRE MUST INCLUDE URBAN ACTIONS, AS WELL. A CEASEFIRE MUST ALSO INCLUDE THAT THE FMLN WILL NOT CARRY OUT OFFENSIVE ACTIONS OR ACTIONS BY FACADE GROUPS IN THE CITIES THAT PROMOTE STREET DISORDER. [END RECORDING]

DURING PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S 15-DAY-ABSENCE, MERINO REPORTED THAT HE WILL WORK ON THE PROPOSAL THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL PRESENT TO THE FMLN IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA ON 16 OCTOBER, WITH AN ADVISORY COMMISSION FORMED BY MILITARY OFFICERS, PRIVATE BUSINESSMEN, INTELLECTUALS, AND POLITICAL PARTY LEADERS.

DEV-MUC3-0518 (UMASS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 24 SEP 89 (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN FOREIGN MINISTER MARIO PALENCIA WAS ASKED TODAY ABOUT THE CASE OF THE GUATEMALANS WHO TRAVELLED TO SPAIN.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PALENCIA] I HAVE NO INFORMATION, THEY DID NOT [WORD INDISTINCT] THE FOREIGN MINISTRY. I HAVE RECEIVED NO OFFICIAL INFORMATION CONCERNING THOSE PEOPLE.

[REPORTER] DO YOU HAVE ANY OFFICIAL INFORMATION CONCERNING THE THREE STUDENTS WHO LEFT FOR PANAMA?

[PALENCIA] NO, I HAVE NOT BEEN INFORMED ABOUT THEM EITHER.

[REPORTER] DO YOU BELIEVE THEY LEFT THROUGH THE NORMAL CHANNELS?

[PALENCIA] THE FOREIGN MINISTRY HAS NOT CARRIED OUT ANY SPECIAL PROCEDURE. [END RECORDING]

THE DEPARTURE OF TWO STUDENT LEADERS WHO SAID THEY HAD BEEN SUBJECTED TO PERSECUTION AND THREATS CAME LESS THAN 2 WEEKS AFTER THE DEATH OF FOUR UNIVERSITY STUDENTS WHO HAD BEEN KIDNAPPED, AND COINCIDED WITH THE PRESENCE IN GUATEMALA OF UN OBSERVER PETER KOOIJMANS, A SPECIALIST IN TORTURE ANALYSIS, WHO MAY REMAIN IN THE COUNTRY FOR 6 DAYS.

FOREIGN MINISTER MARIO PALENCIA ADMITTED THAT THE ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE IN GUATEMALA OVER THE PAST FEW WEEKS, RELATED SITUATIONS SUCH AS THE FLIGHT OF GUATEMALANS TO OTHER COUNTRIES, AND THE REESTABLISHMENT OF THE U.S. GOVERNMENT TRAVEL ADVISORY, HAVE AFFECTED GUATEMALA'S INTERNATIONAL IMAGE.

NEVERTHELESS, THE FOREIGN MINISTER SAID THAT THE CIRCUMSTANCES THAT LED TO THE ATMOSPHERE OF UNREST IN THE COUNTRY HAVE NORMALIZED SOMEWHAT.

DEV-MUC3-0519 (UMASS)

CLANDESTINE, 26 SEP 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] JUST 10 DAYS AFTER A DIALOGUE WAS HELD IN MEXICO, THE SITUATION HAS BECOME MORE TENSE IN VIEW OF THE GOVERNMENTS AND ARMED FORCE'S ATTITUDE. THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HEREBY ANNOUNCES THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE FMLN HAS SHOWN ITS WILLINGNESS AND FLEXIBILITY BY CARRYING OUT UNILATERAL ACTIONS, AND PRESENTING A REALITISTIC PEACE PROPOSAL THAT COVERS THE ASPIRATIONS OF THE ENTIRE NATION IN ENDING THE CONFLICT IN A SHORT PERIOD OF TIME.

2. ON THE CONTRARY, THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE NOT MADE ANY EFFORTS, BUT RATHER THEY HAVE HARDENED THEIR STANDS AND CARRIED OUT REPRESSIVE ACTIONS. IN THE LAST FEW DAYS, WHILE WE OFFERED A UNILATERAL TRUCE, THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE CONDUCTED PROVOKING WAR ACTIONS; LAUNCHED MILITARY OPERATIONS IN THE AREAS UNDER GUERRILLA CONTROL; BOMBED CIVILIAN POPULATIONS IN MORAZAN, CHALATENANGO, AND GUAZAPA; MAINTAINED A MILITARY SEIGE ON THE UNIVERSITY AND TRADE UNION BUILDINGS; AND EVICTED PEASANTS AND TENANTS FROM THEIR LANDS. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN UNLEASHING A MERCILESS REPRESSION AGAINST THE ORGANIZATION OF THE PEOPLE, TRADE UNIONS, PEASANTS, RELIGIOUS GROUPS, AND STUDENTS. THE NATION HAS BEEN SHOCKED TO HEAR THAT OVER 400 PEOPLE WERE CAPTURED IN THE LAST MONTH.

DOZENS OF PEOPLE ARE MISSING OR DEAD. THE FASCIST BRUTAL GOVERNMENT IS NOT ASHAMED TO EXHIBIT UNDIGNIFIED PICTURES OF TRADE UNION LEADERS -- WHO SHOW SIGNS OF HAVING BEEN TORTURED -- TESTIFYING BEFORE JUDGES. THE GOVERNMENT PUBLICLY SHOWS THE HORROR OF WOMEN WHO HAVE BEEN RAPED IN THE PRISONS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE, THE OUTRAGES COMMITTED AGAINST THE BAPTIST CHURCH, AND THE BEATINGS AND THREATS AGAINST NEWSMEN. THE GOVERNMENT EXHIBITS TERRIFYING PHOTOGRAPHS IN THE NEWSPAPERS OF WORKERS TIED BY THEIR THUMBS, AND BLINDFOLDED IN THE MOST REPULSIVE STYLES OF THE DEATH SQUADS.

WE HAVE REACHED SUCH A STATE OF PROVOCATION THAT VICE PRESIDENT FRANCISCO MERINO IS TRYING TO HUMILIATE PUBLICLY THE PEOPLE'S SECTORS BY CALLING THEM TRASH. THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT EVEN TRIED TO SOLVE THE CASE OF THE WAR HANDICAPPED; THERE ARE 45 OF THEM OCCUPYING THE METROPOLITAN CATHEDRAL. THE ONLY ANSWER TO THEIR DEMANDS FOR MEDICAL ATTENTION ABROAD IS THE RIOT POLICEMEN THAT HAVE BEEN SENT TO THREATEN ATTACKING [WORDS INDISTINCT] TO ACHIEVE THE FREEDOM OF 11 INNOCENT YOUTHS WHO WERE CAPTURED AT A LOCAL CLINIC. TO MAKE MATTERS WORSE, THE U.S. CONGRESS HAS APPROVED SENDING $90 MILLION TO THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT TO CONTINUE FINANCING THE WAR AND REPRESSION.

3. THIS STATE OF REPRESSION AND THIS MOCKERY TO THE LEGITIMATE ASPIRATIONS OF THE PEOPLE FOR PEACE IS UNACCEPTABLE. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SAY: NO MORE CAPTURES, TORTURE, MURDERS, BOMBINGS, SIEGES, EVICTIONS, OR HUMILIATION!

TO OUR FRIENDS AND ENEMIES, WE SAY THAT JUST LIKE WE REMAIN FLEXIBLE AND OPEN FOR NEGOTIATIONS, WE WILL LIKEWISE BE WILLING, ABLE, AND READY TO ACCOMPANY THE PEOPLE IN THEIR STRUGGLE AND STRONGLY CARRY THE FLAG OF DEMOCRACY AND PEACE TO ADVANCE UNTIL WE HAVE NAILED THAT FLAG INTO THE HEARTS OF THOSE WHO ONLY WANT WAR.

THIS GENERAL COMMAND HEREBY ORDERS ALL OUR GROUPS, FIGHTERS, MILITIA MEMBERS, AND COLLABORATORS TO DEFEND WITH HONOR AND STRENGTH AND WITH THEIR WEAPONS THE FLAG OF DEMOCRACY AND PEACE THAT THE ENTIRE NATION DEMANDS.

WE HEREBY NOTIFY THAT TODAY, 26 SEPTEMBER 1989, OUR FORCES HAVE BEGUN A NATIONAL MANEUVER THAT WE CALL "STOP THE REPRESSION, EVERYONE FOR THE ACHIEVEMENT OF DEMOCRACY AND PEACE." OUR MANEUVER CALLS FOR ATTACKING SEVERAL GARRISONS AND STRATEGIC POSITIONS OF THE ARMY IN THE FOUR REGIONS OF THE COUNTRY. WE WILL CONTINUE REPORTING ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE ACTIONS IN THE FOUR WAR FRONTS IN A FORTHCOMING COMMUNIQUE.

AGAINST REPRESSION, EVERYONE FOR ACHIEVING DEMOCRACY AND PEACE.

DEV-MUC3-0520 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 SEP 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS ACCUSED THE GOVERNMENT OF NOT WANTING TO NEGOTIATE THE END OF THE WAR AND INCREASING THE "REPRESSION" AGAINST WORKERS.

IN A LETTER DISCLOSED ON MONDAY, 25 SEPTEMBER, AND SENT TO THE UNITED NATIONS, THE OAS, AND THE FOREIGN MINISTRIES OF EUROPE AND THE AMERICAS, THE REBELS SAY THAT SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND OTHER GOVERNMENT AUTHORITIES "ARE MAINTAINING THEIR INFLEXIBILITY, USING THE CONSTITUTION AS AN EXCUSE."

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) IS WARNING THAT THERE ARE TWO STANCES IN THE FACE OF THE DIALOGUE: ONE IS OF "FLEXIBILITY AND GOODWILL," AND THE OTHER, OF "INFLEXIBILITY AND PROVOCATION THAT USES THE DIALOGUE TO ESCALATE THE WAR AND REPRESSION."

IN ITS LETTER, THE FMLN GAVE A RUNDOWN OF ITS BIDS TO "PROMOTE A DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION" WITH THE GOVERNMENT, MENTIONING ITS UNILATERAL TRUCE AND DECISION TO STOP SABOTAGING THE ELECTRICITY AND TELEPHONE NETWORKS AND USING MINES.

IN ADDITION, THE GROUP NOTED IT SUBMITTED A PROPOSAL "THAT IS VERY FLEXIBLE IN ACHIEVING PEACE," AND THAT CONSIDERS THE END OF HOSTILITIES AND THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE REBELS MAY BECOME A POLITICAL PARTY.

HOWEVER, THE REBELS STATED THE GOVERNMENT HAS INCREASED HUMAN RIGHTS "VIOLATIONS," AND IS KEEPING A CIRCLE AROUND THE UNIVERSITY CAMPUS AND TRADE UNIONS, YET IT WANTS DILATORY TALKS WITHOUT COMMITTMENTS.

THE FMLN SAID THE APPROVAL BY THE U.S. SENATE OF MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR, UPPING IT FROM $85 TO $90 MILLION, "ENCOURAGES THE MOST HARD LINE SECTOR OF THE CURRENT SALVADORAN REGIME."

ACCORDING TO THE GUERRILLAS, THE MILITARY AID "CONSTITUTES A HARD BLOW AGAINST THE POSSIBILITY OF FINDING A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT," THAT IN 9 YEARS HAS CLAIMED OVER 70,000 LIVES.

GOVERNMENT AND FMLN DELEGATIONS MET FROM 13 TO 15 SEPTEMBER IN MEXICO AND PLEDGED TO SEEK A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THAT COUNTRY'S STRIFE.

THE TWO DELEGATIONS AGREED TO CONTINUE THE TALKS ON 16 AND 17 OCTOBER IN SAN JOSE TO ANALYZE THE POSSIBILITY OF A CEASE-FIRE AND ESTABLISH THE STEPS TO END THE WAR.

DIVERSE LOCAL SECTORS, WHICH ARE DEMANDING A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE WAR, HAVE RECEIVED THE AGREEMENTS WITH A GREAT DEAL OF OPTIMISM.

HOWEVER, SOME LEADERS OF RIGHTIST NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) AND SOME MILITARY CHIEFS HAVE QUESTIONED THE FMLN'S OFFERS.

DEV-MUC3-0521 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 26 SEP 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] THE M-19 GUERRILLA GROUP [19 APRIL MOVEMENT], WHICH IS ABOUT TO SIGN A PEACE AGREEMENT WITH THE GOVERNMENT, TODAY PROPOSED OPENING A DIALOGUE WITH THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS. ACCORDING TO THE INTELLIGENCE SERVICES, ONE OF THE DRUG LORDS IS SURROUNDED.

MEANWHILE, A POWERFUL BOMB EXPLODED IN A HOTEL IN THE CARTAGENA DE INDIAS TOURIST CENTER, ON THE CARIBBEAN, KILLING TWO PERSONS. IT IS BELIEVED THE BOMB WAS PLACED BY GROUPS LINKED TO NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS.

THE M-19 PROPOSED PARDONING THOSE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS WHO DISMANTLE THEIR BUSINESSES AND BECOME LAW-ABIDING.

IN RADIO STATEMENTS MADE TODAY, M-19 COMMANDER CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ SAID THAT THE GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION HAS MADE CONTACT WITH THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS, WHO HAVE REPORTEDLY SAID THEY ARE WILLING TO JOIN A GENERAL PEACE PLAN.

THE PROPOSAL WAS SIGNED BY THE HIERARCHY OF THE M-19 -- FOUNDED IN 1974 AND ONE OF THE MOST NOTORIOUS COLOMBIAN GUERRILLA GROUPS -- IN THEIR CAMP IN SANTO DOMINGO, SOME 400 KM SOUTHWEST OF BOGOTA.

IN EXCHANGE FOR DISMANTLING THE LABORATORIES AND THE ARMED GROUPS, THE M-19 PROPOSED NOT EXTRADITING THE ALLEGED NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS TO THE UNITED STATES.

THE M-19 PROPOSAL HAS TAKEN BY SURPRISE THE GOVERNMENT OF VIRGILIO BARCO, INASMUCH AS IT HAD VOICED ITS DETERMINATION NOT TO HOLD ANY DIALOGUE WITH THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS, A JUDICIAL SOURCE HAS TOLD REUTER.

"THE ISSUE OF THE DIALOGUE IS BECOMING VERY SERIOUS AND I BELIEVE THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL HAVE TO TAKE IT SERIOUSLY A WAR ALWAYS CONCLUDES WITH A PEACE AGREEMENT," ONE OF THE ADVISERS OF FORMER JUSTICE MINISTER MONICA DE GREIFF SAID.

THE M-19 PROPOSAL, WHICH INCLUDES A PLAN SO THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS THEMSELVES WILL FINANCE A CAMPAIGN AGAINST DRUG CONSUMPTION, HAS NOT BEEN ACCEPTED YET BY THE GOVERNMENT.

IN AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE, IT WAS STRESSED THAT THE ISSUE OF THE DIALOGUE WITH THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS WILL NOT FORM PART OF THE PEACE AGREEMENT REACHED WITH THE M-19.

RELATIONS BETWEEN THE COLOMBIAN GUERRILLA GROUPS AND THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS HAVE HAD THEIR UPS AND DOWNS THROUGHOUT THE YEARS.

AT FIRST, SOME ARMED GROUPS GAVE PROTECTION TO THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS IN EXCHANGE FOR MONEY FOR PURCHASING WEAPONS. HOWEVER, LATER, WHEN THEY TRIED TO TAKE OVER PART OF THE BUSINESS, THEY WERE HARSHLY FOUGHT BY THE PARAMILITARY BANDS OF THE EXTREME RIGHT FINANCED WITH DRUG MONEY.

PIZARRO SAID TODAY THAT THE TOPIC WILL NOT AFFECT THE SIGNING OF THE AGREEMENT, WHICH HAS BEEN POSTPONED SINCE 24 SEPTEMBER FOR "LAST-MINUTE MINOR DIFFICULTIES."

HE ALSO POINTED OUT THAT THE WEAPONS OF THE ORGANIZATION, WHICH HAS OVER 600 MILITANTS, WILL NOT BE TURNED OVER TO THE ARMY, BUT TO AN INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION, PROBABLY THE RED CROSS.

HOWEVER, WHILE THE M-19 -- WHICH ACCORDING TO THE PEACE PLAN SHOULD BE DEMOBILIZED AT THE END OF THE YEAR -- IS ASKING FOR A DIALOGUE WITH THE NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS, THE INTELLIGENCE SERVICES ANNOUNCED THAT GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALSO KNOWN AS "EL MEXICANO," IS SURROUNDED AND WILL BE IMMINENTLY CAPTURED.

A SPOKESMAN FOR THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS) HAS TOLD REUTER: "WE BELIEVE WE WILL BE CAPTURING IMPORTANT PEOPLE WITHIN THE NEXT FEW DAYS, ALTHOUGH WE DO NOT KNOW IF RODRIGUEZ GACHA WILL ALSO BE CAPTURED."

RODRIGUEZ GACHA AND PABLO ESCOBAR ARE CONSIDERED THE CAPOS OF THE FEARFUL MEDELLIN CARTEL, A NARCOTICS ORGANIZATION WHICH TOGETHER WITH ITS TWIN ORGANIZATION IN CALI IS CHARGED WITH EXPORTING 80 PERCENT OF THE COCAINE CONSUMED IN THE UNITED STATES.

THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS OFFERED A 100-MILLION-PESOS REWARD ($250,000) TO ANY CITIZEN PROVIDING INFORMATION ON THE WHEREABOUTS OF THE TWO MOST-WANTED MEN IN COLOMBIA.

ON 25 SEPTEMBER, A JUDGE ORDERED THE ARRESTED OF FREDDY RODRIGUEZ CELADES, SON OF "EL MEXICANO," FOR ILLEGAL PSSESSION OF FIREARMS.

NATIONAL POLICE CHIEF GENERAL MIGUEL GOMEZ PADILLA RECENTLY ANNOUNCED THAT THE TWO NARCOTICS TRAFFICKERS ARE IN COLOMBIAN TERRITORY, THUS DENYING RUMORS TO THE EFFECT THEY WERE SETTING UP BASES IN PANAMA OR BRAZIL.

DEV-MUC3-0522 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [TEXT] IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT THE AIRSTRIP IN CHILANGA, 5 KM NORTH OF THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO DE LA GOTERA, WAS ALMOST COMPLETELY DESTROYED. SEVERAL OTHER POSITIONS INSIDE THE CITY WERE ALSO ATTACKED. UNTIL NOW, NO GOVERNMENT OR REBEL CASUALTIES HAVE BEEN REPORTED. THE HIGHWAY LEADING FROM SAN FRANCISCO GOTERA TO SAN MIGUEL WAS MINED BY THE REBELS. TRAFFIC ALONG THIS HIGHWAY HAS CEASED UNTIL NOW.

IN LA UNION, THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] REBELS SAID THAT TROOPS OF THE FONSECA BATTALION OF THE 3RD DETACHMENT OF LA UNION WERE ATTACKED IN SAN SEBASTIAN NEAR SANTA ROSA DE LIMA. THE REBELS CLAIM THEY CAPTURED 3 SOLDIERS. ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN FRANCISCO GOTERA, THE REBELS CLAIM THEY CAPTURED 2 SOLDIERS OF THE 4TH DETACHMENT OF SAN FRANCISCO GOTERA.

IN OTHER INCIDENTS, IT WAS REPORTED THAT SINCE 1600 LOCAL TIME ON 25 SEPTEMBER THERE HAVE BEEN FIERCE CLASHES IN VALLE NUEVO NEAR EL PARAISO IN CHALATENANGO. UNTIL NOW OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE NOT REPORTED ANY CASUALTIES.

IN EL PAPAYAL, CIVILIAN SOURCES REPORT THAT THERE HAVE BEEN NO INCIDENTS IN THIS GOVERNMENT TELEPHONE EXCHANGE AND MICROWAVE STATION.

CLASHES CONTINUED THIS MORNING BETWEEN TROOPS OF THE 3RD AND 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADES IN USULUTAN. PATROLS ARE CHASING THE REBELS.

IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT IN CIUDAD BARRIOS IN THE DEPARTMENT OF SAN MIGUEL THE REBELS PLACED SOME ROADBLOCKS AND DISTURBED MILITARY POSITIONS. NO CASUALTIES HAVE BEEN REPORTED IN THESE INCIDENTS.

IT WAS REPORTED THAT IN YOLAIQUIN THE REBELS ALSO ATTACKED TROOPS OF THE 4TH DETACHMENT OF GOTERA. YOLAIQUIN IS IN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT.

IN MONCAGUA, ALSO IN SAN MIGUEL, ROADBLOCKS WERE PLACED ON THE HIGHWAY TO CHAPELTIQUE. NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED IN THESE INCIDENTS.

THE NATIONAL GUARD POST IN SESORI, NORTH OF SAN MIGUEL, WAS ALSO ATTACKED. NO CASUALITES WERE REPORTED IN THIS INCIDENT.

IN ANOTHER INCIDENT IN CUSCATLAN , IT WAS REPORTED THAT TROOPS OF THE 5TH DETACHMENT GUARDING THE BRIDGE AT LAS GUARAS WERE ATTACKED EARLY THIS MORNING BY THE REBELS. NO OFFICIAL BULLETIN HAS BEEN ISSUED BY THE 5TH DETACHMENT.

THE TOWN OF SAN BARTOLOME PERULAPIA WAS ATTACKED. NO ADDITIONAL DETAILS ARE KNOWN.

UNTIL NOW, THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE, COPREFA, HAS ONLY REPORTED FOUR SOLDIERS WOUNDED IN THE SAN FRACISCO GOTERA AREA. IT ADMITS THAT THE AIRSTRIP IN CHILANGA WAS DAMAGED. NO CASUALTIES HAVE BEEN REPORTED ANYWHERE ELSE IN THE COUNTRY WERE FIERCE CLASHES TOOK PLACE THIS MORNING STARTING AROUND 0200, AND WHICH ARE CONTINUING NOW IN CERTAIN AREAS.

COPREFA REPORTS THE DEATH OF 14 GUERILLAS NEAR TEJUTLA. ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL BULLETIN, 14 GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED IN CLASHES WITH TROOPS OF THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE IN CHALATENANGO. THE BULLETIN ALSO REPORTS THAT IMPORTANT MILITARY EQUIPMENT WAS SEIZED FROM THE FMLN GUERRILLAS.

DEV-MUC3-0523 (UMASS)

NO CITY (COLOMBIA), 26 SEP 89 -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] ACCORDING TO THE PACT SIGNED TODAY, A BILATERAL COMMISSION THAT WILL BE CREATED SOON WILL DISCUSS THE MANNER IN WHICH THE GUERRILLA GROUP WILL BE DEMOBILIZED.

M-19 COMMANDER CARLOS PIZARRO SAID TODAY THAT THE ORGANIZATION, WHICH HAS A LITTLE MORE THAN 600 MEMBERS, WILL NOT TURN IN ITS WEAPONS TO THE ARMY, BUT TO AN INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION, POSSIBLY THE RED CROSS.

HOWEVER, WHILE THE M-19 IS CALLING FOR A DIALOGUE WITH THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, INTELLIGENCE SERVICES HAVE ANNOUNCED THAT GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALIAS "EL MEJICANO," HAS BEEN SURROUNDED AND WILL SOON BE CAPTURED.

A SPOKESMAN FOR THE ADMINISTRATIVE SECURITY DEPARTMENT, THE COLOMBIAN INTELLIGENCE ORGANIZATION, TOLD REUTER: "WE BELIEVE THAT IMPORTANT ARRESTS WILL BE MADE IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS, ALTHOUGH WE DO NOT KNOW IF WE WILL CATCH RODRIGUEZ GACHA."

RODRIGUEZ GACHA AND PABLO ESCOBAR ARE CONSIDERED TO BE THE HEADS OF THE FEARSOME MEDELLIN CARTEL, AN ORGANIZATION OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS THAT, ALONG WITH ITS TWIN ORGANIZATION IN CALI, IS ACCUSED OF SUPPLYING 80 PERCENT OF THE COCAINE THAT IS CONSUMED IN THE UNITED STATES.

THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS OFFERED A REWARD OF 100 MILLION PESOS ($250,000) TO ANY CITIZEN WHO PROVIDES INFORMATION ON THE WHEREABOUTS OF THE TWO MOST WANTED MEN IN COLOMBIA.

YESTERDAY, A JUDGE ISSUED A WARRANT FOR THE ARREST OF FREDDY RODRIGUEZ CELADES, SON OF "EL MEJICANO," FOR THE ILLEGAL POSSESSION OF WEAPONS.

IN RECENT STATEMENTS TO THE PRESS, GENERAL MIGUEL GOMEZ PADILLA, CHIEF OF THE NATIONAL POLICE, SAID THAT BOTH DRUG TRAFFICKERS ARE IN COLOMBIAN TERRITORY, THUS DENYING REPORTS THAT THEY HAD REPORTEDLY MOVED THEIR BASES OF OPERATION TO PANAMA OR BRAZIL.

FINALLY, IN CARTAGENA DE INDIAS, A TOURIST CENTER ON THE CARIBBEAN COAST, A POWERFUL BOMB EXPLODED IN A HOTEL, KILLING TWO PEOPLE.

THE ATTACK WAS ATTRIBUTED TO THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF AN ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE IN WHICH OVER 70 BOMBS HAVE EXPLODED IN A LITTLE OVER 1 MONTH.

DEV-MUC3-0525 (UMASS)

NO CITY (COLOMBIA), 27 SEP 89 -- [TEXT] [BARCO] SOME OF THE ARRESTED PERSONS ARE EXTRADITABLE. THE PEOPLE HAVE RISEN UP AGAINST TERRORISM, AND THE TERRORISTS CANNOT HIDE FOREVER.

THIRD, MUCH INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT FOR COLOMBIA, ITS DEMOCRACY, ITS PEOPLE, AND ITS GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN MOBILIZED. COLOMBIA IS NO LONGER SEEN AS A COUNTRY OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS, SOMETHING IT HAS NEVER BEEN AND NEVER WILL BE.

NOW EVERYONE UNDERSTANDS THAT WE ARE A COUNTRY OF BRAVE PEOPLE WHERE THE MAJORITY ARE HONEST AND HARD-WORKING. THE WORLD HAS ACKNOWLEDGED AND PRAISED DEMOCRACY IN COLOMBIA, THE VICTIM OF A PROBLEM IT HAS NOT CREATED.

FOURTH, INVESTIGATIONS INTO THE CRIMES COMMITTED BY NARCOTERRORISTS CONTINUE GIVING POSITIVE RESULTS. MORE THAN 25 BANDS OF ASSASSINS HAVE BEEN DISMANTLED, AND THEIR MEMBERS HAVE BEEN DISPERSED. TWO OF THE PEOPLE WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE ASSASSINATION OF LUIS CARLOS GALAN HAVE CONFESSED TO THE CRIME. THE DEPARTMENT OF ADMINISTRATIVE SECURITY HAS IDENTIFIED 110 PERSONS WHO FORM PART OF A NARCOTERRORIST NETWORK. THE MOST IMPORTANT ASSASSINATIONS HAVE BEEN CLEARED UP.

FIFTH, THE AUTHORITIES HAVE BEEN ABLE TO CHECK THE TERRORISTS' COUNTEROFFENSIVE, ALTHOUGH IT CANNOT BE DENIED THAT THE CRIMINALS ARE STILL CAPABLE OF CAUSING MUCH DAMAGE. THIS HAS BEEN MADE EVIDENT BY THE EXPLOSIVES THEY HAVE PLACED, THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE DIED AND WHO HAVE BEEN INJURED, AND THE FIRES THEY HAVE PRODUCED.

THE AUTHORITIES HAVE BEEN ABLE TO FRUSTRATE MANY ATTACKS. CRIMINALS WHO HAVE CARRIED OUT ATTACKS HAVE BEEN CAPTURED. FOR EXAMPLE, IN MEDELLIN, 35 CRIMINALS WHO WERE COORDINATING WITH THE TERRORIST NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY HAVE BEEN CAPTURED.

SIXTH, DRUG TRAFFICKING CAPABILITIES HAVE DECREASED. NOW THERE IS MUCH LESS COCAINE IN THE UNITED STATES AND IN OTHER WORLD MARKETS. IT IS IMPORTANT TO EMPHASIZE THE FACT THAT IT IS UP TO THE UNITED STATES AND THE EUROPEAN COUNTRIES TO INCREASE THEIR ACTIVITIES TO DIMINISH AND CONTROL DRUG CONSUMPTION. IF THERE WERE NO ADDICTS IN THOSE COUNTRIES, THERE WOULD BE NO DRUG TRAFFICKING.

THIS IS NOT THE ONLY RESPONSIBILITY OF THE OTHER COUNTRIES INVOLVED IN THE WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. IF DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE UNABLE TO USE THEIR MONEY THROUGH INTERNATIONAL BANKS AND INVESTMENT OPPORTUNITIES THAT OTHER COUNTRIES OFFER, THE INCENTIVES FOR THE BUSINESS WOULD VANISH.

IF THE CHEMICAL PRODUCTS THAT ARE NECESSARY TO PROCESS COCAINE DID NOT ARRIVE IN OUR COUNTRY FROM EUROPE AND THE UNITED STATES, THE DRUG COULD NOT BE PRODUCED.

IF THE INTERNATIONAL ARMS MARKET WERE UNDER CONTROL, THE TERRORISTS WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN ABLE TO GET THE ARMS THEY HAVE USED TO SPILL SO MUCH BLOOD IN COLOMBIA. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0526 (UMASS)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 27 SEP 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [TEXT] NATIONAL LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT COMMANDER CARLOS NUNEZ HAS STATED THAT THE 39 FORMER GN [NATIONAL GUARD] MEMBERS NOW IN JAIL WILL NOT BE RELEASED UNTIL THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARY FORCES IN HONDURAS ARE DEMOBILIZED. COMMANDER NUNEZ DEMANDED THAT THE CONTRAS RELEASE MORE THAN 1,000 NICARAGUANS THEY HAVE KIDNAPPED AND STOP MURDERING CIVILIANS. HE SAID THAT THE 39 FORMER GN MEMBERS WILL BE RELEASED WHEN THE COUNTERREVOLUTION IS DEMOBILIZED IN HONDURAS, AS WAS AGREED WITH THE 21 NICARAGUAN POLITICAL PARTIES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [NUNEZ] THE 39 FORMER SOMOZIST ARMY MEMBERS, WHO ARE SO STRONGLY DEFENDED BY MORE THAN ONE REPRESENTATIVE WHO ALLEGE QUOTE HUMANITARIAN UNQUOTE REASONS, ARE GOING TO STAY IN PRISON AND WILL NOT BE INCLUDED IN THE LIST [PARDON LIST THAT INCLUDES 457 PRISONERS APPROVED BY THE NICARAGUA LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY ON 26 SEPTEMBER]. LIKEWISE, THE REST OF THE CONTRA PRISONERS, WHO ARE NOT ON THIS LIST, WILL ALSO REMAIN IN PRISON. THEY WILL REMAIN THERE UNTIL WE HAVE HAVE CLEAR, DEFINITE INDICATIONS FROM THE U.S. GOVERNMENT AND THE MERCENARIES THAT THEY ARE GOING TO COMPLY WITH AGREEMENTS. THEY WILL STAY IN PRISON UNTIL WE CAN CLEARLY SEE THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS AND THEIR WILLINGNESS TO ENTER INTO THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL ACTIVITY. WE ARE NOT GOING TO ALLOW THE WORD RECONCILIATION TO BE CHANGED INTO DEMAGOGUERY. THIS WORD HAS REAL MEANING. WE ARE WILLING TO COMPLY WITH AGREEMENTS AND HAVE EVIDENCED OUR WILLINGNESS WITH GESTURES OF GENEROSITY. WE ARE NOT ASKING THE CONTRAS TO BE GENEROUS. WE ARE ASKING THE CONTRAS TO COMPLY WITH THE TELA AGREEMENTS SIGNED IN HONDURAS. WE ARE ALSO ASKING FOR COMPLIANCE WITH THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED WITH THE POLITICAL PARTIES DURING THE NATIONAL DIALOGUE, THAT THE PERSONS WHO HAVE BEEN KIDANAPPED BY THE CONTRAS BE RETURNED, AND THAT THEY STOP THEIR ATTACKS AND MURDERS THAT EVEN NOW -- ALTHOUGH SOME POLITICIANS ARE BLIND TO THIS -- CONTINUE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0527 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 26 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] IN A FIRST RULING, CRIMINAL JUDGE 62 OF RIONEGRO MUNICIPALITY, NORTHWESTERN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, HAS ACQUITTED DRUG TRAFFICKERS PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA OF CHARGES OF MASTERMINDING THE MURDER OF ATTORNEY GENERAL CARLOS MAURO HOYOS AND THE KIDNAPPING OF BOGOTA CITY MAYOR ANDRES PASTRANA.

THE RULING WAS ISSUED ON THE NIGHT OF 25 SEPTEMBER AND REVEALED ON 26 SEPTEMBER.

HOYOS WAS KIDNAPPED ON 25 JANUARY 1988 AND WAS FOUND DEAD 8 HOURS LATER NEAR THE MEDELLIN AIRPORT. PASTRANA WAS KIDNAPPED ON 22 JANUARY 1988 BUT WAS RESCUED BY THE ARMY 3 DAYS LATER.

THE "EXTRADITABLES" CLAIMED CREDIT AT THE TIME FOR THESE TWO ACTIONS.

IN HIS FIRST RULING, JUDGE FRANCISCO CARDENAS SAID "THERE IS NOT SUFFICIENT GROUNDS OR EVIDENCE" FOR LINKING ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND RODRIGUEZ GACHA, THE MAIN CHIEFTAINS OF THE MEDELLIN DRUG CARTEL, TO THE CRIMES. THE EXTRADITION OF THE DRUGPINS HAS BEEN REQUESTED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.

THE PROSECUTOR IN THE CASE HAS APPEALED JUDGE CARDENAS' RULING BEFORE THE SUPERIOR TRIBUNAL OF MEDELLIN, WHICH WILL SOON ISSUE A PRONOUNCEMENT ON THE VALIDITY OF THE COURT RULING.

DEV-MUC3-0530 (UMASS)

LA PAZ, 28 SEP 89 (LA RED PANAMERICANA) -- [TEXT] BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA HAS STATED THAT BOLIVIA NEEDS ADEQUATE ASSISTANCE TO SOLVE ITS PROBLEMS. HE ADDED THAT BOLIVIA NEEDS A LEADER LIKE NORIEGA TO ATTRACT INTERNATIONAL ATTENTION.

IN A NEWS CONFERENCE WITH U.S. REPORTERS, PRESIDENT PAZ YESTERDAY ANSWERED SEVERAL QUESTIONS ABOUT THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING AND THE ERADICATION OF COCA CROPS. THE BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT STRESSED THE EFFORTS MADE BY THE BOLIVIAN PEOPLE TO OVERCOME HYPERINFLATION OF MORE THAN 27,000 PERCENT. HE SAID THAT INFLATION IS PREDICTED TO REACH 12 PERCENT DURING HIS ADMINISTRATION.

PAZ ZAMORA STATED THAT THE HIGHLY INDUSTRIALIZED COUNTRIES MUST PAY ATTENTION TO NATIONS SUCH AS BOLIVIA THAT FACE DIFFICULT ECONOMIC SITUATIONS AND AT THE SAME TIME STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. HE CRITICIZED THE BEHAVIOR OF WORLD POWERS, AND HE SAID THAT SUCH BEHAVIOR MUST BE CHANGED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PAZ ZAMORA] WE ARE SICK AND TIRED OF THE WAY INDUSTRIALIZED COUNTRIES AND THEIR PEOPLE ARE BEHAVING, MAINTAINING CERTAIN SADOMASOCHISTIC RELATIONS WITH THE UNDERDEVELOPED NATIONS. [END RECORDING]

THE BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT TRIED TO MAKE THE U.S. PRESS UNDERSTAND THE INDIFFERENCE THAT CERTAIN COUNTRIES, NAMELY THE ECONOMIC POWERS, SHOW TOWARD BOLIVIA.

TO EXPLAIN HIS REMARKS, HE SAID THAT PERHAPS A GENERAL SHOULD ASSUME POWER, AND MILITARY FORCES SHOULD BESIEGE THE U.S. EMBASSY, AND A FEW HUNDRED PEOPLE SHOULD BE MURDERED TO GET THE ATTENTION OF THE WORLD.

PAZ ZAMORA DEMANDED GREATER UNDERSTANDING FROM THE INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS THAT IMPOSE EXTREMELY DIFFICULT CONDITIONS FOR ACHIEVING ECONOMIC STABILITY. DOES A WAR KILL MORE PEOPLE THAN AN ECONOMIC ADJUSTMENT PROGRAM, THE BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT ASKED. HE INVITED THE U.S. REPORTERS TO REVIEW THE STATISTICS ON THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE KILLED IN THE SALVADORAN WAR AND THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE WHO DIED IN BOLIVIA BECAUSE OF THE ECONOMIC-FINANCIAL ADJUSTMENTS.

PRESIDENT PAZ HAS STATED THAT THE FACT THAT BOLIVIA IS A COCA- PRODUCING COUNTRY IS DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE U.S. TREATMENT OF THE MATTER. HE SAID THAT THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING DEMANDS ACTION TO CONTROL CONSUMPTION. HE ADDED THAT BOLIVIA IS NOT RECEIVING THE NECESSARY RESOURCES TO DEAL WITH THE SOCIAL PROBLEMS RESULTING FROM THE REDUCTION OF COCA PRODUCTION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PAZ] AN ANTINARCOTICS PROGRAM FOR BOLIVIA SIMILAR TO THAT IMPLEMENTED IN COLOMBIA WOULD BE A GREAT MISTAKE [END RECORDING].

HE DEMANDED REAL ALTERNATIVES FOR WORK AND PRODUCTION FOR BOLIVIAN PEASANTS. HE SAID THAT UNTIL THIS IS ACHIEVED, THE MISTAKES OF THE PAST WILL BE REPEATED.

DEV-MUC3-0531 (UMASS)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE -- [INTERVIEW WITH FMLN'S VILLALOBOS BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTED] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [VILLALOBOS] WE ARE CONTRIBUTING TO THE EFFORT TO STOP FASCISM AND BRING ABOUT A GENUINE DEMOCRACY. THE BASIS FOR A NEGOTIATION IN EL SALVADOR SHOULD BE THAT DEMOCRACY PRECEDES PEACE. OUR COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT WE ARE SEARCHING FOR DEMOCRACY AND PEACE. WE MENTION THEM IN THAT ORDER BECAUSE IF WE WERE TO SEEK PEACE FIRST, AS THE GOVERNMENT WANTS, WE WOULD HAVE THE PEACE OF DEATH.

[REPORTER] YOU REFERRED TO COMBATANTS AND THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT. HOWEVER, IN THE PAST FEW DAYS OTHER PEOPLE HAVE BEEN IN THE FOREFRONT OF THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE FASCIST REGIME; THAT IS, THE FMLN MAIMED. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION ABOUT THEIR PLIGHT AND ATTITUDE?

[VILLALOBOS] THE STRUGGLE OF THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT INVOLVING INDIVIDUALS WHO WAGE IMPORTANT BATTLES WITHOUT WEAPONS IS QUITE ADMIRABLE. I BELIEVE THAT THE STRUGGLE OF THE WAR MAIMED IS TWICE AS ADMIRABLE. THEY ARE NOT ONLY WAGING A BATTLE WITHOUT WEAPONS, BUT WITH THEIR MUTILATED BODIES.

THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT IS EXPERIENCING VERY TRYING MOMENTS. IT IS FACING REPRESSION. THIS SHOWS THE REGIME AS IT REALLY IS. THE MAIMED HAVE ALSO DEALT A VERY IMPORTANT BLOW: THEY HAVE EXPOSED THE BRUTALITY AND STUPIDITY OF ARMY LEADERS WHO SET UP ANTIRIOT CORDONS, SURROUNDED THE CATHEDRAL, AND THREATENED PEOPLE WHO ARE UNABLE TO WALK OR ARE MISSING A LIMB [WORDS INDISTINCT]. IT IS REALLY A HEROIC STRUGGLE MUCH LIKE THE ONES THAT MANY MAIMED COMRADES HAVE WAGED FROM THEIR JAILS. THEY HAVE OPENED THE WAY FOR OTHER COMRADES TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY.

I THINK THIS IS TO BE ADDED TO THE FACT THAT ALL OF THE PEOPLE'S FORCES WHO HAVE TAKEN UP THE BANNER OF PEACE AND DEMOCRACY, EVEN THE WAR-DISABLED, HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO OUR EFFORT WITH THEIR SACRIFICE.

DEV-MUC3-0532 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 29 SEP 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] IT WAS REPORTED TODAY IN BOGOTA THAT THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS REJECTED AN APPEAL PRESENTED BY BEATRIZ RODRIGUEZ ZUNIGA'S LAWYER, WHO WANTED HER ARREST FOR EXTRADITION PURPOSES CANCELLED. RODRIGUEZ ZUNIGA IS SAID TO BE AN IMPORTANT MEDELLIN CARTEL CONNECTION.

RODRIGUEZ ZUNIGA WAS ARRESTED SEVERAL WEEKS AGO IN CARTAGENA AND, WITH THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH'S CONSENT, COULD BE THE SECOND PERSON EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES, PART OF THE GOVERNMENT'S OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE DRUG MAFIAS THAT STARTED A MONTH AND A HALF AGO.

ON 6 SEPTEMBER THE ALLEGED "FINANCIAL HEAD" OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO, WAS SENT TO THE UNITED STATES AFTER WASHINGTON PRESENTED DOCUMENTATION TO HAVE HIM TRIED IN AN ATLANTA COURT.

DRUG ENFORCEMENT ADMINISTARTION INVESTIGATIONS REPORT THAT MARTINEZ ROMERO WAS A KEY PERSON IN THE "WASHING" OF APPROXIMATELY $1.2 BILLION THE MAFIA OBTAINED FROM THE COCAINE BUSINESS.

THE DRUG "BARONS" HAVE PUBLICLY THREATENED TO MURDER 10 JUDGES FOR EACH COLOMBIAN EXRADITED TO ANOTHER COUNTRY.

SINCE MARTINEZ ROMERO WAS SENT TO ATLANTA THERE HAVE BEEN HUNDREDS OF DYNAMITE ATTACKS IN DIFFERENT COLOMBIAN CITIES. THESE ATTACKS ARE THE COCAINE CARTELS' DIRECT RESPONSE TO THE GOVERNMENT'S OFFENSIVE AGAINST THEM.

DEV-MUC3-0533 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 24 SEP 89 (EL TIEMPO) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] WHAT IS THE TRUTH OVER THE SIGNING OF THE DECREES? WERE THEY SIGNED ONLY AFTER THE ATTACK ON LUIS CARLOS GALAN?

[DE GREIFF] THE DECREES WERE BEING STUDIED SINCE NOON ON THE DAY OF HIS DEATH. IT HAD BEEN A VERY TOUGH WEEK. THE MAGISTRATE AND THE COLONEL HAD BEEN MURDERED; GALAN WAS MURDERED THAT EVENING. THERE WAS MUCH DISCUSSION OVER THE DRAFTS, BUT I BELIEVE THAT THE ATTACK ON GALAN HURRIED THINGS UP.

IN THE CASE OF THE EXTRADITION DECREE, WE WERE ALL AWARE THAT IT WAS NOT A POPULAR MEASURE. PHILOSOPHICALLY, MOST MINISTERS DID NOT LIKE THE IDEA OF COLOMBIANS BEING TRIED ABROAD. THERE WAS MUCH LEGAL DISCUSSION, NOT ONLY TO DO WITH THIS CASE, BUT ALSO OVER THE NEW MEASURES CONCERNING RAIDS, SEIZURES, AND ARRESTS.

HOWEVER, FINALLY THERE WAS A GREAT DETERMINATION TO GIVE THE COUNTRY ANSWERS.

[REPORTER] THE COUNTRY'S CURRENT PROBLEMS HAVE MUCH TO DO WITH THE EXTRADITION DECREE.

[DE GREIFF] WE MUST NOT FORGET THAT THESE MEASURES ARE NOT AGAINST A GROUP OF PEOPLE, BUT AGAINST VIOLENCE. EXTRADITION HAS BEEN A VERY TOUGH MEASURE FOR EVERYONE. THE INCONVENIENCES AND THE LEGALITY OF THIS DECREE, AS WELL AS THE POSSIBLE REACTIONS AGAINST IT, WERE DISCUSSED A GREAT DEAL. IT CAN BE THAT PART OF THE VIOLENCE GENERATED HAS BEEN DUE TO THE EXTRADITION DECREE.

[REPORTER] IS IT POSSIBLE TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE WITH THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS AS A WAY OF ENDING THE COUNTRY'S VIOLENCE?

[DE GREIFF] THE GOVERNMENT SAID NO TO THE DIALOGUE, BUT WE MUST WAIT AND SEE HOW EVENTS DEVELOP. I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT A GOVERNMENT'S DECISION CAN BE STRICT, BECAUSE SITUATIONS DO CHANGE. THE PRESIDENT HAS SAID THAT DIALOGUE IS IMPOSSIBLE. YOU NEVER KNOW, THINGS MAY CHANGE IN THE FUTURE.

ANYWAY, IN COLOMBIA PRACTICALLY NO WARS HAVE ENDED, BECAUSE IN NEARLY ALL WARS AN AGREEMENT WAS REACHED.

[REPORTER] BUT IF COLOMBIA HOLDS A DIALOGUE, THE WORLD'S DOORS WILL PROBABLY CLOSE ON COLOMBIA.

[DE GREIFF] LOOK, IN THE UNITED STATES I WAS ASKED ABOUT THE EXTRADITION AND I SAID IT WAS NOT POPULAR, THAT IT WAS NOT GOING TO SOLVE THE DRUG TRAFFICKING PROBLEM. IT IS NOT THE GOVERNMENT'S STANCE, BUT IF IT IS DECIDED TO HOLD A DIALOGUE, THEN THIS WOULD BE A SOVEREIGN COLOMBIAN DECISION. OBVIOUSLY, IF THE POSITION CHANGES A BAD IMPRESSION WILL BE GIVEN.

THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN VERY CLEAR THAT IT HAS NOT LOST ITS SOVEREIGNTY.

[REPORTER] THE INTERNATINAL PRESS FEELS A LITTLE DISAPPOINTED WITH YOUR RESIGNATION. ONE MUST NOT FORGET THAT YOU BECAME A SYMBOL FOR THE FOREIGN JOURNALISTS WHEN YOU TRAVELED TO WASHINGTON.

[DE GREIFF] I HELD A NEWS CONFERENCE ON 22 SEPTEMBER AND I TOLD THEM THAT MY RESIGNATION WAS NOT MONICA DE GREIFF'S POSITION, BUT THE GOVERNMENT'S. I TOLD THEM I WAS STAYING IN THE COUNTRY, AND I EXPLAINED TO THEM THAT THE MINISTERS HERE REMAIN AT THEIR POSTS UNTIL THE PRESIDENT DECIDES OTHERWISE. HOWEVER, THEY DID NOT UNDERSTAND WHY.

[REPORTER] WHAT WILL MONICA DE GREIFF DO?

[DE GREIFF] I AM GOING TO REST FOR A FEW DAYS AND THEN RETURN. I AM GOING TO HELP ERNESTO SAMPER'S CAMPAIGN. I ALSO BELIEVE THAT WORKING FOR PRIVATE ENTERPRISE WILL BE A GOOD OPPORTUNITY.

[REPORTER] WHAT POST HAS GIVEN YOU THE GREATEST SATISFACTION?

[DE GREIFF] WHEN I WAS AT THE MINISTRY OF MINES AND ENERGY. IT WAS FASCINATING. I HAD TWO VERY GOOD BOSSES: GUILLERMO PERRY AND OSCAR MEJIA. I WORKED IN DELIGHTFUL HARMONY WITH A GROUP OF GOOD PEOPLE. I BELIEVE THAT MINING AND HYDROCARBONS IS THE SECTOR THAT HAS ENJOYED THE GREATEST PROGRESS UNDER THIS GOVERNMENT.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS YOUR FINAL FEELING UPON LEAVING THE MINISTRY?

[DE GREIFF] EVERY CLOUD HAS A SILVER LINING. I HAVE BEEN SPARED FROM MANY BORING THINGS. I HAVE NOT HAD TO SIGN EXTRADITION ORDERS OR THINGS LIKE THAT. WITHOUT REALIZING IT, I HAVE BEEN SPARED OF TIRING THINGS.

DEV-MUC3-0534 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 29 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [EXCERPT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT WILL OFFER A "TOTAL AMNESTY" TO THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN). IN EXCHANGE, IT WILL ASK THE INSURGENTS TO LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND JOIN CIVILIAN LIFE, JUSTICE MINISTER OSCAR SANTAMARIA ANNOUNCED TODAY.

IN STATEMENTS TO A LOCAL TELEVISION STATION, SANTAMARIA SAID THE PROPOSAL WILL BE OFFICIALLY PRESENTED TO THE REBEL LEADERS DURING THE SECOND ROUND OF THE DIALOGUE, WHICH WILL BE HELD 16 - 17 OCTOBER IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA.

SANTAMARIA, WHO IS THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT DIALOGUE COMMISSION SPOKESMAN, MET FOR THE FIRST TIME WITH THE FMLN LEADERS ON 13, 14, AND 15 SEPTEMBER IN MEXICO CITY.

ON 21 SEPTEMBER, DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL HUMBERTO LARIOS, FOR THE FIRST TIME IN THE 9 YEARS OF WAR, SAID THAT REDUCING THE NUMBER OF ARMY TROOPS, AS DEMANDED BY THE REBELS, IS FEASIBLE. HE SAID THE GOVERNMENT IS DRAFTING A DOCUMENT ON THE CEASE-FIRE THAT IT WILL PRESENT AT THE COSTA RICA MEETING.

DURING THE MEXICO MEETING THE PARTIES IN CONFLICT AGREED TO HOLD MEETINGS TO TRY TO REACH AN AGREEMENT ON THE WAR, WHICH HAS RESULTED IN 70,000 DEATHS OVER A 9-YEAR PERIOD.

DESPITE THE DIALOGUE, THE GUERRILLAS THIS WEEK LAUNCHED ONE OF THE MOST VIOLENT MILITARY CAMPAIGNS YET, WHICH EVEN AFFECTED SAN SALVADOR. THIS GUERRILLA CAMPAIGN IS IN RESPONSE TO "INCREASING REPRESSION AND ASSASSINATIONS" OF LABOR LEADERS.

THE ONLY ISSUE TO BE DISCUSSED AT THE COSTA RICA MEETING WILL BE THE CEASE-FIRE. THE TWO PARTIES HAVE EXPRESSED CONFIDENCE THAT AN AGREEMENT WILL BE REACHED BEFORE THE END OF THIS YEAR.

IN ADDITION TO THE REDUCTION IN THE NUMBER OF ARMY TROOPS, THE REBELS PROPOSED IN MEXICO THAT THE JUDICIAL BRANCH BE REORGANIZED AND THAT A PROSECUTOR [FISCAL] BE APPOINTED AS A RESULT OF A CONSENSUS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE POLITICAL PARTIES. IN RESPONSE TO A QUESTION ABOUT THE INTENSIFICATION OF THE ARMED STRUGGLE BY THE REBELS, SANTAMARIA SAID: "WE ARE AT A STAGE WHERE THE TENSION LEVEL IS DECLINING. WE HAVE FOUND POINTS OF AGREEMENT, AND WE AND WILL HONOR THEM."

DEV-MUC3-0535 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 29 SEP 89 -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] WE REPORT TO YOU THE FOLLOWING CONSIDERATIONS RELATED TO THE PRESENT SITUATION IN THE SEARCH FOR A JUST AND LASTING PEACE IN EL SALVADOR.

1. WE NOTE WITH DEEP CONCERN THAT THERE HAS BEEN AN ALARMING INCREASE IN HUMAN RIGHTS AND HUMANITARIAN WAR NORMS VIOLATIONS BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES. THESE VIOLATIONS CAN BE OBSERVED IN THE REPRESSION OF DEMONSTRATIONS, TORTURES, MURDERS, ARRESTS -- MORE THAN 400 IN THE PAST MONTH -- DISAPEARANCES, AND IN THE GOVERNMENT'S REFUSAL TO ALLOW MAIMED FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] MEMBERS TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY TO GET MEDICAL ATTENTION. THIS NORM IS STIPULATED IN THE GENEVA CONVENTION, AND THIS IS AN AGREEMENT THAT HAS BEEN SIGNED BY THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. THIS SITUATION HAS BEEN CLEARLY DEMONSTRATED BY THE RESOLUTION ISSUED BY THE SUBCOMMISSION [30-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] PERIOD IN AUGUST 1989. MR CRISTIANI SAID THIS RESOLUTION WAS NOT TRUTHFUL.

2. GOVERNMENT SPOKESMEN AND MR CRISTIANI HIMSELF HAVE REPEATEDLY STATED THAT THE ACHIEVEMENT OF PEACE DEPENDS ON THE FMLN'S HALTING HOSTILITIES. THIS PRESENTS A UNILATERAL PLAN THAT HAS NOT BEEN AGREED UPON POLITICALLY, MILITARILY, OR OPERATIONALLY.

IN CONTRAST TO THESE STATEMENTS, WHEN THE FMLN UNILATERALLY DECLARED A TRUCE RECENTLY, MR CRISTIANI, OFFICIALS IN HIS ADMINISTRATION, AND MILITARY COMMANDERS STATED THAT THESE FMLN MEASURES WERE PROPAGANDISTIC AND THAT THE TRUCE WAS NOT RESPECTED. THEIR ARGUMENTS WERE ATTEMPTS TO JUSTIFY THE GOVERNMENT'S BREAKING OF THE TRUCE.

THESE EVENTS GIVE US ADDITIONAL GROUNDS FOR STATING THAT A DEFINITE AND UNCONDITIONAL HALT TO HOSTILITIES IS UNREALISTIC AND UNFEASIBLE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0537 (UMASS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 29 SEP 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] POLICE SOURCES REPORTED TODAY THAT A SPANIARD, A FRENCHMAN, AND AN ITALIAN, KIDNAPPED IN TECUN UMAN ON 27 SEPTEMBER, HAVE BEEN RELEASED WITHIN THE PAST FEW HOURS.

SPANIARD JOSE MARIA MARTINEZ, FRENCHMAN ROBERTO LISANDY, AND ITALIAN DINO ROSSY, WHO WERE STAYING AT A TECUN UMAN HOTEL, WERE KIDNAPPED BY ARMED MEN WHO TOOK THEM TO AN UNKNOWN PLACE.

AFTER THEY WERE RELEASED, THE THREE EUROPEANS WENT TO THE REGIONAL POLICE STATION AND GAVE A FULL ACCOUNT OF THEIR EXPERIENCE WITH THE KIDNAPPERS.

MARTINEZ TOLD THE POLICE THAT THE KIDNAPPERS HELD THEM IN A DARK ROOM AND QUESTIONED THEM.

THE THREE MEN WERE TAKEN TO A MEDICAL CENTER AFTER THEIR RELEASE AND, ACCORDING TO THE MEDICAL REPORT, SUFFERED NO WOUNDS.

OFFICIALS REPORTED THAT MARTINEZ AND LISANDY DO BUSINESS IN TECUN UMAN AND HAVE BEEN LIVING THERE FOR THE PAST 9 MONTHS. ROSSY WAS ENJOYING HIS VACATION HERE, WHEN HE WAS KIDNAPPED.

ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, THE PERSONS WHO KIDNAPPED THE THREE MEN GOT THEM DRUNK BEFORE RELEASING THEM SO THAT THEY WOULD LOSE TRACK OF TIME AND BE UNABLE TO IDENTIFY WHERE THEY HAD BEEN HELD CAPTIVE.

DEV-MUC3-0538 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 25 SEP 89 (EL SIGLO) -- [EDITORIAL] [GERMAN ISAZA ROBLEDO] [TEXT] THE SELF-DETERMINATION OF PEOPLES MEANS NATIONS HAVE THE ABILITY TO SETTLE THEIR DOMESTIC PROBLEMS BY THEMSELVES. BASED ON THIS VIEW, SEVERAL OF THE COUNTRY'S MOST OUSTANDING DEMOCRATS AND DUPES DENOUNCED FOREIGN MILITARY AID TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING, A SCOURGE THAT BECAME AN INTERNATIONAL PROBLEM A LONG TIME AGO AND IS WEAKENING COLOMBIAN SOVEREIGNTY.

I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT THOSE WHO ARE NOW MOST OPPOSED TO THE PRESENCE OF U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS AND EXPERTS ARE THOSE WHO REGARD THIS PRESENCE AS A SERIOUS OBSTACLE TO THE ARMED ORGANIZATIONS THEY PROMOTE AND THAT ARE TRAINED BY LIBYAN, BRITISH, CUBAN, AND ISRAELI EXPERTS.

IT IS OBVIOUS THAT SOVEREIGNTY IS THE MOST IMPORTANT ELEMENT FOR THE EXISTENCE OF A STATE. HOWEVER, WE LOST OUR SOVEREIGNTY LONG AGO AND TO REGAIN IT WE MUST ACCEPT ALL THE AID THE HONEST INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY CAN OFFER US.

SOVEREIGNTY, AMONG OTHER THINGS, MEANS ADOPTING DECISIONS BASED ON THE NEEDS OR PREFERENCES OF THE NATION AS A WHOLE. THAT STOPPED HAPPENING IN COLOMBIA WHEN THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS BEGAN TO INTIMIDATE AND DESTROY THE LEGITIMATE INSTITUTIONS OF THE STATE. HOW CAN WE TALK OF SOVEREIGNTY WHEN WE SEE THAT OUR PEOPLE HAVE FALLEN PREY TO TERRORISM; THAT THEY ARE LIVING AND DYING ENSLAVED BY DAILY BOMBINGS AND LIES; THAT THEY ARE GOVERNING UNDER THE PRESSURE OF THREATS; THAT THEY HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE IN A HOME IMPRISONED BY FEAR? IT IS ABSURD TO TALK OF A TRULY SOVEREIGN STATE WHEN IT IS KNOWN THAT SEVERAL OF THE COUNTRY'S TOP POLITICAL AND BUSINESS LEADERS ARE INVOLVED IN CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES. AN ACT OF SOVEREIGNTY -- ONE IN THE MIDST OF SO MUCH SUBJUGATION -- WOULD BE TO STRIP OURSELVES OF SO MUCH VAIN PRIDE AND ACCEPT THE FACT THAT WE ARE WEAK AND NEED ALL THE HELP OFFERED BY ANYONE WHOSE INTENTIONS ARE BASED ON THE LAW. MOREOVER, IT IS IRONIC THAT SEVERAL OF THOSE WHO ARE CLAMORING FOR "THE DEFENSE OF SOVEREIGNTY" ARE THE SAME ONES WHO ARE NOW ASKING THE U.S. GOVERNMENT TO EXPLAIN THE CANCELLATION OF VISAS. IS IT NOT A MATTER OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY TO DECIDE WHO CAN AND CANNOT ENTER THAT COUNTRY?

I AM REMINDED OF THOSE THOUSANDS OF CASES OF FOOD AND MEDICINE DONATED TO COLOMBIA FOLLOWING THE ARMERO CATASTROPHE THAT ROTTED IN THE COUNTRY'S CUSTOMS WAREHOUSES. ARMERO IS THE BURIAL GROUND FOR 30,000 COLOMBIANS AND THE SCENE OF THE TRAGEDY OF THOUSANDS MORE. DESPITE THE REGRETTABLE END THAT THIS AID MET IN SO MANY WAREHOUSES, NOBODY OPPOSED INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY WITH THAT CORNER OF TOLIMA DEPARTMENT.

THE WAR ON DRUG TRAFFICKERS COULD BURY US. LET US STRUGGLE FOR SOVEREINGTY AND ACCEPT THE ADVICE OFFERED BY THE UNITED STATES, OR WE WILL END UP ROTTING IN A WAREHOUSE FILLED WITH WHITE POWDER.

DEV-MUC3-0539 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 1 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY [ELN] GUERRILLA MOVEMENT, WHICH KIDNAPPED SPANISH BUSINESSMAN PABLO MARTIN BERROCAL ALMOST 2 MONTHS AGO IN QUITO, IS DEMANDING 1 BILLION PESETAS RANSOM FOR HIS RELEASE.

SOURCES CLOSE TO THE REBEL GROUP, THE ONLY ONE THAT HAS NOT JOINED THE GOVERNMENT'S PEACE PROCESS IN COLOMBIA, TOLD EFE THAT NEGOTIATIONS FOR HIS RELEASE ARE BEING CARRIED OUT IN AN UNIDENTIFIED BORDER TOWN.

COLOMBIAN GUERRILLAS, DISGUISED AS POLICEMEN, KIDNAPPED THE 55-YEAR-OLD BUSINESSMAN LAST 9 AUGUST AT THE HOTEL WHERE BERROCAL WAS STAYING IN THE DOWNTOWN SECTION OF THE ECUADORAN CAPITAL. THE SAME SOURCES STATED THAT BERROCAL'S WIFE, BLANCA PARADELA, AND A PARTNER ARE IN COLOMBIA NEGOTIATING FOR THE BUSINESSMAN'S RELEASE DIRECTLY WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE ELN, A REBEL GROUP LED BY FORMER SPANISH PRIEST MANUEL PEREZ,

THE ELN HAS NOT ANNOUNCED THE MOTIVE FOR THE KIDNAPPING. SOURCES CONSULTED WITH BY EFE CONSIDERED THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE COLOMBIAN REBEL GROUP HAS ONLY ECONOMIC MOTIVES.

BERROCAL OWNS A BULLFIGHTING RING IN QUITO AND HE PARTICIPATES WITH HIS BROTHER, BULLFIGHTING BUSINESSMAN LUIS MARTIN BERROCAL, IN LA SEPULVEDANA TRANSPORTATION COMPANY.

NEITHER THE COLOMBIAN NATIONAL POLICE NOR THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS), CHARGED WITH THE COUNTRY'S SECRET INVESTIGATIONS, HAVE ANY INFORMATION ON MARTIN BERROCAL OR HIS ALLEGED PRESENCE IN THE COUNTRY.

EFE HAS LEARNED THAT REPRESENTATIVES OF MARTIN BERROCAL, WHO WENT TO BOGOTA IN MID-SEPTEMBER, DID NOT GET IN CONTACT WITH THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES WHEN THEY PASSED THROUGH THIS CITY.

THE ELN, A MARXIST-LENINIST ORIENTED GROUP THAT HAS BEEN INVOLVED IN ARMED STRUGGLE FOR 25 YEARS, HAS BEEN CHARACTERIZED BY ITS ATTACKS ON THE COLOMBIAN OIL ENTERPRISE AND FREQUENT KIDNAPPINGS OF NEWSMEN AND POLITICIANS OF THE COUNTRY.

THE GROUP HAS BEEN ACTIVE ALONG THE COLOMBIAN BORDER, ESPECIALLY AREAS THAT BORDER ECUADOR AND VENEZUELA.

DEV-MUC3-0540 (UMASS)

JERUSALEM (ISRAEL), 2 OCT 89 (JERUSALEM TELEVISION SERVICE) -- [TEXT] ISRAELI ANTITERROR SECURITY INSTRUCTORS IN PERU HAVE BEEN DECLARED PERSONA NON GRATA AND ARE NOT BEING ALLOWED TO ENTER PERU. THIS WAS LEARNED BY OUR CORRESPONDENT FROM SOURCES CLOSE TO ISRAELI COMPANIES DEALING WITH THE SALE OF SECURITY KNOW-HOW.

THE LONDON OBSERVER, QUOTING PERUVIAN CONGRESS MEMBERS, REPORTED THAT EVIDENCE CONCERNING ISRAELI INVOLVEMENT IN THE TRAINING OF A RIGHT-WING TERRORIST ORGANIZATION IN LIMA DISAPPEARED FROM THE FILES OF A CONGRESSIONAL COMMISSION PROBING ISRAELI INVOLVEMENT IN PERU. OUR CORRESPONDENT HANAN 'AZRAN HAS MORE DETAILS:

THE REPORTS IN THE LONDON OBSERVER APPARENTLY STEM FROM LEFT-WING CIRCLES AND PERUVIAN GUERRILLA GROUPS. THE MOST PROMINENT GROUP IS THE SHINING PATH, A GUERRILLA GROUP AIMING TO OVERTHROW THE REGIME. THESE CIRCLES CONTEND THAT ISRAELIS TRAIN WHAT THEY TERM THE RIGHT-WING DEATH, OR TERROR, SQUADS. THEY APPARENTLY REFER TO THE RODRIGO FRANCO COMMANDO UNITS, TO WHICH THE LIQUIDATION OF GUERRILLA MEMBERS AND OF OPPONENTS TO THE REGIME IS ATTRIBUTED.

POLITICAL CIRCLES IN JERUSALEM HAVE SAID THAT THESE CLAIMS OF ISRAELI INVOLVEMENT IN THE TRAINING OF DEATH SQUADS ARE GROUNDLESS.

ISRAELI COMPANIES ARE INVOLVED IN MILITARY TRAINING AND IN MANEUVERS IN PERU. ISRAELI EXPERTS HAVE SET UP THE PERUVIAN ARMY'S ANTITERROR SQUAD. ONE OF THE SQUAD'S FOUNDERS WAS GABI KOHEN, A FORMER ISRAEL POLICE ANTITERROR UNIT COMMANDER. GABI KOHEN WAS A PARTNER IN THE DAT COMPANY, WHICH OFFERED SIMILAR TRAINING AND INSTRUCTION SERVICES TO ADDITIONAL COUNTRIES IN LATIN AMERICA AND ELSEWHERE IN THE WORLD.

DAT OPERATED IN PERU WITH THE PERMIT OF SIBAT, THE DEFENSE MINISTRY DEFENSE SALES DEPARTMENT. ONE MEMBER OF THE COMPANY WAS A SENIOR BORDER POLICE OFFICER, FORMER BORDER POLICE COMMANDER TZVI BAR, WHO RETIRED FROM THE COMPANY AFTER A SHORT PERIOD, TURNING TO OTHER ENTERPRISES.

ONE COMPANY WITH DIVERSE OPERATIONS IN PERU WAS THE ISDS OWNED BY LEO GLASER, ALSO AN IDF [ISRAEL DEFENSE FORCES] ELITE UNIT GRADUATE. ISDS HAD PERMANENT OFFICES IN LIMA HEADED BY RAN GAZIT, WHO LATER OPENED A BUSINESS OF HIS OWN ELSEWHERE. THE COMPANY HAD DEFENSE MINISTRY APPROVAL FOR ITS WORK IN PERU. ACCORDING TO ITS DIRECTORS, IT TRAINED SECURITY GUARDS FOR CIVILIAN BUSINESSES ONLY, INCLUDING THE USE OF FIREARMS AND PROTECTION MEASURES.

DEV-MUC3-0542 (UMASS)

BOGOTA, 3 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE AUTHORITIES OF THE EASTERN DEPARTMENT OF ARAUCA, IN THE OIL PRODUCING SECTOR OF THE COUNTRY, HAVE ANNOUNCED THAT MSGR JESUS EMILIO JARAMILLO WAS MURDERED AND THAT HIS BODY WAS FOUND TODAY. THE AUTHORITIES BLAMED THE LEFTIST ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) GUERRILLAS FOR THE MURDER.

YESTERDAY SEVERAL ARMED MEN KIDNAPPED JARAMILLO, THE BISHOP OF ARAUCA, AND HIS ASSISTANT, ELMER MUNOZ, BUT LATER RELEASED THE LATTER.

GENERAL RAFAEL PADILLA, COMMANDER OF THE 2D ARMY DIVISION, CONFIRMED THAT BISHOP JARAMILLO DIED FROM TWO GUNSHOTS TO THE HEAD. HE BLAMED THE ELN'S DOMINGO LAIN FRONT FOR THE CRIME.

GEN PADILLA PRAISED MSGR JARAMILLO'S WORK OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS IN FAVOR OF THE POOR IN ARAUCA DEPARTMENT, BUT DID NOT EXPLAIN WHAT REASONS THE GUERRILLAS COULD HAVE HAD FOR MURDERING THE PRELATE.

THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THAT A CHURCH OFFICIAL OF SUCH HIGH RANKING HAS BEEN MURDERED IN COLOMBIA.

THE ELN, THE MOST ACTIVE AND VIOLENT GUERRILLA GROUP IN THE COUNTRY, HAS REPEATEDLY REJECTED THE OFFERS OF PEACE FROM THE LIBERAL ADMINISTRATION OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO. THE ELN--WHICH IS LED BY MANUEL PEREZ, A SPANISH CITIZEN AND FORMER PRIEST--HAS MADE THE COUNTRY'S OIL INFRASTRUCTURE THE MAIN TARGET OF ITS TERRORIST ACTIVITIES.

DEV-MUC3-0543 (UMASS)

SANTIAGO, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] GROUPS HOLDING THE SAME POLICIES THAT FAILED IN CHILE AT THE END OF THE 1960'S AND THE BEGINNING OF THE 1970'S WERE ABLE TO ESTABLISH THEMSELVES IN OTHER PLACES.

NOW WE ARE WITNESSING THE COLLAPSE OF THE ILLUSIONS AND OF THE POSSIBILITIES OF TOTALITARIAN AND COLLECTIVIST SYSTEMS. IT SEEMS THAT PEACE IS BEING CONSOLIDATED. THE WORLD POWERS HAVE AGREED TO WORK FOR A BETTER UNDERSTANDING AND MORE RATIONAL RELATIONS. THE WORLD IS BECOMING INCREASINGLY INTERDEPENDENT.

OUR MODERN KNOWLEDGE, SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY, AND RESOURCES HAVE OVERCOME BORDERS AND LIMITATIONS. THE SAME IS TRUE OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. THESE PROBLEMS, THEREFORE, ARE A CHALLENGE FOR WORLD COOPERATION AND THIS ORGANIZATION.

ONE OF THE GREATEST CHALLENGES FACING THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TODAY IS THE DRAFTING OF EFFECTIVE PROGRAMS TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING. WE SUPPORT COLOMBIA FOR ITS COURAGE TO FACE THE POWERFUL CRIMINAL ORGANIZATIONS THAT ARE USING THE NATION FOR THEIR OWN PURPOSES. CHILE HAS IMPLEMENTED A STRICT PREVENTIVE PROGRAM TO CONTROL THE MOST DANGEROUS MANIFESTATIONS OF THE PROBLEM. WE ARE NOT A DRUG PRODUCING COUNTRY. WE ARE VICTIMS OF DRUG TRAFFICKING.

IN ONE OF ITS FIRST DECISIONS ON THE PROBLEM, IN SEPTEMBER 1973, THE GOVERNMENT EXPELLED A GROUP OF FOREIGN DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHO HAD ESTABLISHED THEMSELVES IN NORTHERN CHILE, TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE PREVAILING POLITICAL AND SOCIAL CRISIS. WE ARE CONVINCED THAT COUNTRIES CANNOT FIGHT THE PROBLEM ALONE. THE WORLD HAS DECLARED WAR ON DRUGS. WE MUST BE AWARE THAT TRANSITORY VICTORIES WILL NOT ERADICATE THE PROBLEM. ONLY WITH PROPER EDUCATION WILL WE BE ABLE TO NURTURE THE STRENGTH OF OUR YOUTH, ALERT THEM TO THE DANGERS OF DRUG CONSUMPTION, AND PREVENT THEM FROM BECOMING VICTIMS.

THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MUST ASSIGN THE NECESSARY RESOURCES TO IMPLEMENT EFFICIENT EDUCATION PROGRAMS.

WE HAVE EXPRESSED CONCERN ABOUT TERRORISM FOR MANY YEARS. TODAY WE WANT TO REITERATE OUR REJECTION AND REPUDIATION OF TERRORISM. CHILEANS ARE ESPECIALLY SENSITIVE TO TERRORISM BECAUSE WE CONTINUOUSLY EXPERIENCE THEIR COWARDLY AND IRRESPONSIBLE ATTACKS. WE HAVE OFTEN SEEN HOW SOME NATIONS RECEIVE CONFESSED TERRORISTS WHO ASK FOR POLITICAL ASYLUM.

IF MODERN SOCIETIES WANT TO DEFEAT TERRORISM AND NARCOTERRORISM, THEY WILL HAVE TO ACT DECISIVELY. TERRORISTS SHOULD NOT BE GIVEN REFUGE OR PROTECTION ANYWHERE.

SOME INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS HAVE PERMITTED THE SYSTEMATIC MANIPULATION OF THE ISSUE OF HUMAN RIGHTS FOR POLITICAL REASONS. THE PARTIES INVOLVED IN SUCH MANIPULATION HAVE TRIED TO INCLUDE THE LEGITIMATE RIGHT OF A NATION TO DEFEND ITSELF FROM TERRORISM AND SUBVERSION IN THE DEFINITION OF HUMAN RIGHT VIOLATIONS. IT IS NOT THAT WE DENY THE INALIENABLE RIGHTS OF PEOPLE. WE CONDEMN THE GROSS MANIPULATION OF THE ISSUE OF HUMAN RIGHTS. THIS MANIPULATION SHOWS THAT THOSE PARTIES DO NOT RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS THEMSELVES. HUMAN RIGHTS SHOULD BE RESPECTED BY ALL NATIONS WITHOUT EXCEPTION.

IT IS NOT FAIR TO PASS JUDGMENT ON COUNTRIES LIKE CHILE THAT HAD TO STRUGGLE HARD TO OVERCOME THE DIFFICULTIES CREATED BY TERRORISM AND SUBVERSION. TERRORISM SET FOOT IN CHILE AS A CONSEQUENCE OF DISRUPTION IN THE INSTITUTIONAL ORDER BETWEEN 1970 AND 1973. THOSE PASSING JUDGMENT MUST CONSIDER THE GENERAL SITUATION THAT PROVOKED THE COLLAPSE OF PEACEFUL COEXISTENCE.

IN CHILE WE HAVE BUILT A SOCIETY IN WHICH HUMAN RIGHTS ARE PROTECTED NOT ONLY BY DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS AND THE LAW, BUT ALSO BY THE CHILEAN PEOPLE'S WILLINGNESS TO RESPECT INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS, VALUES, AND BELIEFS. THOSE RIGHTS ARE ALSO PROTECTED BY TODAY'S SPIRIT OF COEXISTENCE.

DEV-MUC3-0544 (UMASS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 5 OCT 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN SECURITY FORCES TODAY DECLARED A "GENERAL ALERT" AFTER A RADIO STATION IN THE CAPITAL RECEIVED A PHONE CALL IN WHICH AN UNIDENTIFIED PERSON THREATENED A GENERALIZED ATTACK ON RADIO STATIONS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

ODILIO DELEON, 42, AN ANNOUNCER FOR RADIO CULTURAL, TOLD THE POLICE THAT HE RECEIVED A PHONE CALL YESTERDAY IN WHICH AN ATTACK ON RADIO STATIONS WAS THREATENED. NO REASON FOR THE THREAT WAS GIVEN.

POLICE SOURCES SAID THAT IN VIEW OF THIS REPORT, SECURITY FORCES WERE ALERTED AND INVESTIGATIONS BEGUN TO IDENTIFY THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS PLAN.

OVER 20 MONTHS AGO, THE OPERATOR OF A TRANMISSION TOWER FOR CHANNEL 7 TELEVISION WAS KILLED BY A HIGH-POWERED BOMB DETONATED BY UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS.

THE HOME OF ROLANDO ARCHILA, DIRECTOR GENERAL OF GUATEMALA'S EMISORAS UNIDAS, THE RADIO STATION WITH THE LARGEST AUDIENCE IN THE COUNTRY, WAS DAMAGED IN A TERRORIST ATTACK.

THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT ATTRIBUTED THESE ACTIONS TO "EXTREME RIGHTIST" GROUPS SEEKING TO "DESTABILIZE THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS INITIATED IN JANUARY, 1986," AFTER 2 DECADES OF MILITARY REGIMES.

SO FAR, IT IS NOT KNOWN IF THE THREAT TO THE RADIO STATIONS WAS MADE BY THOSE GROUPS, OR IF IT CAME FROM THE EXTREME LEFT (THE GUERRILLAS).

DEV-MUC3-0545 (UMASS)

LIMA, 4 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA HAS ASKED SOME EUROPEAN NATIONS TO ATTEND THE PRESIDENTIAL MEETING OF THE COCA PRODUCING COUNTRIES AND U.S. AUTHORITIES AT WHICH THE DRUG TRAFFICKING ISSUE WILL BE DISCUSSED.

GARCIA SAID THAT THE PROPOSAL WAS ADDRESSED TO THE FRENCH, ITALIAN, AND SPANISH CHIEFS OF STATE, FRANCOIS MITTERRAND, GIULIO ANDREOTTI, AND FELIPE GONZALEZ, RESPECTIVELY.

DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE TO FOREIGN CORRESPONDENTS, ALAN GARCIA SAID THAT EUROPE MUST ATTEND THIS MEETING BECAUSE IT IS A STRONG DRUG MARKET AND BECAUSE OF THE LINKS BETWEEN DRUG TRAFFICKING GANGS AND TERRORISTS.

GARCIA CRITICIZED THE PLAN PROPOSED BY WILLIAM BENNETT, THE WHITE HOUSE'S MAIN ADVISER FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING AFFAIRS, ON THE GROUNDS THAT IT "LACKS SERIOUSNESS AND IS INCONCEIVABLE." THE PLAN PROVIDES FOR $250 MILLION IN AID FOR COLOMBIA, BOLIVIA, AND PERU FOR FIGHTING DRUG TRAFFICKING IN 1990.

THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT SAID THAT THIS AMOUNT IS "RIDICULOUS" IF COMPARED WITH THE $8 BILLION THAT THE BENNETT PLAN ASSIGNS FOR FIGHTING DRUG TRAFFICKING IN THE UNITED STATES, AND WITH THE U.S. $300 BILLION MILITARY BUDGET.

ALAN GARCIA CRITICIZED THE FACT THAT THE UNITED STATES GAVE COLOMBIA "PLANES FROM THE KOREAN WAR ERA AND OLD HELICOPTERS THAT WERE USED HERE (IN PERU)."

HE SAID THAT THE UNITED STATES SHOULD NOT FORM ALLIANCES WITH GOVERNMENTS BUT WITH COCA FARMERS, AND THAT IT SHOULD IMPLEMENT COMPREHENSIVE REPLACEMENT PROGRAMS INCLUDING GUARANTEED SALES.

"PERU DOES NOT HAVE DRUG ADDICTION PROBLEMS, BUT AN AGRICULTURAL SYSTEM WHICH HAS BEEN DISTORTED BY THE U.S. DEMAND," ALAN GARCIA ADDED, NOTING THAT THE MOST FERTILE PERUVIAN LAND IS DEDICATED TO COCA FARMING.

ALAN GARCIA SAID THAT IF THE 200,000 HECTARES OF COCA FARMS IN PERU (WHICH ACCOUNT FOR 60 PERCENT OF WORLD PRODUCTION) ARE "DRASTICALLY ERADICATED," MORE THAN 400,000 PEASANTS WILL BE LEFT "IN ABSOLUTE MISERY," ADDING THAT THESE PEASANTS MAY JOIN THE SUBVERSIVE GROUPS OPERATING IN THE COCA PRODUCING ZONE OF ALTO HUALLAGA, IN THE AMAZONIAN REGION.

"IF THE UNITED STATES HAS LIVED WITH DRUG ADDICTION FOR DECADES, I DON'T SEE WHY IT NOW WANTS TO DROP KIND OF ATOMIC BOMB ON THE HUALLAGA ZONE," HE ADDED.

THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT DECLINED TO COMMENT ON A U.S. CHARGE THAT GENERAL GUILLERMO ARCINIEGAS, CHIEF OF THE HUALLAGA MILITARY ZONE, HAS USED DRUG TRAFFICKERS' MONEY TO FIGHT TERRORISTS.

"JUST AS WE HAVE NEVER SAID THAT U.S. OFFICIALS OR POLICEMEN ARE ACCOMPLICES WITH DRUG ADDICTS, WE CANNOT TOLERATE THE CHARGE THAT THOSE WHO FIGHT SUBVERSION IN PERU ARE ACCOMPLICES WITH DRUG PRODUCERS," HE NOTED.

DEV-MUC3-0546 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 5 OCT 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] SOME 80 MEMBERS AND SUPPORTERS OF THE FEDERATION OF COMMITTEES OF MOTHERS OF POLITICAL PRISONERS (FECMAFAN) TODAY "FORCIBLY" OCCUPIED THE COSTA RICAN EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR TO DENOUNCE "THE REPRESSION OF THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT" OF EL SALVADOR.

COSTA RICAN AMBASSADOR JESUS FERNANDEZ, WHO CONSIDERS HIMSELF A HOSTAGE, SAID THAT THE EMBASSY WAS "TAKEN OVER BY FORCE BY ARMED INDIVIDUALS" WHILE ALL OF ITS PERSONNEL AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WERE INSIDE THE BUILDING.

A MEMBER OF THE FECMAFAN TOLD NEWSMEN THAT "THE PURPOSE OF THIS OCCUPATION IS TO DENOUNCE BEFORE THE GOVERNMENT OF NOBEL PEACE PRIZE WINNER OSCAR ARIAS AND BEFORE THE OTHER GOVERNMENTS OF THE WORLD, THE REPRESSION TO WHICH THE PEOPLE'S ORGANIZATIONS IN EL SALVADOR ARE BEING SUBJECTED."

THE FECMAFAN MEMBER ADDED THAT THE OCCUPATION IS ALSO BEING USED TO REACH THESE GOVERNMENTS TO ASK THEM TO APPLY PRESSURE ON SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TO GET HIM TO ENSURE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS.

AMBASSADOR FERNANDEZ SAID: "THERE IS NO REASON FOR THIS OCCUPATION, BECAUSE I HAVE ALWAYS MET WITH ALL SECTORS. THIS IS HARDLY THE TREATMENT THAT SHOULD BE GIVEN TO A GOVERNMENT THAT HAS SHOWN EXTREME CONCERN IN SEEKING A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT."

IN ADDITION TO AMBASSADOR FERNANDEZ, CONSUL HUMBERTO MURILLO, COUNSELOR CARLOTA DE LOPEZ, AND FIRST SECRETARY LUIS DE ANDA ARE INSIDE THE 54-SQUARE-METER OFFICE, AS WELL AS 10 PERSONS WHO WERE SEEKING VISAS.

DE ANDA TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT HE WAS HIT ON THE LEFT HAND WHEN THE OCCUPIERS TRIED TO OPEN HIS DESK DRAWER.

THE DOORS TO THE EMBASSY, WHICH IS IN A 10-STORY BUILDING IN WESTERN SAN SALVADOR, ARE CLOSED, AND THE OFFICES ARE OCCUPIED BY WOMEN WITH WHITE SCARVES ON THEIR HEADS AND YOUTHS WHOSE FACES ARE COVERED WITH SCARVES AND GLASSES. FECMAFAN MEMBERS, WHO CLAIM THAT THEY ARE NOT CARRYING WEAPONS, ARE GUARDING THE ELEVATOR AND THE DOORS LEADING TO THE EMBASSY.

HOWEVER, CONSUL MURILLO SAID THAT HE SAW SEVERAL YOUTHS ARMED WITH .38-CALIBER REVOLVERS AND EXPLOSIVE DEVICES.

ACCORDING TO A FECMAFAN MEMBER, OVER THE PAST 3 MONTHS, SOME 150 PERSONS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND MORE THAN 500 HAVE BEEN ARRESTED OR MADE TO DISAPPEAR.

ONE OF THE LEADERS OF THE GROUP SAID: "WE ARE PROTESTING THE LIMITATION OF FREEDOMS IN EL SALVADOR. IF WE TAKE TO THE STREETS TO PROTEST WE ARE ARRESTED."

THE AMBASSADOR SAID THAT HE HAS NOT BEEN ABLE TO GET IN TOUCH WITH HIS GOVERNMENT, BECAUSE "I AM BEING PREVENTED FROM MAKING PHONE CALLS AND FROM LEAVING THE EMBASSY."

THE OCCUPIERS ALLOWED FIVE PEOPLE, INCLUDING A PREGNANT WOMAN, TO LEAVE THE PREMISES AND SAID THAT THEY PLANNED TO STAY IN THE EMBASSY INDEFINITELY.

DEV-MUC3-0548 (UMASS)

AYACUCHO, 5 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] AYACUCHO MILITARY SOURCES TODAY REPORTED THAT 35 PEOPLE DIED IN ATTACKS BY ABOUT 150 SHINING PATH MEMBERS AGAINST 4 TOWNS ON THE BORDER OF AYACUCHO AND HUANCAVELICA DEPARTMENTS.

THE ATTACKS TOOK PLACE AT DAWN ON 4 OCTOBER IN THE TOWNS OF SANTO TOMAS DE PATA, PULLUHUAMAN, ANTA, AND ROSASPATA. THERE WERE 26 PEASANTS KILLED, AND 9 REBELS DIED AT THE HANDS OF MEMBERS OF THE CIVILIAN MILITIA, WHO RESISTED THE ATTACKS DESPITE THEIR PRIMITIVE WEAPONS.

THE ZONE WHERE THE TERRORIST ATTACKS TOOK PLACE -- AND IN WHICH 15 PEASANTS WERE ALSO SERIOUSLY WOUNDED -- IS LOCATED 60 KM NORTHWEST OF THIS CITY. THE OTHER TOWNS THAT SUFFERED ATTACKS ARE LOCATED IN SANTO TOMAS DE PATA DISTRICT, HUANCAVELICA DEPARTMENT, AND IN SAN PEDRO DE CACHI DISTRICT, AYACUCHO DEPARTMENT.

THE MILITARY SOURCES REPORTED THAT IN ANTA AND PULLUHUAMAN THE TERRORISTS SET TWO SCHOOLS AND SEVERAL HOUSES ON FIRE, KILLED CATTLE AND DOMESTIC ANIMALS, AND SEIZED LARGE AMOUNTS OF BASIC GOODS.

THEY ADDED THAT THE INJURED WERE BROUGHT TO THIS ANDEAN CITY, 575 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA AND HUANTA.

THE 4 OCTOBER ATTACKS ON THESE TOWNS WERE FOLLOWED TODAY BY A SERIES OF EIGHT BOMB ATTACKS. THESE ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT IN SEVERAL PARTS OF THE CITY, AND ONE OF THEM WAS AGAINST THE NATIONAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS, WHICH IS LOCATED AT 300 METERS FROM THE MAIN SQUARE.

THERE WERE GUNSHOTS AND EXPLOSIONS AT THE POLICE HEADQUARTERS, BUT NO VICTIMS WERE REPORTED.

BOMB ATTACKS WERE ALSO CARRIED OUT AGAINST THE STATE ENERGY COMPANY, LOCATED IN DOWNTOWN AYACUCHO, CAUSING BLACKOUTS IN SEVERAL AREAS. EXPLOSIONS WERE HEARD IN THE CARMEN ALTO, SAN JUAN BAUTISTA, MAGDALENA, CAPILLAPATA, AND CONCHOPATA NEIGHBORHOODS AND AT THE SAN CRISTOBAL DE HUAMANGA UNIVERSITY.

THESE ATTACKS LAUNCHED BY THE SHINING PATH IN AYACUCHO OVER THE PAST 24 HOURS ARE PART OF THE ESCALATING VIOLENCE THAT HAS AFFECTED SEVERAL PARTS OF THE COUNTRY ONLY 5 DAYS BEFORE THE START OF TWO PRESIDENTIAL "SUMMITS" THAT WILL BE HELD IN ICA DEPARTMENT, LOCATED IN THE SOUTHERN REGION OF PERU.

THE PRESIDENTS OF BOLIVIA, COLOMBIA, AND PERU ARE SCHEDULED TO MEET TO DISCUSS THE DRUG TRAFFICKING ISSUE ON 10 OCTOBER IN PARACAS. THE "GROUP OF EIGHT" SUMMIT, (COMPRISING ARGENTINA, BRAZIL, COLOMBIA, MEXICO, PERU, URUGUAY, AND VENEZUELA), IS SCHEDULED TO BE HELD 11-12 OCTOBER IN ICA, THE CAPITAL OF THE DEPARTMENT.

DEV-MUC3-0549 (UMASS)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 OCT 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE MEDIATION OF ARCHBISHOP ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS COULD END THE OCCUPATION BY 20 MEMBERS OF AN OPPOSITION HUMANITARIAN GROUP OF THE COSTA RICAN EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

THE GROUP BELONGING TO THE FEDERATION OF COMMITTEES OF MOTHERS AND RELATIVES OF POLITICAL PRISONERS, MISSING, AND MURDERED PEOPLE (FECMAFAN) OCCUPIED THE EMBASSY ON 5 OCTOBER TO DEMAND "AN END TO THE GOVERNMENT'S REPRESSIVE ESCALATION."

ON THE EVENING OF 5 OCTOBER, THE SALVADORAN PRELATE VISITED THE BUILDING WHERE COSTA RICAN AMBASSADOR JESUS FERNANDEZ, CONSUL HUMBERTO MURILLO, AND FIRST SECRETARY LUIS DE ANDA ARE BEING HELD HOSTAGE TO PERSONALLY ASSESS THE SITUATION INSIDE IN THE DIPLOMATIC HEADQUARTERS.

AMBASSADOR FERNANDEZ MET WITH THE ARCHBISHOP ON THE FIRST FLOOR OF THE "LA CENTROAMERICANA" BUILDING, WHICH HOUSES THE COSTA RICAN EMBASSY, BUT MILITARY MEN DID NOT ALLOW HIM TO REACH THE THIRD FLOOR WHERE EMBASSY OFFICES ACTUALLY ARE.

RIVERA Y DAMAS POINTED OUT THAT "I NEED TO OBTAIN AN ARMY PERMIT TO ENTER THE EMBASSY."

POLICE DEPUTY DIRECTOR COLONEL ALEJANDRO SANCHEZ SAID THAT THE CONFLICT COULD END IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE RULED OUT MILITARY INTERVENTION TO EVICT THE EMBASSY OCCUPANTS, BUT ARE USING "DISSUASIVE" ACTIONS TO PROMPT THEM TO LEAVE.

MEANWHILE, THE GROUP MAINTAINS THAT IT WILL NOT END ITS OCCUPATION "UNTIL THE COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT MEDIATES TO ENSURE THAT OUR COUNTRY'S GOVERNMENT WILL END THE REPRESSION" AND THE ANTIRIOT POLICE LEAVE THE AREA.

NINE YOUNG WOMEN AND 11 YOUNG MEN ARE INVOLVED IN THE OCCUPATION. SOME OF THEM ARE "CARRYING WEAPONS," CONSUL HUMBERTO MURILLO SAID.

FECMAFAN CALLED FOR A MARCH THIS MORNING BEGINNING AT THE "LAS AMERICAS" PLAZA, ABOUT 200 METERS FROM THE COSTA RICAN EMBASSY, TO DEMAND THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT "RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS" AND END THE EMBASSY OCCUPATION.

MEANWHILE, THE ARMED FORCES TODAY BEEFED UP SECURITY IN SAN SALVADOR BY POSTING ADDITIONAL TROOPS ON AVENUES AND AT BUILDINGS, AND SEARCHING VEHICLES AS PART OF OPERATION "ATLACATL II," WHICH IS BEING IMPLEMENTED THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY TO PREVENT "TERRORIST" ACTIONS. [PARIS AFP IN SPANISH AT 1617 GMT REPORTS THAT COSTA RICAN AMBASSADOR JESUS FERNANDEZ WAS PICKED UP BY AN AMBULANCE ON 5 OCTOBER TO BE TREATED FOR A HEART AILMENT. IT ADDS THAT ONE OF NINE REPORTERS STILL INSIDE THE EMBASSY CALLED LOCAL STATIONS TO REPORT THAT THE POLICE DID NOT ALLOW THEM TO RECEIVE FOOD PROVIDED BY THE GREEN CROSS]

DEV-MUC3-0551 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BOGOTA, 6 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] FOUR MEN, WHO HAD 250 KG OF DYNAMITE WITH THEM, WERE ARRESTED TODAY BY THE BOGOTA POLICE WHO SAID THEY HAD DISMANTLED A BAND OF INDIVIDUALS WHO WERE SOWING TERROR IN THIS CITY.

IN ORDER NOT TO HINDER THE INVESTIGATIONS, THE POLICE DID NOT DISCLOSE THE NAMES OF THE INDIVIDUALS WHO WERE CAPTURED DURING THE INTELLIGENCE OPERATION IN SOUTHWESTERN BOGOTA.

A POLICE SPOKESMAN REPORTED THAT THE FOUR MEN WERE ARRESTED, FOLLOWING THE 5 OCTOBER ARREST OF A MAN WHO WAS CARRYING 15 KG OF DYNAMITE IN A TAXI.

SHORTLY BEFORE THAT, ANOTHER TERRORIST WAS NEARLY LYNCHED BY SOME PEOPLE WHO CAPTURED HIM IN NORTHERN BOGOTA, AFTER HE PLACED AN EXPLOSIVE DEVICE IN A PRINTSHOP.

A POLICE PATROL WENT TO THE SITE AND PREVENTED THE PRIVATE CITIZENS AND BUSINESSMEN AFFECTED BY THE BOMBS FROM SERIOUSLY HARMING THE MAN WHO WAS, NONETHELESS, SEVERELY BEATEN.

THE BOGOTA POLICE SAID THAT THE ARREST OF THESE SIX TERRORISTS IN THE LAST 24 HOURS AIDED IN UNCOVERING A PLAN TO DESTROY AN ELECTRICAL GENERATING CENTER.

A POLICE SPOKESMAN REPORTED THAT THE INDIVIDUALS WERE ARRESTED, THANKS TO THE COOPERATION OF THE PEOPLE. HE EMPHASIZED THAT THE QUICK REACTION BY A GROUP OF BUSINESSMEN LED TO THE ARREST OF ONE OF THE TERRORISTS.

THE SECOND TERRORIST WAS ARRESTED BY THE POLICE AFTER A TAXI DRIVER REFUSED TO PROVIDE SERVICE AND REPORTED HIM AS A SUSPECT.

WHEN THE SUSPECT WAS INTERROGATED, HE DISCLOSED INFORMATION THAT ALLOWED THE POLICE TO LOCATE A HOUSE IN SOUTHERN BOGOTA WHERE FOUR MEN WERE HIDING 250 KG OF DYNAMITE.

THE TERRORISM AFFECTING SEVERAL COLOMBIAN CITIES IS THE RESPONSE FROM DRUG TRAFFICKERS TO COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO WHO DECLARED WAR ON THEM IN AUGUST.

DEV-MUC3-0553 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 6 OCT 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [TEXT] GUILLERMO LARCO COX, PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS AND FOREIGN MINISTER, TODAY REITERATED THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT NEGOTIATE WITH THE KIDNAPPERS OF TELEVISION MANAGER HECTOR DELGADO PARKER BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT'S LEGITIMACY ITSELF WOULD BE AT STAKE. LARCO COX ALSO SAID THAT THE MEETING OF GROUP OF EIGHT PRESIDENTS WILL BE HELD AS PREVIOUSLY SCHEDULED AND THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS IMPLEMENTING EXTREME SECURITY MEASURES TO GUARANTEE THE SAFETY OF VISITING DIGNITARIES AND OFFICIALS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] HAS THE MEETING BETWEEN THE PRESIDENTS OF BOLIVIA, PERU, AND COLOMBIA BEEN MOVED FROM PARACAS?

[LARCO COX] IT IS A MATTER OF LOGISTICS. THE ORGANIZATION OF THE TWO MEETINGS IN PARACAS AND LAS DUNAS OVER 2 CONSECUTIVE DAYS WOULD HAVE MEANT A DUPLICATION OF EFFORTS IN GUARANTEEING PROPER COMMUNICATIONS. THIS IS THE ONLY REASON WE HAVE MOVED THE SITE OF THE FIRST MEETING.

I HAVE JUST HAD A MEETING WITH THE AMBASSADORS OF THE COUNTRIES MAKING UP THE GROUP OF EIGHT. WE EXPLAINED TO THEM ALL THE SECURITY MEASURES WE ARE IMPLEMENTING, NOT ONLY FOR THE PERSONAL SECURITY OF DIGNITARIES BUT ALSO FOR THE SECURITY OF THE BUILDINGS IN WHICH THE MEETINGS WILL BE HELD. PERU'S IMAGE IS AT STAKE. WE HAVE TO BE VERY CAREFUL TO PROTECT THIS IMAGE.

[REPORTER] HAS THE MEETING IN TRUJILLO BEEN CANCELED?

[LARCO COX] WE SHOULD NOT FORGET THAT WE LIVE IN A CITY WHERE RUMORS THRIVE LIKE MUSHROOMS. I WOULD NOT SAY THE COUNTRY IS LIKE THAT, BUT IT IS TRUE THAT RUMORS IN THIS CITY USUALLY SPREAD OUT OF CONTROL. THE MEETING IN TRUJILLO WILL BE HELD. I AM PERSONALLY PROUD OF IT.

[REPORTER] WHERE WILL THE MEETING BETWEEN THE PRESIDENTS OF PERU, BOLIVIA, AND COLOMBIA BE HELD?

[LARCO COX] IN ICA, IN THE SAME PLACE WHERE THE GROUP OF EIGHT WILL MEET THE NEXT DAY.

[REPORTER] WILL THE GROUP OF EIGHT DISCUSS THE SITUATION IN PANAMA?

[LARCO COX] IT IS ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT ISSUES ON OUR AGENDA. LET US NOT FORGET THAT PANAMA IS ONE OF THE COFOUNDERS OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT. THE GROUP OF EIGHT IS NOW MORE APPROPRIATELY CALLED THE MECHANISM FOR POLITICAL CONSULTATION AND AGREEMENT, BUT IT WAS ORIGINALLY MADE UP OF THE CONTADORA GROUP, OF WHICH PANAMA WAS A MEMBER, AND THE CONTADORA SUPPORT GROUP, WHICH WAS FOUNDED IN LIMA WHEN ALAN GARCIA TOOK OVER.

[REPORTER] THE SECURITY OF THE PRESIDENTS IS OF GREAT CONCERN. IS EACH ONE ARRIVING WITH THEIR OWN SECURITY? ARE THERE EXCEPTIONAL MEASURES BEING IMPLEMENTED?

[LARCO COX] THE DIGNITARIES MIGHT BRING THEIR OWN PERSONAL SECURITY FORCES. HOWEVER, OUR COUNTRY WILL GUARANTEE THE SECURITY OF THE AREA, THE BUILDINGS, AND THEIR PERSONAL SECURITY.

[REPORTER] FOREIGN SOURCES HAVE BEEN SPECULATING THAT SOME PRESIDENTS MIGHT NOT COME. WHAT CAN YOU SAY AS A REPRESENTATIVE OF THE HOST COUNTRY?

[LARCO COX] THE FIRST THING WE DID WAS TO CALL THE AMBASSADORS OF THESE COUNTRIES TO A MEETING BECAUSE THEY ALSO HAVE AN OBLIGATION TO OBSERVE AND ASSESS OUR GUARANTEES. THE RESULT OF THE MEETING WAS VERY POSITIVE; THEY SUPPORTED US WITHOUT EXCEPTIONS. THE AMBASSADORS HAVE FOUND OUR EXPLANATION ON THE SECURITY MEASURES BEING IMPLEMENTED VERY SATISFACTORY. THESE MEASURES WENT INTO EFFECT TODAY. SOME OF YOU MIGHT HAVE ALREADY OBSERVED THE OPERATIONS: WE ARE NOT ONLY STOPPING TRAFFIC TO CHECK CARS, LUGGAGE, AND PEOPLE TRAVELING ON BUSES, BUT WE HAVE ALSO KEPT A CLOSE WATCH ON NEWCOMERS. ALL FOREIGNERS WHO HAVE ARRIVED IN THE COUNTRY OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS ARE BEING WATCHED. POLICE ARE CHECKING TO SEE IF THEY ARE IN THE HOTELS WHERE THEY SAID THEY WOULD BE. THESE OPERATIONS ARE AIMED AT PREVENTING ANY EXTERNAL AGGRESSION. WE ALSO HAVE OUR OWN RISKS, AND MANY MEN FROM THE NATIONAL POLICE AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE INVOLVED IN THE SECURITY OPERATIONS THAT BEGAN AT NOON TODAY. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0557 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 8 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT HAS ESTABLISHED UNPRECEDENTED SECURITY MEASURES TO GUARANTEE THE SAFETY OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT PRESIDENTS AND FOREIGN MINISTERS WHO WILL BEGIN MEETING ON 9 OCTOBER IN TRUJILLO, THE COUNTRY'S THIRD-LARGEST CITY, 570 KM NORTH OF LIMA.

ACCORDING TO MEDIA REPORTS, SOME 15,000 OFFICERS, INCLUDING POLICE, ARMY, NAVY, AND AIR FORCE PERSONNEL, WILL BE RESPONSIBLE FOR SECURITY AT TRUJILLO AND ICA, 300 KM SOUTH OF LIMA.

ARGENTINE PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM, BRAZILIAN PRESIDENT JOSE SARNEY, COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, URUGUAYAN PRESIDENT JULIO MARIA SANGUINETTI, MEXICAN PRESIDENT CARLOS SALINAS, VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, AND PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA WILL MEET AT THE "LAS DUNAS" HOTEL IN ICA 11-12 OCTOBER. HOTEL WORKERS AND EMPLOYEES HAVE BEEN REPLACED AS A PREVENTIVE MEASURE.

THE PRESIDENTS OF PERU, COLOMBIA, AND BOLIVIA WILL ALSO BE MEETING IN ICA ON 10 OCTOBER TO ANALYZE THE PROBLEM OF DRUG TRAFFICKING, WHICH AFFECTS THEIR COUNTRIES ESPECIALLY.

THIS MEETING WAS ORIGINALLY PLANNED FOR PARACAS, A TOWN NEAR ICA, BUT WAS MOVED TO ICA FOR SECURITY REASONS.

THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE BEEN CONFINED TO BARRACKS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY SINCE LAST NIGHT BECAUSE, ACCORDING TO SOURCES, IT IS EXPECTED THAT THE SHINING PATH AND THE TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA) WILL TRY TO STAGE VIOLENT ACTS DURING THE MEETINGS.

THE GUARDS AROUND THE EMBASSIES OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT COUNTRIES HAVE BEEN REINFORCED WITH POLICE DOGS TRAINED TO DETECT EXPLOSIVES.

POLICE HAVE ALSO ARRESTED THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE IN LIMA TO CHECK ON ANY POSSIBLE CONNECTIONS TO GUERRILLA MOVEMENTS OR TO SEE IF THEY HAVE ACCOUNTS TO SETTLE WITH THE COURTS.

THE ROUNDUPS ARE ALSO BEING CARRIED OUT TO FIND LOCAL TELEVISION MAGNATE HECTOR DELGADO PARKER, WHO WAS APPARENTLY KIDNAPPED BY THE MRTA DURING AN INCIDENT IN WHICH DELGADO'S DRIVER WAS KILLED AND HIS BODYGUARD WOUNDED.

THE KIDNAPPING WAS CARRIED OUT BY A GROUP OF PEOPLE, TWO OF WHOM WERE DRESSED IN POLICE UNIFORMS, IN THE STREETS OF LIMA ON 4 OCTOBER.

NEWSPAPER SOURCES TODAY SAID THAT AN ALLEGED LIEUTENANT TO MRTA CHIEF VICTOR POLAY, WHO HAS BEEN IN PRISON SINCE DECEMBER 1988, HAS ALSO BEEN ARRESTED.

DEV-MUC3-0558 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 8 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO A CONFIDENTIAL PERUVIAN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE DOCUMENT PUBLISHED TODAY BY THE LIMA DAILY LA REPUBLICA, THE PERUVIAN SHINING PATH GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION IS PLANNING TO PROVOKE A FOOD SHORTAGE IN LIMA.

ACCORDING TO THE REPORT, THIS ALLEGED SHINING PATH STRATEGY, BASED ON THE THEORY BY THE LEADER OF THE CHINESE REVOLUTION, MAO ZEDONG, "OF LAYING SIEGE TO THE CITY FROM THE COUNTRYSIDE," IS PART OF THE TERRORISTS' EFFORTS TO BOYCOTT THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS OF 12 NOVEMBER 1989 AND, SUBSEQUENTLY, THE GENERAL AND CONGRESSIONAL ELECTIONS OF APRIL 1990.

ACCORDING TO PASSAGES FROM THE DOCUMENT PUBLISHED IN LA REPUBLICA, THE SHINING PATH "HAS REPORTEDLY GAINED CONTROL OVER AN IMPORTANT SECTOR OF LIMA'S FOOD SUPPLY AND MARKETING NETWORK."

OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE POINTED OUT THAT FARMER IN THE VALLEYS OF THE PERUVIAN COAST AREA HAVE BEEN THREATENED BY "SHINING PATH PEOPLE" SO THAT THEY NEITHER HARVEST NOR SELL THEIR PRODUCTS. SIMILAR INTIMIDATING ACTIONS ARE ALSO EXPECTED IN THE SIERRA VALLEYS AND THE PERUVIAN JUNGLE AREA, THE SAME SOURCES NOTED.

PERUVIAN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE OFFICIALS ALSO EXPECT THE TERRORISTS TO TAKE DIRECT ACTION WITHIN THE NEXT FEW DAYS BY BURNING THE TRUCKS THAT SUPPLY LIMA WITH FOODSTUFFS.

THIS SABOTAGE, THE DOCUMENT POINTS OUT, "WOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY MASSIVE ACTIONS AGAINST THE ELECTRIC POWER SUPPLY SYSTEM AIMED AT REDUCING THE REFRIGERATED STORAGE CAPACITY OF LIMA'S MAIN FOOD SUPPLIERS."

THE REPORTS POINTS OUT THAT THE BOYCOTT OF THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS WILL BE ACCOMPANIED BY A "SHINING PATH" CALL TO HOLD A "NATIONAL ARMED STOPPAGE" FOR 12 NOVEMBER 1989, WHICH WILL SERVE AS A TRIAL FOR SIMILAR ACTIONS IN THE APRIL 1990 GENERAL ELECTIONS.

ELSEWHERE, A CAR BOMB EXPLODED LAST NIGHT IN THE TOWN OF BARRANCA, LIMA DEPARTMENT, CLOSE TO WHERE FORMER EDUCATION MINISTER GROVER PANGO IS STAYING. FOUR PEOPLE WERE INJURED AND PROPERTY WAS DAMAGED.

TERRORIST GROUPS ALSO BLEW UP SEVERAL HIGH-VOLTAGE TOWERS. A BLACKOUT WAS REPORTED IN BARRANCA AND NEIGHBORING TOWNS.

ACCORDING TO A REPORT PUBLISHED BY LA REPUBLICA, THE TERRORIST ESCALATION BEGAN LAST FRIDAY [6 OCTOBER] IN LIMA AND TWO POLICEMEN DIED IN THE TOWN OF CERRO BLANCO.

IN HUANCAYO, THE CAPITAL OF JUNIN DEPARTMENT IN THE PERUVIAN CENTRAL SIERRA, THE SANTA ISABEL HIGH SCHOOL HAS BEEN THE TARGET OF 10 BOMB ATTACKS OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS. THE ATTACKS HAVE APPARENTLY BEEN PERPETRATED BY TERRORISTS WHO HAVE INFILTRATED THEMSELVES INTO THE 5,000 SANTA ISABEL HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS. ONLY PROPERTY DAMAGE HAS BEEN REPORTED AS A RESULT OF THE ATTACKS.

DEV-MUC3-0559 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

TRUJILLO, 9 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] TODAY IN THE CITY OF TRUJILLO THE FOREIGN MINISTERS OF ARGENTINA, BRAZIL, MEXICO, AND PERU BEGAN DISCUSSING THE POSSIBILITY OF OUSTING PANAMA FROM THE GROUP OF EIGHT AND EVENTUALLY ACCEPTING ECUADOR IN ITS PLACE. THE POSSIBILITY OF EXPELLING PANAMA FROM THE GROUP WAS DISCUSSED EVEN THOUGH ARGENTINE FOREIGN MINISTER DOMINGO CAVALLO SAID THE ISSUE WAS NOT ON THE AGENDA.

ASKED ABOUT THE POSSIBLE OUSTING OF PANAMA FROM THE GROUP OF EIGHT AND REPLACING IT WITH ECUADOR, ARGENTINE FOREIGN MINISTER DOMINGO CAVALLO TOLD EFE: "WE ARE GOING TO LISTEN TO THE PROPOSAL, BUT WE PREFER NOT TO COMMENT FOR THE TIME BEING. WE WILL SEE WITHIN THE CONTEXT OF THE MEETING WHAT THE BASIS FOR THAT PROPOSAL IS."

CAVALLO ADDED: "WE DO NOT HAVE PROPOSALS OR INITIATIVES ANY DIFFERENT FROM THE ISSUES TO BE DISCUSSED ON PANAMA."

MEXICAN FOREIGN MINISTER FERNANDO SOLANA TOLD EFE THAT THE PREPARATORY FOREIGN MINISTERS MEETING WILL DISCUSS THE PANAMANIAN ISSUE AND THAT MEXICO WILL DECIDE ITS STANCE "AT THE APPROPRIATE TIME."

BRAZILIAN FOREIGN MINISTER ROBERTO DE ABREU SAID IN THIS CITY YESTERDAY THAT BRAZIL HAS AN INDIVIDUAL POSITION "BUT WILL ACCEPT AND SUPPORT A JOINT AGREEMENT."

PERUVIAN FOREIGN MINISTER GUILLERMO LARCO COX ALSO SAID YESTERDAY THAT PERU WILL PROPOSE "THE FINAL SEPARATION OF PANAMA" FROM THE GROUP OF EIGHT.

LARCO ADDED THAT PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA WILL PROPOSE THE SEPARATION OF PANAMA FROM THE GROUP DURING THE SUMMIT MEETING THAT WILL BE HELD WITH THE PRESIDENTS OF ARGENTINA, BRAZIL, COLOMBIA, MEXICO, URUGUAY, AND VENEZUELA ON 11 AND 12 OCTOBER. THE MEETING WILL TAKE PLACE IN ICA, 850 KM SOUTH OF TRUJILLO.

TODAY LARCO COX OPENED THE GROUP OF EIGHT FOREIGN MINISTERS' MEETING IN TRUJILLO. THE FOREIGN MINISTERS OF COLOMBIA AND VENEZUELA WERE ABSENT BECAUSE THEY WILL GO DIRECTLY TO ICA WITH THEIR RESPECTIVE PRESIDENTS.

IN A BRIEF SPEECH, LARCO COX CALLED ON THE OTHER REPRESENTATIVES TO STRUGGLE FOR THE UNITY, INTEGRATION, AND INDEPENDENCE IN THE REGION.

COX ADDED: "WE MUST WORK FOR OVERALL DEVELOPMENT. WE PROPOSE AS AN ACT OF JUSTICE THE INTEGRATION OF THE CONTINENT WHICH IS NECESSARY FOR THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT OF OUR PEOPLE."

HE ADDED THAT THE INTEGRATION PROCESS CANNOT BE AN ISOLATED PROCESS AND THAT UNITY CAN ONLY BE EFFECTIVE IF THE COUNTRIES RESCUE THE HISTORIC VALUES WHICH CONSOLIDATED THE INDEPENDENCE OF THE AMERICAS.

THE MINISTERS ALSO DISCUSSED, IN ADDITION TO THE PANAMANIAN AND ECUADORAN CASE, THE DRUG TRAFFICKING PROBLEM, JOINT ACTION TO DEAL WITH THE REGION'S FOREIGN DEBT, ESTIMATED AT $420 BILLION, AND TERRORISM.

THE PROPOSALS MADE IN TRUJILLO WILL BE DISCUSSED BY THE SEVEN PRESIDENTS IN ICA.

THE FOREIGN MINISTERS MEETING IS BEING HELD UNDER POLICE AND MILITARY CONTROL TO PREVENT TERRORIST ATTACKS. ON 4 OCTOBER A CAR BOMB EXPLODED ABOUT 500 METERS FROM THE MEETING SITE. FORTUNATELY, THERE WAS ONLY PROPERTY DAMAGE.

SOME OF THE SECURITY MEASURES INCLUDED THE CHANGE OF THE FOREIGN MINISTERS' ARRIVAL TIMES AND SOME CHANGES IN THE OFFICIAL PROGRAM.

THERE IS STRICT POLICE CONTROL NEAR THE CESAR VALLEJO CIVIC CENTER WHERE THE MINISTERS ARE MEETING. VEHICLE AND PEDESTRIAN TRAFFIC WAS PROHIBITED WITHIN ABOUT 200 METERS OF THE CENTER.

THE FIRST MEETING OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT WAS HELD IN ACAPULCO, MEXICO, IN 1987, AND THE SECOND MEETING WAS HELD IN PUNTA DEL ESTE, URUGUAY, IN 1988.

DEV-MUC3-0561 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 10 OCT 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO TODAY ANNOUNCED THE APPOINTMENT OF ARIEL RIVERA IRIAS AS THE NEW FOREIGN MINISTER TO REPLACE MARIO PALENCIA. CEREZO ALSO APPOINTED NEW GOVERNMENT AND FINANCE MINISTERS, GENERAL CARLOS AUGUSTO MORALES AND FRANCISCO PINTO CASAROLA, RESPECTIVELY, TO REPLACE ROBERTO VALLE AND RODOLFO PAIZ.

MEANWHILE, GONZALO MENENDEZ DE LA RIVA, GUATEMALA'S HUMAN RIGHTS ATTORNEY GENERAL, TODAY PRESENTED HIS IRREVOCABLE RESIGNATION TO THE POST THAT HE HAD HELD SINCE 1987. MENENDEZ, WHO IS 82-YEARS-OLD, EXPLAINED THAT HE WAS RESIGNING BECAUSE, "I FEEL TIRED DUE TO MY ADVANCED AGE," AND ADDED THAT THIS WAS FOR "ABSOLUTELY PERSONAL" REASONS.

AT THE GOVERNMENT PALACE THE PRESIDENT EXPLAINED THAT THE CHANGES ARE PART OF A PROJECT AND ORGANIZATION OF HIS 500-DAY ADMINISTRATION PROGRAM.

VINICIO CEREZO ALSO ANNOUNCED THE APPOINTMENT OF HUMBERTO LAU AS PRESIDENT OF THE METROPOLITAN URBAN AND RURAL DEVELOPMENT COUNCIL. THIS POSITION HAD BEEN VACANT SINCE 1 AUGUST WHEN DANILO VARILLAS, CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC LEADER AND FORMER GUATEMALAN AMBASSADOR TO SPAIN, WAS SHOT TO DEATH.

ROBERTO VALLE, WHO WILL RETURN TO CONGRESS AS A DEPUTY, WAS CRITICIZED BY POLITICAL LEADERS AND SOCIAL SEGMENTS OF THE POPULATION FOR HIS INABILITY TO CURB VIOLENCE.

THE PRESIDENT POINTED OUT THAT PAIZ MIGHT BECOME A VICE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE IN NEXT YEAR'S GENERAL ELECTIONS.

DEV-MUC3-0562 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

HAVANA (CUBA), 10 OCT 89 (TELE-REBELDE NETWORK) -- [INTERVIEW WITH COMMANDER GASPAR, RODRIGO ASTURIAS, MEMBER OF THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY, URNG, MILITARY DIRECTORATE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] GREETINGS COMRADE. GUATEMALA ALWAYS COMES UP IN CENTRAL AMERICAN NEWS. WE KNOW LITTLE ABOUT GUATEMALA. INTERNATIONAL NEWS AGENCIES BLOCK REPORTS FROM GUATEMALA . WE HAVE LEARNED THAT IN ADDITION TO THE ATMOSPHERE OF CHAOS AND INSTABILITY, REPRESSION HAS INCREASED IN THE LAST 7 MONTHS. IT WAS REPORTED RECENTLY THAT 2,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED, 2,500 WOUNDED -- MANY OF THEM CRIPPLED -- AND HUNDREDS -- OVER 800 ARE MISSING. WE HAVE TAKEN THE OPPORTUNITY OF A VISIT PAID BY MR RODRIGO ASTURIAS, WHO IS MEMBER OF THE URNG MILITARY DIRECTORATE AND IS ALSO KNOWN AS COMMANDER GASPAR, NOT ONLY IN GUATEMALA AND CENTRAL AMERICA BUT THROUGHOUT THE WORLD, TO TALK AND CLEAR SOME MATTERS PERTAINING TO GUATEMALA.

COMMANDER GASPAR: SOME STEPS HAVE BEEN TAKEN TO FIND A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION. THAT IS, STEPS HAVE BEEN TAKEN TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GUERRILLA AND THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT. SOME JOURNALISTS AND SPECIALISTS WONDER IF THE SEARCH FOR A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION IS COMPATIBLE WITH THE SITUATION PREVAILING IN GUATEMALA. WHAT COULD YOU TELL US ABOUT THIS?

[ASTURIAS] I BELIEVE THIS IS AN INTERESTING QUESTION THAT NEEDS TO BE CLARIFIED. AT THE END OF SEPTEMBER, THE URNG GENERAL COMMAND MADE A NEW PROPOSAL AIMED AT FINDING A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE INTERNAL ARMED CONFLICT OUR COUNTRY IS EXPERIENCING. THE PROPOSAL TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION AND TO ESTABLISH A DIALOGUE AS A FIRST STEP TO CREATE THE CONDITIONS IS VERY IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT ENTAILS AN INCREASED EFFORT IN THE STRUGGLE FOR DEMOCRACY. WE DO NOT THINK OF DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION AS A DEMOBILIZATION ELEMENT BUT AS AN EXTREMELY ACTIVE ELEMENT, AS A CLARIFYING ELEMENT, TO FIND AND PUT IN PLACE CONSENSUS WITH DEMOCRATIC SOLUTIONS. THIS IS WHY ALTHOUGH THERE HAS BEEN, IN FACT, AN INCREASE OF REPRESSION -- WHICH BY THE WAY, IT WAS BRUTALLY INTENSIFIED LAST MONTH -- THE PROPOSAL TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION AND THE CALL ALL NATIONAL SECTORS, WITHOUT EXCEPTION, TO BEGIN CONTACTS, TALKS, AND DIALOGUE WITH THE UNRG DESPITE THE FACT THAT THE GOVERNMENT CONTINUES TO REFUSE THEM AND CONTINUES MAINTAINING A CLOSED POSITION. IT IS AN IMPORTANT STEP IN THE DEMOCRATIC STRUGGLE.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER GASPAR, INSISTING IN THE LAST PART OF YOUR RESPONSE, WHAT ARE THE BASIS IN WHICH THIS TYPE OF TALKS AND DIALOGUE COULD BE INITIATED?

[ASTURIAS] SINCE OCTOBER 1987, WHEN ITS FIRST DIALOGUE INITIATIVE WAS ESTABLISHED, THE GENERAL COMMAND HAS SAID PREESTABLISHED CONDITIONS ARE NOT NECESSARY BUT THAT THE COUNTRY'S FUNDAMENTAL PROBLEMS SHOULD BE INCLUDED IN THE DIALOGUE AND THE PREPARATION OF THE AGENDA. THE MAIN PROBLEM THE COUNTRY HAS AND HAS HAD IN THE LAST FEW YEARS IS THE LACK OF RESPECT TOWARD HUMAN RIGHTS, THE MILITARIZATION OF THE GUATEMALAN SOCIETY, AND THE GENERALIZED OPPRESSION EXPERIENCED. THEREFORE, WE BELIEVE THE MAIN POINT THAT NEEDS TO BE ADDRESSED IN THE AGENDA IS THE DEMOCRATIZATION.

[REPORTER] SPEAKING OF THE INTERNAL SITUATION FROM THE MILITARY POINT OF VIEW, NEWS AGENCY REPORT EVERY DAY OF MISSING PERSONS, KILLINGS, AND TORTURES. ARE THE ONES EVERYONE KNOWS AS THE DEATH SQUADRONS INCREASING THEIR ACTIVITIES?

[ASTURIAS] INDEED, THERE HAS BEEN AN INCREASE IN REPRESSION. WE COULD SAY WITHOUT BEING MISTAKEN THAT THERE IS A TERRORIST ESCALATION HEADED BY STATE SECURITY FORCES. IT IS VERY IMPORTANT TO DENOUNCE AND TO BE CLEAR ON THIS BECAUSE THE ONES THAT ARE CARRYING OUT THIS REPRESSION AND THE ONES THAT ARE TAKING FORWARD THIS TERROR CAMPAIGN ARE NOT PARAMILITARY GROUPS AS THE PEOPLE HAVE BEEN LED TO BELIEVE AND THEY ARE NOT EXTREME-RIGHT CIVILIAN GROUPS. THEY ARE ARMY OPERATIVE GROUPS THAT ACT BASED ON INFORMATION, CHARGES, SUSPICIONS, OR MANY TIMES BLINDLY TO SEE WHAT INFORMATION THEY CAN FIND, IN WHAT WAY THEY CAN HIT OR INFILTRATE THE PEOPLE'S AND REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT. WE ARE FACED WITH AN ESCALATION OF THE STRONGEST STATE TERRORISM. IT CANNOT BE CONFUSED WITH DEATH SQUADRONS OR DIFFERENCES WITHIN THE RIGHT WING. THE ARMY IS THE ONE RESPONSIBLE OF THE REPRESSION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0564 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BOGOTA, 11 OCT 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] JOSE RAFAEL ABELLO SILVA, CHIEF OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKING CARTEL ON THE COAST AND FOURTH MAN IN THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS ARRESTED BY THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY, DAS, IN NORTHERN BOGOTA DURING THE LAST FEW HOURS. ABELLO IS WANTED BY A U.S. FEDERAL COURT IN OKLAHOMA, THE UNITED STATES, FOR CONSPIRACY TO DISTRIBUTE DRUGS. ACTIVE IN THE MARIJUANA BUSINESS DURING THE LAST DECADE AND IS NOW RESPONSIBLE FOR THE TRANSPORTATION OF A SUBSTANTIAL PART OF THE COCAINE WHICH THE MEDELLIN CARTEL SENDS TO THE UNITED STATES.

AVELLO, 34, NATIVE OF SANTA MARTA, HAD BEEN ARRESTED IN EARLY 1988 FOR ILLEGAL POSSESSION OF WEAPONS ON THE ATLANTIC COAST. SHORTLY AFTER LUIS CARLOS GALAN'S ASSASSINATION, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT ASKED FOR HIS EXTRADITION, BEARING IN MIND THAT THE FEDERAL COURT IN OKLAHOMA IS TRYING HIM FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING. HIS EXTRADITION IS TAKEN FOR GRANTYED, AND IT IS BELIEVED THAT IT WILL TAKE PLACE ONCE ALL LEGAL REQUIREMENTS ARE MET, WHICH WILL NOT BE BEFORE 1 WEEK.

DAS SOURCES SAID THAT MONO AVELLO OFFERED 100 MILLION PESOS TO THE SIX DETECTIVES WHO ARRESTED HIM LAST NIGHT AT AN EXCLUSIVE RESTAURANT IN BOGOTA'S NORTHERN SECTION. THE AUTHORITIES HAD BEEN TRAILING HIM IN BOGOTA FOR SEVERAL DAYS. THE ARMY HAS OCCUPIED SEVERAL OF HIS PROPERTIES ON THE ATLANTIC COAST AND HAS SEIZED VEHICLES AND YACHTS BELONGING TO HIM.

IN ANOTHER DEVELOPMENT, IT HAS BEEN LEARNED THAT PERUVIAN JUSTICE YESTERDAY INSISTED AGAIN ON THE EXTRADITION OF EVARISTO PORRAS ARDILA, WHO ESCAPED FROM A JAIL IN PERU WHILE SERVING A SENTENCE FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0565 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 10 OCT 89 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] SEVERAL SALVADORAN SECTORS HAVE CONDEMNED THE MURDER OF THE WIFE OF THE DEPUTY EDITOR OF EL DIARIO DE HOY. SHE WAS RIDDLED WITH BULLETS NEAR THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY THIS MORNING. SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS DESCRIBED THE ACTION AS TERRORIST. HE SAID THIS IS A FLAGRANT VIOLATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS, WHICH WILL SURELY ALSO BE CONDEMNED BY THE UN HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, PASTOR RIBREJO, WHO IS IN THE COUNTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] THE LAST STRAW IS THAT TERRORISTS, WITHOUT ANY RISK TO THEMSELVES, KILL DEFENSELESS WOMEN. THIS PARTICULAR LADY WAS ACCOMPANIED BY HER CHILDREN, ONE OF WHOM WAS WOUNDED. WE THINK THIS IS THE LIMIT. WE ARE NOT SURE WHO DID IT, BUT, CONSIDERING THE NATURE OF THE ACTION, IT APPEARS TO BE A TERRORIST CRIME. WE ALREADY KNOW WHO PERPETRATES SUCH ACTIONS. WE THINK THIS IS PART OF WHAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS BEEN DOING. THEY HAVE BEEN SILENCING VOICES THAT UPHOLD PHILOSOPHIES THAT RUN CONTRARY TO THEIR'S. [END RECORDING]

REFERRING TO THE PRESENCE OF PASTOR RIBREJO IN THE COUNTRY, CRISTIANI SAID THE UN OFFICIAL WILL BE ABLE TO CONFIRM THAT THE POLICY OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES DOES NOT FIT THE VIOLATION OF THE HUMAN RIGHTS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] I WILL NOT REFER TO MONSIGNOR ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS ALONE, BUT TO ALL OF THE ORGANIZATIONS LINKED TO THE FMLN THAT HAVE BEEN TRYING TO DISCREDIT THE GOVERNMENT. I THINK DR RIBREJO WILL BE ABLE TO CONFIRM THAT NEITHER THE GOVERNMENT NOR THE ARMED FORCES ARE IN THE HABIT OF VIOLATING HUMAN RIGHTS. I THINK IF ONE TRIES TO BE OBJECTIVE AND REALISTIC, HE WILL REALIZE THAT THE FMLN HAS BEEN TRYING TO MAKE THE HOMELAND FALL INTO A STATE OF TOTAL ANARCHY. I THINK THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ACTED VERY PROFESSIONALLY. THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY HAS BEEN TO TRY TO SEEK SOLUTIONS THROUGH REASON RATHER THAN VIOLENCE. THESE EVENTS MUST BE SEEN IN THE LIGHT OF WHAT THE FMLN SAID IT WOULD DO. IT SAID IT WOULD UNLEASH EVEN GREATER VIOLENCE. [END RECORDING]

AS FOR THE UPCOMING DIALOGUE MEETING TO BE HELD IN SAN JOSE ON 16 AND 17 OCTOBER, CRISTIANI SAID A COMMISSION IS READY TO RESUME TALKS WITH THE FMLN, TO WHICH A CEASE-FIRE WILL BE PROPOSED, AMONG OTHER THINGS. CRISTIANI SAID THAT THE COSTA RICAN GOVERNMENT HAS REPORTED WORKING ON THE LOGISTICS OF THE MEETING SO THE TALKS CAN BE HELD IN PEACE.

DEV-MUC3-0566 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BUENOS AIRES, 8 OCT 89 (CLARIN) -- [TEXT] THROUGH DECREE NO. 1003 THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH HAS PARDONED SEVERAL TERRORISTS FROM DIFFERENT ARMED ORGANIZATIONS AND SOME MEMBERS OF URUGUAY'S MILITARY AND POLICE WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE REPRESSION OF TERRORISM IN ARGENTINA.

THE MOST WELL-KNOWN INDIVIDUALS ARE FERNANDO VACA NARVAJA, ROBERTO PERDIA, OSCAR BIDEGAIN, MIGUEL BONASSO, NORMAN BRISKI, GONZALO AND RENE CHAVEZ, RODOLFO GALIMBERTI, JAIME DRI, AND RAUL AND OSVALDO LOVEY, ALL OF WHOM ARE LINKED TO THE MONTONEROS SUBVERSIVE ORGANIZATION.

THE LIST ALSO INCLUDES MARIA ANTONIA BERGER, RUBEN JESUS EMPERADOR, AND FERMIN ANGEL NUNEZ.

DECREE NO. 1003 -- FOR REASONS IDENTICAL TO THOSE OF DECREE NO. 1002, WHICH PARDONS MILITARY OFFICERS WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE ANTISUBVERSIVE REPRESSION -- STATES THAT ABOVE ANY OTHER CONSIDERATION "OF REASONS OF DOCTRINARY OR IDEOLOGICAL POSITIONS" IT IS NECESSARY TO ADOPT MEASURES THAT WILL CREATE "THE APPROPRIATE CONDITIONS TO ARRIVE AT A DEFINITE RECONCILIATION OF ALL THE ARGENTINE PEOPLE THANKS TO THE SPIRITUAL GREATNESS OF THE MEN AND WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY."

THE DECREE STATES THAT THIS MEASURE IS "ONLY A POLITICAL MECHANISM FORSEEN BY THE CONSTITUTION TO CREATE CONDITIONS FOR NATIONAL PACIFICATION," ALTHOUGH IT DOES NOT MEAN THAT THIS OBJECTIVE HAS BEEN REACHED.

THE DECREE ALSO INCLUDES THE NAMES OF THE URUGUAYAN OFFICERS WHO STOOD TRIAL FOR PARTICIPATING IN ARGENTINA'S ANTISUBVERSIVE REPRESSION INTHE CASE ENTITLED "RODRIGUEZ LARRETA PIERA, ENRIQUE, ON CHARGES": JOSE GAVAZZO, JORGE SILVEIRA, MANUEL CORDERO, AND HUGO CAMPOS HERMIDA.

THE NAMES OF THOSE PARDONED ARE:

NATIONAL FEDERAL CRIMINAL COURT NO. 3 OF THE FEDERAL CAPITAL.

CASE NO. 42335 BIS "RODRIGUEZ LARRETA PIERA, ENRIQUE, ON CHARGES": GAVAZZO, JOSE NINO; SILVEIRA, JORGE; CORDERO, MANUEL; CAMPOS HERMIDA, HUGO.

NATIONAL CRIMINAL COURT NO. 5 OF THE FEDERAL CAPITAL.

CASE NO. 1199 ENTITLED "FIRELLI, ENRIQUE HORACIO; ON VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 189 BIS OF THE PENAL CODE, LAW NO. 20840, ON MURDER AND UNLAWFUL ASSOCIATION FOR CRIMINAL PURPOSES" ATTACHED TO CASE NO. 1430 ON "ALEMANN, JUAN MINO; VENTURA Y CONSIGLERI, SILVIO, VICTIMS OF MURDER AND TORTURE": VACA NARVAJA, FERNANDO HUGO; PERDIA, ROBERTO CIRILO; BIDEGAIN, OSCAR RAUL. CASE NO. 2230/86 ENTITLED "FIRMENICH, MARIO EDUARDO AND OTHERS, ON MURDER, VIOLATION OF LAW NO. 20,840": VACA NARVAJA, FERNANDO HUGO.

NATIONAL FEDERAL COURT NO. 6 OF THE FEDERAL CAPITAL.

CASE NO. 5148 ENTITLED "BAVIO, GERARDO AND OTHERS, ON VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 210 OF THE PENAL CODE": BAVIO, GERARDO; BERMAN, SILVIA; BERROZPE, EDUARDO; BONASSO, MIGUEL; BRISKY, NAUM; CHAVEZ, GONZALO LEONIDAS; CHAVEZ RENE; GELMAN, JUAN; MASSAFERRO, LIDIA; ORGAMBIDE, PEDRO; RAPPARI DE LENCINAS, NILDA; SANZ DE LLORENTE, SUSANA; DIAZ, OLIMPIA; FERNANDEZ LONG, PABLO; GALIMBERTI, RODOLFO; PEDREIRA, MANUEL; RAMOS, PABLO; RODRIGUEZ ANIDO, JULIO; DRI, JAIME; VACA NARVAJA, DANIEL.

CASE NO. 4679 ENTITLED "FIRMENICH, MARIO EDUARDO AND OTHERS, ON VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 210 OF THE PENAL CODE": VACA NARVAJA, FERNANDO; PERDIA, ROBERTO CIRILO; BIDEGAIN, OSCAR RAUL.

CASE NO. 5048 ENTITLED "LEVEY, OSVALDO RAUL AND LEWINGER, JORGE OMAR, ON VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 210 OF THE PENAL CODE": LOVEY, OSVALDO RAUL; LEWINGER, JORGE OMAR.

CASE NO. 5448/87 ENTITLED "YACUZZI, RAFAEL ON VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 210 OF THE PENAL CODE [NO CLOSING QUOTATION MARKS AS PUBLISHED]: YACUZZI, RAFAEL.

SAN ISIDRO CRIMINAL COURT.

CASE NO. 17680/78 ENTITLED "KLEIN, GUILLERMO WALTER ON TORTURE, HARM, ATTACK AND DISOBEDIENCE OF AUTHORITIES, PUBLIC INTIMIDATION, AND MURDER": VACA NARVAJA, FERNANDO HUGO; BIDEGAIN, PERDIA, ROBERTO CIRILO.

CASE NO. 959/85 ENTITLED: "METZ, HEINRICH FRANZ, ON KIDNAPPING AND EXTORTION": MAGARIO, RAUL JOSE MELCHOR; DALEO, GRACIELA BEATRIZ; CLASIREGUI, MARCELINO EDUARDO; QUINTEROS, JOSE DANIEL; LARRALDE, AMALIA MARIA; CUBAS, LISANDRO RAUL; MENDEZ, JORGE; WEISSEN, ANA DORA; ALBERTI DE MURPHY, GRACIELA ESTELA; MURPHY, SANTIAGO ULISES; LUJAN, JESUS MARIA; SORIA, RICARDO; AHUMADA, ROBERTO JOSE; PORTOMENE, ALICIA; ESPINOSA, EDUARDO; GOMEZ, NORBERTO; MORCILLO, MARIA ALICIA; CREUS, CARLOS; SCHMELIN, GERMAN; ISLAS, JOSE LUIS; KHUN, GUILLERMO ADRIAN; MARCUS, ADRIANA RUTH; GRIGENA, GUSTAVO ALBERTO; BERGER, MARIA ANTONIA; PASTORIZA, LILIA VICTORIA; LARRALDE, LUZ MARIA.

FEDERAL COURT NO. 1 OF MORON.

CASE NO. 8814 ENTITLED "RODRIGUEZ, LAZARO MARTIN, ON VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 310 BIS OF THE PENAL CODE": RODRIGUEZ, LAZARO MARTIN.

FEDERAL COURT NO. 1 OF SAN MARTIN.

CASE NO. 41811: ON THE INVESTIGATION OF THE KIDNAPPING AND EXTORTION OF JUAN AND JORGE BORN [NO QUOTATION MARKS AS PUBLISHED] : MAGARIO, RAUL JOSE MELCHOR.

CASE NO. 191 ENTITLED "LOPEZ, JUAN DOMINGO AND OTHERS ON ILLEGAL ARREST AND MURDERS": LOPEZ, JUAN DOMINGO; MAO, LUIS OSCAR; IBANEZ, SERGIO MARIA.

FEDERAL COURT NO. 1 OF TUCUMAN.

CASE NO. 478/74 ENTITLED "FIGUEROA, ROLANDO C. AND OTHERS, ON DOUBLE MURDER AND TORTURE": CARRIZO, FRANCISCO ANTONIO; PAZ, JOSE MARTINI; EMPERADOR, RUBEN JESUS; NUNEZ, FERMIN ANGEL.

DEV-MUC3-0568 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BUENOS AIRES, 10 OCT 89 (TELAM) -- [TEXT] ARGENTINE FOREIGN MINISTER DOMINGO CAVALLO AND HIS PERUVIAN COUNTERPART GUILLERMO LARCO COX SIGNED THREE INTEGRATION AGREEMENTS TODAY IN TRUJILLO, LIBERTAD DEPARTMENT. CAVALLO SAID THAT THE AGREEMENTS "CLEARLY SHOW THE EFFORTS BEING MADE TOWARD COMMON GOAL" WHICH MEANS "MOVING AHEAD TO BUILD A GREAT LATIN AMERICAN NATION."

THE AGREEMENTS, WHICH WERE PREPARED BY THE FOREIGN MINISTRIES OF THE TWO COUNTRIES, WERE SIGNED TODAY BY THE TWO FOREIGN MINISTERS IN THE OLD HOUSE THAT BELONGED TO SIMON BOLIVIAR DURING THE TIME HE LIVED IN TRUJILLO. THE CEREMONY WAS HELD UNDER STRICT SECURITY MEASURES, SEEKING TO PREVENT SUBVERSIVE ACTIONS. SECURITY MEASURES WERE REINFORCED IN THE LAST FEW HOURS FOLLOWING AN ATTACK EARLY THIS MORNING 12 BLOCS FROM THE HOTEL WHERE THE DELEGATIONS ARE STAYING.

THE FIRST AGREEMENT CREATES THE POLITICAL COORDINATION AND INTEGRATION COMMITTEE. CAVALLO SAID THAT THIS IS AIMED AT "TAKING MORE ORDERLY STEPS IN THE EFFORTS WHICH HAVE BEEN MADE THROUGHOUT OUR HISTORY BECAUSE THE ARGENTINE AND PERUVIAN DESIRE FOR INTEGRATION HAS ROOTS AS OLD AS THE STRUGGLE FOR INDEPENDENCE."

THE SECOND AGREEMENT REFERS TO THE COORDINATION OF EFFORTS FOR THE PREVENTION AND REPRESSION OF DRUG TRAFFICKING. CAVALLO SAID: "THIS PROBLEM IS REACHING TERRIFYING DIMENSIONS BECAUSE ITS ECONOMIC POWER IS MIXED WITH TERRORIST AND SUBVERSIVE GROUPS. AS SUCH IT IS BECOMING A GROWING THREAT TO THE LATIN AMERICAN DEMOCRACIES."

IN A BRIEF SPEECH CAVALLO ALSO REFERRED TO THE THIRD AGREEMENT TO PREVENT DOUBLE TAXATION AMONG AIR AND MARITIME ENTERPRISES. HE SAID: "INTEGRATION REQUIRES GOOD TRANSPORTATION METHODS WITH WHICH TO BRING PEOPLE CLOSER TOGETHER" THUS MAKING "PROGRESS THROUGH CONCRETE MECHANISMS IN THE INTEGRATION PROCESS IN WHICH OUR COUNTRIES ARE INVOLVED."

LARCO COX SAID THAT THROUGH THESE AGREEMENTS "ARGENTINE PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM HAS CONFIRMED, THROUGH HIS REPRESENTATIVE, HIS POLITICAL WILL TO AGREE" TO FIND SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEMS AFFECTING THE REGION BY SEEKING "NEW ROADS FOR UNDERSTANDING AND TO STRENGTHEN OUR ALREADY RICH BILATERAL RELATIONS."

A FEW HOURS BEFORE THIS CEREMONY, WHICH WAS ALSO ATTENDED BY UNDER SECRETARY JOSE LUIS FERNANDEZ VALONI AND AMBASSADOR JULIAN LICASTRO, TRUJILLO WAS SHAKEN AT 0400 BY FOUR POWERFUL DYNAMITE EXPLOTIONS (A FIFTH BOMB DID NOT EXPLODE) WHICH DESTROYED ABOUT HALF DOZEN OFFICES OF THE NATIONAL HOUSING ENTERPRISE.

THIS ENTERPRISE, WHICH OPERATES WITH STATE AND PRIVATE CAPITAL, IS LOCATED IN THE MONSERRATE DISTRICT WHERE THERE IS A HOUSING DEVELOPMENT FOR POOR PEOPLE. IT IS LOCATED 1 KM FROM THE PARADE GROUND, DOWNTOWN TRUJILLO, ACROSS FROM WHICH IS LOCATED THE TURISTA HOTEL. THIS IS THE HOTEL WHERE THE FOREIGN MINISTERS OF ARGENTINA, PERU, COLOMBIA, URUGUAY, BRAZIL, MEXICO AND VENEZUELA ARE STAYING.

THE EXPLOSIONS DID NOT CAUSE ANY CASUALTIES AND THE POLICE HOLD THE TUPAC AMARY REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ATTACK. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0569 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [BARCO] SECOND, MY ADMINISTRATION HAS ADOPTED MEASURES TO CONFRONT ORGANIZED TERRORISM WHICH IS CONDUCTED BY DRUG CARTELS OR GANGS OF CRIMINALS, TRAINED BY FOREIGN MERCENARIES AND FINANCED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THEY HAVE MURDERED JUDGES, A MINISTER OF JUSTICE, A ... [TELEVISION BROADCAST INTERRUPTED FOR 4 MINUTES DUE TO TRANSMISSION PROBLEMS] ... IN A LETTER DATED OCTOBER 9 TO UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR AND THE RESPECTIVE AMBASSADORS.

THIS SPECIAL ASSEMBLY DOES NOT MEAN THAT THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL SHOULD EXCLUDE WORLD SECURITY ISSUES. IT IS IMPORTANT THAT [TELEVISION BROADCASTING INTERRUPTED FOR HALF A MINUTE DUE TO TRANSMISSION PROBLESM]... WORLD DEVELOPMENT AND POLITICAL POWER. TO THIS WE MUST ALSO ADD THE UNIFICATION OF THE EUROPE IN 1992. BESIDES, THE SOVIET POLICIES OF PERESTROYKA AND GLASNOST HAVE SUBSTANTIALLY MODIFIED NOT ONLY THE COMMUNIST IDEAS BUT ALSO THE FUTURE WORLD POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC SCENE.

THESE TRANSFORMATIONS ARE ATTRACTIVE FOR THE INDUSTRIALIZED EUROPEAN COUNTRIES. THEY PROMOTE THE DEVELOPMENT OF EASTERN EUROPE AND PROBABLY REDUCE EUROPEAN INTEREST IN LATIN AMERICA. BESIDES, THE UNITED STATES AND CANADA ARE PERMANENTLY MAKING PROGRESS TOWARD THEIR SOCIOECONOMIC INTEGRATION.

WE STAND BEFORE A DIFFERENT WORLD WHICH IS OFFERING OPPORTUNITIES WHICH MUST BE TAKEN INTO ACCOUNT, BUT WHICH ALSO CREATES DIFFICULTIES FOR WHICH WE MUST BE PREPARED. LATIN AMERICA SHOULD RECONSIDER ITS SITUATION AND POLICIES IN FACE OF THE RAPID WORLD CHANGES. WE MUST ANALYZE THE WAY IN WHICH WE WILL INTEGRATE AND HARMONIZE OUR ECONOMIES IN THIS NEW INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL SCENE.

IN FACE OF THESE EVENTS, WE MUST REDEFINE OUR INTEGRATION FORMULAS AND OUR DEVELOPMENT MODELS. I SUGGEST THAT A WORK GROUP BE FORMED TO STUDY THIS SUBJECT AND TO ADOPT SPECIFIC MEASURES LEADING TO THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL PROGRESS OF LATIN AMERICA IN THIS NEW WORLD THAT IS BEING BORN.

MY DEAR PRESIDENTS AND FRIENDS, THIS NEW MEETING OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT MUST MAKE US STRENGTHEN OUR SOLIDARITY IN FACE OF THE THREATS AGAINST DEMOCRACY AND OUR SOCIAL PROGRESS. WE MUST STRENGTHEN THE REGIONAL COOPERATION MECHANISM AND OUR NEGOTIATED CAPACITY THROUGH THE IMPLEMENTATION OF AN EFFICIENT STRATEGY OF CONSENSUS TO MAKE OUR PROPOSALS MORE SOLID.

WE MEMBER COUNTRIES OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT ARE UNITED BY UNDENIABLE HISTORIC TIES OF FRIENDSHIP. WE ARE ALSO UNITED BY STRATEGIC, POLITICAL, AND ECONOMIC INTERESTS WHICH MUST BE COORDINATED TO BE ABLE TO SUCCESSFULLY FACE THE CHALLENGES OF TOMORROW.

AS I RECENTLY TOLD MY VENEZUELAN COUNTERPART, UNITY CAN BE SOLIDLY BUILT ON FEASIBLE INITIATIVES RATHER THAN ON WORDS. INTEGRATION THRIVES ON ACHIEVEMENT THAT IN PRACTICE BRING PEOPLES TOGETHER AND ALLOW THEM TO ENJOY THE RESULTS OF PROGRESS OBTAINED THROUGH COMMON EFFORT. YEARS OF STRUGGLE FOR REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT HAVE SHOWN US THAT DEVELOPMENT MUST BE BASED ON ACTIONS THAT WILL GENERATE CONFIDENCE AND WELL-BEING, CONTRIBUTE TO NATURALLY COMPLEMENTARY ACTIONS, AND SOLVE SMALL AND LARGE PROBLEMS.

COLOMBIA IS DETERMINED TO CONTINUE STRENGTHENING THE MECHANISM OF CONSENSUS BY ENDORSING THE SUGGESTIONS I HAVE MADE AND THOSE THAT WILL SPRING FROM THIS SUMMIT MEETING. THANK YOU. [APPLAUSE]

DEV-MUC3-0570 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 OCT 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] APPROXIMATELY 1,600 SALVADORANS HAVE VOICED THEIR DETERMINATION TO RETURN TO EL SALVADOR ON 17 OCTOBER, WITHOUT THE GOVERNMENT'S APPROVAL, AFTER HAVING REMAINED AS REFUGEES IN A HONDURAN CAMP SINCE THE EARLY 80'S.

"WE INSIST ON RETURNING TO EL SALVADOR ON 17 OCTOBER. HERE, WE ARE BEING IMPRISONED FOR NO REASON. WE ARE LEAVING BECAUSE OTHERWISE, WE WILL BE KILLED. WE ARE SALVADORANS, AND THAT IS WHY WE WANT TO RETURN TO OUR COUNTRY," SAID ONE OF THE REFUGEES IN A TELEVISION INTERVIEW.

INTERIOR MINISTER FRANCISCO MERINO WARNED THAT HIS GOVERNMENT WILL NOT ALLOW THE ENTRY OF REFUGEES WHO DO NOT HAVE IDENTIFICATION DOCUMENTS ISSUED BY THE UN HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR REFUGEES [UNHCR].

"IF THEY ARRIVE ABRUPTLY AT THE SALVADORAN BORDER, WITHOUT THE DOCUMENTS THAT CERTIFY THEY ARE SALVADORANS, THEY CANNONT ENTER THE COUNTRY," MERINO POINTED OUT.

ACCORDING TO MERINO, WHO IS ALSO THE SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT, THE REFUGEES' DETERMINATION TO RETURN WITHOUT THE GOVERNMENT'S APPROVAL IS "EVIDENCE" OF THEIR RELATIONS WITH THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS.

HOWEVER, THE REFUGEES -- INCLUDING WOMEN, THE ELDERLY, AND CHILDREN -- DENIED ANY LINKS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS.

MERINO INTERPRETED THE REFUGEES' WISHES TO REPATRIATE IN A MASSIVE AND IMMEDIATE MANNER AS "PLANS TO PROVOKE PROBLEMS THAT WILL AFFECT THE IMAGE OF THE GOVERNMENT WITH REGARD TO THE ISSUE OF RESPECTING HUMAN RIGHTS."

ON 10 OCTOBER, AN OFFICIAL COMMISSION, HEADED BY DEPUTY INTERIOR MINISTER COLONEL CARLOS FIGUEROA VISITED THE HONDURAN CAMP AT MESA GRANDE TO TRY TO REACH AN AGREEMENT WITH THE REFUGEES SO THEY COULD PREPARE FOR THEIR REPATRIATION IN 1990 AND AGREE ON THE PLACES WHERE THEY WOULD BE RELOCATED.

THE NATIONAL COMMISSION WAS UNABLE TO REACH ANY AGREEMENT FOR POSTPONING THE REPATRIATION OF THE SALVADORANS TO 1990.

THE MILITARY OFFICER DISCLOSED THAT THERE ARE LOGISTICAL PROBLEMS IN PREPARING FOR THE 17 OCTOBER REPATRIATION.

"THE UNHCR IS NOT PREPARED TO GIVE LOGISTICAL SUPPORT TO THE SALVADORANS WHO WANT TO RETURN NEXT WEEK AND IT NEEDS FOR BOTH PARTIES THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REFUGEES) TO REACH AN AGREEMENT IN ORDER TO GO AHEAD WITH THE REPATRIATION," COL FIGUEROA ADDED.

ONE OF THE REFUGEES, WHO PREFERRED NOT TO BE IDENTIFIED, CHARGED THAT UNHCR "HAS BEEN UNABLE TO GIVE US TRANSPORTATION AND THE HONDURAN ARMY IS NOT ALLOWING FOOD AND MEDICINE TO REACH US. IN ADDITION, WE ARE THE TARGET OF HONDURAN MILITARY ATTACKS."

IN MESA GRANDE, THERE ARE 3,718 SALVADORANS, OF WHICH 900 ARE CHILDREN. THESE REFUGEES LEFT EL SALVADOR EARLY IN 1980 WHEN THE WAR WHICH HAS LEFT OVER 70,000 DEAD BROKE OUT.

THERE ARE ALSO AN ADDITIONAL 13,000 SALVADORANS IN MESA GRANDE WHO WANT TO BE REPATRIATED, SAYS THE NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD ON REFUGEES, THAT CLAIMS TO REPRESENT THEM.

THE REFUGEES ARE DEMANDING THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT COMPLY WITH THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE AGREEMENTS THAT WERE SIGNED 2 YEARS AGO IN GUATEMALA, WHICH -- ACCORDING TO THEM -- WOULD ALLOW THEM TO RETURN TO THE COUNTRY WITH GUARANTEES.

DEV-MUC3-0571 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 12 OCT 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH ARGENTINE PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [EXCERPTS] [PASSAGE OMITTED] [REPORTER] WHAT IS THE POSITION OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT REGARDING THE MALVINAS ISLANDS? WILL THE GROUP OF EIGHT SUPPORT ARGENTINA IN THE DEFENSE OF ITS SOVEREIGNTY?

[MENEM] THE GROUP OF EIGHT HAS SUPPORTED ARGENTINA FOR A LONG TIME, SO HAS OAS AND THE UN. THEIR SUPPORT IS UNQUESTIONABLE.

[QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[MENEM] CUBA MAY JOIN THE OAS. WE HAVE NO OBJECTIONS TO IT. AS FOR PANAMA, IT CONTINUES TO BELONG TO THE OAS BUT NOT TO THE GROUP OF EIGHT. PANAMA HAS BEEN SUSPENDED TEMPORARILY FROM THIS GROUP UNTIL DEMOCRACY RETURNS TO THAT COUNTRY. THIS WILL BE STATED IN A DOCUMENT WE ARE PREPARING DURING THIS MEETING. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

[REPORTER] IS THE PARDON FOR MILITARY OFFICERS AND TERRORISTS IN ARGENTINA DAMAGING THE MORAL HEALTH OF YOUR COUNTRY OR ARGENTINA DEMOCRACY?

[MENEM] NO, BECAUSE THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME A PARDON HAS BEEN GRANTED IN THE WORLD. THERE HAVE BEEN PARDONS EVERYWHERE. NOT LONG AGO A PARDON WAS GRANTED IN URUGUAY AND IT HAS BEEN RATIFIED BY THE URUGUAYAN PEOPLE. A PARDON WAS GRANTED IN SPAIN AFTER THE [WORD INDISTINCT]. THERE WERE PARDONS GRANTED AFTER THE SECOND WORLD WAR. PARDONS AND FORGETTING HAVE ALLOWED THE INTEGRATION OF THE EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY. IT ALSO ALLOWED PRESIDENT BUSH TO PAY HOMMAGE TO EMPEROR HIROITO, ONE OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE SECOND WORLD WAR, DURING HIS FUNERAL. THEREFORE WE CAN COMPLETELY OVERCOME THIS MATTER.

[REPORTER] [PASSAGE OMITTED] REPORTED THAT ARGENTINA WOULD ASK TO PARTICIPATE IN THE SUMMIT MEETING OF THE PRESIDENTS OF COLOMBIA, PERU, AND BOLIVIA AND THE UNITED STATES. IS THIS TRUE, AND WHAT WOULD BE THE ARGENTINE ROLE IN THIS SUMMIT?

[MENEM] NO, THAT IS NOT CORRECT. WE SUPPORT THIS SUMMIT MEETING, AND CONTINUE MAINTAINING OUR SAME ATTITUDE TOWARD THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. WE CURRENTLY DO NOT DIFFERENTIATE BETWEEN COCA PRODUCER AND COCA CONSUMER COUNTRIES. THEY ARE BOTH PART OF A SAME PROCESS, SO WE MUST CARRY OUT AN ALL OUT WAR AGAINST THE THREE [AS HEARD] PHASES OF DRUG PRODUCTION AND MERCHANDISING.

[REPORTER] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] A STRONGER ACTION IS REQUIRED BY [WORD INDISTINCT] ESPECIALLY THE UNITED STATES TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING.

[MENEM] I THINK THAT WE NEED THE WILL OF EVERY ONE. WE WOULD NOT GAIN ANYTHING BY RESTRICTING THE PRODUCTION OF COCA IN PERU, COLOMBIA, AND BOLIVIA IF THE UNITED STATES DOES NOT HELP TO SUBSTITUTE THIS CROP. WE CANNOT DIVIDE THIS ACTION. THE FIGHT MUST BE AN ALL OUT WAR BY ALL THE COUNTRIES OF THE WORLD, BECAUSE DRUGS ARE CURRENTLY PRESENT IN ALL COUNTRIES. THERE IS NOT A SINGLE COUNTRY THAT CAN CLAIM THAT THERE IS NO DRUG ADDICITON OR TRAFFICKING IN ITS TERRITORY. NOT LONG AGO, I READ THAT 14 DRUG TRAFFICKERS WERE HANGED IN SAUDI ARABIA, WHERE THEY ARE VERY CONSERVATIVE AND WHERE THERE IS STRICT CONTROL OVER ANY KIND OF VICE.

[REPORTER] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] WHAT POSITION HAS ARGENTINA MAINTAINED THROUGHOUT THIS MEETING REGARDING THE FOREIGN DEBT ISSUE? DO YOU THINK ALL THE GROUP OF EIGHT MEMBERS WILL ARRIVE TO A JOINT POSITION REGARDING THIS ISSUE?

[MENEM] WE ARE CURRENTLY RENEGOTIATING OUR DEBTS INDIVIDUALLY BECAUSE EACH COUNTRY IS DIFFERENT. THE ECONOMIC POLICIES HAVE SO FAR NOT BEEN INTEGRATED BUT THEY MUST BE INTEGRATED. AS LONG AS WE DO NOT ATTAIN INTEGRATION, THE FOREIGN DEBT NEGOTIATIONS WILL BE CARRIED OUT INDIVIDUALLY. IF WE MAKE PROGRESS TOWARDS INTEGRATION, THINGS MAY CHANGE FOR THE BENEFIT OF ALL. FOR THE TIME BEING THE NEGOTIATIONS WILL BE CARRIED OUT SEPARATELY.

[REPORTER] PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA YESTERDAY CALLED FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT OF CONCRETE INTEGRATION GOALS FOR 1992. HAS THIS BEEN DISCUSSED BY THE PRESIDENTS? WILL CONCRETE GOALS BE FIXED?

[MENEM] WE ARE DISCUSSING THIS. WE HAVE ALREADY SET CONCRETE GOALS, BASED ON EXPERIENCES. FOR EXAMPLE WE HAVE AN ECONOMIC INTEGRATION WITH BRAZIL, WHICH URUGUAY RECENTLY JOINED. THIS MUST SERVE AS AN EXAMPLE FOR THE REST OF THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES. OF COURSE WE MUST NOT FORGET SOME OF THE POSITIVE RESULTS, LIKE IN THE CASE OF THE ANDEAN PACT WHICH IS REVIVING AND REORGANIZING ITSELF, AND OTHER AGREEMENTS NOT ONLY IN LATIN AMERICA BUT IN THE WHOLE AMERICAN CONTINENT. WE ARE HEADING TOWARD A CONTINENTAL UNITY LIKE THAT OF CANADA AND THE UNITED STATES. AFTER LATIN AMERICA ACHIEVES INTEGRATION WE WANT INTEGRATION WITH CENTRAL AND NORTHERN AMERICA. [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[MENEM] PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO WAS SURPRISED, BECAUSE HE THOUGHT THAT THE CREW OF THE THREE PLANES WE DONATED TO COLOMBIA HAD ALREADY RETURNED TO ARGENTINA. HOWEVER, THEY ARE STILL THERE WAITING FOR THE AIRPLANES TO BE PLACED AT THE SERVICE OF THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0572 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 12 OCT 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [PRESS CONFERENCE WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [REPORTER] THERE ARE SERIOUS DISCREPANCIES AMONG THE PREESIDENTS ATTENDING TO THIS MEETING REGARDING THE FOREIGN DEBT ISSUE. IS IT BECAUSE OF THE DIFFERENT SITUATIONS PREVAILING IN EACH COUNTRY?

[GARCIA] WE HAVE A COMMON STANCE. NO COUNTRY CAN PAY WHAT IT IS BEING ASKED TO PAY. WE ALL KNOW THIS. PEOPLE KNOW IT. THE LABOR UNIONS KNOW IT. THEREFORE, THAT IS OUR STANCE.

A FEW YEARS AGO SOME COUNTRIES MADE AN EFFORT TO PAY. NOWADAY, EVERYBODY KNOWS THEY CANNOT PAY AND THEY ARE STRUGGLING TO CHANGE THE PAYMENT CONDITIONS. THIS IS THE BASIC ISSUE THAT WE ALL SHARE.

THE FACT THAT SOME COUNTRIES RESORT TO THE BRADY PLAN, THAT OTHERS SEEK OTHER ALTERNATIVES, OR THAT OTHERS CHOOSE NOT TO PAY A DEBT THAT THEY CONSIDER TO BE UNFAIR -- AT LEAT UNTIL CONDITIONS CHANGE OR PAYMENTS ARE REDUCED -- ARE SIMPLY DIFFERENT SHADES OF A COMMON STANCE. THE IMPORTANT POINT IS THAT WE ARE GRADUALLY VERIFYING THAT NO COUNTRY IS ABLE TO PAY THE DEBT IN CONTRACTED, A DEBT THAT HAS GROWN ONLY BECAUSE OF INTERESTS.

I WILL REITERATE SOME DRAMATIC BUT REALISTIC FIGURES: 10 YEARS AGO LATIN AMERICA OWED $190 BILLION. IT PAID $289 BILLION TO DECEMBER 1988 -- THAT IS 10 YEARS -- AND IT STILL OWES $430 BILLION. IN THE PAST 10 YEARS LATIN AMERICA HAS REDUCED ITS PER CAPITA CONSUMPTION DRAMATICALLY BY 2 TO 3 PERCENT A YEAR. IN THE PAST 10 YEARS LATIN AMERICA REDUCED ITS IMPORTS, SEEKING TO SPEND LESS DOLLARS. IT INCREASED ITS EXPORTS AND DEVALUED ITS CURRENCIES TO OBTAIN DOLLARS WITH WHICH TO PAY THE DEBT.

IN THE PAST 10 YEARS LATIN AMERICA GREW ONLY 1 PERCENT PER YEAR, AND IT HAS USED THAT 1 PERCENT, PLUS AN ADDITIONAL 4-PERCENT OF ITS GNP, TO PAY THE DEBT.

THEREFORE, UNDER THESE CONDITIONS, 10 YEARS LATER WE FIND THAT WE OWE MORE, PRODUCE LESS, AND IT IS IMPOSSIBLE TO PAY OUR DEBT. WE ALL KNOW THIS. IT HAS COST US 10 YEARS TO UNDERSTAND IT. HOWEVER IT IS AN EXPERIENCE THAT CONSTITUTES THE BASE FOR OUR COMMON STANCE.

[REPORTER] HAS PROGRESS BEEN MADE IN THIS FIELD SINCE THE PUNTA DEL ESTE SUMMIT?

[GARCIA] WOULD THERE HAVE BEEN A BRADY PLAN IF WE HAD NOT MET IN ACAPULCO OR IN PUNTA DEL ESTE? ONE OF JAMES BRADY'S ADVISERS PUBLISHED AN ARTICLE IN THE NEW YORK TIMES STATING THAT THE BRADY PLAN WAS ANNOUNCED IN SEPTEMBER 1985 TO PREVENT THE DISSEMINATION OF THE PERUVIAN ATTITUDE OF UNILATERALLY REDUCING ITS DEBT PAYMENTS.

WHO KNOWS IF THE ACAPULCO AND PUNTA DEL ESTE MEETINGS HAVE NOT LED THE CREDITORS TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THE DEBT IS NOT WORTH ITS FACE VALUE AND THAT IT MUST BE REDUCED?

THEREFORE, THERE HAS BEEN PROGRESS. WHO KNOWS IF NEXT YEAR WE WILL BE SPEAKING OF REDUCING THE DEBT BY 50 PERCENT AND NOT JUST THE 20 PERCENT THAT WE NOW SEEK?

YOU SEE, THE FACT IS THAT NOT ONLY ARE WE UNABLE TO PAY AND THAT WE ARE NEGOTIATING TO PAY LESS, BUT THE CREDITORS ALSO KNOW THAT THEY WILL NOT BE ABLE TO COLLECT THEIR MONEY IF THEY INSIST ON THEIR CLAIMS.

THEREFORE, IF THE UNITED STATES AND THE SOVIET UNION ARE HEADING TO WARD DISARMAMENT, WHY CAN'T THERE BE A FINANCIAL DISARMAMENT BETWEEN THE RICH AND POOR? I THINK THAT ECONOMIC TRENDS WILL FOLLOW THIS LINE.

[REPORTER] PRESIDENT, WHY HASN'T PANAMA BEEN DEFINITIVELY EXPELLED FROM THIS GROUP, AND WILL THE GROUP OF EIGHT EXPAND?

[GARCIA] PANAMA AS A COUNTRY, INDEPENDENT OF ITS PAST ADMINISTRATIONS, WAS A FOUNDER MEMBER OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT. NO COUNTRY CAN BE EXPELLED. THIS IS A TERM THAT WOULD OFFEND THE CITIZENRY OF A COUNTRY. WE SIMPLY RATIFIED THE SUSPENSION OF PANAMA INDEFINITELY UNTIL PANAMA IS GOVERNED BY A DEMOCRATICALLY ELECTED GOVERNMENT. THAT WAS OUR DECISION.

[REPORTER] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] THE OAS?

[GARCIA] WE ARE PREPARING A PROPOSAL IN WHICH WE STATE THAT THE OAS IS AN IMPORTANT FORUM OR MECHANISM FOR HEMISPHERIC DIALOGUE BUT WHICH MUST INCLUDE THE PRESENCE OF CUBA AND OTHER COUNTRIES WHICH ARE YET NOT MEMBERS.

[REPORTER] WILL THE GROUP OF EIGHT EXPAND?

[GARCIA] I HOPE SO. THIS IS THE LAST YEAR IN WHICH I WILL ATTEND A MEETING OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT, WHICH I HELPED TO CREATE. HOWEVER, I HOPE THIS GROUP WILL LEAD ANNUAL AND PERIODICAL MEETINGS OF ALL LATIN AMERICA PRESIDENTS. I HAVE MAINTAINED THIS HOPE SINCE 1985. I HOPE THAT LATIN AMERICA WILL ANNUALLY COORDINATE SOME KIND OF COLLEGIAL EXECUTIVE BRANCH TO MAKE IMPORTANT DECISIONS. THE GROUP OF EIGHT IS THE BEGINNING OF THIS, AND I AM SURE THAT IT WILL EXPAND IN THE FUTURE.

HOWEVER, AT A CONTINENTAL LEVEL, THE ISSUES CANNOT RUN AS FAST AS FOR A COUNTRY, A PEOPLE, OR A POLITICAL PROCESS. A CONTINENT REQUIRES MUCH LONGER TERMS AND WE MUST BE PATIENT. LET US GO TO ANOTHER SUBJECT NOW.

[REPORTER] HUMAN RIGHTS. TWO OF THE MAIN ISSUES IN LATIN AMERICAN LIFE ARE DEMOCRATIZATION AND HUMAN RIGHTS. PRESIDENT MENEM HAS RECENTLY PARDONED MILITARY OFFICERS AND TERRORISTS WHO WERE SERVING PRISON SENTENCES. THERE IS ALSO A CONFLICTIVE SITUATION IN PERU REGARDING SOME MILITARY OFFICERS WHO ARE BEING TRIED FOR MURDERS COMMITTED IN JAILS. ARE YOU WILLING TO PARDON THOSE MILITARY OFFICERS TO PACIFY THE SITUATION? THIS IS MY FIRST QUESTION.

SECOND, THE PERUVIAN IMAGE THROUGH THE INTERNATIONAL MEDIA IS VERY BAD BECAUSE OF A LACK OF INFORMATION. IN CONTRAST WITH ACAPULCO AND PUNTA DEL ESTE, WHICH ARE HOLIDAY RESORTS WITH MULTIMILLION DOLLAR INFRASTRUCTURES, THE CITY OF ICA REPRESENTS THOUSANDS OF LATIN AMERICAN CITIES. THEREFORE, WHAT IS YOUR ADMINISTRATION DOING TO THRUTHFULLY REPORT ON PERUVIAN REALITY? TION DOING TO THRUTHFULLY REPORT ON PERUVIAN REALITY? [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0574 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

QUITO, 12 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THIS YEAR, FRANCE WILL GRANT ECUADOR A 310 MILLION-FRANC LOAN AND A NON-REPAYABLE LOAN FOR 20 MILLION. FRANCE WILL ALSO PROVIDE TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE, AND WILL SUPPORT ECUADOR'S STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND ITS EFFORTS TO SOLVE ECUADOR'S FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM, PRESIDENTS FRANCOIS MITTERRAND AND RODRIGO BORJA ANNOUNCED TODAY IN QUITO.

THUS, THE FRENCH AID TO ECUADOR IN 1989 WILL TOTAL 400 MILLION FRANCS, SINCE FRANCE PREVIOUSLY AGREED TO GRANT LOANS FOR 180 MILLION FRANCS TO ECUADOR.

THE ANNOUNCEMENT WAS MADE ON 12 OCTOBER, SHORTLY BEFORE MITTERRAND CONCLUDED HIS OFFICIAL 2-DAY VISIT TO ECUADOR, WHERE HE HELD A PRIVATE MEETING WITH BORJA -- A FELLOW MEMBER OF SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL -- AFTER ECUADORAN FOREIGN MINISTER DIEGO CORDOVEZ AND EDWIGE AVICE, DELEGATE FROM THE FRENCH MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS, SIGNED AN LETTER OF INTENTION.

FROM THE TOTAL LOANS, 165 MILLION FRANCS WILL BE USED FOR THE FIRST PHASE OF A PROJECT TO REHABILITATE THE CENTRAL RAILROAD. THE PROJECT INCLUDES THE REHABILITATION OF 900 KM OF THE RAILWAY LINE BETWEEN THE ECUADORAN MOUNTAIN RANGE AND THE ECUADORAN COAST, BORJA SAID. HE REVEALED THAT THE LOAN IS TO BE PAID BACK IN 25 YEARS, WITH A 5-YEAR GRACE PERIOD AND LOW INTEREST RATES. HE ALSO NOTED THE SOCIAL SIGNIFICANCE OF THE PROJECT, IN A COUNTRY WITH DIFFICULT AND RUGGED TERRAIN. THE REMAINING FUNDS WILL BE USED TO SUPPLY POTABLE WATER TO THE PROVINCES OF IMBABURA IN THE MOUNTAIN RANGE, AND MANABI IN THE COASTAL REGION.

WITH REGARD TO ECUADOR'S FOREIGN DEBT, WHICH EXCEEDS $11 BILLION, MITTERRAND SAID HE IS "WILLING TO PERSONALLY ASSIST," IN THE STUDY OF BILATERAL AGREEMENTS TO REDUCE THE DEBT BURDEN, AND TO INTERCEDE BEFORE THE PARIS CLUB, TO WHICH ECUADOR OWES $400 MILLION.

MITTERRAND ASKED BORJA TO GIVE HIM TIME TO STUDY THE BILATERAL AGREEMENTS ON THE DEBT. IN THIS REGARD, MITTERRAND CLEARLY EXPRESSED THAT THE DEBT WILL NOT BE FORGIVEN. HE BELIEVES THIS IS AN OVERALL PROBLEM AND IS "MORE DANGEROUS THAN THE ATOMIC BOMB," BECAUSE THE COUNTRIES FACING THIS PROBLEM CANNOT CONTROL IT." AT THE SAME TIME, MITERRAND ASKED: "WHO CAN CONTROL THE MISERY AND THE DISTURBANCES" THIS PROBLEM WILL GENERATE?

MITTERRAND ADDED THAT EFFORTS WILL BE MADE TO IMPROVE THE WEAK BILATERAL TRADE, WHICH IN 1988 TOTALLED 321.3 MILLION FRANCS ($50.6 MILLION), WITH A DEFICIT OF 56.5 MILLION FRANCS FOR ECUADOR ($8.9 MILLION).

MITTERRAND SAID FRENCH EXPERTS WILL STUDY THE POSSIBILITY OF BOOSTING SALES OF ECUADORAN PRODUCTS TO FRANCE, ESPECIALLY SEAFOOD PRODUCTS, SUCH AS SHRIMP, AS WELL AS BANANAS, WHICH FRANCE CURRENTLY BUYS FROM AFRICAN COUNTRIES. "WHAT WE WANT TO DO IS OPEN NEW DOORS," MITTERRAND ADDED. HOWEVER, HE INSISTED ON THE NEED TO WAIT FOR THE STUDIES THE EXPERTS WILL CARRY OUT.

THE CHIEFS OF STATE ANNOUNCED THE SIGNING OF A COOPERATION AGREEMENT TO STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, STILL AT AN EARLY STAGE IN ECUADOR. THROUGH THIS AGREEMENT, SIGNED BY ECUADORAN GOVERNMENT MINISTER ANDRES VALLEJO AND FRENCH INTERIOR MINISTER PIERRE JOXE, A PLAN WILL BE DRAFTED TO STRUGGLE AGAINST THIS SCOURGE. FRANCE WILL PROVIDE ELECTRONIC EQUIPMENT AND OTHER SUPPLIES TO THE ECUADORAN POLICE.

MITTERRAND SAID HE THOROUGHLY DISCUSSED THIS PROBLEM WITH BORJA, ALTHOUGH THIS IS NOT A SPECIFIC PROBLEM OF ECUADOR, WHICH IS NOT A PRODUCING COUNTRY, BUT IS USED FOR THE TRANSSHIPMENT OF DRUGS. HE MADE AN APPEAL TO ORGANIZE A WORLD FRONT TO ELIMINATE THIS SCOURGE.

BORJA CONFIRMED MITTERRAND'S STATEMENTS AND ADDED THAT ALTHOUGH ECUADOR "IS NOT A DRUG-PRODUCING COUNTRY, WE WILL NOT REST," BECAUSE I BELIEVE OTHER COUNTRIES "BEGAN LATE" IN THEIR STRUGGLE AGAINST THIS EVIL.

THE TWO PRESIDENTS AGREED ON THE NEED TO CONCERTED EFFORTS -- AMONG COUNTRIES PRODUCING AND CONSUMING DRUGS, COUNTRIES USED FOR THE TRANSSHIPMENT OF DRUGS, AND FOR MONEY LAUNDERING -- TO FACE THIS SCOURGE. THE TWO PRESIDENTS COMMITTED THEIR EFFORTS IN THIS RESPECT.

MITTERRAND, WHO UPON CONCLUDING HIS VISIT TO ECUADOR WILL MAKE A STOPOVER IN BOGOTA, SAID THAT HIS UNSCHEDULED VISIT TO COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO IS "TO GIVE OPEN TESTIMONY ON THE SOLIDARITY THAT MUST BE GIVEN TO THE PRESIDENT OF SUCH A COURAGEOUS GOVERNMENT.

FINALLY, MITTERRAND NOTED THE BENEFITS OF HIS VISIT TO ECUADOR -- WHICH HE EXPECTS TO REPEAT -- AND THE ENTHUSIASTIC WELCOMING HE RECEIVED. BORJA THANKED THIS "GREAT EUROPEAN AND WORLD LEADER, WHO IS OFFERING HIS FRIENDSHIP TO US," FOR HIS VISIT.

DEV-MUC3-0576 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 12 OCT 89 (RADIO MAGALLANES) -- [COMMENTARY] [CHILEAN JOURNALIST ROLANDO CARRASCO] [TEXT] WE HAD BEEN LEFT COMPLETELY ALONE AND ISOLATED FROM THE WORLD, THE POPULAR GOVERNMENT HAD BEEN OVERTHROWN, THE DICTATORSHIP HAD SCATTERED CONCENTRATION CAMPS AND ANONYMOUS DEAD AROUND THE COUNTRY, CONGRESS WAS CLOSED, ALL LEFTIST COMMUNICATION MEDIA WERE ALSO CLOSED, AND THE IMAGE OF THE DICTATORSHIP MONOPOLIZED THE TELEVISION SCREENS. PINOCHET NEEDED TO BE LEFT ALONE IN ORDER TO CONSOLIDATE HIS POWER BY MURDERING HIS OPPONENTS. AT THE SAME TIME, HE SENT MISSIONS ABROAD TO SEEK RECOGNITION AND SUPPORT.

IN THE FIRST DAYS IMMEDIATELY AFTER THE COUP, RADIO MOSCOW BEGAN TO BEAM PROGRAMS TO CHILE, AND I AM NOW TALKING TO YOU FROM ITS STUDIOS. VOLODIA TEITELBOIM, CURRENT SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE CHILEAN COMMUNIST PARTY, WAS BY CHANCE IN MOSCOW IN SEPTEMBER 1973, AND IT FELL TO HIM TO INITIATE THE PROGRAMS "LISTEN, CHILE" [ESCUCHA, CHILE] AND RADIO MAGALLANES OVER THE MICROPHONES OF RADIO MOSCOW. THE AUDIENCE OF THESE PROGRAMS SUDDENLY GREW INSIDE CHILE.

AT FIRST, THE PROGRAMS DENOUNCED THE ARBITRARY ACTION OF THE MILITARY REGIME. IT WAS DIFFICULT TO SMUGGLE NEWS OUT OF CHILE SO THAT IT COULD BE BROADCAST ALL OVER CHILE BY RADIO MOSCOW, BUT NEWS OF THE WORLD'S SOLIDARITY WAS BROADCAST NIGHT AFTER NIGHT TO CHILE. THUS, THE WALL OF SILENCE THE DICTATOR INTENDED TO RAISE AROUND HIM TO HIDE HIS CRIMES WAS CRACKED.

A TRADITION OF LISTENING RADIO MOSCOW PROGRAMS TO LATIN AMERICA WAS DEVELOPED IN CHILE AS ATTESTED BY THE MAIL THAT REACHED ITS STUDIOS. THE BULK OF MAIL FROM CHILE CONFIRMS THIS. SO IT WAS EASY TO SEE THAT THE MOSCOW TRANSMISSIONS WERE HELPING THE CAUSE OF THE PERSECUTED, THE WORKERS, THE STUDENTS, THE PRISONERS, THE MUZZLED DEMOCRATS, AND THE GRIEVING WIDOWS OF CHILE. THROUGH THESE TRANSMISSIONS, THOSE PEOPLE RECEIVED THE MESSAGE OF SUPPORT AN ENCOURAGEMENT SENT BY THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD.

THE FIRST BROADCASTS WERE MADE IN THOSE YEARS, AND VERY FEW HAVE NOT LISTENED TO THEM AT SOME TIME, ALTHOUGH NOBODY ADMITTED TO KNOWLEDGE OF THOSE PROGRAMS. THE TYRANT HIMSELF VIOLENTLY ATTACKED THE PROGRAMS IN SEVERAL PUBLIC SPEECHES. NOT LONG AGO, PINOCHET'S FOREIGN MINISTER AGAIN SCATHINGLY REFERRED TO RADIO MOSCOW'S BROADCASTS. THAT IS TO SAY THAT THOSE PROGRAMS HAVE CONTINUED TO AFFECT THE DICTATORSHIP IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER AND THAT THEY HAVE HELPED THE RESURGENCE OF THE DEMOCRATIC FORCES. THE RESURGENCE AND ORGANIZATION OF THE DEMOCRATIC FORCES THROUGH THE IMPETUS OF THE WORKERS AND BROAD SECTORS OF THE POPULATION HAVE RESHAPED THE CHILEAN POLITICAL SITUATION, TO THE POINT THAT WE ARE NOW APPROACHING THE REAL POSSIBILITY OF AN ELECTORAL TRIUMPH BY A SINGLE OPPOSITION CANDIDATE TO THE PRESIDENCY, THUS SETTING THE PROCESS OF TRANSITION IN MOTION.

IN FACT THE SITUATION NOT ONLY HAS CHANGED IN CHILE, BUT ALSO IN THE SOVIET UNION WHERE THE PERESTROYKA -- A REVOLUTIONARY PROCESS INSIDE A REVOLUTION -- HAS OPENED IMMENSE POSSIBILITIES FOR THE ECONOMIC, SOCIAL, AND POLITICAL DEVELOPMENT OF SOVIET SOCIETY. WE FREQUENTLY KEEP YOU ABREAST OF THESE DEVELOPMENTS IN THE PROGRAMS OF RADIO MOSCOW. SO, ALL THIS HAS GALVANIZED OUR DISPOSITION TO CONTINUE COOPERATING IN THIS PROCES THAT HAS REACHED NEW LEVELS.

OUR PROGRAMS CONTINUE TO BE OPEN AND AT THE DISPOSAL OF ALL ADVANCE FORCES THAT MARCH WITH THE DEMOCRATS. A FEW WEEKS AGO, RADIO MOSCOW COMPLETED 16 YEARS OF BROADCAST TO CHILE. NOW, ON 29 OCTOBER RADIO MOSCOW WILL CELEBRATE ITS 60TH ANNIVERSARY. ALL THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD KNOW THE PROGRAMS OF RADIO MOSCOW IN 81 LANGUAGES. THE PROGRAMS TO CHILE HAVE A PRIVILEGED PLACE AMONG THEM. FOR THE OCCASION, GREETINGS HAVE BEEN SENT TO THE PROGRAMS OF RADIO MOSCOW AND RADIO MAGALLANES. FROM CHILEANS SCATTERED IN 40 COUNTRIES BY THE FASCIST EXPLOSION, RADIO MOSCOW ALSO RECEIVES MAIL AND POSTCARD WITH MESSAGES OF APPRECIATION AND THANKS. THIS IS A MODEST WAY OF RESPONDING TO THE VALUABLE ASSISTANCE RADIO MOSCOW HAS GIVEN, IS GIVING, AND WILL CONTINUE TO GIVE US.

WE HAD BEEN LEFT ALONE, ISOLATED FROM THE WORLD, AND RADIO MOSCOW PROVED TO BE OUR FRIEND DURING SHAMEFUL TIMES. GOOD NIGHT.

DEV-MUC3-0577 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 15 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] VICTOR POLAY, THE LEADER OF THE PERUVIAN TERRORIST TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA) GROUP, TODAY ADMITTED THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE MRTA WILL PROPOSE HIS RELEASE IN EXCHANGE FOR THE RELEASE OF TELEVISION IMPRESARIO HECTOR DELGADO PARKER. POLAY IS BEING HELD AT A PENITENTIARY IN LIMA.

THE REMARKS BY POLAY, WHO WAS CAPTURED BY PERUVIAN POLICE IN FEBRUARY 1989 IN THE CITY OF HUANCAYO, 315 KM EAST OF LIMA, WERE PUBLISHED TODAY BY THE LIMA DAILY "LA REPUBLICA," WHICH INTERVIEWED HIM AT HIS CELL IN LIMA'S CANTO GRANDE PENITENTIARY.

LAST THURDAY [12 OCTOBER], THE WEEKLY "CAMBIO," WHICH IS DESCRIBED BY POLICE SOURCES AS THE MRTA'S UNOFFICIAL MOUTHPIECE, REPORTED THAT THE MRTA -- WHICH UPHOLDS THE BELIEFS OF GUERRILLA ERNESTO "CHE" GUEVARA -- KIDNAPPED IMPRESARIO DELGADO PARKER ON 4 OCTOBER 1989 IN LIMA, SAYING THAT HE WILL BE TRIED "BY A REVOLUTIONARY COURT."

DELGADO PARKER WAS AN ADVISER TO PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AND IS THE GODFATHER OF ONE OF HIS DAUGHTERS.

POLAY TOLD "LA REPUBLICA" THAT THE KIDNAPPING OF THE IMPORTANT PERUVIAN TELEVISION IMPRESARIO IS OF A"POLITICAL" NATURE AND IS DIFFERENT FROM OTHER KIDNAPPINGS OF OTHER PROMINENT TYCOONS CARRIED OUT BY THE MRTA PEOPLE TO OBTAIN RANSOM MONEY, AND THAT, THEREFORE, THE PETITION THAT WILL BE MADE "MUST BE POLITICAL."

POLAY TOLD "LA REPUBLICA" THAT HE IS NOT RESPONSIBLE FOR DELGADO PARKER'S KIDNAPPING, A BLOODY ACTION IN WHICH THE IMPRESARIO'S DRIVER WAS KILLED AND THE IMPRESARIO'S BODYGUARD WAS INJURED. POLAY SAID THAT HE CANNOT PREDICT THE DECISION THAT THE "REVOLUTIONARY COURT" WILL MAKE AFTER THE "PEOPLE'S JUDGMENT" TO WHICH THE IMPRESARIO WILL BE SUBJECTED.

POLAY, HOWEVER, ADMITTED THE POSSIBILITY OF AN EXCHANGE DEAL BECAUSE "THE KIDNAPPING IS POLITICAL AND THE PETITION THAT WILL BE MADE MUST BE POLITICAL."

THE PUBLICATION OF POLAY'S INTERVIEW TODAY COINCIDES WITH REPORTS BY LOCAL NEWSPAPERS ON THE CAPTURE OF 12 REGIONAL MRTA LEADERS. THIS NEWS WAS ANNOUNCED IN THE CITY OF CAJAMARCA, 870 KM NORTH OF LIMA.

THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE ANNOUNCED THAT THE OPERATIONS, LEADING TO THE CAPTURE OF THE MRTA LEADERS, HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS, AND THAT ACTIVISTS, WHO WERE OPERTING IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF CAJAMARCA, LA LIBERTAD, AND ANCASH IN NORTHERN PERU AND WHO WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR AT LEAST 20 BOMB ATTACKS IN DIFFERENT LOCATIONS, HAVE BEEN DETAINED.

THE NATIONAL POLICE ADDED THAT FIREARMS, EXPLOSIVES, AND PROPAGANDA MATERIAL WERE SEIZED FROM THE MRTA LEADERS.

DEV-MUC3-0583 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN JOSE, 18 OCT 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] TODAY AGREED TO INSTITUTIONALIZE THE DIALOGUE AND TO MEET IN OTHER COUNTRIES EVERY MONTH DESPITE THE DISAGREEMENTS BETWEEN THE TWO SIDES.

ALTHOUGH THE GOVERNMENT COULD NOT CONVINCE THE GUERRILLAS TO LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND RETURN TO POLITICAL LIFE AND THE FMLN COULD NOT SUCCEED IN SECURING FROM THE AUTHORITIES "TRUE GUARANTEES" FOR DEMOCRATIZATION AND SECURITY PRIOR TO ENDING THE ARMED STRUGGLE, THE PROTAGONISTS OF THE DIALOGUE SEEMED SATISFIED AT THE END OF THE MEETING.

MONSIGNOR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, SAN SALVADOR AUXILIARY BISHOP AND MEDIATOR IN THE TALKS, TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT LAST NIGHT'S MEETING WAS "DIFFICULT YET FRUITFUL" AFTER COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS VISITED THE CONVENT SITE OF THE MEETING.

ARIAS MET FOR A WHILE ON 17 OCTOBER WITH THE DELEGATION MEMBERS AND THE MEDIATORS AT THE SAINT CLARE CONVENT, WHERE THE DIALOGUE IS TAKING PLACE, AND SUCCEEDED IN UNBLOCKING THE MEETING, WHICH HAD BEEN BOGGED DOWN IN THE MORNING, ACCORDING TO ROSA CHAVEZ.

ARIAS, WHO WAS AWARDED THE 1987 NOBEL PRIZE FOR HIS PEACE EFFORTS IN CENTRAL AMERICA, SAID WHILE LEAVING THE MEETING WITH THE NEGOTIATORS AND MEDIATORS ON 17 OCTOBER THAT HE WAS MOVED TO INTERVENE BECAUSE HE WANTED TO "ENCOURAGE THE SIDES TO KEEP NEGOTIATING."

ARIAS STRESSED THE DIFFICULTY IN FINDING A RAPID SOLUTION FOR A PROBLEM OF VIOLENCE THAT HAS LASTED 10 YEARS AND KILLED MORE THAN 70,000 PEOPLE. HE POINTED OUT THAT "THERE IS STILL WILLINGNESS TO SEEK PEACEFUL WAYS TO END THIS BLOODY CONFRONTATION."

ACCORDING TO THE INFORMATION AVAILABLE, BOTH SIDES ARE WILLING TO "GO OVER SOME IDEAS," PRESENTED IN THIS MEETING, AND KEEP ELABORATING ON THEM IN THE CONTEXT OF THE SALVADORAN SITUATION.

REGARDING THE CESSATION OF HOSTILITIES, WHICH WAS MENTIONED AS THE MAIN POINT EARLY IN THE MEETING BUT HAS NOT YET BEEN APPROVED BECAUSE OF A DISAGREEMENT BETWEEN THE SIDES, AN ACCORD WAS FINALLY REACHED TO "CLARIFY" THE MEANING OF THE PHRASE.

ACCORDING TO FMLN SPOKESMAN JESUS ROJAS, THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION HAS CONTINUED TO INDICATE THAT "IT HAS NO DECISIONMAKING ABILITY" AND THIS HAS CAUSED UNCERTAINTY IN THE NEGOTIATIONS.

CESAR MARTI, ANOTHER FMLN MEMBER, SAID "SUBSTANTIAL ACCORDS" HAVE NOT BEEN ANTICIPATED, BUT THE "THE DIALOGUE HAS BEEN SAVED."

ROSA CHAVEZ SAID THE MEETING, THE SECOND SINCE DIRECT CONTACTS WERE RESUMED IN MEXICO CITY IN SEPTEMBER ENDS TODAY.

TODAY IT WILL BE ANNOUNCED WHERE AND WHEN THE 3D MEETING WILL BE HELD, PERHAPS IN CARACAS, ALTHOUGH THE REBELS INSIST THAT THE MEETING SITE SHOULD BE SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0585 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LA PAZ, 18 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PERU HAS GIVEN BOLIVIA FREE ZONES IN TWO PERUVIAN PORTS TO FACILITATE THAT COUNTRY'S ACCESS TO THE SEA. BOLIVIA LOST ITS PACIFIC COASTLINE IN A WAR AGAINST CHILE IN 1879.

THIS AGREEMENT WAS REACHED DURING A MEETING BETWEEN PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AND BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA ON BOARD A SHIP ANCHORED ON THE HIGHEST LAKE IN THE WORLD, LAKA TITICACA.

"IT HAS BEEN A FRUITFUL MEETING BECAUSE WE AGREED ON SEVERAL ISSUES THAT GO BEYOND THE RHETORIC OF INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS," THE PERUVIAN CHIEF OF STATE SAID AFTER THE SESSION.

"WE MET TO DEFINITIVELY IMPLEMENT AN OLD PERUVIAN OFFERING," GARCIA ADDED.

ACCORDING TO THE JOINT DECLARATION THAT WAS RELEASED TO THE PUBLIC AFTER THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT, THE FREE ZONES ARE LOCATED IN THE PORTS OF MATARANI AND ILO, IN SOUTHERN PERU, IN KEEPING WITH AN OFFER MADE BY THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT IN 1979.

THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THAT BOLIVIA HAS GAINED ACCESS TO FREE ZONES IN PERUVIAN PORTS. THE ONLY FREE PORT BOLIVIA PREVIOUSLY HAD ACCESS TO WAS THE CHILEAN PORT OF IQUIQUE.

AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT THE BOLIVIAN FREE ZONE LOCATIONS AREAS, AND OPERATIONS SYSTEMS IN PERUVIAN PORTS WILL BE DEFINED DURING A MEETING OF BOLIVIAN AND PERUVIAN EXPERTS, WHO MUST PREPARE PROPOSALS WITHIN 60 DAYS.

THE TWO PRESIDENTS DECIDED TO CREATE A MARITIME TRANSPORTATION COMPANY WITH TWO COMPANIES FROM EACH COUNTRY. THE PRESIDENTS INSTRUCTED THEIR DECLARATION, THE CHIEFS OF STATE DECIDED THAT PERUVIAN LEAD AND SILVER CONCENTRATE WILL BE PROCESSED IN BOLIVIAN METAL PLANTS. THEY ALSO DECIDED TO CREATE A BINATIONAL COMPANY TO MARKET MINERALS.

THE TWO PRESIDENTS, THE COMMUNIQUE STATES, "EXPRESSED THEIR WILL TO PROMOTE IN THE FUTURE THE CREATION OF A BINATIONAL MINISTRY FOR THE COMPLETE DEVELOPMENT AND MANAGEMENT OF THE HIGH PLATEAU REGION SHARED BY THE TWO COUNTRIES."

GARCIA AND PAZ ZAMORA RATIFIED "THEIR CONVICTION TO CARRY OUT BILATERAL TRADE WITHIN THE ANDEAN INTEGRATION PROGRAM," AND THE PERUVIAN ADMINISTRATION PROMISED TO GRANT BOLIVIA FACILITIES "TO ENCOURAGE TRADE OF BOLIVIAN AGRICULTURE AND AGRO-INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTS."

ON THE SUBJECT OF DRUG TRAFFICKING, THE TWO PRESIDENTS "REITERATED THEIR POLITICAL WILL" TO COORDINATE ACTIONS AGAINST ILLEGAL DRUG TRAFFICKING, ACCORDING TO THE COMMITMENT ASSUMED ON 10 OCTOBER BY GARCIA, PAZ ZAMORA, AND COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO IN THE PERUVIAN CITY OF ICA.

BOLIVIA AND PERU ARE TWO OF THE WORLD'S MAIN PRODUCERS OF COCA LEAVES, THE RAW MATERIAL FOR MAKING COCAINE, OF WHICH 80 PERCENT IS PROCESSED IN COLOMBIAN LABORATORIES.

THE TWO CHIEFS OF STATE ALSO DECIDED TO "REVIEW AND MODERNIZE" PUBLIC TRANSIT BETWEEN THEIR TWO COUNTRIES "IN KEEPING WITH HISTORICAL, GEOGRAPHIC, AND ECONOMIC RELATIONS" BETWEEN BOLIVIA AND PERU.

IN A REMARKABLE SIDELIGHT, PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA DECIDED TO RENAME THE PERUVIAN SHIP "OLLANATA," WHERE THE MEETING TOOK PLACE, THE "GREAT MARSHAL ANDRES DE SANTA CRUZ," AFTER THE FIFTH BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT AND SPONSOR OF THE PERUVIAN- BOLIVIAN CONFEDERATION.

ONE OF THE AGREEMENTS INCLUDED IN THE 18-POINT FINAL DECLARATION STATES THAT BOLIVIA WILL BE ABLE TO SEND NAVY OFFICERS WITH THE NEXT PERUVIAN MISSION TO ANTARCTICA.

THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT WAS HELD ON THE WATERS OF LAKE TITICACA, 3,800 METERS ABOVE SEA LEVEL.

A BOMB EXPLODED TODAY AT DAWN IN THE PERUVIAN TOWN OF YUNGUYO, NEAR THE LAKE, VERY NEAR WHERE THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT WAS TO TAKE PLACE.

ALTHOUGH THE EXPLOSION DID NOT CAUSE ANY CASUALTIES, THE LOCAL POLICE STATION DID SUSTAIN SOME PROPERTY DAMAGE.

DEV-MUC3-0586 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BOGOTA, 19 OCT 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] SPECIAL SECURITY MEASURES WERE ADOPTED AT THE CONGRESS TODAY. ONLY PARLIAMENTARIANS, JOURNALISTS, AND EMPLOYEES ARE ALLOWED TO ENTER THE BUILDING. THE GENERAL PUBLIC HAS BEEN BANNED. THESE MEASURES WERE IMPLEMENTED AFTER A PAID ASSASSIN WAS KILLED RIGHT IN BOLIVAR SQUARE BY A GRENADE HE WAS TRYING TO THROW AT THE CONGRESS BUILDING.

THE ABORTED ACTION BY THE TERRORIST ON 18 OCTOBER FORCED THE AUTHORITIES TO REINFORCE SECURITY AT THE CONGRESS. HOWEVER, BOLIVAR SQUARE WAS POORLY PATROLLED. SEVERAL ONLOOKERS ARRIVED AT THE SQUARE EARLY THIS MORNING TO SEE WHERE THE TERRORIST WAS KILLED WHEN THE GRENADE EXPLODED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED SECURITY OFFICER] THOSE WHO CANNOT SHOW PROPER IDENTITY CARDS WILL NOT BE ADMITTED.

[REPORTER] DOES THIS INCLUDE REPRESENTATIVES AND SENATORS?

[OFFICER] YES, ANYONE WHO HAS LEGITIMATE BUSINESS HERE AT THE CONGRESS. [END RECORDING]

THE MEASURES CAUSED VARIOUS REACTIONS AND ANGERED SOME CONGRESSMEN.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] WHY WAS THIS SENATOR NOT ADMITTED?

[OFFICER] BECAUSE HE REFUSED TO BE SEARCHED, AS EVERYBODY MUST BE.

[UNIDENTIFIED CONGRESSMAN] SEARCHING CONGRESSMEN IS NOT VERY NICE, BUT IT WOULD BE WORSE IF ONE WERE KILLED. [END RECORDING]

EMPLOYEES DID NOT ESCAPE THE CHECK EITHER. THE POLICE EVEN CORDONED OFF THE OUTSIDE AREAS NEAR WHERE THE COMMISSIONS WORK.

DEV-MUC3-0587 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 OCT 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [SPEECH] [SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] ...WHICH IS THE OVERALL RESULT, BUT ALSO ANALYZED THE MANNER IN WHICH THIS MEETING WAS HELD BECAUSE WE BELIEVE, AND WE HAVE ALWAYS BELIEVED, THAT THE PEOPLE MUST BE INFORMED, THE PEOPLE MUST KNOW THE TRUTH. INITIALLY, THIS SECOND MEETING WITH THE FMLN IS A FOLLOWUP TO THE MEXICO ACCORD IN SEPTEMBER.

WE WANT TO BEGIN BY BRIEFLY EXPLAINING WHAT THE MEXICO ACCORD WAS, PARTICULARLY WHAT WE AGREED TO DISCUSS IN THE MEETING IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA. WE HAVE HERE THE TEXT OF THE MEXICO ACCORD, AND IN THE CHAPTER CONCERNING THE NEXT MEETING IT SAYS: THE TOPIC OF DISCUSSION WILL BE THE END OF HOSTILITIES, BASED ON PROPOSALS BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT].

IN VIEW OF THE MEXICO ACCORD, OUR DELEGATION BEGAN TO WORK ON A PROPOSAL THAT WOULD MAKE EVERY POSSIBLE EFFORT TO OUTLINE WHAT COULD BE AN END TO HOSTILITIES. WHY HAVE WE INSISTED ON THIS TOPIC? BECAUSE WE WANT AN END TO VIOLENCE IN OUR COUNTRY, THE END OF WEAPONS FIRING, THE END OF BOMB EXPLOSIONS, THE END OF MINES MUTILATING THE LITTLE HANDS AND FEET OF CHILDREN IN RURAL AREAS. WE WANT TO SEE AN END TO THE DESTRUCTION OF EL SALVADOR, AND AN ATMOSPHERE OF CORDIALITY AND TRANQUILITY WITH GREATER POSSIBILITIES FOR THE DIALOGUE PROCESS.

THAT IS THE PHILOSPHY, BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AND EACH ONE OF YOU AS PART OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, DO NOT DESERVE THIS VIOLENT SITUATION, THIS HOSTILE SITUATION GENERATED BY THE ARMED GROUPS OF THE FMLN.

THE PROPOSAL IS ALSO BASED ON THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PLAN, ESQUIPULAS II, AND THE SUBSEQUENT AGREEMENTS SIGNED BY THE FIVE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. I WOULD LIKE TO RECALL THE TELA AGREEMENT, THE LAST AGREEMENT. IN PART III, THE AGREEMENT READS AS FOLLOWS:

THE FMLN IS STRONGLY URGED TO END HOSTILITIES IN AN IMMEDIATE AND EFFECTIVE MANNER TO HOLD A DIALOGUE THAT WILL LEAD TO GIVING UP THE ARMED STRUGGLE; THE FMLN MEMBERS WILL RETURN TO DEMOCRATIC LIFE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0589 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 20 OCT 89 -- [SPEECH] [CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE FMLN HAS DONE NOTHING BUT INSIST ON AN IMMEDIATE ANSWER TO ALL OF THIS. LOGICALLY, I CANNOT SAY THAT THEIR'S IS A SERIOUS POSITION BECAUSE WHEN A NUMBER OF DOCUMENTS ARE PUT FORWARD, A PERIOD OF TIME IS REQUIRED TO ANALYZE THEM. HOWEVER, THE FMLN IMMEDIATELY REJECTED THE GOVERNMENT'S PROPOSAL, SAYING THAT IT WOULD NOT ACCEPT IT. WHAT DOES THIS MEAN? THAT THE FMLN NO LONGER WANTS TO TALK ABOUT THE END OF THE HOSTILITIES, BUT WANTS TO INTRODUCE NEW TOPICS AT THE SAN JOSE MEETING.

HOWEVER, DESPITE THE FMLN'S POSITION, AND ALTHOUGH THERE HAS NOT BEEN AN IN-DEPTH STUDY OF ALL THE DOCUMENTS, ONE CAN SEE AT FIRST GLANCE THAT THE PROPOSALS THEY HAVE PUT FORWARD ARE TOTALLY ABSURD. I WILL CITE AN EXAMPLE: YOU KNOW VERY WELL THAT THE FMLN HAS ADMITTED TO BEING UNABLE TO MAINTAIN A POSITION, THAT IF IT ATTEMPTS TO OCCUPY A TOWN, IN LESS THAN 24 HOURS THE ARMED FORCES DRIVE IT OUT. IT CANNOT MAINTAIN A POSITION IN THE COUNTRY. NEVERTHELESS, THE FMLN PROPOSAL ATTEMPTS TO ESTABLISH TERRITORIAL LIMITS WITH THE GOVERNMENT.

WHILE IT IS TRUE THAT THE FMLN EXISTS AND IS A REALITY, I BELIEVE THAT REALITY HAS A DIMENSION, A SIZE. THE RESULTS OF THE PAST ELECTIONS, THE RESULTS OF SOMETHING OVER 3 PERCENT [WON BY THE DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE], INDICATE THAT THE FMLN IS A REALITY BUT A VERY SMALL ONE, AND THAT IT DOES NOT HAVE THE RIGHT TO FORCE A GOVERNMENT AND A PEOPLE TO VIOLATE THEIR CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM.

MEANWHILE, THE FMLN HAS COME UP WITH THE TOTALLY ABSURD NOTION THAT THE GOVERNMENT MUST DISMISS THE ENTIRE [MILITARY] CLASS OF '66, THE DEFENSE MINISTER, AND THE COMMANDER OF THE AIR FORCE. THAT IS TOTALLY ABSURD, IT IS A RIDICULOUS POSITION THAT DOES NOT TRULY SHOW ANY INTENTION TO MOVEMENT TOWARD PEACE. THE FMLN PROPOSAL ALSO CALLS FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO INSTRUCT THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY TO CHANGE ALL OF THE SUPREME COURT JUSTICES. THESE, SALVADORAN FRIENDS, ARE TOTALLY ABSURD POSITIONS; ALTHOUGH THESE ARE SOMEWHAT DIFFERENT, THEIR PREVIOUS POSITIONS ARE EVER PRESENT.

THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT AT ANY TIME VIOLATE THE CONSTITUTION, IT WILL NEVER QUESTION THE SACRIFICES THAT YOU AND ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE MADE DURING THESE LONG YEARS IN ORDER TO GRADUALLY STRENGTHEN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, WHICH MAY NOT BE PERFECT -- AND WE WOULD LIKE TO DISCUSS DIFFERENT WAYS OF PERFECTING IT -- BUT WE WILL NEVER SELL IT OR SACRIFICE IT, ESPECIALLY UNDER CIRCUMSTANCES WHICH, BY ALL MEANS, ARE ABSURD.

WHAT IS WORSE, HOWEVER, IS THAT ALONG WITH THE ATTITUDE THE FMLN HAS DISPLAYED IN COSTA RICA, ALONG WITH ITS REJECTION OF EVERYTHING THE GOVERNMENT SAYS, ITS ATTEMPTS TO MODIFY THE AGENDA WE HAD AGREED UPON IN MEXICO, ITS EFFORTS TO INTRODUCE A SERIES OF DOCUMENTS, AND ITS DEMAND FOR IMMEDIATE ANSWERS, IT HAS INITIATED A STRATEGY OF MURDERS HERE IN EL SALVADOR. EVERYONE HAS NOTICED; THEY MURDERED A REPORTER'S WIFE AND SON. WHY? BECAUSE THEY HAD A RELATIVE IN THE ARMED FORCES. THEY HAVE MURDERED AN INNOCENT YOUNG GIRL, AT A SAFE DISTANCE, IN A COWARDLY MANNER, ONLY BECAUSE SHE WAS A RELATIVE OF AN ARMED FORCES MEMBER. YESTERDAY THEY ATTEMPTED TO MURDER A FORMER MILITARY MAN WHO ALSO HAS A RELATIVE IN THE ARMED FORCES.

WHAT DOES ALL OF THIS MEAN? THAT THE FMLN INTENDS TO TALK OVER THERE [COSTA RICA] AND TO MAKE AN ENTIRE CASE OUT OF ITS DEFENDING HUMAN RIGHTS, WHILE MURDERING PEOPLE AND VIOLATING THE HUMAN RIGHTS THEY CLAIM TO BE DEFENDING, ON A DAILY BASIS. ALL OF THESE FMLN ATTITUDES FORCE US TO DIALOGUE, AND AS I SAID AT THE BEGINNING, I MUST BE COMPLETELY CLEAR AND OPEN. I MUST TELL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THE TRUTH.

I BELIEVE THAT SO FAR THE FMLN HAS NOT DISPLAYED THE POLITICAL RESOLVE TO ACHIEVE PEACE. FIRST OF ALL, THE FMLN DOES NOT WANT TO TALK ABOUT ENDING THE CONFLICT, IT DOES NOT WANT TO GIVE THE ENTIRE COUNTRY -- YOU AND I, MY DEAR VIEWERS -- THE OPPORTUNITY TO STOP LIVING IN THIS WHIRLPOOL OF VIOLENCE, TO LIVE IN PEACE, AND TO ALLOW THE PROCESS TO PROGRESS IN THE SEARCH FOR SOLUTIONS THAT WILL GRADUALLY GIVE US FIRM AND LASTING PEACE, WITHIN AN ATMOSPHERE OF TRANQUILITY.

THE FMLN'S ATTITUDE IS ONE OF PROVOCATION. IT WANTS TO PROVOKE THE GOVERNMENT INTO GETTING UP FROM THE DIALOGUE TABLE; IT HAS TRIED TO ANGER THE MEMBERS OF THE COMMISSION BY INSULTING THEM. ALL IN ALL, THE FMLN IS TRYING TO FORCE THE GOVERNMENT TO DESIST. WHY ARE THEY SEEKING THIS? BECAUSE ALL THEY WANT IS A LITTLE MORE IMAGE, THE IMAGE THAT THEY HAVE COMPLETELY LOST BECAUSE THEIR SPACES HAVE BEEN CLOSED. NO ONE IN THE WORLD WILL CONTINUE TO JUSTIFY AN ARMED STRUGGLE. THAT IS A THING OF THE PAST. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0590 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 20 OCT 89 -- [SPEECH] [CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] PRESIDENT ARIAS WAS RIGHT WHEN HE SAID THAT PERHAPS FIDEL CASTRO IS THE ONLY ONE WHO INSISTS ON THE SITUATION -- AND WHO SEEMS TO HAVE NOT YET RETURNED FROM THE SIERRA MAESTRA WHERE HE WAS IN 1959. THAT SEEMS TO BE THE ATTITUDE OF THE FMLN LEADERS. WHAT ELSE DO THE ARMED FORCES, I MEAN [CORRECTS HIMSELF], DOES THE FMLN WANT WITH ALL THESE ABSURD PROPOSALS AND ATTITUDES? IT IS SEEKING TO DIVIDE THE ARMED FORCES. IT IS SEEKING TO ISOLATE THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC. IT WANTS TO [DISCREDIT] THE GOVERNMENT IMAGE, WHICH HAS BEEN CONSOLIDATED LITTLE BY LITTLE AT THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL, BECAUSE WE ARE SHOWING TO THE WORLD THAT THERE IS A DEMOCRACY HERE, THAT A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IS BEING CONSOLIDATED, AND THAT THE FORCES THAT ALREADY EXIST WITHIN THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM ARE FORCES THAT TRULY WANT AND SEEK PEACE, RATHER THAN FORCES THAT ASSASSINATE AND CAUSE DESTRUCTION. THEREFORE, WE CAN NO LONGER THINK AT THIS MOMENT, THAT THE FMLN HAS ONLY VIEWED THE DIALOGUE FROM A STRATEGIC POINT OF VIEW.

HOWEVER, WE WANT TO SAY SOMETHING. ALL THIS STRATEGY SHOULD NOT CONFUSE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE MUST BE CALM BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC WILL NOT GIVE AN INCH AND WILL CONTINUE, THROUGH RATIONAL MEANS, TO STRUGGLE AND SEARCH FOR PEACE, TO WHICH YOU AND ALL SALVADORANS ARE ENTITLED. WE ARE NOT GOING TO FALL INTO THE TRAPS THE FMLN IS TRYING TO PUT BEFORE US. HOWEVER, AT THIS MOMENT, WHAT WE SHOULD SEE IS WHO WANTS PEACE AND WHO DOES NOT WANT TO SEARCH FOR PEACE. UP TO THIS MOMENT, THE FMLN HAS GIVEN NO EVIDENCE IT WANTS TO ATTAIN PEACE AND TRANQUILITY FOR YOU, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

NEVERTHELESS, WE MUST NOT BE PESSIMISTIC. ALTHOUGH IT IS TRUE THAT ONE CANNOT SAY, FOR PROPAGANDA PURPOSES, THAT OUTSTANDING RESULTS WERE OBTAINED AT THE MEETING IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, SOME RESULTS WERE ATTAINED. THE DIALOGUE PROCESS WILL CONTINUE AND THAT SHOULD ELIMINATE ALL TRACES OF PESSIMISM. WE MUST THINK THAT THE DIALOGUE PROCESS THAT BEGAN IN MEXICO WAS NOT BROKEN IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, AND THAT THIS PROCESS WILL CONTINUE NEXT MONTH IN CARACAS, VENEZUELA. THE ISSUE AGAIN WILL BE CEASING HOSTILITIES. WE ARE BECOMING MORE AND MORE AWARE OF THE VARIOUS POSITIONS, AND THERE IS LESS ROOM TO PLAY STRATEGIC GAMES WITH THE DIALOGUE PROCESS.

THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO DISCUSS ANY SUBJECT IN THIS DIALOGUE PROCESS. HOWEVER, WE MUST DO THIS IN AN ORDERLY MANNER. WHEN WE REACH AN AGREEMENT, SUCH AGREEMENTS MUST BE RESPECTED. THAT IS THE ATTITUDE THAT SHOULD PREVAIL IF THERE IS A TRUE POLITICAL DESIRE TO ACHIEVE PEACE. THEREFORE, ONCE AGAIN I WANT TO CONCLUDE MY MESSAGE BY MAKING AN APPEAL FOR UNITY. WE MUST BE UNITED FOR PEACE. ALL SECTORS -- POLITICAL, LABOR, RELIGIOUS, AND BUSINESS -- MUST DEMAND THAT THE FMLN SHOW A TRUE DESIRE TO ACHIEVE PEACE. WE MUST DEMAND THAT THE FMLN STOP TRYING TO USE PEACE IN EL SALVADOR FOR STRATEGIC PURPOSES. IF THE FMLN TRULY WANTS PEACE, WHY DOES IT CONTINUE TO SMUGGLE WEAPONS -- PROBABLY FROM NICARAGUA -- INTO EL SALVADOR. TODAY, A TRUCK FROM NICARAGUA LOADED WITH WEAPONS AND EXPLOSIVES FOR THE FMLN WAS CONFISCATED AT THE BORDER WITH HONDURAS. THIS SHOWS THAT THE FMLN IS NOT YET SERIOUSLY SEARCHING FOR PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. HOWEVER, THE UNITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SHOULD FORCE THE FMLN TO SEARCH FOR PEACE. THE UNITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SHOULD CLOSE POLITICAL SPACE SO THE [FMLN] WILL STOP ITS STRATEGIC GAMES. ALL OF US, UNITED, SHOULD DEMAND THAT THE FMLN TAKE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS SERIOUSLY, EQUALLY AS SERIOUSLY AS THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. WE FIRMLY BELIEVE WE MUST SEARCH THROUGH PEACEFUL MEANS TO HAVE PEACE AND CALM IN EL SALVADOR.

SALVADORAN BROTHERS, LET US NOT DISMAY. WE HAVE ALWAYS SAID THAT WE SHOULD NOT HAVE EXCESSIVE ENTHUSIASM. THIS IS NOT AN EASY PROBLEM, THERE WILL BE OBSTACLES, IT IS A DIFFICULT PROBLEM. HOWEVER, WE HAVE ALWAYS SAID YOU CAN BE SURE THAT YOUR GOVERNMENT IS WORKING FOR PEACE AND WILL NOT CEASE TO WORK FOR PEACE.

MAY GOD BLESS YOU. GOOD EVENING.

DEV-MUC3-0591 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 OCT 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS, SALVADORAN DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [LARIOS] THIS HAS REALLY BEEN AN AGREEMENT THAT REFLECTS THE GOVERNMENT'S INTERESTS, AS WELL AS THE INTERESTS OF THE TERRORIST FRONT. IN THIS RESPECT, WE AGREE WITH THE TEXT OF THE SAN JOSE ACCORD.

[REPORTER] AT A NEWS CONFERENCE HELD YESTERDAY AT THE UND, THE NATIONALIST DEMOCRATIC UNION, IT WAS SAID THAT THE PARTICIPATION OF TWO U.S. ADVISERS AND ONE U.S. MILITARY ADVISER PREVENTED GREATER PROGRESS IN THE DIALOGUE. HOW DO YOU FEEL ABOUT THAT?

[LARIOS] WE MUST NEVER FORGET THAT TERRORISTS TRY TO CONFUSE AND TRY TO FOSTER AN ATTITUDE AND ACTIONS IN THE PEOPLE SOLELY TO JUSTIFY THEMSELVES. AT NO TIME WAS THE MILITARY DELEGATION, WHICH PARTICIPATED AS ADVISERS IN THE DIALOGUE, ABLE TO INFLUENCE THE DECISIONS OF THE DIALOGUE COMMISSION. THEIR ROLE AS ADVISERS ENABLED THEM TO GIVE ADVICE TO THE DIALOGUE COMMISSION, BUT IT IS ABSURD TO THINK THAT THE PRESENCE OF OUR TWO MILITARY ADVISERS AND OTHER ADVISERS PREVENTED REAL AND COMPLEX POSITIONS FROM BEING TAKEN AT THAT MEETING.

[REPORTER] THERE IS NO U.S. ADVISER...

[LARIOS, INTERRUPTING] MOREOVER, WE CANNOT.... [CHANGES THOUGHT] NO U.S. ADVISER ACCOMPANIED OUR DELEGATION. IF THERE WAS ONE, HE WENT STRICTLY ON HIS OWN. YOUR QUESTION, THEREFORE, IS IMPORTANT, BECAUSE IT ALLOWS US TO TELL YOU THAT THE SALVADORAN MILITARY DELEGATION NEVER HAMPERED THE WORK OF THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION DURING THE TALKS.

[REPORTER] THE NONGOVERNMENT HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION PRESENTED THE RELATIVES OF TORTURED AND CAPTURED PERSONS. IT ACCUSED 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE COMMANDER FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES AND OTHER OFFICERS OF HAVING TIES TO THE DEATH SQUADS.

[LARIOS] I HAVE BEEN DEALING WITH THESE KINDS OF REPORTS OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS. FRIENDS -- AND HERE I AM APPEALING TO MY FRIENDS -- LET US NOT ALLOW THE TERRORISTS' DESPERATE ACTIONS TO CONFUSE AND CONVEY A FALSE MESSAGE TO THE PEOPLE. THE FACT IS THAT THIS IS PART OF THE STRATEGY OF DECEIT, LIES, AND DISRESPECT FOR THE PEOPLE AND THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS IMPLEMENTED BY THE TERRORISTS.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[LARIOS] LET ME REPEAT THAT THIS IS PART OF THE ABOVE-MENTIONED STRATEGY. WE MUST NOT BE DECEIVED. WE KNOW FULL WELL WHO THE PERSONS ARE WHO ARE TRYING TO SOW MISTRUST AND CONFUSION AMONG CIVILIANS. WE ARE A RESPONSIBLE, SERIOUS, AND FORMAL INSTITUTION. IT IS UP TO US TO INVESTIGATE ALL THESE VIOLENT INCIDENTS AND DEATHS. WE WILL DO OUR DUTY BY CONDUCTING AN INVESTIGATION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0593 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BOGOTA, 20 OCT 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] AUTHORITIES CONTINUE TO DEAL SUCCESSFUL BLOWS AGAINST TERRORISM. CAPTURED TODAY WERE TWO [AS HEARD] EXTRADITABLES AND ONE BOMB PLANTER, WHICH IS WHAT PEOPLE HERE ARE CALLING THESE TERRORISTS.

THE TERRORIST, WHO GIVES HIS NAME AS GONZALO PINZON LAGOS, 24, WAS CAPTURED BY DIJIN [DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS]. HE CONFESSED TO PARTICIPATING IN BOMB ATTACKS EARLY THIS MONTH AGAINST THE ENERGY TOWERS LOCATED AT ROJAS AVENUE AND 75TH STREET AND IN CAFAN SARSAMORA. A TERRORIST WORKING FOR THE JOHN BOLANOS LOPEZ GANG WAS KILLED IN THIS ATTACK. RICARDO BOLANOS RODRIGUEZ, THE GANG LEADER'S FATHER, WAS ALSO ARRESTED. HE IS ACCUSED OF RECRUITING TERRORISTS. THIS MORNING, HE WAS GOING TO PUT A BOMB AT THE AZULEJOS CORONA STORE, ALONG THE MEDELLIN SPEEDWAY.

AN EXTRADITABLE WAS CAPTURED BY THE POLICE WHILE HE WAS IN THE CERREJON INSTALLATIONS, IN THE TOWN OF MAICAO, GUAJIRA INTENDANCY. HE COMES FROM BARRANQUILLA AND IS IDENTIFIED AS ROBERT JAMIS SOCOLOGUISQUI SALA. THE STATE OF SOUTH CAROLINA IS REQUESTING HIS EXTRADITION, BUT MEANWHILE HE WILL REMAIN AT DIJIN INSTALLATIONS.

DEV-MUC3-0594 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LONDON (UK), 19 OCT 89 (BEIJING XINHUA) -- [TEXT] BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA TODAY AGREED TO RESUME THEIR CONSULAR RELATIONS AND DIRECT AIR AND SEA LINKS SEVERED DURING THEIR WAR OVER SOVEREIGNTY OF THE MALVINAS (FALKLANDS) ISLANDS SEVEN YEARS AGO.

AFTER THREE DAYS OF SUBSTANTIVE TALKS IN MADRID, THE TWO COUNTRIES AGREED "TO LIFT ALL REMAINING RESTRICTIONS" ON TRADE AND FINANCIAL EXCHANGES, SAID A JOINT COMMUNIQUE ISSUED HERE TODAY.

THEY ALSO EXPRESSED A WISH TO NORMALIZE THEIR TIES "WITH A VIEW TO RESUMING DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS," IT SAID.

THE DISCUSSIONS WERE HELD BETWEEN BRITISH NEGOTIATOR CRISPIN TICKELL, BRITAIN'S AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED NATIONS, AND VETERAN ARGENTINE DIPLOMAT LUCIO GARCIA DE SOLAR.

THE TALKS, ARRANGED AFTER THE TWO SPECIAL ENVOYS MET IN NEW YORK IN AUGUST, WERE EXTENDED A DAY BEYOND ITS TWO-DAY SCHEDULE.

THEY AGREED TO HOLD FURTHER NEGOTIATIONS TO STRIVE FOR THE RESUMPTION OF THE TWO COUNTRIES' DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS BROKEN DURING THE 1982 MALVINAS WAR. THE NEXT SUBSTANTIVE MEETING WILL BE HELD ON FEBRUARY 14-15, 1990.

DURING THE MADRID TALKS, THE TWO COUNTRIES PUT ASIDE THE CONTROVERSIAL ISSUE OF SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE SOUTH ATLANTIC ISLANDS, WHICH BLOCKED THEIR FIRST RECONCILIATION ATTEMPT IN BERN, SWITZERLAND, IN 1984.

THE COMMUNIQUE SAID THAT THE TALKS ALLOWED BOTH SIDES TO HOLD THEIR RESPECTIVE POSITIONS ON THE ISSUE OF SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE ISLANDS AND THAT NOTHING OF THEIR AGREEMENT COULD BE INTERPRETED AS A CHANGE IN THEIR POSITIONS.

AS REGARDS FISHERIES, THE COMMUNIQUE SAID, BOTH DELEGATIONS HAD DIFFERENT POSITIONS BUT AGREED "TO SET UP A WORKING GROUP WITH A VIEW TO MAKING PROPOSALS" TO BE SUBMITTED TO FURTHER DISCUSSIONS.

ARGENTINA HOPES FOR THE LIFTING OF THE 150-MILE (240-KILOMETER) EXCLUSIVE ZONE AROUND THE MALVINAS ISLANDS IMPOSED BY BRITAIN AFTER THE 10-WEEK WAR, WHICH KILLED MORE THAN 1,000 PEOPLE.

A BRITISH TRADE MISSION WILL VISIT ARGENTINA FROM NOVEMBER 27 TO DECEMBER 1, THIS YEAR, AND A NEW CULTURAL AGREEMENT COULD BE EXPECTED AS NORMALIZATION ADVANCED FURTHER, ACCORDING TO THE DOCUMENT.

LINKS AND CONTACTS BETWEEN THE FALKLANDS AND THE CONTINENTAL MAINLAND WOULD BE DEVELOPED AS BENEFICIAL.

BRITAIN ALSO AGREED TO HELP ARGENTINA ESTABLISH ITS COOPERATIVE LINKS WITH THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY, WHICH HAS REJECTED COMMERCIAL TIES WITH THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRY BECAUSE OF ITS UNNORMALIZED RELATIONS WITH BRITAIN. BRITAIN IS ONE OF THE 12 MEMBERS OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY.

DESCRIBING THE AGREEMENT AS REMARKABLE, TICKELL, THE BRITISH CHIEF NEGOTIATOR, SAID: "WE HAVE TAKEN A VERY LARGE STEP TOWARDS DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS ... WE ARE NOT THERE YET."

ARGENTINE NEGOTIATOR DEL SOLAR EXPRESSED OPTIMISM FOR THE RESUMPTION OF FULL DIPLOMATIC TIES AND SAID: "MY IMPRESSION IS THAT THIS WILL NOT BE TOO LONG."

THE ANGLO-ARGENTINE RAPPROCHEMENT WAS INITIATED BY ARGENTINA'S PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM, WHO TOOK OFFICE IN JULY. MENEM SAID ON THE SECOND DAY AFTER HIS INAUGURATION THAT TALKS COULD BE RESUMED ON RESTORATION OF THE TWO COUNTRIES' DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITHOUT DISCUSSING SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE MALVINAS ISLANDS.

HE VOICED THE HOPE THAT THE DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS COULD RESUME BY CHRISTMAS, A TIMETABLE THAT BRITAIN SAID IS EXTREMELY AMBITIOUS.

HOWEVER, OBSERVERS HERE SAID THE MADRID AGREEMENT HAS PAVED THE WAY FOR BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA TO TALK TO EACH OTHER WITHOUT TOUCHING THE THORNY ISSUE OF SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE ISLANDS.

BY REACHING THE AGREEMENT, BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA HAVE TAKEN A STRIDE TOWARD RECONCILIATION, THEY SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0595 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 OCT 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, TODAY SAID THAT THE WEAPONS CONFISCATED BY HONDURAN TROOPS WERE SENT FROM NICARAGUA AND INTENDED FOR THE URBAN PONCE REFERRED TO THE RECENT SEIZURE OF WEAPONS FROM A VAN WITH A SALVADORAN LICENSE PLATE WHICH WERE SENT BY THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT VIA COSTA RICA TO THE FMLN. HE SAID THAT THE ARSENAL INCLUDED A LARGE QUANTITY OF EXPLOSIVES AND HIGH CALIBER WEAPONS THAT WERE HIDDEN IN SECRET COMPARTMENTS OF THE VAN, WHICH WAS CARRYING FURNITURE FOR A SALVADORAN FAMILY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] THIS DEMONSTRATES ONCE MORE THAT THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT CONTINUES SUPPORTING THE FMLN STRUGGLE AND IS DIRECTLY SUPPORTING THE URBAN COMMANDOS, WHICH ARE THE FMLN DEATH SQUADS IN THIS CITY. THESE MANUALS HAVE BEEN PREPARED IN NICARAGUA AND BEAR THE FMLN LETTERHEAD. THEY ARE INTENDED FOR THE URBAN COMMANDOS AND INCLUDE TACTICAL INSTRUCTIONS AS WELL AS DIRECTIONS ON HOW TO USE ARMS. [END RECORDING]

IN ADDITION, COL PONCE SHOWED A DOCUMENT THAT WAS SEIZED AT EL TIGRE HILL, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, ON 30 JULY, DEALING WITH MILITARY THEORY AND URBAN WAR WHICH, HE SAID, THE FMLN IS CARRYING OUT IN SAN SALVADOR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] THE DOCUMENT SAYS THE FOLLOWING IN ONE OF ITS PARAGRAPHS: THE WAR AGAINST THE AUTHORITIES MUST BE TOTAL AND MUST REACH THEIR PROPERTIES, FAMILIES, HOMES, WORK PLACES, AND VACATION RETREATS. WE MUST ALWAYS GIVE PRIORITY TO EXECUTIONS, BUT HARASSMENT, PSYCHOLOGICAL WARFARE, ETC, ARE ALSO PART OF THIS POLICY AND MAY BE CARRIED OUT BY THE LESS EXPERIENCED ECHELONS TO DEVELOP EXPERIENCE IN USING WEAPONS. THIS SHOWS THAT THE CLAIM THAT WAS MADE BY THE TERRORIST RINGLEADERS IN COSTA RICA IS NOT VALID. IT IS NOT TRUE THAT THEY DISAGREE WITH THIS LINE. [END RECORDING]

ACCORDING TO PONCE'S STATEMENTS, THE ACTIONS UNCOVERED BY MILITARY INTELLIGENCE ARE TOTALLY AT VARIANCE WITH THE TOPICS DISCUSSED AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLES IN MEXICO AND COSTA RICA, BECAUSE THEY TALK ABOUT REACHING PEACE BUT THEIR ACTIONS SHOW THE CONTRARY.

DEV-MUC3-0597 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 21 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO UNOFFICIAL REPORTS AT LEAST 80 PERCENT OF THE APPROXIMATELY 130 PASSENGERS WHO WERE KILLED IN TODAY'S CRASH OF A HONDURAN AIRLINE SASHA BOEING 727 WHICH OCCURRED IN SOUTHERN TEGUCIGALPA WERE FOREIGNERS.

SIXTY-FIVE OF THESE FOREIGNERS WERE NICARAGUANS WHO BOARDED THE AIRPLANE IN MANAGUA DURING A STOPOVER ON ITS WAY FROM COSTA RICA.

INCLUDED AMONG THE FOREIGNERS WERE FOUR CUBANS, THREE FRENCHMEN, THREE AMERICANS, TWO SWEDES, TWO SPANIARDS, ONE FINN, ONE ARGENTINE, ONE BOLIVIAN, ONE CZECHOSLOVAK, ONE SOVIET, ONE ENGLISHMAN, ONE BELGIAN, ONE CHILEAN, AND ONE COSTA RICAN.

AMONG THE FIFTEN SURVIVORS IDENTIFIED BY THE HONDURAN AUTHORITIES ARE SPANIARDS CARLOS AND VIVIAN PELLAS, AUSTRALIANS RONALD AND HELLEN DEVOROUTH, AMERICANS KURT SCHREFFER, JAMES BRANDRICK, CONNY MONTEALEGRE, AND TONNY FRECH, AND PARAGUAYAN RAMON SANCHEZ.

THE FRENCHMEN WHO WERE ON THE AIRPLANE WERE JEAN GEORGES CABINET, MAURICE ALBERT PIERSON, AND BERNARD GEORGES LEVALLOIS AND HIS NICARAGUAN WIFE.

THE SPANIARDS KILLED IN THE ACCIDENT WERE FRANCISCO JAVIER IRANETA AND MARIA DEL VALLE LOZANO, SECRETARY OF THE SPANISH AMBASSADOR IN MANAGUA.

THE PASSENGERS NAMED BY THE AUTHORITIES INCLUDED AMERICANS EVANS LOCKWOOD, GREGORY VINCENT PAGLIA, AND AN UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN. PAGLIA WAS APPARENTLY CARRYING A DIPLOMATIC PASSPORT. THEY ALSO IDENTIFIED SWEDES ANDER JOHANSSON AND AKE CARLSSON.

TRAVELING ON THAT AIRPLANE WERE THE FOLLOWING EUROPEAN CITIZENS: FINN HILKRA HELEN SERJAMO, BRITON HUK KUET WONG, CZECHOSLOVAK ZDEENIK KLIAPA, BELGIAN CARL JEAN NELLIS, AND SOVIET MIKHAIL STAROUCHIK.

ALSO TRAVELLING WERE LATIN AMERICANS CARLOS ALANO EGAN (ARGENTINE), JESUS HERRERA (BOLIVIAN), DANIEL RODRIGUEZ OSORIO (CHILENO), AND MARIO RODRIGUEZ, A SENIOR OFFICER OF THE COSTA RICAN PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE.

THE BOEING 727 LEFT COSTA RICA AT 0600, MADE A STOPOVER IN MANAGUA, AND CRASHED AT APPROXIMATELY 0745 BEFORE LANDING IN TEGUCIGALPA, FROM WHERE IT WAS GOING TO FLY TO HOUSTON, TEXAS.

IN NICARAGUA, DANIEL ORTEGA DECREED 3-DAYS OF MOURNING AND ANNOUNCED THAT FOUR AIRPLANES WERE GOING TO FLY THE RELATIVES OF THE VICTIMS TO HONDURAS TO BRING BACK THE REMAINS.

DEV-MUC3-0598 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 21 OCT 89 (LA PRENSA GRAFICA) -- [TEXT] THE ARSENAL CONFISCATED IN HONDURAS CONFIRMS THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT VIOLATION OF THE TELA AGREEMENTS. [COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE] CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF SAID THE COMMUNISTS ARE NOT TO BE TRUSTED BECAUSE THEY ALWAYS TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE SERIOUSNESS AND GOODWILL OF OTHERS.

COL PONCE EXPLAINED HOW THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES DISCOVERED THE COMING FROM NICARAGUA. HE SAID THE TRUCK WAS FIRST SENT TO COSTA RICA IN ORDER TO CONFUSE THE HONDURAN AUTHORITIES. THE CARGO SEEMED TO BE FURNITURE EARMARKED FOR A SALVADORAN BUSINESSMEN, PONCE SAID.

THE WEAPONS WERE DISCOVERED BY A HONDURAN SOLDIER AT THE BORDER AREA KNOWN AS EL ESPINO, IN CHOLUTECA. THE SOLDIER SAID THE WEAPONS WERE DISCOVERED BY ACCIDENT WHEN HE LOOSENED A WELDED SECTION OF THE TRUCK WHICH REVEALED A SECRET COMPARTMENT IN THE VEHICLE.

COL PONCE ADDED THAT WHEN THE SOLDIERS SEARCHED THE TRUCK THEY FOUND SEVERAL SOVIET MADE AK-47 RIFLES; UZI SUBMACHINEGUNS, RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHERS, 60 MM MORTARS, RADIO COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT, PLASTIC EXPLOSIVES, FRAGMENTATION GRENADES, CARTRIDGE CLIPS, WIRE AND ELECTRIC DETONATORS, DELAYED-ACTION FUSES, AND INSTRUCTION MANUALS FOR THE WEAPONS IN URBAN COMBAT.

FINALLY, COL PONCE EMPHASIZED THAT THIS IS HOW THE NICARAGUAN COMMUNIST GOVERNMENT CONTINUES VIOLATING ITS OWN COMMITMENTS BY SENDING WEAPONS TO OUR COUNTRY SO REBELS CONTINUE KILLING OTHER SALVADORANS.

DEV-MUC3-0599 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BUENOS AIRES, 19 OCT 89 (NA) -- [TEXT] AFTER MEETING WITH PRESIDENT MENEM, FORMER MONTONEROS CHIEFS FERNANDO VACA NARVAJA AND ROBERTO CIRILO PERDIA HAVE STATED THAT THEY WILL BECOME "LEADERS" OF THE NATIONAL RECONCILIATION MOVEMENT AND ENTIRELY SUPPORT THE JUSTICIALIST GOVERNMENT ECONOMIC PROGRAM.

THE MEMBERS OF THE REVOLUTIONARY FACTION OF THE PERONIST MOVEMENT HAVE ASKED PRESIDENT MENEM TO PARDON MONTONEROS LEADER MARIO FIRMENICH, WHO IS CURRENTLY BEING HELD AT THE CASEROS PRISON. VACA NARVAJA AND PERDIA ALSO ANNOUNCEDS THE THEY WILL ASK FOR A MEETING WITH ARMY CHIEF OF STAFF GENERAL ISIDRO CACERES, PJ [JUSTICIALIST PARTY] LEADER ANTONIO CAFIERO, AND TOP LEADERS OF THE CATHOLIC CHURCH WITH THE GOAL OF "ACHIEVING NATIONAL RECONCILIATION."

VACA NARVAJA AND PERDIA WENT TO GOVERNMENT HOUSE TODAY AT NOON TO THANK PRESIDENT MENEM FOR THEIR PARDON AND TO EXPRESS "OUR COMMITMENT TO DO WHATEVER POSSIBLE TO STRENGTHEN THE PROCESS OF RECONCILIATION AND NATIONAL UNITY." THIS REMARK WAS MADE BY VACA NARVAJA TO SOME 50 JOURNALISTS GATHERED IN THE PRESIDENTIAL PRESS ROOM. HE TOLD THE JOURNALISTS THAT PRESIDENT MENEM RECEIVED THEM AND TOLD THEM THAT THEY WILL ENJOY ALL THE RIGHTS GRANTED TO ARGENTINES. HE ALSO ASKED THEM TO JOIN THE PRODUCTIVE REVOLUTION. INTERIOR MINISTER EDUARDO BAUZA WAS ALSO PRESENT AT THE 40-MINUTE MEETING.

DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE, THE RECENTLY PARDONED MONTONEROS LEADERS POINTED OUT THAT THEY ASKED THE PRESIDENT TO PARDON MARIO FIRMENICH. THEY IMPLICITY ADMITTED THAT THE MILITARY MEN WHO LED THE PROCESS OF NATIONAL RECONSTRUCTION COULD BE RELEASED.

VACA NARVAJA SAID IN RESPONSE TO A QUESTION THAT THE MONTONEROS "HAVE MADE A COMMITMENT AT THE LUJAN BASILICA NATIONAL SANCTUARY," AND THAT "IT IS NOT POSSIBLE -- NOR IT IS CORRECT OR JUST -- TO CARRY OUT ARMED OR CLANDESTINE ACTIONS WHEN DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS ARE FULLY EFFECTIVE."

ASKED ABOUT THE MONEY COLLECTED IN THE KIDNAPPING OF IMPRESARIO JORGE BORN, ROBERTO PERDIA SAID THAT "THIS MATTER WAS NOT DISCUSSED" WITH PRESIDENT MENEM. "WE MAINTAIN OUR DECISION THAT THE FUNDS WILL BECOME AVAILABLE SO THAT THEY CAN BE USED TO SOLVE THE PROBLEMS TROUBLING OUR PEOPLE," PERDIA ADDED.

PERDIA ALSO NOTED THAT "MOST OF THE PEOPLE HAVE SHOWN OBVIOUS SIGNS OF UNDERSTANDING THE PRESIDENTIAL MESSAGE AND OF WORKING FOR THE FINAL PACIFICATION."

ASKED IF THE MONEY OBTAINED FROM THE KIDNAPPING OF BORN WOULD BE RETURNED, PERDIA RESPONDED THAT "IT WILL BE RETURNED TO PEOPLE WHO CAN BEST USE IT; WE BELIEVE THAT NO ONE CAN REFUSE OR BLOCK THIS MONEY FROM BEING RETURNED TO ITS LEGITIMATE OWNERS, THE PEOPLE, WHO BUILT THE COUNTRY'S WEALTH WITH THEIR LABOR."

REGARDING THE SUBJECT OF MISSING PERSONS AND IN RESPONSE TO A QUESTION ON WHETHER THIS "WAS A CLOSED CASE," PERDIA EMPHASIZED THAT "IT IS NECESSARY TO THINK IN THE FUTURE ABOUT THE RIGHTS OF THOSE WHO ARE ALIVE AND TO BUILD THE COUNTRY WITHOUT FORGETTING THE PAST." PERDIA ALSO SADI THAT "PAST EVENTS MUST BE REGISTERED IN THE PEOPLE'S CONSCIENCE, IN THE PEOPLE'S MEMORY, SO THAT FUTURE GENERATIONS WILL LEARN OUR GOOD AND EVIL EXPERIENCES."

WHEN A CAMERAMEN FROM A FOREIGN TELEVISION STATION ASKED HIM WHEN THE MONTONEROS WOULD RETURN THEIR WEAPONS, PERDIA SAID THAT "WE HAVE NOT USED WEAPONS SINCE 1983" BECAUSE "WE HAVE BEEN SAYING THAT THERE IS NO ROOM FOR WEAPONS WHENEVER THERE ARE DEMOCRATIC WAYS."

BUT THE CAMERAMEN LOUDLY INSISTED: WHERE ARE THE WEAPONS? PERDIA RESPONDED: "THERE ARE NO WEAPONS. THEY WERE USED IN COMBAT WHEN THERE WAS A MILITARY DICTATORSHIP. THERE IS NO REASON FOR THEM IN A DEMOCRACY."

VACA NARVAJA POINTED OUT THAT THE GUARANTEE OF NOT TAKING UP ARMS "LIES IN THE PEOPLE'S CONSCIENCE, BECAUSE ARGENTINA HAS SAID 'NEVER AGAIN' TO MILITARY COUPS AND GUERRILLA WARFARE."

"THE SECOND GUARANTEE IS THAT THE POLITICAL STEPS THAT WE TAKE BEFORE THE PEOPLE MUST BE CREDIBLE ENOUGH; THEREFORE, SOME TIME MUST PASS FOR OUR ACTIONS TO BE CONFIRMED," VACA NARVAJA ADDED.

CONCLUDING, THE TWO MONTONEROS LEADERS PERFORMED A SELF- CRITICISM OF THE MONTONEROS ORGANIZATION, STATING THAT IT WENT UNDERGROUD "IN AN UNTIMELY FASHION, BECAUSE THERE WERE STILL SOVEREIGN WAYS LEFT FOR THE PEOPLE TO EXPRESS THEMSELVES."

DEV-MUC3-0603 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BOGOTA, 24 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE POSSIBILITIES FOR A DIALOGUE WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE INCREASED IN COLOMBIA DURING THE PAST FEW HOURS AFTER THE EXTRADITABLES ANNOUNCED THEY ARE WILLING TO END THE WAR.

THREE OF THE LEADERS MENTIONED IN THE EXTRADITABLES' LETTER THAT CONTAINED A PROPOSAL TO TAKE PART IN A COMMISSION THAT WOULD REPORTEDLY BEGIN MAKING CONTACTS FOR THE DIALOGUE TODAY ACCEPTED THE MISSION AND SAID THAT THEY ARE READY TO COOPERATE IN THE COUNTRY'S PEACE EFFORTS.

THEY ARE MEDELLIN MAYOR JUAN GOMEZ MARTINEZ, FORMER LIBERAL LEGISLATOR GUIDO PARRA, AND FORMER CONSERVATIVE MINISTER JOAQUIN VALLEJO. MEANWHILE, CARDINAL MARIO REVOLLO SAID THAT "THE MATTER MUST BE STUDIED."

THE EXTRADITABLES PROPOSED CREATING A NEGOTIATING COMMISSION IN A LETTER SENT FROM CLANDESTINITY TO LIBERAL SENATOR LUIS GUILLERMO GIRALDO, PRESIDENT OF THE NATIONAL CONGRESS.

THE POSSIBILITY OF A DIALOGUE IS UNDER CONSIDERATION BY SOME POLITICAL GROUPS, DESPITE THE POSITION ASSUMED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF LIBERAL PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, WHO HAS REPEATEDLY STATED HIS OPPOSITION TO ANY STEP LEADING TO NEGOTIATIONS WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND DRUG TERRORISTS.

BARCO, THROUGH GOVERNMENT (INTERIOR) MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS, HAS PUBLICLY SAID THAT A DIALOGUE WITH TERRORISM IS IMPOSSIBLE, AT LEAST IN THE NEAR FUTURE.

IN VIEW OF THE SITUATION, SOME POLITICAL SECTORS HAVE SPECULATED ON THE POSSIBILITY OF NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN BARCO'S SUCCESSOR, WHO WILL BE ELECTED IN FREE ELECTIONS IN MAY 1990. BARCO WILL LEAVE POWER ON 7 AUGUST 1990.

THE MAFIA HAS PROMISED TO END THE WAVE OF TERRORISM UNLEASHED SEVERAL WEEKS AGO IF BARCO'S GOVERNMENT SUSPENDS THE EXTRADITION OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS TO THE UNITED STATES.

THEY HAVE ALSO PROPOSED ACCEPTING THE DECISION OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE, WHICH RECOGNIZED THE LEGALITY OF THE MEASURES ADOPTED TO FACE THE MAFIAS, BUT DID NOT RECOMMEND EXTRADITION BY EXECUTIVE DECREE.

THE COURT RULED THAT INTERNATIONAL LAW PREVAILS OVER COLOMBIAN LAW, AND NOTED THAT EXTRADITION THROUGH A STATE OF SIEGE DECREE IS NOT COMPATIBLE WITH THE CURRENT COLOMBIAN-U.S. TREATY.

COLOMBIA AND THE UNITED STATES SIGNED AN EXTRADITION TREATY IN 1979 WHICH, ALTHOUGH IT IS STILL IN EFFECT, CANNOT BE APPLIED BECAUSE AT THE END OF 1987 THE SUPREME COURT ITSELF INVALIDATED THE LAW THAT ENFORCED IT.

HOWEVER, SEVERAL COLOMBIAN JURISTS SAID TODAY THAT ONLY THE COLOMBIAN FOREIGN MINISTRY CAN DETERMINE WHETHER TO ACCEPT THE COURT'S DECISION OR TO CONTINUE ACTING BY EXECUTIVE DECREE.

IN THEIR PEACE PROPOSAL, THE EXTRADITABLES DEMANDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT "GRANT COLOMBIANS THEIR LEGITIMATE RIGHT TO DEFENSE, ALLOWING THEM -- AS DEPORTED FOREIGNERS ARE ALLOWED -- TO EXHAUST ALL LEGAL MEANS UNDER ADMINISTRATIVE LAW BEFORE RENOUNCING SOVEREIGNTY AND TURNING THEM OVER BY EXTRADITION."

VALLEJO, PARRA, AND GOMEZ MARTINEZ -- THE THREE MEMBERS PROPOSED BY THE MAFIA TO PARTICIPATE IN THE NEGOTIATING COMMISSION -- SAID TODAY THAT THEY ARE WILLING TO WORK IN FAVOR OF PEACE IN THE COUNTRY. THEY AGREED THAT DIFFERENCES CAN ONLY BE EASED THROUGH DIALOGUE.

"I AM WILLING TO TALK," SAID GOMEZ MARTINEZ, MAYOR OF MEDELLIN, WHERE THE MEDELLIN CARTEL OPERATES. OVER A YEAR AGO, GOMEZ MARTINEZ WAS THE TARGET OF AN ATTACK BY THE THE EXTRADITABLES, WHO TRIED TO KIDNAP HIM. "I AM WAITING FOR THE GOVERNMENT'S OKEY TO BEGIN THE DIALOGUE," HE ADDED.

VALLEJO, WHO DISCLOSED THAT IN MID-1988 HE PRESENTED TO BARCO'S GOVERNMENT AN INITIAL DIALOGUE PROPOSAL FROM THE EXTRADITABLES, SAID THAT "I AM WILLING TO TALK IN ORDER TO ACHIEVE PEACE."

PARRA, A FORMER PARLIAMENTARIAN AND FRIEND OF PABLO ESCOBAR, THE MEDELLIN CARTEL'S CHIEF, SAID THAT "I AM WILLING TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE PEACE EFFORTS."

OTHER SECTORS, PARTICULARLY POLITICAL GROUPS, AGREED THAT NEGOTIATION IS THE ONLY WAY TO PUT AN END TO TERRORIST VIOLENCE IN COLOMBIA.

DEV-MUC3-0604 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

BOGOTA, 24 OCT 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [REPORT] [PILAR CALDERON] [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT SAID TODAY THAT IT WILL CONTINUE TO EXTRADITE COLOMBIAN CITIZENS SOUGHT BY THE UNITED STATES. THE GOVERNMENT WILL USE ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS BECAUSE THERE IS CURRENTLY NO EXTRADITION TREATY WITH THAT COUNTRY.

IN A COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL, THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH ALSO DENIED ANY POSSIBILITY OF PARTICIPATING IN A DIALOGUE WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL'S COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT THE GOVERNMENT POLICY IS TO STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG-TRAFFICKING GROUPS AND THEIR CRIMINAL ORGANIZATIONS. THE COMMUNIQUE ADDS THAT THE POLICY ALLOWS NO ROOM FOR TRANSACTIONS, NEGOTIATIONS, OR DIALOGUES. THEREFORE, THE GOVERNMENT REJECTS ANY PROPOSAL TO MEDIATE WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS -- EVEN IF THE PROPOSAL IS DIRECTLY ISSUED BY THE EXTRADITABLES OR THEIR SPOKESMEN.

THE COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS ANNOUNCED THAT IT WILL CONTINUE TO ENFORCE LEGISLATIVE DECREE 18-60 OF 1989, WHICH ALLOWS FOR EXTRADITIONS THROUGH ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS. THIS DECREE WAS UNANIMOUSLY APPROVED BY THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE.

THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL JUSTIFIES ITS DECISION BY RECALLING THE MANY ACTS OF TERRORISM PERPETRATED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS -- 222 IN 2 MONTHS -- AND THE NAMES OF THE VICTIMS. THE COMMUNIQUE SAYS THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS ARE NOW TRYING TO DISGUISE THEIR CRIMINAL POSITIONS BY CLAIMING THAT THEY ADVOCATE PEACE.

THE DISCUSSIONS ABOUT THE ENFORCEMENT OR SUSPENSION OF COLOMBIAN CITIZENS' EXTRADITION WAS THE MAIN TOPIC DISCUSSED TODAY IN JURIDICAL AND POLITICAL CIRCLES IN OUR COUNTRY AND IN THE UNITED STATES. JOURNALISTS AND LAWYERS CAREFULLY READ THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE'S RULING ON THE DECREE ALLOWING FOR EXTRADITIONS THROUGH ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS. EVERYONE WANTED TO KNOW WHY THE EXTRADITABLES SAID, IN A LETTER ISSUED YESTERDAY, THAT THEY FULLY ABIDED BY THE COURT'S RULING.

THE COURT RULED THAT, ALTHOUGH THE EXTRADITIONS VIA ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS ARE ALLOWED BY THE CONSTITUTION IN CASES WHERE THERE IS ALREADY AN INTERNATIONAL TREATY, THE EXTRADITION MUST BE CARRIED OUT ACCORDING TO THE TREATY. THE COURT BELIEVES THAT THE RULING IS QUITE CLEAR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GOVERNMENT MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS] THE GOVERNMENT MUST DECIDE IF THERE IS A TREATY WITH THE UNITED STATES OR NOT BEFORE IT ENFORCES THE EXTRADITION THROUGH ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS. [END RECORDING]

NEVERTHELESS, THE COURT'S RULING DOES NOT END THE EXTRADITIONS TO THE UNITED STATES BECAUSE, EVEN THOUGH THE COURT BELIEVES THAT AN EXTRADITION TREATY IS STILL IN EFFECT WITH THAT COUNTRY -- THE ONE SIGNED IN 1888 -- AND THAT IT SHOULD BE ENFORCED INSTEAD OF RESORTING TO EXTRADITIONS THROUGH ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS, THE GOVERNMENT CLEARLY SAYS THERE IS NO EXTRADITION TREATY WITH THE UNITED STATES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GOVERNMENT MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS] THE 1979 TREATY HAD BEEN ANNULLED BY THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE, BUT ACCORDING TO THE STATE COUNCIL, THAT TREATY REPLACED -- SO TO SPEAK -- THE 1933 TREATY SIGNED IN MONTEVIDEO AND THE 1888 TREATY. THEREFORE, THINGS ARE NOW THE SAME AS YESTERDAY OR THE DAY BEFORE. [END RECORDING]

MEANWHILE, THE BODYGUARD OF EL ESPECTADOR'S CHIEF OF DISTRIBUTION IN MEDELLIN, PEDRO LUIS OSORIO, WAS ASSASSINATED THIS AFTERNOON IN A DOWNTOWN AREA OF ANTIOQUIA'S CAPITAL.

DEV-MUC3-0606 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LA PAZ, 23 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [EXCERPTS] BOLIVIAN OFFICIALS HAVE EXPRESSED THEIR CONCERN OVER THE PRESENCE OF PERUVIAN SHINING PATH TERRORISTS ON THE BORDER BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES. THE ALSO ANNOUNCED THE DEPLOYMENT OF MILITARY FORCES ALONG THE BORDER.

IN REMARKS PUBLISHED TODAY BY THE LOCAL PRESS. GENERAL FELIPE CARVAJAL, COMMANDER GENERAL OF THE NATIONAL POLICE, STATED: "THE SHINING PATH IS OPERATING ALONG OUR BORDERS AND WE HAVE DONE NOTHING ABOUT IT SO FAR." [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEFENSE MINISTER HECTOR ORMACHEA YESTERDAY ANNOUNCED THAT MILITARY TROOPS WILL BE DEPLOYED FROM BOLIVIAN CITIES TO THE BORDER AREAS.

ACCORDING TO THE DEFENSE MINISTER, THE NEXT DEPLOYMENT OF MILITARY FORCES TO REINFORCE THE BORDER AREAS FOLLOWS REPORTS ON "THE UNPRECEDENTED ENTRY OF FOREIGNERS WHO ARE PLUNDERING" THE COUNTRY'S NATURAL RESOURCES, INCLUDING WOOD AND GOLD.

MOREOVER, THE POLICE COMMANDER HAS STATED THAT TERRORISM "IS A PERMANENT LATENT FACTOR" IN BOLIVIA. AS AN EXAMPLE HE MENTIONED THE INDIAN-MARXIST ORGANIZATION "ZARATE WILLKA ARMED FORCES OF LIBERATION."

THIS GROUP BEGAN ITS ACTIVITIES IN AUGUST 1988 WHEN IT ATTACKED THE OFFICIAL MOTORCADE IN WHICH THE THEN-SECRETARY OF STATE GEORGE SHULTZ WAS TRAVELING. NO INJURIES WHERE CAUSED BY THE ATTACK.

ON 24 MAY THIS YEAR, THE SAME ORGANIZATION MURDERED TWO U.S. MORMON MISSIONARIES ON A CROWDED STREET IN LA PAZ.

DEV-MUC3-0610 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 27 OCT 89 (IZVESTIYA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH VLADIMIR KOTOV, HEAD OF THE TASS DEPARTMENT IN PERU, BY OWN CORRESPONDENT YEVGENIY BAY] [TEXT] ON THE MORNING OF 26 OCTOBER THE EDITORIAL OFFICE RECEIVED TELEGRAMS FROM REUTERS AND AFP FROM THE PERUVIAN CAPITAL, WHICH SAID THAT BOMBS HAD GONE OFF THE DAY BEFORE OUTSIDE THE SOVIET AND PRC EMBASSIES IN LIMA. OUR CORRESPONDENT YEVGENIY BAY CONTACTED VLADIMIR KOTOV, HEAD OF THE TASS DEPARTMENT IN PERU, BY TELEPHONE AND ASKED HIM FOR THE DETAILS.

[KOTOV] ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS DROVE UP TO THE SOVIET EMBASSY BUILDING AND PLANTED A BOMB UNDER A CAR BELONGING TO ONE OF OUR DIPLOMATIC PERSONNEL. THEY HARDLY HAD TIME TO DRIVE OFF BEFORE AN EXPLOSION RANG OUT. ONE CAR WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED AND THREE NEIGHBORING VEHICLES WERE DAMAGED. THIS HAPPENED AT 2015 LOCAL TIME. AND AT 2030 HOURS A VOLKSWAGEN PARKED NEAR THE ENTRANCE OF THE PRC EMBASSY EXPLODED AFTER BEING PACKED WITH DYNAMITE.

FORTUNATELY, THERE ARE NO CASUALTIES AND NO MEMBERS OF THE DIPLOMATIC MISSIONS ARE HURT. THE BUILDINGS ARE NOT REALLY DAMAGED.

[BAY] SO FAR, ACCORDING TO THE INFORMATION AGENCIES, NONE OF THE TERRORIST GROUPS OPERATING IN THE COUNTRY HAVE TAKEN RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS ACTION, ALTHOUGH THE POLICE SUSPECT THE EXTREME LEFT-WING MAOIST ORGANIZATION, "SENDERO LUMINOSO."

[KOTOV] JUDGING BY THE HALLMARK, IT COULD QUITE WELL BE. AS IS WELL KNOWN, "SENDERO LUMINOSO" HAS CARRIED OUT SEVERAL ATTACKS ON SOVIET MISSIONS AND OUR CITIZENS IN THE LAST 3 YEARS. MANY REMEMBER THE INCIDENT WHEN FOUR UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE TELEPHONED THE SOVIET EMBASSY -- ALLEGEDLY TO DELIVER SOME SORT OF PACKAGE. IN THE END, ONE OF THE TERRORISTS GOT INTO THE EMBASSY GROUNDS AND, AT THAT MOMENT, THE "PACKAGE" EXPLODED IN HIS HANDS. AND SEVERAL MONTHS AGO (IZVESTIYA REPORTED THIS) TERRORISTS PLANTED A BOMB UNDER A BUS IN WHICH SOVIET FISHERMEN WERE TRAVELING.

[BAY] AN EXTENSION OF THE STATE OF EMERGENCY IN THE COUNTRY HAS BEEN ANNOUNCED IN CONNECTION WITH THE ESCALATION IN TERRORIST ACTIONS. HOW DOES THE SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY LOOK FROM WHERE YOU STAND?

[KOTOV] THE STATE OF EMERGENCY WAS INTRODUCED HERE IN FEBRUARY 1986 AND HAS BEEN EXTENDED VIRTUALLY EVERY 30-60 DAYS SINCE THEN. IT IS IN EFFECT IN 35 PERCENT OF THE COUNTRY'S TERRITORY, PARTICULARLY IN LIMA AND THE CAPITALS OF A NUMBER OF DEPARTMENTS. HOWEVER, THE WAVE OF TERRORISM IS SHOWING NO SIGN OF ABATING -- EITHER ON THE PART OF THE FAR RIGHT OR THE FAR LEFT. IN OCTOBER ALONE, THEIR ACTIONS CLAIMED 200 LIVES.

"SENDERO LUMINOSO" IS TRYING TO INTIMIDATE THE POPULATION AND WRECK THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS PLANNED FOR 12 NOVEMBER. THEY HAVE PARTIALLY ACHIEVED THEIR AIM. TO THE UNINFORMED, PERUVIAN STATISTICS ARE SIMPLY HORRIFYING: IN THE LAST 3 YEARS, 64 MAYORS OF VARIOUS SMALL AND MEDIUM-SIZED TOWNS IN THE ANDES HAVE BEEN KILLED. NATURALLY, THERE ARE FEW BRAVE ENOUGH TO TAKE THE RISK OF HOLDING THIS POST.

[BAY] WHAT KIND OF CONDITIONS ARE SOVIET REPRESENTATIVES IN PERU LIVING AND WORKING IN?

[KOTOV] SO FAR THERE HAVE BEEN NO RESTRICTIONS ON OUR FREEDOM OF MOVEMENT. HOWEVER, THE ESCALATION OF TERRORISM NATURALLY AFFECTS OUR WELLBEING. PEOPLE LIVE IN A STATE OF TENSION. YOU EXPECT SOMETHING AWFUL TO HAPPEN AT ANY MOMENT. YOU HAVE TO SHOW THE MAXIMUM CAUTION EVERYWHERE: BOTH AT HOME AND ON THE STREET.

DEV-MUC3-0612 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

WASHINGTON DC (USA), 28 OCT 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI SAID TODAY THAT THE DECISION TO SUSPEND THE CEASE-FIRE IN NICARAGUA, AS IT HAS BEEN ANNOUNCED BY NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA, WOULD BE "VERY UNFORTUNATE" AND "WOULD POSE PROBLEMS FOR THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PLAN."

DURING AN INTERVIEW GRANTED IN SAN JOSE TO CNN, A U.S. TELEVISION NETWORK, CRISTIANI ALSO SAID THAT HE HAS DISCARDED THE POSSIBILITY OF A MILITARY INTERVENTION IN PANAMA. REGARDING HIS TALKS WITH THE ARMED OPPOSITION IN HIS COUNTRY HE SAID HE IS "CAUTIOUSLY OPTIMISTIC."

CRISTIANI SAID HE WOULD BE "DISAPPOINTED" IF THE NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT WERE TO SUSPEND THE UNILATERAL CEASE-FIRE DECREED ON 21 MARCH 1988. THIS WOULD PROVE, CRISTIANI SAID, THAT ORTEGA IS NOT WILLING "TO RESPECT THE PROMISES MADE IN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PLAN" SIGNED IN 1987 BY COSTA RICA, EL SALVADOR, NICARAGUA, GUATEMALA, AND HONDURAS.

ACCORDING TO CRISTIANI, ORTEGA HAS ALREADY BROKEN HIS COMMITMENT BY CONTINUING TO SEND ARMS TO THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN), AS HONDURAS REVEALED THIS WEEK.

CRISTIANI ADMITTED, HOWEVER, THAT "NOT MUCH CAN BE DONE" IF ORTEGA UPHOLDS THE DECISION HE ANNOUNCED ON 27 OCTOBER IN SAN JOSE WHERE HE AND 15 OTHER CHIEFS OF STATE OF THE CONTINENT ATTENDED AN INTER - AMERICAN SUMMIT.

REGARDING PANAMA, THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT SAID THAT THE OAS COUNTRIES WILL "CONTINUE MAKING EFFORTS, ESPECIALLY DIPLOMATIC EFFORTS, TO ESTABLISH DEMOCRACY" IN THAT COUNTRY "IN THE NEAR FUTURE." HE DISCARDED THE POSSIBILITY OF A MILITARY INTERVENTION IN PANAMA. "NO ONE HERE (IN SAN JOSE, WHERE MEMBERS OF THE PANAMANIAN OPPOSITION WERE ALSO PRESENT) IS IN FAVOR OF A MILITARY INTERVENTION IN PANAMA."

CRISTIANI STATED HIS SUPPORT FOR U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH WITH REGARD TO THE RECENT COUP ATTEMPT IN PANAMA. CRISTIANI SAID THAT BUSH "DID WHAT HE HAD TO" WHEN HE REJECTED A MILITARY INTERVENTION ON THE SIDE OF THE COUPISTS. REGARDING THE PEACE TALKS HIS GOVERNMENT IS HOLDING WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN], CRISTIANI DECLARED HIMSELF "CAUTIOUSLY OPTIMISTIC" AND NOTED THAT CONTRARY TO THE TALKS HELD BETWEEN THE FMLN AND FORMER PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, THE CURRENT MEETINGS ARE NOT "ISOLATED EVENTS." NOW, HE SAID, "THE PROCESS IS COMPLETELY DIFFERENT." THIS PROCESS, HE ADDED, IS THE "RESULT OF AN AGREEMENT SIGNED LAST SEPTEMBER IN MEXICO BY THE TWO SIDES."

REGARDING CHARGES BY A SALVADORAN SOLDIER, CESAR VIELMAN JOYA MARTINEZ, WHO SAID THIS WEEK THAT HE PARTICIPATED IN ASSASSINATIONS COMMITTED BY A DEATH SQUAD ON ORDERS, ACCORDING TO HIM, FROM THE SALVADORAN HIGH MILITARY COMMAND AND WHO ALSO NOTED THAT U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS HAD TO KNOW WHAT WAS GOING ON, CRISTIANI SAID THAT THESE CHARGES ARE PART OF "FMLN EFFORTS" TO DISCREDIT HIS GOVERNMENT.

MARTINEZ WILL BE "SENTENCED TO JAIL FOR HAVING DONE WHAT HE HAS SAID HE HAS DONE," CRISTIANI SAID. THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ADMITTED THAT THIS TYPE OF INCIDENT STILL OCCURS BUT NOTED THAT THE SALVADORAN AUTHORITIES PUNISH CRIME.

CRISTIANI CONCLUDED BY STATING: "MARTINEZ IS A DESERTER AND A WARRANT FOR HIS ARREST HAS BEEN ISSUED."

JOYA MARTINEZ, WHO FLED HIS COUNTRY IN JULY AND SOUGHT POLITICAL ASYLUM IN THE UNITED STATES, MADE HIS STATEMENTS TO A GROUP OF JOURNALISTS IN WASHINGTON.

DEV-MUC3-0614 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 28 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PERUVIAN DRUG TRAFFICKER EMILIO REYNOSO AGUILAR, ALIAS "RETACO I," ARRIVED IN LIMA TODAY UNDER STRICT POLICE SECURITY. REYNOSO WAS EXTRADITED FROM COLOMBIA TO BE TRIED HERE ON CHARGES OF MURDER, KIDNAPPING, DRUG TRAFFICKING, ROBBERY, AND OTHER CRIMES.

"RETACO I" IS LINKED TO COLOMBIA'S MEDELLIN CARTEL. HE WAS HANDED OVER TO PERUVIAN POLICE OFFICERS WHO HAD TRAVELED TO COLOMBIA TO BRING HIM TO LIMA, WHERE HE IS UNDER INDICTMENT BY NINE DIFFERENT COURTS.

REYNOSO IS KNOWN IN LIMA AS "THE ESCAPE KING" BECAUSE HE HAS ESCAPED FROM PERUVIAN JAILS A NUMBER OF TIMES DISGUISED AS A WOMAN OR A POLICE OFFICER. REYNOSO ESCAPED FROM THE JUSTICE PALACE AFTER TAKING THE POLICE OFFICER GUARDING HIM HOSTAGE.

"RETACO I'S" BROTHERS HAVE SIMILAR ALIASES; THEY ARE CALLED RETACO II, III, AND IV. ALL OF THEM HAVE ACCOUNTS TO SETTLE WITH THE COURTS, BUT ONLY ONE OF THEM IS CURRENTLY IN JAIL.

"RETACO I" LEFT PERU ON 1984 TO CONTINUE HIS CRIMINAL CAREER IN OTHER COUNTRIES. HE FINALLY ENDED UP IN COLOMBIA, WHERE HE WORKED WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS UNTIL HIS ARREST. REYNOSO IS CONSIDERED VERY DANGEROUS. THE PROBLEM FOR THE PERUVIAN POLICE WILL NOW BE TO KEEP "THE ESCAPE KING" IN JAIL.

DEV-MUC3-0615 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 29 OCT 89 (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] RADIO VENCEREMOS IN SPANISH TO EL SALVADOR AT 0000 GMT ON 30 OCTOBER BROADCASTS A WEEKLY MILITARY BULLETIN. ACCORDING TO THE REPORT, "THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIUONAL LIBERATION FRONT] INFLICTED A TOTAL OF 52 CASUALTIES IN VARIOUS ATTACKS ON ENEMY POSITIONS AND AMBUSHES ON MOVING MILITARY CONVOYS DURING THE WEEK THAT HAS JUST ENDED. THESE CASUALTIES INCLUDE AN ARTILLERY LIEUTENANT."

THE REPORT GOES ON TO SAY THAT "ANTIAIRCRAFT ACTIONS HAVE OCCURRED IN CINQUERA, CABANAS DEPARTMENT, ALSO THIS WEEK. AS THE STATION REPORTED EARLIER IN THE WEEK, A UH-1H TRANSPORT HELICOPTER WAS DAMAGED. ARTILLERY TROOPS WERE ATTACKED BETWEEN SAN PABLO TACACHICO AND SAN ISIDRO, LA LIBERTAD DEPARTMENT. COPREFA [ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE] HAS ADMITTED THAT AN ARTILLERY LIEUTENANT WAS INCLUDED IN THE CASUALTIES. TROOPS FROM THE 5TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, WHO OPERATED IN CINQUERA OUT OF THEIR JURISDICTION, WERE WORN OUT DURING THE WEEK."

THE STATION ALSO SAYS THAT "THE ATLACATL BATTALION WAS ATTACKED ON THE SLOPES OF THE SAN SALVADOR VOLCANO, NEJAPA JURISDICTION. FMLN TROOPS ALSO ATTACKED LOCAL TROOPS IN SAN AGUSTIN IN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, YAMABAL IN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT, AND SUCHITOTO IN CUSCATLAN DEPARTMENT. VARIOUS SABOTAGING ACTIONS OCCURRED DURING THE WEEK. SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT, IN THE PARACENTRAL FRONT, SUFFERED SABOTAGE ON THE GREATEST NUMBER OF PYLONS AND POSTS BY OUR SAPPERS."

DEV-MUC3-0619 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 OCT 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [RENE HURTADO] [TEXT] THERE WAS A STRONG EXPLOSION EARLY THIS MORNING. A BOMB WENT OFF AT THE BUILDING OF THE "MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO" COMMITTEE OF MOTHERS, RELATIVES OF POLITICAL PRISONERS, MISSING, AND MURDERED PEOPLE IN EL SALVADOR, LOCATED ON NORTH SECOND AVENUE BETWEEN 15TH AND EAST 17TH STREETS. THE EXPLOSION DID EXTENSIVE DAMAGE TO THIS OFFICE, AND THREE PERSONS WERE SERIOUSLY INJURED, INCLUDING U.S. CITIZEN BRENDA HOOVARIT, 41. ALSO INJURED WERE LUCIO GUTIERREZ AND 4-MONTH-OLD ELMER ANTONIO ALVARENGA, SON OF ARGENTINA ALVARENGA. THEY WERE TAKEN TO A HOSPITAL BY THE RED CROSS.

THE EXPLOSIVE DEVICE, WHICH WENT OFF AT 0230 [0830 GMT], DAMAGED THE COMMITTEE'S BUILDING. RED CROSS WORKERS RUSHSED TO THE SCENE TO TAKE THE INJURED TO THE HOSPITAL. THE BLAST WAS HEARD ALL OVER SAN SALVADOR.

I REPEAT: U.S. CITIZEN BRANDA HOOVARIT, LUCIO GUTIERREZ, AND ELMER ALVARENGA WERE INJURED. THEY WERE TAKEN TO DIFFERENT HOSPITALS BY THE RED CROSS BECAUSE THEY SUSTAINED SERIOUS INJURIES DUE TO THE INTENSITY OF THE EXPLOSION, WHICH DESTROYED THE COMMITTEE'S OFFICES.

DEV-MUC3-0620 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 OCT 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [REPORT] [RAUL BELTRAN] [TEXT] [BELTRAN] A BOMB IN A CAR PARKED OUTSIDE THE FENSATRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] BUILDING DETONATED AND CAUSED A STRONG EXPLOSION. WE CAN REPORT THAT SEVEN PEOPLE WERE KILLED. WE REPEAT: 7 PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND 12 WERE SERIOUSLY INJURED....

[STUDIO REPORTER, INTERRUPTING] WHERE DID THE BOMB EXPLODE?

[BELTRAN] AT THE FENASTRAS BUILDING. LABOR LEADER FEBE ELIZABETH VELASQUEZ AND SEVEN [NUMBER AS HEARD] OTHER PEOPLE WERE KILLED. TWELVE WERE SERIOUSLY INJURED. AMONG THE INJURED ARE TWO GIRLS WHO WERE CLOSE TO THE MAIN ENTRACE OF FENASTRAS' BUILDING. WHEN WE SAY THAT THE EXPLOSION WAS CAUSED BY A CAR BOMB, WE MEAN THAT A PICKUP TRUCK PARKED OUTSIDE THE BUILDING'S MAIN GATE TOTALLY DESTROYED THIS BUILDING. MEETING AT THAT TIME WERE LEADERS OF [2-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR. THIS IS OUR REPORT FROM THE SITE OF THE EXPLOSION.

[STUDIO REPORTER] A FEW MINUTES AGO A CAR BOMB WAS DETONATED OUTSIDE THE FENASTRAS BUILDING. THE BOMB WAS IN A PICKUP TRUCK WITH LICENSE PLATE NUMBER 15242. APPROXIMATELY 7 PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND 12 INJURED, INCLUDING 2 MINORS. IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT THE BUILDING WAS DESTROYED. WE HAVE BEEN INFORMED THAT POLICE UNITS AND SALVADORAN RED CROSS OFFICIALS ARE AT THE SCENE.

DEV-MUC3-0621 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 OCT 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [TEXT] THE ATTACK WITH EXPLOSIVES THAT HAS BEEN PERPETRATED BY UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS AGAINST THE OFFICE OF THE OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO COMMITTEE OF MOTHERS, RELATIVES OF POLITICAL PRISONERS, MISSING, AND MURDERED PEOPLE, LEFT FOUR WOUNDED AND SUBSTANTIAL PROPERTY DAMAGE.

NATIONAL UNION OF SALVADORAN WORKERS, UNTS, SPOKESMEN SAID THAT ONE OF THE WOUNDED IS U.S. CITIZEN BRENDA FUGART, TWO COMADRES ACTIVISTS IDENTIFIED ONLY AS PABLO AND MARGARITA, AND A 4-MONTH-OLD MINOR CALLED NELSON ANTONIO.

THE UNTS MEMBERS SAID THAT PERSONS LIVING NEAR THE OFFICE, LOCATED IN THE SAN MIGUELITO DISTRICT OF THIS CAPITAL, NOTICED THAT THE ATTACKERS WERE SOLDIERS IN UNIFORM.

THE COMADRES MEMBERS HAVE SCHEDULED A NEWS CONFERENCE AT 0900 TODAY AT THE SITE OF THE ATTACK, DURING WHICH THEY WILL REPORT ON THE CONDITION OF THE PEOPLE WOUNDED IN THE EXPLOSION AND THE AMOUNT OF THE PROPERTY DAMAGE, WHICH TOOK PLACE AT 0215 TODAY.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE, COPREFA, DENIED ANY RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK AND, INSTEAD, BLAMED THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. ACCORDING TO COPREFA, ALL THE FMLN HAS TRIED TO DO WITH THIS ATTACK IS TO PAPER OVER YESTERDAY'S FOILED ATTACK AGAINST THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF.

IN ANOTHER REPORT, THE ARMED FORCES CLAIMED IN A REPORT THAT THEY INFLICTED EIGHT CASUALTIES ON THE FMLN IN FIGHTING DURING THE LAST FEW HOURS IN SEVERAL PARTS OF THE COUNTRY. THE MILITARY REPORT POINTS OUT THAT TROOPS ENGAGED INSURGENTS IN THE VILLAGES OF CHIAPAS, TAMULASCO, AND TEPEYAC, ALL OF WHICH ARE IN THE JURISDICTION OF CHALATENANGO, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT. ONE GUERRILLA WAS KILLED, AND FOUR GUERRILLAS AND ONE SOLDIER WERE WOUNDED IN THIS ACTION.

IN ADDITION, IN A BATTLE AT FINCA CATORCE, JURISDICTION OF QUEZALTEPEQUE, LA LIBERTAD, A REBEL WAS KILLED AND TWO WERE WOUNDED. THE MILITARY REPORT ADDS THAT EARLY TODAY THREE HARASSMENT ACTIONS AGAINST CIVIL DEFENSE POSTS WERE REPORTED. THESE TOOK PLACE IN SAN JOSE AGUACATITAN, JURISDICTION OF SAN MARCOS; EL CARRIZALILLO CANTON, IN METAPAN, SANTA ANA; AND AGAINST MEMBERS OF THE ARTILLERY BRIGADE IN ILOBASCO, CABANAS DEPARTMENT. NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED ON EITHER SIDE DURING THESE ACTIONS.

FINALLY, ACCORDING TO A POLICE REPORT, ALLEGED URBAN GUERRILLA COMMANDOS THIS MORNING KILLED AN EMPLOYEE OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE IN SAN SALVADOR. THIS INCIDENT TOOK PLACE AT 0430 TODAY BETWEEN SAN ANTONIO ABAD STREET AND ANTEL - [NATIONAL ADMINISTRATION FOR TELECOMMUNICATIONS] (MONTEBELLO), IN THE WESTERN SECTOR OF THE CAPITAL. THE VICTIM WAS IDENTIFIED AS JUAN CARLOS MERIOS. HE WAS AN ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICIAL OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE. ACCORDING TO THE CORONER'S REPORT, MERIOS' BODY HAD FOUR BULLET WOUNDS.

DEV-MUC3-0622 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 OCT 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] MEDICAL SOURCES HAVE ANNOUNCED THAT OPPOSITION LABOR LEADER FEBE ELIZABETH VELAZQUEZ DIED IN A HOSPITAL THIS AFTERNOON AS A RESULT OF THE DYNAMITE ATTACK AGAINST THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION (FENASTRAS).

THE LABOR LEADER DIED IN THE OPERATING ROOM OF THE HOSPITAL WHERE SHE WAS TAKEN AFTER UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS THIS AFTERNOON PLACED A POWERFUL EXPLOSIVE DEVICE AT FENASTRAS HEADQUARTERS, WHICH LEFT 7 OTHER PEOPLE DEAD AND 30 INJURED.

HOSPITAL SOURCES CONFIRMED AT 1545 (2145 GMT) THAT FEBE VELAZQUEZ, AGE 27 AND THE MOTHER OF THREE, DIED FROM SEVERE SKULL INJURIES.

MEANWHILE, A SALVADORAN RADIO STATION ANNOUNCED THAT UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS THIS AFTERNOON LEVELLED MACHINEGUN FIRE AT A WATCHMAN, WHOSE IDENTITY WAS NOT DISCLOSED, IN A NEIGHBORHOOD IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

THIS MORNING, A CIVILIAN EMPLOYEE AT THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE WAS SHOT TO DEATH IN THE MIRALVALLE NEIGHBORHOOD, ALSO IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

SO FAR NO ORGANIZATION HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THESE TWO MURDERS OR FOR THE PLACEMENT OF THE EXPLOSIVE DEVICE THAT DESTROYED THE FENASTRAS HEADQUARTERS.

AN AMERICAN IDENTIFIED AS MIKE HAMMER, WHO WAS INJURED IN THE ATTACK PERPETRATED BY UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS [AT FENASTRAS HEADQUARTERS], WAS TAKEN TO THE OPERATING ROOM THIS AFTERNOON.

THE LEADING OPPOSITION UNIONS AND NON-GOVERNMENT HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS WILL HOLD A NEWS CONFERENCE THIS AFTERNOON AT THE SITE OF THIS MORNING'S ATTACK.

DEV-MUC3-0624 (MCDONNELL DOUGLAS)

LIMA, 30 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [EXCERPTS] PERUVIAN INTERIOR MINISTRY SOURCES HAVE REPORTED THAT A MEMBER OF THE PERUVIAN NATIONAL POLICE, WHO IS ALSO AND INTERPOL COMMANDER, WAS KILLED TODAY IN LIMA BY PRESUMED SHINING PATH TERRORISTS DURING A OFFENSIVE UNLEASHED 12 DAYS BEFORE THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

IN LIMA, ANOTHER COMMANDO THAT APPARENTLY ALSO BELONGING TO THE MAOIST "SHINING PATH" ARMED ORGANIZATION, SHOT DEAD PERUVIAN NATIONAL POLICE SERGEANT LUIS CACERES TAVARA, 24.

TWO HIGH-VOLTAGE POWER PYLONS WERE SABOTAGED ON THE NIGHT OF 29 OCTOBER, CAUSING A PARTIAL BLACKOUT IN THE PERUVIAN CAPITAL.

DURING THE BLACKOUT, TERRORISTS THREW INCENDIARY BOMBS AT A POLICE PRECINCT, INJURING THREE POLICEMEN.

THE POLICE BELIEVE THAT THESE ATTACKS WAS PERPETRATED BY THE SHINING PATH.

PERUVIAN INTERIOR MINISTRY SOURCES HAVE POINTED OUT THAT 160,000 NATIONAL POLICEMEN ARE CONFINED TO BARRACKS AS OF TODAY. THEIR CONFINEMENT WILL END AFTER THE HOLDING OF THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS ON 12 NOVEMBER.

ACCORDING TO PROVISIONAL DATA, DURING OCTOBER MORE THAN 350 PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN PERU AS A RESULT OF THE TERRORIST OFFENSIVE AGAINST THE ELECTIONS.

THE SHINING PATH HAS CALLED HAS CALLED A BOYCOTT AGAINST THE ELECTIONS AND AN "ARMED STOPPAGE," THAT IS, A STRIKE UNDER THE THREAT OF ATTACKS, FOR 3 NOVEMBER.

IN RESPONSE, THE MAIN POLITICAL PARTIES HAVE ASKED THE PEOPLE TO PARTICIPATE IN A "MARCH FOR PEACE AND THE DEFENSE OF DEMOCRACY." THIS MARCH IS ALSO SCHEDULED FOR 3 NOVEMBER IN LIMA.

DEV-MUC3-0626 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 31 OCT 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] CONCERNING THE MASSACRE AT THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] HEADQUARTERS, THE FMLN REPORTS THE FOLLOWING:

1. WE BLAME THIS COWARDLY CRIME ON THE GENERAL STAFF AND COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, WHO YESTERDAY PROMISED TO REACT TO OUR ATTACKS ON THE GENERAL STAFF. IT HAS BEEN CONFIRMED THAT THE HIGH COMMAND IS WAGING WAR AGAINST THE PEOPLE [WORDS INDISTINCT] ESTABLISHED IN SAN JOSE WITH REGARD TO HIS VIEW OF THE HOSTILITIES, THAT HE CONSIDERS POPULAR MOVEMENTS TO BE FMLN SUPPORT ORGANIZATIONS.

2. THIS TERRORIST ACTION, ADDED TO THOSE COMMITTED AT THE UNIVERSITY; UPON THE HOMES OF POLITICAL LEADERS; AND AT THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO COMMITTEE OF MOTHERS, RELATIVES OF POLITICAL PRISONERS, MISSING, AND MURDERED PEOPLE [COMADRES], WHICH HAVE RESULTED IN 9 DEATHS AND 46 INJURIES, CREATE A NEW SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY THAT FORCES THE PEOPLE'S STRUGGLE TO IMPLEMENT THE USE OF SELF-DEFENSE.

THE FMLN HAD RELAXED SOME OF ITS POSITIONS IN AN EFFORT TO OPEN A TRUE NEGOTIATION PROCESS, BUT THIS INADMISSIBLE SITUATION REAFFIRMS THAT IT IS NOT POSSIBLE TO ABANDON THE ARMED STRUGGLE.

3. THESE EVENTS CARRIED OUT BY THE HIGH COMMAND AND LA TANDONA [NAME GIVEN TO 1966 GRADUATES OF THE CAPTAIN GENERAL GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY SCHOOL] ENDANGER THE CARACAS MEETING.

WE JOIN IN THE PROFOUND GRIEF OF THE POPULAR MOVEMENT AND THE MEMBERS OF FENASTRAS OVER THEIR COMRADES' DEATH, ESPECIALLY THAT OF THEIR BELOVED LEADER FEBE ELIZABETH VELAZQUEZ. ALL OF THESE PEOPLE ARE ADDED TO THE GROWING LIST OF CRIMES THAT THESE SINISTER FORCES HAVE PERPETRATED OVER THE PAST 10 YEARS. ONLY A RESOLUTE, COMBATIVE STRUGGLE WITH WEAPONS IN HAND WILL DO JUSTICE FOR ALL OF THESE CRIMES.

LA TANDONA AND ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] MEAN DICTATORSHIP AND WAR. EVERYONE MUST GO AGAINST ARENA AND LA TANDONA.

[SIGNED] GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FMLN -- COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANTOS SERENG, FRANCISCO BOVELL, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, EDUARDO SANCHO, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS

[DATED] 31 OCTOBER 1989, EL SALVADOR

DEV-MUC3-0629 (GE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 1 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, REGARDING POINT NO. 6 IN WHICH YOU SPOKE ABOUT SPECIFIC RESULTS CONCERNING THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS, TO WHAT SPECIFIC AMOUNTS IS THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT REFERRING TO? ARE YOU SAYING THAT 20 PERCENT, 10 PERCENT OR 50 PERCENT OF THE CONTRAS HAVE TO BE DEMOBILIZED IN ORDER FOR THE CEASE-FIRE TO BE IMPLEMENTED AGAIN?

[ORTEGA] THE IMPORTANT POINT IS TO BEGIN IMPLEMENTING THE PLAN. THEN, THE NUMBER OF CONTRAS THAT ARE DEMOBILIZED WOULD BE ESTABLISHED ACCORDING TO THE DECISIONS MADE AT THE UNITED NATIONS. THAT IS, HOW MANY CONTRAS CAN BE DEMOBILIZED RIGHT AWAY, HOW MANY OF THEM WILL BE RETURNING TO NICARAGUA, HOW MANY WILL GO TO THIRD COUNTRIES. THEREFORE, TO THE EXTENT THE PLAN IS BEING IMPLEMENTED, WE WILL BE WILLING TO REINSTATE THE CEASE-FIRE.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, UP UNTIL LAST WEEK, THE U.S. CONGRESS DISCUSSED GIVING MORE AID TO THE CONTRAS. NO ONE EVEN WANTED TO TALK ABOUT THE CONTRAS, IT WAS A STALE ISSUE. HOWEVER, IT HAS BECOME A BURNING ISSUE OVERNIGHT AND EVERYBODY IS NOW TALKING ABOUT AID FOR THE CONTRAS AND EVEN THE POSSIBILITY OF GIVING MILITARY AID TO THEM. LAST NIGHT, THE U.S. SENATE ISSUED A RESOLUTION STRONGLY CONDENMING THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT. MY QUESTIONS ARE: FIRST, WHY HAS THERE BEEN SUCH A SUDDEN AND UNEXPECTED CHANGE. SECOND, WHAT IS YOUR MESSAGE TO THE U.S. CONGRESS.

[ORTEGA] U.S. CONGRESSMEN ARE ONLY CONCERNED ABOUT THEIR REELECTION. WITH THE DUE RESPECT THAT SOME OF THEM DESERVE, U.S. CONGRESSMEN ARE ONLY WORRIED ABOUT THEIR REELECTION. I HAVE TALKED TO MANY OF THEM HERE AND THEY ARE CYNICAL. THEY TELL ME: I DISAGREE WITH THAT BUT I HAVE TO THINK ABOUT THOSE WHO ELECTED ME. IF THOSE WHO ELECTED ME HAVE A DIFFERENT OPINION, THEN I HAVE TO EXPRESS SUPPORT FOR THEIR VIEWPOINTS AND FORGET ABOUT MY OWN OPINION. LET US NOT MISLEAD OURSELVES. YOU KNOW VERY WELL HOW U.S. CONGRESSMEN ACT. THEREFORE, IT WAS EASIER FOR THEM TO SIMPLY APPROVE FUNDS FOR THE CONTRAS AS THEY HAD DONE -- BECAUSE THE CONGRESS HAD APPROVED THE SO-CALLED HUMANITARIAN AID FOR THE CONTRAS [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND LET THE WAR CONTINUE, AND LEAVE THE BURDEN ON THE CENTRAL AMERICAN GOVERNMENTS, ESPECIALLY ON THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE WHO ARE SUFFERING THE EFFECTS OF THIS WAR. THEREFORE, WE HAVE BEEN REPORTING THE KILLINGS, THE ASSASSINATIONS, THE CRIMES, THE CONTRAS ATTACKS, AND THE YANKEE CONGRESS HAS REMAINED SILENT.

THEREFORE, WE SEE AN EASY-GOING ATTITUDE IN THE U.S. CONGRESS. OBVIOUSLY, WHEN WE ANNOUNCE WE ARE NOT GOING TO EXTEND THE CEASE-FIRE THE U.S. CONGRESS REACTS IMMEDIATELY. THEY REACT BECAUSE THEY ARE FULLY AWARE THAT THEY ARE MEDDLING IN NICARAGUAN POLITICS. THEY WILL HAVE TO RESUME DISCUSSIONS ON THE NICARAGUAN ISSUE, AND THEY DO NOT WANT TO DISCUSS THE NICARAGUAN ISSUE AGAIN. IT WAS EASY TO SET ASIDE THE NICARAGUAN ISSUE AND TO SIMPLY APPROVE FUNDS FOR THE CONTRAS SO THE CONTRAS COULD CONTINUE KILLING NICARAGUANS WHILE EVERYTHING ELSE REMAINS CALM -- LET THE PEACE PLAN CONTINUE AS FAR AS IT CAN AND AS FAR AS PRESIDENT BUSH ALLOWS IT TO DEVELOP. THE U.S. CONGRESSMEN CAN THEN FORGET ABOUT THE NICARAGUAN ISSUE AND WORK ON OTHER DOMESTIC OR INTERNATIONAL ISSUES IN WHICH THEY ARE MORE INTERESTED.

HOWEVER, WHEN NICARAGUA SAYS: WE WILL NOT EXTEND THE CEASE-FIRE, THEN THEY RAISE AN OUTCRY. WHY DO THEY RAISE AN OUTCRY? BECAUSE THEY KNOW THEY WILL HAVE TO RESUME DISCUSSIONS ON THE NICARAGUAN ISSUE. MOREOVER, THERE MIGHT BE A FEVERISH CONGRESSMAN WHO WILL PROPOSE GIVING MILITARY AID TO THE CONTRAS. WELL, LET THEM DISCUSS MILITARY AID. DO THEY WANT TO DISCUSS MILITARY AID, WELL THAT IS THEIR PROBLEM. WE SIMPLY BELIEVE THAT THE WAY THE YANKEE CONGRESS ACTIONS WILL EASE OR HINDER THE ELECTORAL PROCESS. THE DEVELOPMENT OF ELECTIONS ON 25 FEBRUARY WILL DEPEND NOW ON THE YANKEE CONGRESS AND ON THE YANKEE PRESIDENT. IT WILL DEPEND ON THEM. WE HAVE THE DESIRE TO DO IT. HOWEVER, WHETHER OR NOT THE ELECTIONS ARE HELD ON 25 FEBRUARY WILL DEPEND ON THEM. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0632 (GE)

LIMA, 1 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT TODAY TURNED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE INTERNAL ORDER IN LIMA OVER TO THE ARMED FORCES, 2 DAYS BEFORE AN "ARMED STRIKE" DECLARED BY THE MAOIST SHINING PATH TERRORIST GROUP GOES INTO EFFECT.

ACCORDING TO AN OFFICIAL REPORT, THE MILITARIZATION OF LIMA WAS DECLARED AT THE SAME TIME A GROUP OF 100 HOODED SHINING PATH ACTIVITS STAGED A DEMONSTRATION, ENGAGED IN A SHOOT-OUT, AND HURLED EXPLOSIVES AT THE POLICE IN LA VICTORIA DISTRICT.

INTERIOR MINISTER AGUSTIN MATILLA REPORTED THAT 2 PEOPLE DIED AND 15 OTHERS WERE WOUNDED IN THE THE CLASH, WHICH PLACE WHILE A RELIGIOUS GROUP WAS CARRYING OUT A PEACEFUL MARCH.

ACCORDING TO A DECREE, THE ARMED FORCES WILL TAKE CONTROL OF LIMA DEPARTMENT AND EL CALLAO PROVINCE, NEXT TO THE CAPITAL, WHERE A STATE OF EMERGENCY IS IN FORCE.

ON 23 OCTOBER, THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT EXTENDED FOR 1 MONTH THE STATE OF EMERGENCY IN LIMA DUE TO AN OUTBURST OF THE POLITICAL VIOLENCE THAT HAS RESULTED IN MORE THAN 350 DEATHS NATIONWIDE LAST MONTH.

DESPITE THE STATE OF EMERGENCY, WHICH SUSPENDS IMPORTANT CONSTITUTIONAL GUARANTEES, UNTIL TODAY INTERNAL ORDER WAS THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE NATIONAL POLICE.

PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA TODAY TOLD THE MEDIA THAT THE POLICE ARRESTED 149 PEOPLE, OF WHOM ABOUT 100 ARE ALLEGED SHINING PATH MEMBERS, DURING TODAY'S RIOTS.

THE PERUVIAN CHIEF OF STATE SAID THAT THE RIOTS WERE MEANT "TO HINDER" THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS SCHEDULED FOR 12 NOVEMBER. HE ADDED THAT HIS ADMINISTRATION WILL EXERT "ALL THE NECESSARY ENERGY TO COMBAT SUBVERSION."

THE SHINING PATH MEMBERS TODAY DEMONSTRATED WITH SHOUTS FAVORING THE "ARMED STRUGGLE," AND THEY HANDED OUT LEAFLETS CALLING ON THE PEOPLE TO ENGAGE IN AN "ARMED STRIKE" ON 3 NOVEMBER.

THE SHINING PATH, WHICH HAS BEEN ENGAGING IN WARFARE FOR THE PAST 10 YEARS, INTENDS TO PARALYZE LIMA WITH THE "ARMED STRIKE" -- A GENERAL STRIKE UNDER ARMED COERCION -- ONLY 9 DAYS BEFORE THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS.

THE "SHINING PATH" HAS ALSO ANNOUNCED IT INTENDS TO BOYCOTT THE ELECTIONS [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] LEADER OF THE ORGANIZATION, ABIMAEL GUZMAN.

THE MAIN PERUVIAN POLITICAL PARTIES, THE CHURCH, AND LABOR AND PROFESSIONAL ORGANIZATIONS HAVE CALLED, FOR THE SAME DAY, A DEMONSTRATION IN FAVOR OF PEACE AND IN DEFENSE OF DEMOCRACY, WHICH IS CONSIDERED TO BE THREATENED BY TERRORISM.

THE "SHINING PATH" HAS INTENSIFIED ITS ARMED ACTIVITIES NATIONWIDE DUE TO THE 12 NOVEMBER MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS. AS A RESULT, HUNDREDS OF CANDIDATES HAVE WITHDRAWN FROM THE RACE.

IN ITS PROCLAMATIONS, THE "SHINING PATH" THREATENED "TO ANNIHILATE, SOONER OF LATER" ALL CANDIDATES WHO RUN IN THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS. THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS ARE BEING HELD JUST 6 MONTHS BEFORE THE PRESIDENTIAL AND CONGRESSIONAL ELECTIONS, WHICH ARE SCHEDULED FOR 8 APRIL 1990.

DEV-MUC3-0633 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 NOV 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [ALFREDO VILLARREAL] [TEXT] FOR THE THIRD DAY IN A ROW, THE BLOODBATH CONTINUES TO ROCK THIS CAPITAL CITY AND THE END TO THIS SITUATION, WHICH IS ALARMING THE PEOPLE, DOES NOT SEEM TO BE NEAR. ACCORDING TO REPORTS, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] URBAN COMMANDS FAILED ONCE AGAIN THIS AFTERNOON WHEN THEY ATTACKED THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE LOCATED IN LAICO NEIGHBORHOOD. THE FMLN URBAN COMMANDS FIRED TWO RPG-2 ROCKET LAUNCHERS WHICH HIT A PRIVATE VEHICLE WITH LICENSE PLATE 72246 THAT WAS PASSING THE MILITARY GARRISON. AS A RESULT OF THE REBEL ATTACK, AN AGRONOMIST, IDENTIFIED AS 57- YEAR- OLD JOSE HERMOGENES MARTINEZ, WAS KILLED. WE DID NOT TAKE PICTURES OF HIS BODY BECAUSE IT WAS TOTALLY MUTILATED AS A RESULT OF THE STRONG EXPLOSION. ALSO INJURED WAS A STREET VENDOR IDENTIFIED AS MARIA DEL CARMEN PEREZ.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] THERE WERE FOUR MEN IN A PICKUP, TWO SEATED IN FRONT AND TWO IN THE BACK. THE TWO WHO WERE IN THE BACK TOOK OUT THE BAZOOKAS AND FIRED ON THE GARRISON'S GATE. A MAN DRIVING A SUZUKI DROVE AT THE SAME TIME THE ROCKETS WERE LAUNCHED AND HE WAS HIT.

[REPORTER] HOW MANY PEOPLE WERE IN THE VEHICLE?

[UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] FOUR. THE CAR WHERE THE INJURED MAN WAS? ONLY ONE PERSON, THE MAN WHO WAS INJURED.

[REPORTER] HOW MANY PEOPLE WERE IN THE VEHICLE FROM WHERE THE ROCKETS WHERE FIRED?

[UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] FOUR PERSONS.

[REPORTER] AT WHAT TIME DID THAT HAPPEN?

[UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] ABOUT 30 MINUTES AGO, AT APPROXIMATELY 1530.

[REPORTER] HOW MANY ROCKETS WERE FIRED?

[UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] TWO.

[SECOND UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] THE MAN WAS IN THE CAR. AFTER THE DEVICES EXPLODED -- WE DO NOT KNOW WHAT KIND WERE FIRED -- THERE WAS SMOKE AND GUNPOWDER ALL OVER THE PLACE. HIS CLOTHES AND BODY WERE TOTALLY DESTROYED. WHEN WE TOOK HIM TO THE ROSALES HOSPITAL WE TALKED TO A DOCTOR, AND HE SAID THAT THEY WERE GOING TO DO ALL THEY COULD TO SAVE HIS LIFE. [END RECORDING]

MEANWHILE, COLONEL FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES, COMMANDER OF THE MILITARY GARRISON, REGRETTED THE ATTACK AND SAID THAT THESE ATTACKS ARE WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE VIOLENCE UNLEASHED IN THE PAST FEW DAYS BY GROUPS THAT ARE OUT OF CONTROL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [FUENTES] YOU HAVE ALREADY SEEN THE VEHICLE. WE BELIEVE THE ROCKETS WERE AIMED AT THE GATE, AT THE GUARDS STANDING AT THE ENTRANCE OF THE HEADQUARTERS. PERHAPS THEY WERE AIMED AT ME BECAUSE I HAD BEEN IN THE AREA 5 MINUTES EARLIER.

THOSE PEOPLE ARE COMPLETELY OUT OF THEIR MINDS. THEY DO NOT CARE IF THE KILL INNOCENT CIVILIANS. THESE COULD BE GROUPS THAT THE FMLN CAN NO LONGER CONTROL OR PERHAPS THEY ARE ONLY KILLERS WHO ONLY KNOW HOW TO MURDER PEOPLE. [END RECORDING]

THE INJURED PERSONS WERE TAKEN TO ROSALES HOSPITAL IN SAN SALVADOR WHERE THEY WERE GIVEN EMERGENCY TREATMENT. THE STREET VENDOR SAYS THAT IT WAS A MIRACLE THAT SHE WAS NOT KILLED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PEREZ] I DO NOT KNOW WHAT HAPPENED. I WAS JUST SITTING THERE AND I HEARD THE NOISE [WORDS INDISTINCT]. [END RECORDING]

MEANWHILE, THE FMLN URBAN GUERRILLAS SET FIRE TO A PUBLIC BUSH IN SANTA MARTA, SAN JACINTON NEIGHBORHOOD. THE REBELS DISTRIBUTED LEAFLETS STATING THAT THEY BURNED THE BUS IN REPRISAL FOR THE KILLING OF LEFTIST LEADER FEDE ELIZABETH VELASQUEZ.

DEV-MUC3-0635 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 2 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE GUERRILLAS' ANNOUNCEMENT TODAY THAT THEY DECIDED TO SUSPEND THEIR DIALOGUE WITH THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT CAUSED GREAT SURPRISE AMONG VARIOUS CIRCLES IN THE COUNTRY THAT VOWED TO MAKE NEW EFFORTS TO REESTABLISH THEM.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) SUSPENDED ITS DIALOGUE WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TO PROTEST A DYNAMITE ATTACK ON THE HEADQUARTERS OF A LABOR UNION ON 31 OCTOBER THAT LEFT 10 DEAD AND 30 INJURED.

ACCORDING TO THE GUERRILLAS, THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DYNAMITE ATTACK ON THE SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION (FENASTRAS).

THE FMLN, IN A COMMUNIQUE SIGNED BY ITS TOP FIVE LEADERS, STATED THAT "WE MUST NOT ALLOW OUR PRESENCE IN THE DIALOGUE TO BE USED TO COVER UP THE GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSIBILITY FOR THAT MASSACRE."

IT ALSO DEMANDED THAT THE OAS, UNITED NATIONS, AND THE CHURCH OFFER GUARANTEES TO EL SALVADOR'S OPPOSITION GROUPS.

REVEREND EDGAR PALACIOS, COORDINATOR OF THE PERMANENT COMMITTEE FOR THE NATIONAL DIALOGUE (CPDN), WHICH IS MADE UP OF OVER 60 SOCIAL ORGANIZATIONS, TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT "WE REGRET THIS KIND OF DECISION VERY MUCH, BUT WE WILL IMMEDIATELY CONTACT THE GUERRILLAS TO TRY TO RESUME THE DIALOGUE."

PALACIOS ADDED THAT "IF THE DOOR OF DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION IS CLOSED, THE DOOR OF WAR WILL OPEN."

EDUARDO COLINDRES, LEADER OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY, THE MAIN OPPOSITION PARTY, SAID THAT THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS "MUST CONTINUE."

"THE GOVERNMENT OF THE RIGHTIST NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) MUST INVESTIGATE AND PUNISH THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CRIME COMMITTED AGAINST FENASTRAS; HOWEVER, THE DIALOGUE MUST NOT BE SUSPENDED," COLINDRES ADDED.

JUAN JOSE MARTEL, LEADER OF THE SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT (MPSC), WHICH IS A MEMBER OF THE LEFTIST DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE, EXPRESSED SURPRISE OVER THE GUERRILLAS' DECISION.

MARTEL SAID THAT RIGHT-WING SALVADORAN GROUPS ARE TRYING TO ELIMINATE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, WHICH SEEKS TO END THE WAR THROUGH NEGOTIATED POLITICAL MEANS.

SO FAR, NO GOVERNMENT SPOKESMAN HAS REACTED TO THE FMLN'S DECISION TO SUSPEND THE DIALOGUE THAT BEGAN IN MID-SEPTEMBER AND WOULD HAVE CONTINUED ON 20 AND 21 NOVEMBER IN CARACAS, VENEZUELA.

PALACIOS, ALONG WITH OTHER RELIGIOUS, POLITICAL, AND LABOR LEADERS, HEADED A MARCH TO ACCOMPANY THE BODIES OF 10 WORKERS WHO WERE KILLED DURING THE DYNAMITE ATTACK ON THE FENASTRAS HEADQUARTERS IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR, ONLY 200 METERS FROM A NATIONAL POLICE GARRISON.

THE UNION MEMBERS' BODIES, INCLUDING THAT OF FENASTRAS LEADER FEBE ELIZABETH VELASQUEZ, WERE ACCOMPANIED BY SEVERAL THOUSAND WORKERS WHO SHOUTED ANTIGOVERNMENT SLOGANS AND CARRIED RED FLOWERS.

TENSION WAS HIGH DURING THE MARCH, MAINLY BECAUSE OF THE HEAVY MILITARY PRESENCE IN SAN SALVADOR'S MAIN STREETS AND BECAUSE THE UNION MEMBERS DETAINED AT LEAST 30 PLAINCLOTHES POLICEMEN WHO, ACCORDING TO THE UNIONISTS, INFILTRATED THE DEMONSTRATION.

THE MARCH ENDED AT THE GENERAL CEMETERY WHERE THE BODIES OF THE UNION MEMBERS WERE BURIED.

DEV-MUC3-0638 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 4 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] VICE PRESIDENT FRANCISCO MERINO SAYS THAT THE GUERRILLAS ARE HURTING THEMSELVES BY CARRYING OUT ATTACKS SUCH AS THE ONE PERPETRATED RECENTLY. HE SAID THE REBELS ARE ACTING LIKE OSTRICHES BY HIDING THEIR HEADS UNDER THE SAND.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] LOGICALLY THAT IS NO SOLUTION. THEY MUST REALIZE THAT THE PEOPLE HAVE REJECTED THEM. THE PEOPLE CONDEMN ALL OF THESE ACTIONS. THE LATEST ATTACKS ARE HURTING THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] ITSELF. THEY HAVE BEEN ISOLATED INTERNATIONALLY, THE PEOPLE HAVE REJECTED THEM, AND THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMY ARE FULFULLING THEIR CONSTITUTIONAL ROLE. THEREFORE, THEY MUST CONTINUE WITH THE TALKS AND PARTICIPATE IN THEM SERIOUSLY BY REACHING AGREEMENTS THAT CAN BRING PEACE TO ALL. THE TERRORIST AGGRESSION MAKES NO SENSE.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION? WILL IT CONTINUE WITH THE TALKS? WILL IT GO TO THE TALKS EVEN IF THE GUERRILLA COMMANDERS DO NOT ATTEND?

[MERINO] THE GOVERNMENT DEFINITELY HAS A COMMITMENT TO THE PEOPLE. IT IS A COMMITMENT THE GOVERNMENT HAS MADE. BESIDES OUR WILLINGNESS TO ACHIEVE PEACE WE ARE ALSO COMMITTED TO THESE TALKS. WE WILL CONTINUE ON THIS ROAD. IT IS CERTAINLY A DIFFICULT ROAD BUT WE MUST CONTINUE ON IT. I BELIEVE THAT THE SAN JOSE MEETING LIKE THE ONE IN CARACAS, AND MAYBE OTHERS AFTER THAT, HAS BEEN QUITE DIFFICULT. HOWEVER, WE HAVE DISCUSSED ALL THE PROBLEMS AND THE GUERRILLAS WILL LOGICALLY REACH THE CONCLUSION THAT THEY WILL HAVE TO SIT DOWN AT THE TABLE.

[REPORTER] THEY ASK FOR GUARANTEES FOR LABOR ORGANIZATIONS.

[MERINO] I BELIEVE WE CANNOT GIVE THEM MORE GUARANTEES THAN THE ONES WE HAVE ALREADY GIVEN THEM. THERE IS A GENERAL FEELING THAT THESE PEOPLE ONLY UNDERSTAND STRONG ACTIONS. HOWEVER, THE GOVERNMENT HAS REVIEWED THE SITUATION QUITE WELL, AND WE ARE NOT GOING TO FALL INTO THAT TRAP OR MAKE THAT MISTAKE. OTHERWISE, WE WOULD GIVE THEM THE OPPORTUNITY TO ACCUSE THE GOVERNMENT. WE WILL LOGICALLY BE PRUDENT. [END RECORDING]

VICE PRESIDENT MERINO SAID THAT DESPITE THE DIFFICULTIES THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO CONTINUE THE DIALOGUE. THE FMLN GUERRILLAS WITHDREW FROM THE TALKS AND DEMANDED SECURITY FOR LABOR UNION ORGANIZATIONS FOLLOWING THE ATTACK AGAINST FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION], IN WHICH 10 LABOR UNION MEMBERS WERE KILLED, INCLUDING OPPOSITION LEADER ELIZABETH VELAZQUEZ.

NEXT WEEK, GUERRILLA LEADERS WILL MEET IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA WITH PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS TO SEEK SOLUTIONS TO THE COMPLEX SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0639 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [EL SALVADOR GOVERNMENT] [TEXT] CONCERNING THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] COMMUNIQUE, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HEREBY ANNOUNCES THE FOLLOWING:

1. ON THE DAY OF THE TERRORIST ATTACK AGAINST FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION], THE GOVERNMENT STRONGLY CONDEMNED THE ATTACK AND ANNOUNCED ITS PLANS TO CARRY OUT A THOROUGH INVESTIGATION. HOWEVER, IT IS REGRETTABLE THAT FENASTRAS LEADERS HAVE BEEN HINDERING THE INVESTIGATIONS THAT COULD CLEAR UP THE ATTACK.

NONETHELESS, THE GOVERNMENT REITERATES ITS DETERMINATION TO CARRY OUT A THOROUGH INVESTIGATION, AND WILL EVEN BRING TO THE COUNTRY SOME EXPERTS IN THIS FIELD SO THAT WITH THE HELP OF MODERN SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY THEY WILL HELP THE INVESTIGATIVE COMMITTEE CLARIFY THIS BLOODY AND CRIMINAL ATTACK AND ESTABLISH WHO IS RESPONSIBLE.

LIKEWISE, THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO APPOINT A COMMISSION THAT WILL GUARANTEE THE INVESTIGATIONS, AND IT WILL INVITE THE FOLLOWING: ONE REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE UNITED NATIONS; ONE REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE OAS; ONE REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE SALVADORAN BISHOPS' CONFERENCE; ONE REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE POLITICAL PARTIES; TWO LABOR UNION REPRESENTATIVES, ONE OF THEM BEING FROM FENASTRAS; DR IGNACIO ELLACURIA [JESUIT PRIEST AND RECTOR OF THE JOSE SIMEON CANAS CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY]; THE ATTORNEY GENERAL OF THE REPUBLIC; AND THE MINISTER OF JUSTICE.

2. THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC HAS SUPPLIED EVIDENCE FROM THE BEGINNING THAT IT IS SINCERELY SEEKING PEACE. THE DIALOGUE COMMISSION ATTENDED A FIRST MEETING WITH THE FMLN IN MEXICO, AND ACCEPTED A COMMITMENT, AS FOLLOWS, AND I QUOTE: BOTH PARTIES COMMIT THEMSELVES NOT TO WITHDRAW UNILATERALLY FROM THE DIALOGUE.

THE FMLN'S WITHDRAWAL FROM THE DIALOGUE IS NOT ONLY A VIOLATION OF THE MEXICO AGREEMENT, BUT ALSO [WORD INDISTINCT] THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S HOPES FOR PEACE. FAR FROM SUSPENDING THE DIALOGUE, THE FMLN SHOULD UNDERSTAND THAT THE SEARCH FOR PEACE IS NOW MORE NECESSARY THAN EVER IN ORDER TO HALT THE BLOODSHED.

3. EVIDENTLY, IN SITUATIONS LIKE THIS ONE, THE ENEMIES OF PEACE ARE TRYING TO MAKE THE DIALOGUE FAIL. THE RECENT TERRORIST ACTIONS ARE AN INSULT TO THE CIVILIZED MECHANISMS THAT HAVE COME UP AT THE NEGOTIATIONS TABLE.

THE GOVERNMENT HEREBY NOTIFIES THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY THAT THE DIALOGUE COMMISSION WILL CONTINUE TO DO ITS WORK, AND IT WILL NOT WITHDRAW FROM THE TALKS IN SPITE OF THE SORROWFUL EVENTS THAT HAVE BROUGHT MORE MOURNING TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE IN RECENT DAYS.

4. IN THESE DIFFICULT MOMENTS THAT OUR COUNTRY IS EXPERIENCING, THE GOVERNMENT REITERATES ITS CALL FOR THE PEOPLE TO REMAIN CALM, SO THAT IN A PRUDENT AND UNDERSTANDING MANNER WE WILL JOIN EFFORTS TO HELP REACH PEACE AND NOT PROMOTE VIOLENCE, WHICH ONLY SERVES TO HINDER THE DIALOGUE.

[ISSUED IN] SAN SALVADOR, 3 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0640 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 4 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN, COMMANDER SALVADOR SANCHEZ, ALIAS COMMANDER LEONEL GONZALEZ, MEMBER OF THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] COMMANDER LEONEL GONZALEZ, ON FRIDAY NIGHT MR ALFREDO CRISTIANI ANNOUNCED SOME MEASURES WHICH THE GOVERNMENT WILL ADOPT IN CONNECTION WITH FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] AND THE DIALOGUE. THE FMLN ANNOUNCED IT HAD SUSPENDED ITS TRIP TO CARACAS, BUT CRISTIANI SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION WILL GO TO CARACAS REGARDLESS OF OUR DECISION. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION ON THE GOVERNMENT'S DECISION?

[GONZALEZ] IN MY OPINION, TWO POSITIONS ON THE DIALOGUE AND THE NEGOTIATIONS PROCESS WERE MADE EVIDENT IN SAN JOSE. THE GOVERNMENT OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND VIEW THE DIALOGUE AS AN OPPORTUNITY FOR TALKING, BUYING TIME, AND BUILDING A GOOD IMAGE FOR THEMSELVES. ON THE OTHER HAND, THE FMLN IS WORKING FOR A REAL NEGOTIATIONS PROCESS. THE FMLN HAS OPENED A BROADER DEBATE, A DEBATE THAT INCLUDES DISCUSSIONS WITH AND THE PARTICIPATION OF POLITICAL PARTIES, THE SOCIAL FORCES, THE CHURCH, ALL THE SECTORS. WE HAVE INITIATED A NATIONAL DIALOGUE. AS WE SEE IT, THE GOAL IS PART OF A WHOLE, IT IS NOT EVERYTHING. THE ENTIRE PROCESS OF ALLOWING THE PARTICIPATION OF THE SOCIAL FORCES IS IMPORTANT ALSO.

IN RECENT DAYS WE HAVE SEEN ACTIONS UNPRECEDENTED IN THE HISTORY OF EL SALVADOR. THERE WAS THE ATTACK ON WORKERS IN WHICH 10 WORKERS DIED AND 31 WERE INJURED. THE FMLN CANNOT IGNORE THIS FACT. THIS IS PART OF THE PROCESS. WE HAVE SAID THAT WE ARE GOING TO ESTABLISH CONTACT WITH OBSERVERS AND MEDIATORS TO ANALYZE THE SITUATION, AND WE WILL DISCUSS THIS PROCESS WITH THE POLITICAL PARTIES AND THE SOCIAL FORCES. WHAT WE WANT IS TO CONSOLIDATE THE NEGOTIATIONS PROCESS. WE ARE NOT TRYING TO ENHANCE OUR IMAGE; OUR PEOPLE KNOW WHO IS TELLING THE TRUTH.

IN SAN JOSE WE MADE A SOLUTION PROPOSAL THAT ENVISAGES DEMOCRACY, HUMAN RIGHTS, AND A PROCESS TO FIND A WAY OUT OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. ON MONDAY AND WEDNESDAY OF NEXT WEEK WE ARE GOING TO MEET IN WASHINGTON WITH OAS AND UN REPRESENTATIVES. ALSO ON MONDAY IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, WE COULD BE IN CONTACT WITH THE COSTA RICAN GOVERNMENT TO ANALYZE THE SITUATION.

WE WILL ANALYZE DEVELOPMENTS TO DETERMINE THE POSITION OF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT. IF ACTIONS BY THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT CLOSE THE POSSIBILITIES OF CARACAS, THEN WE WILL ADOPT MEASURES. WHAT WE HAVE DONE IS TO ANNOUNCE A SUSPENSION TO CREATE CONDITIONS FOR MAKING PROGRESS TOWARD REAL NEGOTIATIONS, AS THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENTS ESTABLISH.

[REPORTER] THEN WHY IS THE GOVERNMENT GOING TO CARACAS, COMMANDER?

[GONZALEZ] I BELIEVE THAT THE ANNOUNCEMENT ON THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION GOING TO CARACAS IS AIMED AT ENHANCING THE GOVERNMENT'S IMAGE, AT CREATING A SMOKE SCREEN AROUND THE MASSACRE COMMITTED AGAINST THE POPULAR MOVEMENT.

[REPORTER] NOW THAT YOU MENTION THE FENASTRAS MASSACRE, WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THE CREATION OF A COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE THIS CASE THAT CRISTIANI HAS ANNOUNCED?

[GONZALEZ] ONE OF THE POINTS OF OUR SAN JOSE PROPOSAL CALLS FOR CHANGING THE SALVADORAN LEGAL SYSTEM BECAUSE IT IS VITIATED AND IS IN THE HANDS OF ONE SINGLE PARTY. SO, IN THIS FRAMEWORK, CONDUCTING AN INVESTIGATION IS LIKE PUTTING THE CASE INSIDE A FORGOTTEN DRAWER. THIS IS WHAT HAPPENED TO THE MONSIGNOR ROMERO CASE, THE CASE OF THE REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT LEADERS, AND THE CASES OF THOUSANDS OF WORKERS WHO HAVE BEEN MURDERED AND WHOSE CASES HAVE BEEN FORGOTTEN. THE PURPOSE OF THIS COMMISSION IS TO CREATE A SMOKE SCREEN AROUND THE GRAVE HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS BEING COMMITTED BY THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT. WE BELIEVE THAT THE PERSONS WHO HAVE BEEN INVITED TO FORM PART OF THIS COMMISSION SHOULD NOT LEND THEMSELVES TO PLAYING A PART IN THE EFFORT TO HIDE WHAT IS REALLY BEHIND ALL THIS. WHAT THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT WANTS IS TO DIVERT AWAY FROM EMILIO PONCE ALL THE ACCUSATIONS AND CHARGES, AND PONCE IS THE ONE WHO IS DIRECTLY INVOLVED IN THIS KIND OF ATTACK. THE STATE POLICY OF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT IS REPRESSION, AND THIS STATE POLICY IS BEING IMPLEMENTED BY THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT, CRISTIANI, AND THE HIGH COMMAND, AND THEY ARE DOING IT THROUGH THE REPRESSIVE BODIES, REGARDLESS OF WHETHER THEY FUNCTION AS CIVILIANS, AS DEATH SQUADS, OR IN UNIFORM. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0641 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 2 NOV 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] COLONEL FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES, COMMANDER OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, IN ANALYZING RECENT ACTS OF VIOLENCE IN SAN SALVADOR, HAS REPORTED THAT GROUPS OUT OF THE CONTROL OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT - REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT [FMLN -FDR] ALLIANCE COULD BE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MOST RECENT ACTS OF VIOLENCE.

THE MILITARY COMMANDER WAS CAREFUL IN MAKING HIS STATEMENT. HE SAID THAT HE HAS NO EVIDENCE THAT THOSE GROUPS ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE EXPLOSIONS IN THE SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION [FENASTRAS] AND COMADRES [COMMITTEE OF MOTHERS AND RELATIVES OF THE PAST, THE ARMY HAS BEEN BLAMED, AND LATER IT HAS BEEN DISCOVERED THAT FMLN TERRORISTS HAD CARRIED THEM OUT.

ELENA FUENTES RECALLED THAT A FEW DAYS AGO THERE WAS AN EXPLOSION ON THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY CAMPUS AND HE WENT THERE AND IT WAS ESTABLISHED IN FRONT OF STUDENT LEADERS THAT THE EXPLOSION WAS CAUSED BY A GRENADE THAT WENT OFF IN THE HANDS OF A YOUNG LEFTIST WHO WAS HANDLING IT. BY THEN, HOWEVER, STATEMENTS HAD ALREADY BEEN MADE ACCUSING THE MILITARY.

ELENA FUENTES ALSO REFERRED TO INTERNAL PURGES WITHIN COMMUNIST GROUPS, PURGES LIKE THE CASE OF MELIDA ANAYA MONTES, ALIAS COMMANDER MARIA; SALVADOR CAYETANO CARPIO, ALIAS MARCIAL; AND OTHERS.

HE SAID: "IT WOULD NOT BE STRANGE TO FIND THAT THESE ACTIONS HAVE BEEN THE RESULT OF A PURGE OR A DIVERSIONARY TACTIC BY THE COMMUNISTS TO ATTRACT POLITICAL ATTENTION AND GAIN THE PEOPLE'S SUPPORT, WHICH EVERYBODY BELIEVES THEY ARE LOSING."

IT WAS RECALLED, WITH ALL DUE RESPECT, THAT THE NAME OF ONE OF THE VICTIMS OF THE FENASTRAS ATTACK, FEBE ELIZABETH VELASQUEZ, WAS MENTIONED IN THE INVESTIGATIONS BEING CARRIED OUT BY INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS OVER THE EMBEZZLEMENT OF AID FROM EUROPEAN COUNTRIES THAT WAS TO BENEFIT THE MOST NEEDY PEOPLE IN OUR COUNTRY, BUT THAT ENDED UP IN THE HANDS OF TERRORIST GROUPS TO BE USED FOR TERRORIST PURPOSES.

ELENA FUENTES STATED: "TIME AND INVESTIGATIONS WILL TELL WHAT REALLY HAPPENED."

HE SAID THAT THE PURPOSE OF THESE ATTACKS, ESPECIALLY THE ONE ON THE DEFENSE MINISTRY, FOR WHICH THE FMLN - FDR CLAIMED CREDIT, AS WELL AS THE ATTACKS ON COMADRES AND FENASTRAS, WAS TO GIVE THE FMLN - FDR LEADERSHIP JUSTIFICATION TO WITHDRAW FROM THE DIALOGUE.

ELENA FUENTES SAID THAT THE TERRORIST GUADALUPE MARTINEZ SAID IN MANAGUA YESTERDAY THAT THE LEFTIST LEADERSHIP IS CONSIDERING NOT GOING TO THE DIALOGUE MEETINGS BECAUSE OF THE ATTACKS.

DEV-MUC3-0642 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 5 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] IT HAS BEEN REPORTED IN THIS CAPITAL THAT A DELEGATION OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) WILL MEET THIS WEEK IN WASHINGTON WITH UN AND OAS REPRESENTATIVES TO ANALYZE THE COUNTRY'S SITUATION AND THE FUTURE OF THE TALKS BETWEEN THE REBELS AND ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S ADMINISTRATION.

COMMANDER LEONEL GONZALEZ, ONE OF THE FIVE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND MEMBERS, ISSUED A STATEMENT THROUGH RADIO VENCEREMOS -- THE OFFICIAL VOICE OF THE GUERRILLA ORGANIZATIONS -- AND SAID THAT THE MEETINGS WILL START TOMORROW 6 NOVEMBER.

OTHER FMLN DELEGATES WILL MEET TOMORROW WITH COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS, WHO HAS STATED HIS CONCERN REGARDING THE TALKS BETWEEN THE REBELS AND CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT AFTER RIGHT-WING SQUADS ASSASSINATED 10 LABOR LEADERS.

COMMANDER GONZALEZ SAID "THAT THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION'S DOUBLE-FACED CONDUCT IS PRECLUDING THE POSSIBILITIES FOR ACHIEVING A PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT."

"THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION AND THE ARMY OPPOSE REAL NEGOTIATIONS, AND THEIR CONCEPT OF A DIALOGUE IS TO TALK AND TALK -- BUT ONLY TO GAIN TIME AND PROJECT A GOOD IMAGE AT THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL LEVEL," THE REBEL LEADER SAID.

REFERRING TO THIS, GONZALEZ ASSERTED THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S DECISION TO SEND ITS DELEGATION TO THE 20-21 NOVEMBER MEETING IN CARACAS, WHETHER THE GUERRILLA REPRESENTATIVES ATTEND IT OR NOT, IS AIMED AT "CREATING A SMOKE SCREEN TO COVER THE MASSACRES PERPETRATED THIS WEEK AGAINST THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT."

COMMANDER GONZALEZ ALSO REFERRED TO CRISTIANI'S ANNOUNCEMENT THAT A COMMISSION WILL BE CREATED WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF UN AND OAS DELEGATES TO INVESTIGATE THE 10 LABOR LEADERS' MASSACRE.

"IT IS IMPOSSIBLE TO CARRY OUT AN INVESTIGATION WITH A CORRUPT JUDICIAL SYSTEM LIKE THE ONE IN EL SALVADOR ," GONZALEZ SAID. HE RECALLED THAT THE AUTHORITIES HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO SOLVE THE MURDER OF SAN SALVADOR ARCHBISHOP OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO IN 10 YEARS. THE GUERRILLA BLAMES MAJOR ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON, ONE OF THE GOVERNMENT PARTY'S IDEOLOGISTS, FOR ROMERO'S MURDER.

THE FMLN COMMANDER ALSO WARNED THAT THE ARMY "HAS LAUNCHED A CAMPAIGN TO CONFUSE NATIONAL AND WORLD OPINION BY ACCUSING THE GUERRILLAS OF PERPETRATING TERRORIST ACTIONS."

THE ARMED FORCES ACTUALLY WANT "TO COVER UP THEIR REPRESSIVE POLICY BECAUSE THEY HAVE SHIFTED FROM SELECTIVE ARRESTS TO MASS ARRESTS -- AND FROM GENOCIDE TO INDISCRIMINATE ATTACKS," HE ADDED.

THE GUERRILLA COMMANDER ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT THE GUERRILLA FORCES WILL MAINTAIN A HIGH LEVEL OF MILITARY ACTIONS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY AS LONG AS THERE IS NO POSSIBILITY OF CONTINUING A REAL DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION PROCESS WHICH LEADS THE COUNTRY TO AN EVERLASTING PEACE.

DEV-MUC3-0643 (GE)

MOSCOW (USSR), 5 OCT 89 (RADIO PEACE AND PROGRESS) -- [COMMENTARY] [MARINA PETROVSKAYA] [TEXT] THE US HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES HAS APPROVED BY A MAJORITY VOTE AN ANTI-NICARAGUAN RESOLUTION WHICH GRANTS $4 MILLION WORTH OF SO-CALLED HUMANITARIAN AID FOR THE CONTRAS. ANALYST MARINA PETROVSKAYA DISCUSSES THE SUBJECT.

THIS RESOLUTION IN ESSENCE ALLOWS THE CONTINUATION OF THE DIRTY WAR AGAINST NICARAGUA. THE SOMOSA FORCES HAVE LATELY INCREASED THEIR TERRORIST ACTIONS IN SEVERAL PARTS OF NICARAGUA BY KILLING CIVILIANS AND SANDINIST SOLDIERS. AS WITNESSED BY THE [WORD INDISTINCT], THIS HAS NOT HAPPENED BY CHANCE. MANY CONTRAS TURNED THEMSELVES INTO THE NICARAGUAN AUTHORITIES WHEN AND AMNESTY WAS DECLARED. THEY ADMITTED THAT THEY RECEIVED ORDERS FROM THEIR LEADERS IN HONDURAS TO CROSS THE BORDER AND, BY MEANS OF TERROR AND THREAT, FORCED CIVILIANS TO VOTE FOR THE OPPOSITION CANDIDATES.

SUPRISINGLY, THE SOMOSA FORCES HAVE NOT AIMED AT MORE AMBITIOUS GOALS. INSTEAD OF BEING CONDEMNED BY WASHINGTON THEY ARE RECEIVING COMPLEMENTARY AID FROM IT. CURIOUSLY, THIS NEW [WORD INDISTINCT] FOR THE CONTRAS COINCIDES WITH THE GRANTING OF $9 MILLION TO FINANCE THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN OF THE NICARAGUAN OPPOSITION, JUST WHEN MRS VIOLETA DE CHAMORRO HAS RECEIVED $3 MILLION FOR HERSELF.

SUCH US GOVERNMENT AID FOR THE NICARAGUAN RIGHTIST SECTORS ALARMS THE NICARAGUAN AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITIES. ELECTIONS WILL BE HELD IN NICARAGUA IN A FEW MONTHS FOLLOWING THE NATIONAL DEMOCRATIZATION PROCESS WHICH IS BEING CONDUCTED IN KEEPING WITH THE COMMITMENTS ASSUMED BY THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT, ACCORDING TO INTELLIGENCE REPORTS FROM GUATEMALA AND HONDURAS.

THIS DEMOCRATIZATION PROCESS CANNOT BE NORMAL SINCE CONFRONTATIONS BETWEEN CONTRAS AND [WORD INDISTINCT] ARE INCREASING, AND THESE ARE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE UNITED STATES. AS IS KNOWN, THE SANDINIST AUTHORITIES HAVE BEEN FORCED TO SUSPEND THE CESSATION OF MILITARY OPERATION AGAINST THE SOMOSA FORCES, WHICH HAD BEEN IN EFFECT SINCE MAY 1988.

MEANWHILE, WASHINGTON HAS ACCUSED THE SANDINISTS OF VIOLATING DEMOCRACY AND OF HINDERING A [WORD INDISTINCT] POLITICAL SOLUTION.

[WORDS INDISTINCT] SUCH AN EVALUATION OF THE SANDINIST ACTION IS UNJUST IN ORDER TO ACHIEVE PEACE AND SECURITY IN THE REGION, INCLUDING NICARAGUA, IT IS NECESSARY THAT ALL THE PARTIES INVOLVED IN THE CONFLICT MAKE AN EFFORT, NOT JUST ONE.

LOOK AT THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR THESE DAYS. IT LOOKED LIKE THE CONDITIONS FOR A CEASE-FIRE HAD IMPROVED AND THIS IS WHY WE APPLAUDED THE NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. BUT THE PROGRESS MADE WAS REJECTED BY THE RIGHTIST GROUPS WHICH REFUSED TO HOLD CONSTRUCTIVE NEGOTIATIONS. THIS IS WHY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] REFUSES TO HOLD THE THIRD ROUND OF NEGOTIATIONS UNTIL THE GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS CHANGE THEIR OLD METHODS OF SOLVING INTERNAL PROBLEMS WITHOUT GUARANTEEING THE SECURITY OF THE LEFTIST FORCES.

IT SEEMS TO ME THAT THE EVENTS TAKING PLACE IN NICARAGUA AND EL SALVADOR ARE SIMILAR BECAUSE THE PEACE EFFORTS IN THE TWO COUNTRIES ARE BEING OBSTRUCTED BY MILITARY FORCES FINANCED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT, WHICH CONTINUES TO KEEP A HEATED ENVIRONMENT IN THOSE COUNTRIES AND TO LOOK FOR SOLUTIONS FROM A POSITION OF FORCE.

DEV-MUC3-0645 (GE)

TEGUCIGALPA, 7 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] POLICE SOURCES REPORTED TODAY THAT JORGE CASTILLO GARCIA, NICARAGUAN CONSUL IN COSTA RICA, WHO CAME HERE TO PROMOTE THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS, WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED. HE WAS SHOT ON THE EVENING OF 5 NOVEMBER AT A TEGUCIGALPA RESTAURANT.

ARNALDO AMADOR, SECURITY GUARD AT THE DOMOS RESTAURANT TOLD POLICE THAT CASTILLO, VISIBLY DRUNK, TRIED TO TAKE A MOTORCYCLE FROM IN FRONT OF THE RESTAURANT. AMADOR ORDERED CASTILLO TO SURRENDER, BELIEVING HE WAS A THIEF.

ACCORDING TO AMADOR THE NICARAGUAN CONSUL ATTACKED HIM, HITTING HIM ON THE HEAD. AMADOR SAYS HE THEN SHOT CASTILLO WITH HIS SUBMACHINEGUN, WOUNDING HIM IN THE LEFT SIDE OF THE CHEST, VERY NEAR THE HEART.

CASTILLO GARCIA WAS RUSHED TO THE HOSPITAL WHERE HE IS NOW "RECOVERING", WHILE AMADOR HAS BEEN ARRESTED BY THE POLICE.

A FEW MINUTES AFTER THE INCIDENT, WHICH OCCURRED AT 2200 ON 5 NOVEMBER, DONAL OLIVA, SECRETARY OF THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY HERE, CAME TO THE RESTAURANT TO GET DETAILS OF THE INCIDENT.

OLIVA SAID THAT CASTILLO GARCIA HAD LEFT THE EMBASSY ABOUT 2 HOURS BEFORE. HE SAID THAT CASTILLO HAD ARRIVED IN HONDURAS LAST WEEK TO PROMOTE THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS, ESTABLISHED ALONG THE NICARAGUAN BORDER.

DEV-MUC3-0646 (GE)

MOSCOW (USSR), NO DATE (RADIO MAGALLANES) -- [STATEMENT] [CHILEAN COMMUNIST PARTY] [TEXT] THE COUNTRY IS EXPERIENCING ONE OF THE WORST ANTICOMMUNIST AND TERRORIST CAMPAIGNS IN A LONG TIME. THIS CAMPAIGN IS SIMILAR TO THE ONE UNLEASHED BETWEEN 1964 AND 1970. THE SITUATION IS FURTHER AGGRAVATED BECAUSE IT IS TAKING PLACE UNDER A DICTATORSHIP THAT WILL STOP AT NOTHING TO ACHIEVE ITS OBJECTIVES.

DURING HIS SPEECH IN COIHAIQUE, PINOCHET THREATENED TO END THE STATE OF LAW. THIS HAS BEEN FOLLOWED BY OTHER THREATS BY [DEPUTY OPPONENTS, AND BY EQUALLY THREATENING STATEMENTS AND SYSTEMATIC AGGRESSION AGAINST ARMY MEMBERS WHO CRITICIZE THE DICTATORIAL REGIME.

MEANWHILE EL MERCURIO AND THE PROGOVERNMENT NEWS MEDIA HAVE ORCHESTRATED A CAMPAIGN THAT IS FINANCED BY BUCHI'S ELECTORAL MANAGERS. THIS CAMPAIGN USES EDITORIALS, ATTRIBUTED ARTICLES, AND PAID ADS THAT ARE AIMED AT MISINFORMING AND MANIPULATING PUBLIC OPINION.

THE OBJECTIVE IS TO CREATE A MOOD OF AGGRESSION TOWARD THE LEFT AND TOWARD THE COMMUNIST PARTY, A MOOD THAT WOULD JUSTIFY ANY KIND OF PROVOCATION.

THE WORST EXAMPLE WAS A RECENT PAID AD PUBLISHED BY BUCHI'S ELECTORAL MANAGERS ON AN ALLEGED THREAT OF COMMUNIST STRIKE SQUADS THAT WERE GOING TO GUN DOWN THE PROGOVERNMENT CANDIDATE. IT IS WELL KNOWN THAT THIS STATEMENT, REPORTEDLY MADE BY A YOUNG CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY LEADER TO LA SEGUNDA ON 31 OCTOBER, WAS LATER FLATLY DENIED BY THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC LEADER HIMSELF. DESPITE THIS DENIAL, BUCHI'S CAMPAIGN MANAGERS ARE STILL HARPING ON THE SUBJECT, TRYING TO CREATE AN ATMOSPHERE OF VIOLENCE AND UNEASE.

THE BRUTAL MURDER OF JECAR NEGHME, UNSOLVED LIKE SO MANY OTHERS, HAS BEEN FOLLOWED BY OTHER SERIOUS EVENTS INCLUDING THE KIDNAPPING OF THE DRIVER OF VOLODIA TEITELBOIM, THE SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY. THIS WAS A THREAT TO COMRADE VOLODIA TEITELBOIM'S SAFETY AND PHYSICAL INTEGRITY. THERE HAS ALSO BEEN HARASSMENT OF LEADERS AND CANDIDATES OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY AND OTHER DEMOCRATIC PARTIES, AN INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF ARBITRARY ARRESTS OF OPPONENTS IN GENERAL, THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A NEW JOINT COMMAND HEADED BY THE DEFENSE MINISTER. THE ALLEGED OBJECTIVE OF THIS COMMAND IS TO FIGHT CRIME, BUT THE PEOPLE HAVE RIGHTLY GUESSED THAT IT IS A COVER FOR POLITICAL REPRESSION SIMILAR TO THAT CONDUCTED BY A PRIOR ORGANIZATION THAT BORE THE SAME NAME.

IN THIS ANTICOMMUNIST AND ANTIDEMOCRATIC ATMOSPHERE, MEETINGS HAVE BEEN HELD WITH OFFICERS AND RELATIVES OF MILITARY MEN. DURING THESE MEETINGS THE AUDIENCE IS MISINFORMED, THREATENED, AND URGED TO OPPOSE DEMOCRATIC CHANGES. THEY ARE ALSO URGED TO HOARD STAPLES AND TO TAKE SPECIAL MEASURES TO PROVIDE FOR EXTREME CONTINGENCIES.

THERE IS YET ANOTHER ESPECIALLY SERIOUS DEVELOPMENT ABOUT WHICH WE WANT TO INFORM THE PEOPLE. WE HAVE RECEIVED INFORMATION FROM VARIOUS SOURCES TO THE EFFECT THAT THE CROWNING POINT OF THIS ANTICOMMUNIST CAMPAIGN WILL BE AN ATTACK ON A HIGH-RANKING ARMY OFFICER WHO HAS BEEN CRITICIZED FOR HIS INVOLVEMENT IN HUMAN-RIGHTS VIOLATIONS. THE CHARGES AGAINST THIS OFFICER MADE BY COMMUNIST PARTY CANDIDATES FOR SENATORS, AND THE DEMONSTRATIONS HELD AGAINST HIM BY THE RELATIVES OF THE VICTIMS, WILL BE USED TO BLAME THE COMMUNISTS FOR THIS ATTACK.

WE WANT TO REITERATE OUR ABSOLUTE REJECTION OF HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS AND OUR DEMAND FOR TRUTH AND JUSTICE. HOWEVER, WE ALSO WANT TO MAKE IT CLEAR THAT WE ARE STRUGGLING TO HAVE EVERY CRIME AND EVERY VIOLATION INVESTIGATED AND THE CULPRITS TRIED.

THE ATMOSPHERE OF FEAR AND PSYCHOLOGICAL WARFARE IS AIMED AT TWISTING THE POPULAR WILL OF THE CHILEAN PEOPLE AND DESTABILIZING IN ADVANCE THE NEXT DEMOCRATIC ADMINISTRATION.

WE CALL UPON THE CITIZENRY TO BE PREPARED TO DISPLAY UNITY AND DEMOCRATIC ORGANIZATION SO AS TO GUARANTEE THE NORMAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE ONGOING ELECTORAL PROCESS AND TO BE ON GUARD AGAINST ANY PROVOCATION AIMED AT CREATING A CLIMATE FAVORABLE TO AN INTERRUPTION OF THE PROCESS. WE MUST DEPLOY OUR FORCES IF WE ARE TO ENSURE THE VICTORY OF FREEDOM AND DEMOCRACY IN A LANDSLIDE VICTORY FOR PATRICIO AYLWIN ON 14 DECEMBER AND THE ELECTION OF A CONGRESS CAPABLE OF GUARANTEEING PROGRESS TOWARD THE GOVERNMENT SYSTEM THAT MOST CHILEANS WANT.

SIGNED: CHILEAN COMMUNIST PARTY

DATED: SANTIAGO, 2 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0647 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 7 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH VENANCIO SALVATIERRA, WITH NOM DE GUERRE OF MARIO LOPEZ, A COMMANDER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [SALVATIERRA] FROM THIS STANDPOINT, THE PROPOSAL BROUGHT BY THE CHRISTIANI GOVERNMENT DELEGATION TO SAN JOSE SOUGHT TO GAIN TIME WHILE KEEPING THE IMAGE THAT THE GOVERNMENT WAS ENGAGED IN A DIALOGUE. HOWEVER, THE GOVERNMENT WAS NOT REALLY SEEKING THE PATH TOWARD A NEGOTIATION. ON THE CONTRARY, IT SOUGHT TO CONDUCT UNDER THE SHADOW OF THE DIALOGUE ACTIONS THAT WILL GIVE IT AN ADVANTAGE OVER THE FMLN, INCLUDING TERRORIST ATTACKS LIKE THIS ONE. THE OPERATION AGAINST THE FENASTRAS LEADERSHIP IS PART OF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT POLICY, AND SO IS THE WAVE OF REPRESSION AGAINST THE MASS MOVEMENT FROM THE ONSET OF THIS GOVERNMENT.

THE PROPOSAL SUBMITTED IN COSTA RICA INCLUDED MASS GROUPS AS PART OF THE ENEMY. ALL THESE THINGS ARE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT POLICY. WE CANNOT ALLOW THE GOVERNMENT TO HIDE THIS POLICY BEHIND THE DIALOGUE, AS THIS POLICY ALLOWS ACTIONS LIKE THE ONE AT FENASTRAS TO GO UNPUNISHED AND DO NOT LEAD TO A TRUE SOLUTION OF THE CONFLICT. THAT IS WHY THE FMLN SUSPENDED ITS PARTICIPATION IN CARACAS, BUT HAS NOT SUSPENDED ITS PARTICIPATION IN THE DIALOGUE. IN FACT, THE FMLN HAS UNDERTAKEN BIDS TO CONDUCT A MEDIATION SO THAT THE ADEQUATE CONDITIONS FOR A DIALOGUE ARE CREATED AND ACTIONS LIKE THE ONE IN FENASTRAS DO NOT CONTINUE. DEEP DOWN, WE FEEL THAT IN ORDER FOR THE DIALOGUE TO TURN INTO A NEGOTIATION THAT WILL END THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT...[CHANGES THOUGHT] THE PROGRESS OF THE MASS MOVEMENT IN EL SALVADOR WITH ALL THE EXISTING FORMS OF STRUGGLE IS WHAT WILL COMPEL THE OTHER SIDE TO REALLY SIT DOWN AT THE NEGOTIATIONS TABLE.

SO LONG AS THE OTHER SIDE FEELS THAT IT CAN DEFEAT THE PEOPLE, IT WILL NOT BE TRULY COMMITTED TO NEGOTIATING AN END TO THE CONFLICT. WHEN IT SEES THAT THE PEOPLE WILL DEFEAT IT, AND THAT IT IS FORCED TO NEGOTIATE, THEN A NEGOTIATION WILL TRULY TAKE PLACE IN THE COUNTRY.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER MARIO LOPEZ, THE LATEST DEVELOPMENTS, EVEN FOLLOWING THE FENASTRAS ATTACK, INDICATE THAT GOVERNMENT POLICY DOES NOT SEEM TO CHANGE REGARDING THE HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS AND THREATS TO THE MASS MOVEMENT. IN FACT, THE LUTHERAN CHURCH, OR RATHER ITS PASTOR LEARDO GOMEZ, HAS RECEIVED DEATH THREATS. DO YOU THINK AN INTERNAL PURGE IN THE ARMED FORCES IS POSSIBLE? DO YOU THINK THAT WITH THAT INTERNAL PURGE IT CAN BE POSSIBLE TO STOP THE EXTREME HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS IN THE COUNTRY?

[SALVATIERRA] THE FMLN HAS PROPOSED AN INTERNAL PURGE IN THE ARMED FORCES AS AN IMPORTANT FACTOR IN THE PROCESS OF DIALOGUE OR NEGOTIATIONS, MEANING THAT THE ARMED FORCES THEMSELVES MUST GET RID OF THE CORRUPT AND CRIMINAL ELEMENTS. HOWEVER, THE CRUX OF THE MATTER IS THE NEED TO PURGE THE ARMED FORCES. THE FMLN HAS TOLD THEM: PURGE YOURSELVES. HOWEVER, THAT IS PRACTICALLY IMPOSSIBLE. ON ONE SIDE, THE NEED TO HAVE A TRUE PURGE IN THE ARMED FORCES BECOMES APPARENT, BECAUSE OTHERWISE WE CANNOT MAKE PROGRESS AND HAVE TRUE DEMOCRACY IN OUR COUNTRY. RECENT DEVELOPMENTS ARE PROVING THE FMLN IS RIGHT. ON THE OTHER SIDE, IT IS CLEAR THAT THE CRIMINAL ELEMENTS CONTROL THE MILITARY POWER AND HAVE INFLUENCE OVER THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL POWER.

THE PRESENCE OF LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO 1966 GRADUATES OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY SCHOOL] IN FRONT OF THE TELEVISION CAMERAS, FOLLOWING THE DIALOGUE SESSION IN COSTA RICA, WAS MEANT TO TELL THE PEOPLE: WE RULE AND CAN DO AS WE PLEASE. THEN THE ATTACKS CAME. I FEEL THAT THE NEED TO END THAT SITUATION IS EVIDENT TO ALL, AS WELL AS HOW RIGHT THE FMLN STAND IS. I NOW WANT TO REITERATE THAT WE CANNOT ACHIEVE THAT GOAL UNLESS WE FORCE THE ARMED FORCES AND THE GOVERNMENT TO CARRY OUT THAT PURGE. BY FORCING THEM, I MEAN THAT THE PEOPLE'S FORCE MUST TELL THEM TO DO THAT IF THEY WANT TO SURVIVE. THE DEMAND THAT COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE [CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF] LEAVE, AS HE IS ONE OF THE CHIEF CULPRITS OF THE ABOVE-MENTIONED POLICY, WILL GROW STRONGER. THE PEOPLE MUST PRESS AND ARE PRESSING THIS DEMAND.

DEV-MUC3-0648 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 7 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH VENANCIO SALVATIERRA, WITH NOM DE GUERRE OF MARIO LOPEZ, A COMMANDER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] COMMANDER MARIO LOPEZ, FOLLOWING RECENT INCIDENTS AND TERRORIST ACTIONS SUCH AS THE ATTACK ON FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION], THE U.S. OFFICIAL ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INTER-AMERICAN AFFAIRS BERNARD ARONSON CAME TO OUR COUNTRY. HE SAID THAT U.S. ASSISTANCE WILL DEPEND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT HIS VISIT TO OUR COUNTRY?

[SALVATIERRA] IT IS BASICALLY AIMED AT SAVING CRISTIANI'S PRESTIGE AND IMAGE, AS THIS HAS BEEN A MATTER OF GREAT CONCERN FOR THE U.S. GOVERNMENT FROM THE BEGINNING. THEY NEED A POTABLE IMAGE, AN IMAGE THAT PORTRAYS LEGITIMACY, AND AN IMAGE OF MODERATION THAT WILL NOT ISOLATE THE GOVERNMENT INTERNATIONALLY. THE FENASTRAS INCIDENT UNDOUBTEDLY UNMASKED CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT. THEREFORE, ARONSON'S VISIT IS AIMED AT SAVING CRISTIANI'S IMAGE AND SUPPORTING CRISTIANI'S INITIATIVE OF CREATING A COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE THOSE INCIDENTS, IN ORDER TO FOSTER HOPES AND CREDIBILITY AMONG SOME GROUPS REGARDING THE GOVERNMENT'S INTEREST IN CLARIFYING THE INCIDENTS. THAT WAS ARONSON'S INTENTION.

AS A MATTER OF FACT, CRISTIANI'S IMAGE IS IMPORTANT FOR THE AID ITSELF. ASPECTS RELATED TO HUMAN RIGHTS PLAY A VERY IMPORTANT ROLE IN THE DEBATES AT THE U.S. CONGRESS, WHERE THE AID IS APPROVED. THEREFORE, THAT AID WOULD BE ENDANGERED IF THE DEBATES ON VIOLATIONS OF HUMAN RIGHTS IN EL SALVADOR ARE INTENSIFIED. IT COULD HAVE AN EFFECT ON THAT. SO WHAT THEY ARE REALLY TRYING TO SAVE IS THE AID TO CONTINUE SUPPORTING THE WAR.

IN THAT REGARD, WE MUST ALSO REMEMBER THAT WITHIN THE DOCTRINE OF LOW INTENSITY WARFARE, THE POLITICAL ASPECTS OF THE COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN PLAY AN IMPORTANT ROLE [WORDS INDISTINCT] THAT WILL NOT APPEAR TO BE IN THE EXTREME RIGHT; A GOVERNMENT THAT APPEARS TO BE MORE IN THE CENTER THAN IN THE EXTREME RIGHT, IN ORDER TO CREATE EXPECTATIONS WITHIN SOME GROUPS REGARDING THE GOVERNMENT'S CREDIBILITY, AND ALSO AT THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL. WHILE TRYING TO DEFEAT THE REBELS MILITARILY AND THROUGH REPRESSION, IT IS NECESSARY TO MAINTAIN AN ACCEPTABLE IMAGE OF THE GOVERNMENT.

[REPORTER] YOU ARE A MEMBER OF THE FMLN'S POLITICAL-DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION. AS A RESULT OF THE FENASTRAS INCIDENTS, OUR FRONT CANCELLED ITS ATTENDANCE AT THE CARACAS MEETING. WHAT ARE THE POSSIBILITIES FOR RESTORING THE TALKS AND CONTINUING THE DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION WITH THE GOVERNMENT?

[SALVATIERRA] THE FMLN IS INTERESTED IN A REAL DIALOGUE, A DIALOGUE THAT WILL LEAD TO A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION OF THE CONFLICT; IN OTHER WORDS, A DIALOGUE THAT WILL LEAD TO NEGOTIATIONS. WE DIFFER WITH CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT ON THIS. FROM THE BEGINNING, ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] HAS EXPRESSED ITS WILLINGNESS TO PARTICIPATE IN A DIALOGUE, BUT NOT TO NEGOTIATE. THEY HAVE A TOTALLY DIFFERENT CONCEPT. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0649 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 7 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THREE MILITANTS OF THE SALVADORAN LEFTIST SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT (MPSC) HAVE BEEN KILLED BY ARMY SOLDIERS IN THE CITY OF SONSONATE, APPROXIMATELY 50 KM WEST OF SAN SALVADOR, ACCORDING TO MEMBERS OF THAT POLITICAL ORGANIZATION.

AMONG THE VICTIMS ARE CECILIO RIVERA, WHO WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR MPSC ORGANIZATIONAL ACTIVITIES IN EASTERN SONSONATE DEPARTMENT. RIVERA WAS SHOT TO DEATH ALONG WITH TWO OTHER PARTY MILITANTS WHOSE IDENTITIES WERE NOT REVEALED. JUAN JOSE MARTEL, A TOP MPSC LEADER, TOLD AFP THAT AFTER LEAVING THE ORGANIZATION'S OFFICE ON THE NIGHT OF 6 NOVEMBER, THREE MEMBERS WERE ARRESTED BY "A GROUP OF ARMED SOLDIERS IN CIVILIAN CLOTHES BELONGING TO SONSONATE'S MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6.

"WE HAVE LEARNED OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN CAPTURED BY THESE SAME INDIVIDUALS AND HAVE APPEARED IN THE GARRISON LATER ON. THEREFORE, WE HAVE NO DOUBT THAT ARMY SOLDIERS KILLED THEM," HE ADDED.

MARTEL EXPLAINED THAT THE THREE BODIES WERE FOUND ON TUESDAY NEAR THE CITY'S CEMETERY WHERE THEY WERE GOING TO BE BURIED BY LOCAL AUTHORITIES AS UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS. HE NOTED THAT, BY CHANCE, A NEIGHBOR IDENTIFIED RIVERA, AND THIS ALLOWED HIM TO SPREAD THE NEWS.

THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE TRIPLE CRIME LEFT A PIECE OF PAPER ON THE BODIES WHICH READ: "BECAUSE THEY BETRAYED THE FATHERLAND."

CONDEMNING THIS MURDER, MARTEL SAID THAT "THIS NEW ACTION SHOWS, ONCE MORE, THAT IN EL SALVADOR THERE IS NO DEMOCRACY AND NO RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, AND THE DEATH SQUADS CONTINUE TO OPERATE."

ON 19 OCTOBER, SUSPECTED DEATH SQUAD MEMBERS STAGED A BOMB ATTACK ON THE HOME OF MPSC SECRETARY GENERAL RUBEN ZAMORA, WOUNDING TWO PEOPLE AND CAUSING CONSIDERABLE PROPERTY DAMAGE.

DEV-MUC3-0650 (GE)

LIMA, 7 NOV 89 (MOSCOW KRASNAYA ZVEZDA) -- [TEXT] SUBUNITS OF THE PERUVIAN GROUND FORCES AND POLICE, SUPPORTED BY ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS, HAVE CONDUCTED A MAJOR OPERATION TO ARREST GROUPS OF ARMED EXTREMISTS ON THE STUDENT CAMPUS OF THE SAN MARCOS STATE UNIVERSITY. THE OPERATION TOOK PLACE AFTER SEVERAL TERRORISTS BROKE INTO THE BUILDING OF THE NATIONAL INDUSTRIALISTS SOCIETY, WHERE THEY SET OFF THREE BOMBS CAUSING EXTENSIVE DAMAGE TO THE BUILDING. AFTER THE ATTACK THE EXTREMISTS FLED TO THE UNIVERSITY CAMPUS.

AS A RESULT OF THE OPERATION AROUND 100 STUDENTS WERE ARRESTED ON SUSPICION OF TERRORIST ACTIVITY. WEAPONS, AMMUNITION, AND SUBVERSIVE LITERATURE WERE CONFISCATED FROM SOME OF THEM.

POLITICAL TERRORISM HAS BECOME PART OF EVERYDAY LIFE IN PERU. RECENTLY A SERIES OF ARMED ATTACKS HAS BEEN CARRIED OUT IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY BY THE EXTREMIST GROUPING SENDERO LUMINOSO, WHICH IS TRYING TO DISRUPT THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS PLANNED FOR 12 NOVEMBER. IN TIRAPATA VILLAGE (PUNO DEPARTMENT) A SENDERO LUMINOSO DETACHMENT SEIZED THE LOCAL MAYOR AND SHOT HIM IN THE CENTRAL SQUARE IN FRONT OF LOCAL RESIDENTS WHO HAD BEEN MADE TO GO THERE. IN THE TOWN OF SAN CLEMENTE TERRORISTS THREW BOMBS AT THE HOMES OF MAYORAL CANDIDATES FROM VARIOUS POLITICAL PARTIES. IN THE VILLAGE OF CORIS (ANCASH DEPARTMENT) SENDERO LUMINOSO FIGHTERS SET FIRE TO THE TELEPHONE EXCHANGE AND THE MUNICIPAL COUNCIL AND ALSO TOOK AWAY THE INHABITANTS' VOTING CARDS -- THE MAIN IDENTIFICATION DOCUMENT IN AN ELECTION. THEY THREATENED TO DEAL WITH ANYONE WHO TAKES PART IN THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS.

AS A RESULT OF THE EXTREMISTS' THREATS AROUND 90 MAYORAL CANDIDATES HAVE WITHDRAWN THEIR NOMINATIONS, AS HAVE HUNDREDS OF CONTENDERS FOR MUNICIPAL COUNCIL SEATS.

DEV-MUC3-0652 (GE)

NO CITY (HONDURAS), 8 NOV 89 -- [INTERVIEW WITH AZCONA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] NICARAGUA SAYS THAT THE HONDURAN ARMY IS MOVING THE CONTRAS TO OLANCHO THIS WEEK SO THEY WILL ESCAPE INSPECTION BY [WORD INDISTINCT].

[AZCONA] NO, NO, NO. THE HONDURAN ARMY HAS NO RELATIONSHIP, NO CONTACTS, WITH THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARIES. [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF CARLOS FLORES' SPEECH IN...[CHANGES THOUGHT] WHICH HAS BEEN SEVERELY CRITICIZED BY SOME AND PRAISED BY OTHERS [WORDS INDISTINCT]?

[AZCONA] I THINK IT WAS A GOOD SPEECH. IT IS DIRECTLY IN LINE WITH WHAT I HAVE SAID; THAT IS, THAT THE IMF'S PRESCRIPTIONS CANNOT BE ACCEPTED AND APPLIED TO THIS COUNTRY, FOR INSTANCE, BECAUSE THE PEOPLE WILL NOT PUT UP WITH MEASURES LIKE THOSE WHICH HAVE BEEN PROPOSED BY THE IMF AND ENDORSED BY HONDURAN PRIVATE ENTERPRISE.

[REPORTER] WHAT ABOUT FLORES' STATEMENTS SAYING THAT RELATIONS WITH THE UNITED STATES WILL BE DIFFERENT IN HIS GOVERNMENT?

[AZCONA] I DO NOT KNOW. THE RELATIONS WITH MY GOVERNMENT HAVE BEEN RELATIONS OF TOTAL UNITY. I THINK HE WAS NOT REFERRING TO THIS ADMINISTRATION. HE MUST HAVE BEEN REFERRING TO A PREVIOUS

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[AZCONA] NO. I AM NOT BEING PRESSURED. WHAT I SAID THE OTHER DAY HAS BEEN MISINTERPRETED. WHEN I SAID I NEEDED OXYGEN, IT WAS NOT OXYGEN THAT NEWSMEN, OR BUSINESSMEN, OR INTELLECTUALS WERE GOING TO GIVE ME. I WAS GOING TO GIVE MYSELF THE OXYGEN BY NOT VETOING AN AMENDMENT TO THE LAW ON ELECTIONS THAT INCREASES THE POLITICAL DEBT AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] PER VOTE, PITTING THE PARTIES AGAINST EACH OTHER--MY PARTY AND THAT OF OUR ADVERSARY. IN OTHER WORDS, I AM NOT ASKING FOR FAVORS FROM ANYONE OR ANY SUCH THING. I HAVE MY CHIN HELD HIGH. NOW, IF ANYBODY THROWS A BLOW AT ME I WILL RETURN IT IF I CAN. I WILL DO SO WITHIN THE BOUNDS OF NOBLENESS AND PROPRIETY, BUT I WILL RETURN IT. SO, IT IS NOT A QUESTION OF ME ASKING FOR OXYGEN. I AM QUITE AT EASE, NOT LIKE A MINI-EDITORIAL WRITER SAID THE OTHER DAY--EDITORIAL WRITERS CAN BE QUITE MEAN, YOU KNOW [LAUGHTER]--WHO SAID THAT I SLEPT LIKE A LOG THE FIRST 2 YEARS. I ALWAYS SLEEP LIKE A LOG [LAUGHTER] AND DO NOT [WORD INDISTINCT].

THOSE WHO THOUGHT THEY WOULD MAKE ME LEAVE HERE A PHYSICAL WRECK OR SOMETHING OF THAT SORT WILL NOT SUCCEED. I THINK HE IS THE ONE WHO CANNOT SLEEP LIKE A LOG WITH THE DIRTY CONSCIENCE HE MUST HAVE BECAUSE OF THE DREADFUL THINGS THAT ARE WRITTEN IN THOSE EDITORIALS.

[REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, IT HAS BEEN LEARNED THAT AID HAS EVEN CUT THE AID FOR SMALL PROGRAMS, BECAUSE...[CHANGES THOUGHT] AND THAT HONDURAS HAS TO PAY OVER 2 MILLION [CURRENCY NOT SPECIFIED]...

[AZCONA] [INTERRUPTING] THAT IS NOT TRUE, NOT TRUE. ALL AID PROGRAMS ARE ONGOING. A FEW DAYS AGO, THE PRESS ALSO MADE AN IMPROPER INTERPRETATION WHEN I SAID THAT MILITARY AID WAS BEING CUT. NO. WHAT HAPPENS IS THAT, IN THE CASE OF AID, IF THERE IS A DELAY IN PAYMENTS OF OVER 1 YEAR ON ANY PROGRAM, THE DISBURSEMENTS OF ALL PROGRAMS ARE STOPPED. THERE WAS A PAYMENT CORRESPONDING TO MILITARY AID, OR MILITARY COMMITMENTS, THAT HAD NOT BEEN MADE. SO, WE HAD TO MAKE IT BECAUSE OTHERWISE THE DISBURSEMENTS NOT ONLY OF THE MILITARY SECTOR BUT OF ALL WOULD BE SUSPENDED. IN OTHER WORDS, ALL THAT IS COVERED, AND, AS I SAY, ALL THAT IS PROCEEDING QUITE WELL. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0653 (GE)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 8 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMY SAID TODAY THAT TWO "ATTACKERS" HAD LOST THEIR LIVES WHEN THEY CONFRONTED SOLDIERS AFTER HAVING "ROBBED AND RAPED" THE OWNER OF A BUSINESS IN A CITY OF WESTERN EL SALVADOR. OPPOSITION SOURCES, HOWEVER, REJECTED THIS ACCOUNT AND DESCRIBED THE INCIDENT AS "MURDER."

JUAN JOSE MARTELL, LEADER OF THE SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT (MPSC, OPPOSITION), REJECTED THE MILITARY VERSION AND ACCUSED THE ARMY OF "MURDERING" PARTY LEADER CECILIO RIVERA AND TWO OTHER PARTY SUPPORTERS.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE SAID THAT RIVERA AND APOLINARIO ALFARO -- THE THIRD PERSON WAS NOT MENTIONED -- LOST THEIR LIVES WHEN THEY CONFRONTED, ALONG WITH FOUR OTHER MEN, TROOPS OF MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6, IN SONSONATE, 65 KM WEST OF SAN SALVADOR.

THE MILITARY REPORT ADDED THAT THE "CRIMINALS" HAD ROBBED A SMALL SHOP, WHOSE OWNER, MARIA TERESA LOPEZ, HAD BEEN "RAPED" BY THE ATTACKERS.

MARTELL SAID THAT THE BODIES OF THE [MPSC] MEMBERS WERE FOUND LAST NIGHT AT THE SONSONATE CEMETERY ALONG WITH A SIGN THAT READ: "BECAUSE THEY BETRAYED THE FATHERLAND."

"WE HAVE EVIDENCE THAT THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR RIVERA'S MURDER AND THE TWO OTHER [MPSC] SUPPORTERS ARE SOLDIERS OF MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6," MARTELL STRESSED.

THE [MPSC] IS PART OF THE LEFTIST DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE COALITION, WHICH TOOK PART IN THE 19 MARCH PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS.

IN ANOTHER TURN OF EVENTS, THE ARMY HAS ACCUSED THE GUERRILLAS OF KIDNAPPING APPROXIMATELY 30 PEASANTS IN CUSCATLAN AND SANTA ANA DEPARTMENTS, LOCATED TO THE NORTH AND WEST OF SAN SALVADOR, RESPECTIVELY.

MEANWHILE, THE REBELS STEPPED-UP THEIR SABOTAGE AGAINST THE ELECTRICAL POWER GRID BY DESTROYING TWO HIGH-VOLTAGE PYLONS AND SEVEN POWER POLES IN GUAZAPA, CHALATENANGO, AND ILOBASCO, LOCATEDE NORTH AND EAST OF SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0655 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 7 NOV 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [MARIA DE LOS ANGELES TENORIO] [TEXT] THE MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO FEDERATION OF COMMITTEES OF MOTHERS AND RELATIVES, FECMAFAM, HAS CRITICIZED THE VISIT TO OUR COUNTRY BY BERNARD ARONSON, ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INTER - AMERICAN AFFAIRS. THE GROUP SAID THAT BY REITERATING U.S. GOVERNMENT SUPPORT FOR THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT THE CONTINUATION OF OUR COUNTRY'S MILITARY STRUGGLE IS ENCOURAGED. HOWEVER, THE GROUP NOTED THAT ARONSON'S PRESENCE ALSO SERVES TO REVEAL A DETERIORATION IN THE IMAGE OF THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT BECAUSE OF THE RECENT UPSURGE IN VIOLENCE.

[BEGING RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED PERSON] WHAT DOES YESTERDAY'S VISIT BY THIS U.S. CITIZEN MEAN? IT MEANS THAT U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH IS CONCERNED THAT THE IMAGE OF THE PERSON TO WHOM HE HAS PROVIDED ALL HIS AID TO CONTINUE MURDERING SALVADORANS IS IN DANGER. CRISTIANI HAS BEEN CONDEMNED ABROAD FOR HIS REPRESSIVE ACTIONS. [END RECORDING]

FECMAFAM ALSO REJECTED THE CREATION OF A COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION], AS PROPOSED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI. THE GROUP FEELS INVESTIGATIONS OF CRIMES HAVE NEVER BEEN FULLY CONDUCTED AND THE GUILTY HAVE NEVER BEEN TRIED.

DEV-MUC3-0657 (GE)

LIMA, 9 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] WITH JUST THREE DAYS TO GO BEFORE THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS SCHEDULED FOR 12 NOVEMBER, TERRORISTS HAVE STEPPED UP THEIR VIOLENCE AND SECURITY FORCES HAVE INTENSIFIED THEIR ANTISUBVERSIVE OPERATIONS IN SEVERAL PERUVIAN REGIONS.

SHINING PATH MEMBERS LAST NIGHT BOMBED AN OFFICE OF THE RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE (APRA) PARTY IN LIMA, INJURING FOUR PEOPLE, ONE OF THEM SERIOUSLY.

DURING THE ATTACK THE OFFICE WAS SET ON FIRE. AN EYEWITNESS SAID THAT SOME 150 ELECTORAL CARDS WERE BURNED. THE CARDS, WHICH ARE THE ONLY VALID DOCUMENT FOR PARTICIPATION IN THE ELECTIONS, HAD BEEN TAKEN TO THE PARTY OFFICE SO THAT THE VOTING STATION COULD BE DEFINED.

POLICE SOURCES HAVE REPORTED AT LEAST SIX BOMBINGS LAST NIGHT IN THE ANDEAN CITY OF AYACUCHO, 575 KM SOUTHEAST OF THE LIMA. THE SOURCES, HOWEVER, DID NOT MENTION THE BUILDINGS THAT WERE ATTACKED.

ON 7 NOVEMBER, SHINING PATH TERRORISTS BLEW UP 4 PYLONS IN THE VICINITY OF AYACUCHO, RAZING TO 17 THE NUMBER OF PYLONS THAT HAVE BEEN BLOWN UP BY THIS MAOIST ORGANIZATION IN AYACUCHO AND IN ZONES OF HUANCAVELICA DEPARTMENT IN THE PAST FEW DAYS.

A SHINING PATH "ELIMINATION COMMANDO" MURDERED A NATIONAL POLICE COMMANDER ON 7 NOVEMBER IN THE RESIDENTIAL LIMA DISTRICT OF MIRAFLORES. THE POLICE HAVE REPORTED A POWER OUTAGE IN TOWNS OF THE HUAYLAS VALLEY, IN THE MOUNTAINOUS REGION OF THE NORTHERN DEPARTMENT OF ANCASH, FOLLOWING THE DESTRUCTION OF TWO PYLONS.

IN ONE OF THE TOWNS -- RANRAHIRCA -- THE SOURCES SAID THAT THE SHINING PATH MEMBERS SET THE CITY HALL FACILITY ON FIRE, DESTROYING VALUABLE DOCUMENTS. IN LA OROYA, JUNIN DEPARTMENT, IN THE CENTRAL PERUVIAN MOUNTAIN RANGE, PUBLIC BUILDINGS WERE BOMBED AND A CAR-BOMB WAS DETONATED.

REPORTS RECEIVED FROM AYACUCHO AND FROM OTHER RURAL AREAS SAY THAT TERRORISTS ARE STOPPING VEHICLES IN HIGHWAYS AND THAT THEY ARE STRIPPING PASSENGERS OF THEIR ELECTORAL CARDS, WHICH THEY THEN DESTROY.

IN VIEW OF THIS ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE, THE GOVERNMENT ON 7 NOVEMBER DECREED A STATE OF EMERGENCY IN THE 10 PROVINCES OF THE DEPARTMENT OF LIMA, PLACING THEM UNDER MILITARY CONTROL. THIS IS THE PERUVIAN DEPARTMENT WITH THE LARGEST POPULATION AND WITH THE LARGEST NUMBER OF VOTERS. IT HAS MORE THAN 6,000,000 PEOPLE, AND INCLUDES THE PORT OF CALLAO.

ON 6 NOVEMBER, THE MILITARY AUTHORITIES IMPOSED A CURFEW BETWEEN 1000 AND 0500 IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF JUNIN AND PASCO IN THE CENTRAL MOUNTAIN RANGE. THE SAME MEASURE HAS ALREADY BEEN ENFORCED IN AYACUCHO, APURIMAC, AND HUANCAVELICA.

THE POLITICAL-MILITARY COMMAND OF THE AYACUCHO EMERGENCY ZONE LAST NIGHT ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE ENFORCING STRICT MEASURES THAT WILL BE OBSERVED BY THE PEOPLE DURING THE ELECTIONS.

THE COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT AS OF 13 NOVEMBER, THOSE ELECTORAL CARD THAT DO NOT BEAR THE SEAL THAT IS STAMPED AT THE VOTING STATIONS AND WHICH PROVES THAT THE BEARER HAS CAST HIS VOTE WILL BE ARRESTED AND "PLACED AT THE DISPOSAL OF THE COURTS."

IT ADDS THAT IF SOMEONE WANTS TO TRAVEL,TO MAKE ADMINISTRATIVE ARRANGEMENTS, TO OBTAIN DOCUMENTS, OR TO PERFORM COMMERCIAL TRANSACTIONS, THEY WILL HAVE TO SHOW THEIR ELECTORAL CARD WITH THE CORRESPONDING SEAL, UNDER PENALTY OF BEING FORBIDDEN TO PROCEED.

DURING A PRESS CONFERENCE YESTERDAY, THE TECHNICAL POLICE PRESENTED 27 ALLEGED SHINING PATH MEMBERS WHO WERE CAPTURED IN SOUTHERN LIMA PROVINCES AND IN ICA. THEY ARE CHARGED WITH BEING INVOLVED IN AT LEAST 40 ATTACKS AND MURDERS OF AUTHORITIES, AND WITH PLANNING FUTURE ATTACKS AGAINST ELECTORAL OFFICES AND CANDIDATES IN THE UPCOMING MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS.

COMBINED MILITARY AND POLICE FORCES YESTERDAY RAIDED THE SAN FERNANDO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE OF THE LIMA UNIVERSITY OF SAN MARCOS, ARRESTING 600 PERSONS AND SEIZING EXPLOSIVES AND PROPAGANDA MATERIAL.

ON 6 NOVEMBER, DURING A SEARCH OF THE SAN MARCOS UNIVERSITY CAMPUS IN LIMA, THE POLICE SEIZED FIREARMS, EXPLOSIVES, AND TERRORIST PROPAGANDA MATERIAL.

DEV-MUC3-0658 (GE)

BUENOS AIRES, 9 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [EXCERPTS] THE MOTOR TRANSPORT WORKERS UNION [UTA] BEGAN AN INDEFINITE STRIKE AT MIDNIGHT, CONTRADICTING GOVERNMENT ORDERS WHICH STATED THAT THE UTA AND THE ARGENTINE FEDERATION OF AUTOMOTIVE PASSENGER CARRIERS [FATAP] MUST SOLVE THE SALARY PROBLEM THROUGH NEGOTIATIONS.

THE SITUATION ON THE THIRD DAY OF THE STOPPAGE IS SLIGHTLY BETTER, ALTHOUGH A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE ARE STILL WAITING ON THE STREETS TRYING TO GET ON THE FEW BUSES BEING DRIVEN BY THEIR OWNERS.

A FEW MINUTES AGO, DEPUTY SECRETARY FOR TRANSPORTATION NESTOR FERNANDEZ ANNOUNCED THAT AT MIDDAY ONLY 30 PERCENT OF THE USUAL NUMBER OF BUSES IN THE FEDERAL CAPITAL WERE WORKING NORMALLY; BECAUSE OF THIS, MEASURES WILL BE ADOPTED TO ENSURE THAT AT LEAST 50 PERCENT OF THE BUSES WILL RUN TODAY.

REPRESENTATIVES OF THE FEDERAL POLICE, THE BUENOS AIRES PROVINCIAL POLICE, AND THE NATIONAL GENDERMERIE ARE MEETING AT TRANSPORTATION SECRETARIAT OFFICES TO STUDY WAYS OF RESTORING NORMAL BUS SERVICE.

SUBWAY CHAIRMAN JOSE BARBERO REPORTS THAT HIS SECTOR'S SERVICES HAVE ALSO IMPROVED, AND FIVE SUBWAY LINES ARE FUNCTIONING NORMALLY. ALTHOUGH THE SUBWAY PERSONNEL ARE MEMBERS OF THE UTA, THEY HAVE DECIDED TO SUSPEND THEIR STRIKE.

THE RAILROAD SERVICE IS NORMAL. MORE COACHES WILL BE PUT INTO SERVICE, AND THE NUMBER OF TRAINS IN SERVICE WILL BE INCREASED, BUT TRAINS OF THE ROCA LINE CONNECTING CONSTITUCION TO LA PLATA THROUGH THE TEMPERLEY STRETCH ARE DELAYED BECAUSE OF A DERAILMENT.

UTA SECRETARY GENERAL JUAN MANUEL PALACIOS HAS CONFIRMED THAT THE INDEFINITE STRIKE WILL CONTINUE AND THAT THE UTA WILL NOT ACCEPT COMPULSORY NEGOTIATIONS BECAUSE THIS IS NOT A LEGAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT. HE SAYS THAT THIS WOULD MERELY PUT OFF THE PROBLEM FOR A MONTH OR SO. PALACIOS ADDED THAT IT WOULD ONLY CREATE MORE DIFFICULTIES FOR THE WORKERS.

FATAP DIRECTOR LUIS CARRAL ASSERTED THAT THE BUSINESS SECTOR WILL DOUBLE ITS EFFORTS TO PUT THE BUSES BACK INTO SERVICE. CARRAL SAID THAT IN VIEW OF COMPULSORY NEGOTIATIONS FATAP WILL URGE WORKERS TO RETURN TO THEIR JOBS UNLESS THEY WANT TO BE DISMISSED.

TRANSPORTATION SECTOR BUSINESSMEN HAVE INFORMED THE TRANSPORTATION SECRETARIAT THAT A FEW DRIVERS ARE RETURNING TO WORK. BUSINESSMEN BELIEVE THAT IN A FEW MORE HOURS 40-50 PERCENT OF THE BUSES WILL BE FUNCTIONING NORMALLY.

PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM COMMENTED THIS MORNING ON THE UTA ATTITUDE:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MENEM] THIS IS AN EMERGENCY SITUATION. WE CANNOT PAY MORE THAN WE HAVE. I BELIEVE THAT THE BUSINESSMEN HAVE OFFERED A BASIC SALARY OF AROUND 75,000 AUSTRALES PER MONTH. UNTIL YESTERDAY THIS AMOUNT REPRESENTED NEARLY $100, AND THIS IS A GOOD INCREASE.

EVIDENTLY, THERE IS A POLITICAL INFILTRATION OF IDEAS THAT ARE NOT SHARED BY ALL ARGENTINE PEOPLE. I DO NOT BELIEVE THE INFILTRATION COMES FROM PERONIST OR RADICAL MOVEMENTS. THIS IS THE WORK OF THE ULTRA-LEFT. [END RECORDING]

MENEM ASSERTED THAT THOSE WHO WANT TO WORK AND WHO ARE SACRIFICING THEMSELVES FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE PEOPLE WILL BE REWARDED. HE URGED THEM NOT TO LEAVE THEIR POSTS. MENEM ADDED THAT YESTERDAY MANY MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC ASKED HIM NOT TO GIVE IN. THE PRESIDENT SAID HE HAS DECIDED NOT GIVE IN, NOT BECAUSE HE IS STUBBORN, BUT BECAUSE PEOPLE WHO NEED THE PUBLIC TRANSPORT SERVICES CANNOT BE DEFRAUDED.

ASKED IF THE RAILROADS THAT JOIN THE STRIKE WILL BE CLOSED DOWN, MENEM SAID:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MENEM] THE RAILROAD LINES THAT STRIKE WILL BE CLOSED.

[UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] BUT MANY PEOPLE WILL BE LEFT WITHOUT TRANSPORTATION.

[MENEM] WE WILL FIND A WAY OF GETTING THESE PEOPLE TO THEIR JOBS. WE CANNOT ACCEPT THIS TYPE OF ATTITUDE. OR WOULD YOU PREFER TO SEE THE COUNTRY EXPLODE? [END RECORDING]

AT 1700 THIS AFTERNOON THE CABINET MEETING THAT STARTED LAST NIGHT WILL BE RECONVENED. THE CABINET MEMBERS ATTENDING THE MEETING WILL ANALYZE THE DIFFICULTIES CREATED BY THE UTA DECISION TO CONTINUE THE STRIKE. THE MEETING WILL BE HELD AT THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] ROOM UNDER THE CHAIRMANSHIP OF INTERIOR MINISTER EDUARDO BAUZA. JUSTICIALIST LEADER ANTONIO CAFFIERO WILL ATTEND THE MEETING. PRES MENEM WILL NOT ATTEND.

IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT 50 BUS COMPANIES HAVE BEEN URGED TO RETURN TO NORMAL WORK; OTHERWISE DECREE 429, WHICH PROVIDES FOR THE TEMPORARY CONFISCATION OF BUSES, WILL BE IMPLEMENTED. THIS DECREE, WHICH HAS BEEN MENTIONED BY PRESIDENT MENEM, ESTABLISHES THAT BUSES WILL BE CONFISCATED AND DRIVEN BY NATIONAL GENDARMERIE PERSONNEL.

IN A JUSTICIALIST PARTY COMMUNIQUE SIGNED BY ANTONIO CAFFIERO, THE PARTY EXPRESSES ITS SUPPORT FOR THE DECISIONS MADE BY PRESIDENT MENEM.

COMMANDER ADALINO BARBERI, THE NATIONAL GENDARMERIE DIRECTOR GENERAL, HAS REPORTED THAT THE TRANSPORTATION SECRETARIAT OFFICIALS ARE STILL STUDYING THE MEASURES TO BE TAKEN TO CONFISCATE THE BUSES FROM THE OWNERS WHO FAIL TO FOLLOW GOVERNMENT INSTRUCTIONS.

DEV-MUC3-0659 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 NOV 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI YESTERDAY REAFFIRMED ITS WILLINGNESS TO THOROUGHLY INVESTIGATE THE ATTACK AGAINST FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION]. IT ALSO MADE AN APPEAL SO THAT NO ACCUSATIONS LACKING SCIENTIFIC SUPPORT ARE MADE IN ORDER NOT TO GENERATE SPECULATIONS THAT POLITICIZE THIS CASE.

IN AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE, THE GOVERNMENT MADE THE PRECEDING STATEMENT BECAUSE OF THE "BIASED PROPAGANDISTIC CAMPAIGN BEING DEVELOPED BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AND OTHER POLITICAL AND LABOR UNION ORGANIZATIONS, SEEKING TO CREATE A DISTORTED VIEW OF THE RECENT TERRORIST ATTACKS IN THE COUNTRY."

THE COMMUNIQUE RECALLS THAT ON THE SAME DAY OF THE TERRORIST ATTACK AGAINST FENASTRAS, THE GOVERNMENT CONDEMNED SUCH CRIMINAL ACTION. THE COMMUNIQUE ALSO EXPRESSES THE GOVERNMENT'S INTENTION TO CONDUCT A THOROUGH INVESTIGATION WITHIN A FRAMEWORK WORTHY OF CONFIDENCE. THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO CREATE A COMMISSION THAT WILL BE COMPOSED OF REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE UNITED NATIONS, THE OAS, CEDES [SALVADORAN EPISCOPAL CONFERENCE], POLITICAL PARTIES, LABOR UNION ORGANIZATIONS -- INCLUDING ONE FROM FENASTRAS -- DR IGNACIO ELLACURIA, THE PROSECUTING ATTORNEY'S OFFICE, AND THE JUSTICE MINISTER.

HOWEVER, FENASTRAS LEADERS HAVE CONTINUED HINDERING THE INVESTIGATION AT THE SITE OF THE INCIDENT, THE COMMUNIQUE ADDS.

THE GOVERNMENT COMMUNIQUE STATES THAT THE FENASTRAS REFUSAL TO PARTICIPATE IN THE COMMISSION COULD BE INTERPRETED AS "AN INTENTIONAL PLAN BY FENASTRAS LEADERS TO PREVENT THE INVESTIGATION TO DETERMINE WHO IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS TERRORIST ATTACK." THEREFORE, THE GOVERNMENT COMMUNIQUE REQUESTS THE ABANDONMENT OF SUCH AN ATTITUDE.

THE GOVERNMENT, THE COMMUNIQUE ADDS, BELIEVES THAT THE INVESTIGATION IS LEGAL AND THAT FENASTRAS HAS THE MORAL DUTY TO HELP IN THE INVESTIGATION TO CLARIFY THIS CASE.

THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT CRISTIANI REITERATED ITS APPEAL TO CITIZENS TO ABSTAIN FROM MAKING ACCUSATIONS LACKING SCIENTIFIC EVIDENCE, IN ORDER TO PREVENT SPECULATION THAT HAMPERS THE NORMAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE JUDICIAL PROCESS THAT HAS ALREADY BEGUN. THE GOVERNMENT REITERATED THAT "ITS TRUE OBJECTIVE IS TO CLARIFY THIS BARBARIC ACTION AND TO PUNISH THOSE RESPONSIBLE, NO MATTER WHO THEY ARE."

"WE REQUEST ALL CITIZENS TO ABSTAIN FROM ISSUING SPECULATIVE OPINIONS, AND, SHOULD THEY HAVE SOMETHING TO REPORT THAT WOULD HELP CLARIFY THIS REGRETTABLE INCIDENT, THEY SHOULD DO IT WITHIN THE JUDICIAL PROCESS," THE OFFICIAL GOVERNMENT COMMUNIQUE STATES.

THE GOVERNMENT REAFFIRMED ITS DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE SEARCHING FOR PEACE THROUGH PEACEFUL MEANS AND DIALOGUE. ACCORDING TO THE MEXICO AGREEMENTS, THE FLMN IS ALSO OBLIGED TO CONTINUE WITH THE DIALOGUE PROCESS AND "CANNOT UNILATERALLY WITHDRAW BECAUSE IT WOULD BE VIOLATING NOT ONLY THOSE AGREEMENTS, BUT ALSO THE ASPIRATION OF OUR PEOPLE, WHICH IS TO ATTAIN PEACE," THE COMMUNIQUE SAYS.

DEV-MUC3-0660 (GE)

SANTIAGO, 10 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] LUIS CORVALAN, FORMER SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE CHILEAN COMMUNIST PARTY [PCCH], HAS REQUESTED A NUREMBERG-STYLE TRIAL FOR MEMBERS OF THE CURRENT ADMINISTRATION IF PATRICIO AYLWIN WINS THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS.

CORVALAN'S STATEMENTS WERE PUBLISHED IN THE LATEST ISSUE OF COSAS MAGAZINE. HE JUSTIFIED THE EXISTENCE OF THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT [FPMR] AND THE COMMUNISTS' RIGHT TO HAVE MILITARY TRAINING.

THE FORMER PCCH SECRETARY GENERAL SAID THAT HIS PARTY IS WORKING HARD FOR AYLWIN'S TRIUMPH ON THE 14 DECEMBER ELECTIONS. HE SAID THAT IF AYLWIN WINS THE ELECTIONS, THE PCCH IS READY TO PARALYZE THE COUNTRY IF ANY SECTOR THREATENS THE NEW ADMINISTRATION.

THE PCCH LEADER POINTED OUT THE NEED TO MODIFY THE CHILEAN JUDICIAL BRANCH SUBSTANTIALLY. HE REQUESTED SPECIAL COURTS, LIKE THE ONES THAT EXISTED IN NUREMBERG, TO TRY THE MEMBERS OF THE CURRENT ADMINISTRATION.

CORVALAN REQUESTED THE FREEDOM OF THE SO-CALLED POLITICAL PRISONERS, INCLUDING FPMR AND LAUTARO MOVEMENT TERRORISTS. HE SAID HE DOES NOT CARE WHETHER LEFTIST SYMPATHIZERS ARE INVOLVED IN ANY CRIME, INCLUDING IN THE MURDER OF CARABINEROS.

THE PCCH WILL HELP PATRICIO AYLWIN FACE HIS ENEMIES DURING THE NEXT ADMINISTRATION, CORVALAN SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0662 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 9 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [HANDAL, MEMBER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] WHAT DOES THIS TELL US? WHAT MESSAGE DOES THIS CONVEY? IT TELLS US THAT THESE ORGANIZATIONS, THE SO-CALLED SUPPORT ORGANIZATIONS -- THE COPREFA [ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE] CALLS THEM FRONTS -- ARE COMPONENTS OF THE ENEMY SIDE IN THE WAR.

WHEN THEY SIT DOWN TO TALK TO THE MAIN REPRESENTATIVES OF THE ENEMY, THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], AND WHEN THEY NEGOTIATE ISSUES LIKE THE END TO HOSTILITIES, THE GOVERNMENT IMMEDIATELY MAKE DEMANDS AND ALL THESE POLITICAL, IDEOLOGICAL, PSYCHOLOGICAL, ETCETERA, ETCETERA, ACTIONS STOP. THE MESSAGE THIS CONVEYS IS THAT AS FAR AS THE GOVERNMENT IS CONCERNED, ALL THOSE ORGANIZATIONS ARE PART OF THE ENEMY SIDE IN THE WAR. WHAT HAPPENED LATER WAS THE CREATION OF MANY SUCH FRONTS. THE REPRESSION HAS BEEN GOING ON FOR QUITE SOME TIME AND HAD INCREASED. HOWEVER, THE GOVERNMENT HAD NEVER PRESENTED AN IDEA LIKE THIS ONE. ONCE IT DID, EVERYTHING BECAME VERY CLEAR. ALL THE PAST ACTIONS ARE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT'S AND THE ARMY'S WAR ACTIONS AGAINST ALL THESE EXPRESSIONS AND DEMONSTRATIONS BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] MASSACRE WAS PART OF THIS PLAN. THE KILLING OF 3 MEMBERS OF THE MPSC [SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT] IN SONSONATE CARRIED OUT BY THE 6TH MILITARY DETACHMENT IN FRONT OF WITNESSES -- THEY LEFT MESSAGES ON THE BODIES STATING THAT THEY WERE TRAITORS TO THE HOMELAND -- WAS CARRIED OUT WITH THE CLEAR INTENTION OF SENDING ANOTHER MESSAGE. THE MESSAGE IS: NOT ONLY IN THEORY DO WE CONSIDER YOU COMPONENTS OF THE ENEMY SIDE. YOU ARE THE ENEMY AND THAT IS WHY WE ARE KILLING YOU. [END RECORDING]

REGARDING THE VISIT TO EL SALVADOR OF BERNARD ARONSON, ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INTER-AMERICAN AFFAIRS, COMMANDER JORGE SHAFIK HANDAL SAID:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HANDAL] THE HEADS OF THE ARMED FORCES AND MILITARY UNITS WHO CARRIED OUT THESE CRIMES REMAIN IN OFFICE. THOSE WHO GAVE THE ORDERS REMAIN IN OFFICE. THEN HOW CAN AN INVESTIGATION BE CARRIED OUT? A CHAIN OF COMMAND MUST BE FOLLOWED IN THE MILITARY. IF A SUBORDINATE IS GOING TO BE INTERROGATED, ONE MUST FIRST ASK PERMISSION FROM HIS SUPERIOR, AND THEY ARE THE SUPERIORS. BESIDES, NO ONE KNOWS WHO THE SUBORDINATES WHO PARTICIPATED ARE. THAT INFORMATION MUST COME FROM THE ARMY. THAT IS WHY WE HAVE SAID THAT THE LEAST THEY CAN DO BEFORE THEY BEGIN INVESTIGATING THIS INCIDENT IS REMOVE COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE. THAT WOULD BE THE RIGHT THING TO DO. I WOULD EVEN ADD THAT THERE ARE A FEW OTHERS WHO SHOULD BE REMOVED.

IF WE WERE LIVING IN A COUNTRY WITH A DEMOCRATIC POLITICAL SYSTEM AND WITH LABOR UNIONS, THAT WOULD BE COMMON PRACTICE. IT WOULD NOT EVEN BE NECESSARY TO BRING THIS UP AT A PUBLIC DEBATE. THE FIRST THING THE PRESIDENT SHOULD HAVE DONE AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES -- HE IS INVOLVED IN THESE CRIMES BECAUSE HE IS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES -- IS REMOVE THEM AND NOT SAY THAT HE WAS NOT CONSULTED ON THIS MATTER. HE CLAIMS HE KNEW NOTHING ABOUT THIS, BUT WE HAVE OUR OWN SOURCES OF INFORMATION AND WE KNOW THAT HE KNEW. BUT IF HE WANTS US TO BELIEVE HIM WHEN HE SAYS THAT HE DID NOT KNOW, THEN THE FIRST THING HE SHOULD DO IS WHAT ANY MAN WITH ANY SELF-RESPECT WOULD DO: ASK FOR AN INVESTIGATION. HOWEVER, HE IS HINDERING THE INVESTIGATION, WHICH IS WHAT IS ALWAYS DONE WHEN SOMETHING LIKE THIS HAPPENS. WHEN THINGS LIKE THIS HAPPEN, A FEW -- THOSE WHO WANT TO SEE MATTERS CLARIFIED -- RESIGN, WHILE OTHERS ARE REMOVED. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0666 (GE)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 10 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] MEXICAN NARCOTICS POLICE HAVE ARRESTED COLOMBIAN CITIZEN JORGE HUMBERTO CHALARIA, KNOWN AS "EL NEGRO," THE REPRESENTATIVE IN MEXICO OF COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKER GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, OTHERWISE KNOWN AS "EL MEXICANO," THE TOP CHIEF OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE (PGR) MADE KNOWN TODAY.

CHALARIA, 30 YEARS OLD, 5 OTHER COLOMBIANS, 1 VENEZUELAN, AND 12 MEXICANS HAVE BEEN ARRESTED "IN THE LAST 2 DAYS" AND 550 KG OF PURE COCAINE HAVE BEEN CONFISCATED IN OPERATIONS CONDUCTED IN THIS CITY AND IN THE STATES OF SONORA AND TAMAULIPAS, A PGR SPOKESMAN SAID.

THE GANG OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS LED BY CHALARIA WERE ABLE TO DELIVER OVER 50 TONS OF PURE COCAINE TO THE STATES OF CALIFORNIA AND FLORIDA IN THE LAST 4 YEARS, THE PGR SPOKESMAN ADDED.

"EL NEGRO" CONFESSED THAT HE HAD BEEN IN MEXICO SINCE 1988 UNDER THE ORDERS OF GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ACCORDING TO THE SAME SOURCE.

THE INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING GANG HAD THE PROTECTION OF ARTURO CUELLAR TIJERINA, COMMANDER OF THE TAMAULIPAS JUDICIAL POLICE, WHO WAS ALSO ARRESTED.

CUELLAR AND A GROUP OF POLICEMEN UNDER HIS ORDERS SUPPLIED FUEL TO THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, WHO BROUGHT THE DRUG INTO MEXICO BY MEANS OF LIGHT AIRCRAFT, WHICH LANDED ON CLANDESTINE RUNWAYS NEAR THE BORDER WITH THE UNITED STATES.

THOSE ARRESTED CONFESSED THAT AMERICAN JULIO CHAGY DE LA ROSA, A MIAMI RESIDENT, DISTRIBUTED THE DRUG AND "LAUNDERED" THE MONEY OBTAINED IN THE DRUG TRAFFICKING BUSINESS THROUGH A COMPANY CALLED "ITAL BAGNO," WHICH SUPPOSEDLY MANUFACTURED STOVES.

THEY SAID THAT ON 29 OCTOBER THEY RECEIVED A LOAD OF 550 KG OF PURE COCAINE FROM COLOMBIA, BROUGHT INTO THE COUNTRY FROM A RANCH LOCATED IN SONORA. THE NARCOTICS POLICE DETECTED THE ILLEGAL OPERATION AT THE RANCH AND ARRESTED ALFONSO CASTILLO ARMENTA AND HIS DAUGHTER, WHO HAD MODERN RADIO COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT TO MAKE CONTACT WITH THE COLOMBIAN PLANES AND WITH "EL NEGRO."

THE INVESTIGATIONS LED THE POLICE TO A RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD IN THIS CAPITAL, WHERE "EL NEGRO" HAD RENTED A HOME IN WHICH HE LIVED WITH A VENEZUELAN WOMAN BY THE NAME OF CRIATINA ROSAS RODRIGUEZ, WHO COVERED UP THE ACTIVITIES CONDUCTED BY HER COMPANION.

THE ARREST IS THE THIRD HEAVY BLOW DEALT ON THE INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING BUSINESS BY THE MEXICAN POLICE IN THE LAST 3 WEEKS.

ON 19 OCTOBER, THE POLICE ARRESTED COLOMBIANS RODRIGO DIZUNZA OCHOA, NEPHEW OF DRUG TRAFFICKER FABIO OCHOA, AND ALFREDO AGUILAR CASTRO, NEPHEW OF COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKER RODRIGUEZ GACHA, WHO HAD 10 KG OF PURE COCAINE IN THEIR POSSESSION.

EARLY THIS MONTH, MEXICAN RAFAEL MUNOZ TALAVERA WAS ARRESTED. HE ALLEGEDLY OWNS THE 20 TONS OF PURE COCAINE DISCOVERED IN A WAREHOUSE IN LOS ANGELES, CALIFORNIA, IN SEPTEMBER.

SINCE PRESIDENT CARLOS SALINAS DE GORTARI TOOK OFFICE LAST DECEMBER, THE MEXICAN NARCOTICS POLICE HAVE CONFISCATED 23 TONS OF PURE COCAINE AND HAVE ARRESTED NEARLY 10,000 DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

DEV-MUC3-0667 (GE)

BOGOTA, 11 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] PEREIRA -- THREE PERSONS WERE INJURED AND HEAVY MATERIAL DAMAGE WAS REPORTED DURING A NEW TERRORIST WAVE THAT HIT PEREIRA LAST NIGHT. THREE BOMBS EXPLODED AT THE FRONT DOORS OF A POLITICAL PARTY HEADQUARTERS AND TWO BANKS. THE ALMOST SIMULTANEOUS BLASTS WERE HEARD AT APPROXIMATELY MIDNIGHT. THE RESIDENTS IN THE DOWNTOWN AREA WERE SHAKEN BY THE EXPLOSIONS. INJURED BY THE SHOCK WAVE WERE: AN UNIDENTIFIED TAXI DRIVER; ELMER MACHADO, A YOUNG BEGGAR WHO WAS SLEEPING ON THE SIDEWALK NEAR ONE OF THE BANKS; AND RAUL CASTANO GUTIERREZ, A BAKER WHO WAS PASSING BY. THE INJURED PERSONS WERE TAKEN TO THE SOCIAL SECURITY'S SAN JORGE HOSPITAL AND THE PIO XII CLINIC, AND IT WAS REPORTED THAT THEY ARE OUT OF DANGER.

GLASS WAS BROKEN AND OFFICE FURNITURE AND EQUIPMENT DESTROYED AT THE LIBERAL UNITY HEADQUARTERS, A GROUP THAT FOLLOWS THE GUIDELINES OF PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO; AT THE LAS VILLAS SAVINGS AND LOANS OFFICE; AND AT THE INTERNATIONAL BANK OF COLOMBIA BRANCH. THE PEREIRA SECURITY COUNCIL, PRESIDED OVER BY MUNICIPAL SECRETARY BERNARDO GIL JARAMILLO, IS CURRENTLY HOLDING AN URGENT MEETING. SECRETARY GIL JARAMILLO SAID THAT THE MOST DRASTIC AND EFFECTIVE MEASURES WILL BE ADOPTED TO BRING THE SITUATION UNDER CONTROL, TO FIND THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR LAST NIGHT'S ATTACKS, AND TO PREVENT FURTHER INCIDENTS.

THE ATTACK ON THE LIBERAL UNITY HEADQUARTERS OCCURRED A FEW HOURS AFTER THE DIRECTORATE CALLED A MEETING WITH CIVIC, UNION, CULTURAL, SPORTS, AND RELIGIOUS GROUPS TO CHOOSE THEIR CANDIDATE FOR MAYOR. THE CANDIDATE WILL RUN ON THE ALVARISTA CONSERVATIVE MOVEMENT TICKET HEADED BY SENATOR EMILIANO ISAZA ENAO.

THIS IS THE SECOND ATTACK IN 2 MONTHS. ON 6 SEPTEMBER THREE BOMBS EXPLODED -- THREE OTHERS WERE DEFUSED -- RESULTING IN 60 MILLION PESOS IN DAMAGE AND 17 PERSONS INJURED. ONE OF THE INJURED LOST A LEG.

DEV-MUC3-0669 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS SAID THAT TODAY'S ATTACK ON THE NATIONAL GUARD HEADQUARTERS -- IN WHICH TWO CHILDREN WERE KILLED AND EIGHT PEOPLE WERE INJURED -- SHOWS THAT THE GUERRILLAS "DO NOT WANT PEACE AND WANT TO ESCALATE VIOLENCE."

IN A PRESS COMMUNIQUE, THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT SAID THAT THE ATTACK "IS ANOTHER TERRORIST ACTION WHICH DIRECTLY AFFECTS THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND TRAMPLES HUMAN RIGHTS."

LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT RICARDO VALDIVIESO TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT THESE ACTIONS "SHOW THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S (FMLN) BLINDNESS AND DESPERATION."

NATIONAL GUARD DIRECTOR CORONEL JUAN CARLOS CARRILLO SAID: "THESE ARE SUPPOSEDLY THE BIG ATTACKS BY THE TERRORISTS; HOWEVER, TODAY'S ATTACK DID NOT CAUSE MUCH DAMAGE TO THE GARRISON; INSTEAD, TWO CHILDREN WERE KILLED." THE CHILDREN WERE 1 AND 1/2 - AND 4-YEARS- OLD. TWO SOLDIERS WERE ALSO WOUNDED.

URBAN GUERRILLAS TODAY HURLED BOMBS AT THE NATIONAL GUARD HEADQUARTERS. ONE OF THE BOMBS EXPLODED INSIDE THE MILITARY FACILITIES AND THE REST LANDED IN A RAVINE.

ONE OF THE EXPLOSIVES HIT A MODEST HOME KILLING TWO CHILDREN AND INJURING FIVE CIVILIANS.

BOMB EXPERTS DISMANTLED A CAR BOMB WHICH PRESUMABLY HAD BEEN LEFT BY GUERRILLAS NEAR THE GARRISON.

MEANWHILE, OFFICIAL SOURCES REPORTED THAT THE ARMY AND REBELS HAVE SUSTAINED AT LEAST 20 CASUALTIES DURING THE PAST FEW HOURS AS A RESULT OF CLASHES IN SAN SALVADOR AND MORAZAN DEPARTMENTS.

ACCORDING TO THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA), 6 GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED AND 13 WERE WOUNDED IN THOSE CLASHES. THE REPORT NOTES THE DEATH OF ONE SOLDIER.

ONE OF THE CLASHES, WHICH LASTED OVER 1 HOUR, OCCURRED ON THE SLOPES OF THE SAN SALVADOR VOLCANO, NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR.

ALONG WITH THE INTENSIFICATION OF MILITARY ACTIONS, THE FMLN HAS RESUMED ITS SABOTAGING OF THE ELECTRICITY SYSTEM, LEAVING VAST AREAS OF EL SALVADOR WITHOUT POWER.

THE RATIONING OF ELECTRICITY HAS LASTED BETWEEN 4 TO 6 HOURS IN THE METROPOLITAN AREA, AFFECTING INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTION. THE LACK OF TRAFFIC LIGHTS HAS RESULTED IN LARGE TRAFFIC JAMS.

DEV-MUC3-0670 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [ROSIE CASTILLO] [TEXT] RIGHT NOW WE ARE HEARING HEAVY SHOOTING NEAR TO THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE. STRONG BOMB EXPLOSIONS AND HEAVY GUNFIRE IS BEING HEARD NEAR TO THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE. AS WE ARRIVED HERE, WE ARE TOLD THERE ARE SNIPERS ON THE HOUSES LOCATED ON EL MIRADOR STREET, AND THAT IS WHY THE SHOOTING HAS INCREASED.

WE ALSO CONTACTED THE CHIEF OF PUBLIC SECURITY OF THE MILITARY ACADEMY LOCATED IN SANTA TECLA, AND HE TOLD US THAT RIGHT NOW, THE ATTACK HAS BEEN REPELLED BY THE ARMED FORCES. THERE ARE NO CASUALTIES ON EITHER SIDE, COLONEL SOTO MARTINEZ HAS TOLD US.

WE HAVE ALSO CONFIRMED THAT THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL WAS NOT ATTACKED, BUT THERE WAS AN ATTACK AGAINST THE ELECTORAL PROGRAM OFFICES WHERE SOME BOMBS WERE DETONATED. THERE ARE NO REPORTS OF CASUALTIES OR OTHER DETAILS.

HOWEVER, CONCERNING THE ATTACK ON THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE, THAT IS LOCATED NEAR EL MIRADOR STREET, IT IS SAID THAT RIGHT NOW IT IS IMPOSSIBLE TO GO BY THE AREA, AS THERE ARE SNIPERS ON TOP OF THE HOUSES NEXT TO THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE. THERE ARE STRONG EXPLOSIONS AND GUNFIRE, AND THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE IS THE TARGET. THE SECURITY CORPS ARE NOT ALLOWING ANYONE TO GO THROUGH EL MIRADOR STREET AS THEY ARE NOT ALLOWING ANYONE NEAR THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE.

THERE ARE ALSO SECURITY CORPS MEMBERS IN THE JUSTICE MINISTRY, WHICH IS CLOSE TO THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE. WE HAVE OBSERVED THAT THEY ARE FIRING THEIR WEAPONS TO REPEL THE SIMULTANEOUS ATTACKS BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT].

WE HAVE ALSO CONTACTED PEOPLE NEAR THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY, AND THEY TOLD US THAT GUNFIRE EXCHANGES HAVE BEEN HEARD AT THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY AND THE SAN CARLOS GARRISON [SITE OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE]. THEREFORE, THE PEOPLE GOING TO THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD SHOULD BEAR IN THE MIND THAT THE ATTACKS ARE TAKING PLACE AT THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY AND THE SURROUNDING AREA, AS WELL AS AT THE SAN CARLOS GARRISON.

DEV-MUC3-0672 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [EDWIN GONGORA] [TEXT] SEVERAL ATTACKS ARE TAKING PLACE RIGHT NOW IN SEVERAL PARTS OF THE CITY OF SAN SALVADOR. IT HAS BEEN CONFIRMED THAT THE CIVIL DEFENSE SECTOR IN SOYOPANGO IS UNDER ATTACK RIGHT NOW, AS WELL AS A SECTOR OF THE AIR FORCE. STRONG EXPLOSIONS AND EXCHANGES OF GUNFIRE HAVE BEEN HEARD. FOR THE TIME BEING, WE HAVE NO REPORTS OF ANY CASUALTIES ON EITHER SIDE, THAT IS, THE EXTREMISTS OR THE ARMY. HOWEVER, IT HAS BEEN CONFIRMED THAT THE ATTACKS AGAINST THE MILITARY GARRISONS BEGAN AT APPROXIMATELY 2045, AND THESE ATTACKS CONTINUE NOW AT 2125.

THESE ATTACKS ARE BEING CARRIED OUT BY MEMBERS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT AGAINST VARIOUS MILITARY GARRISONS IN SAN SALVADOR.

WE URGE THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN THOSE AREAS TO REFRAIN FROM GOING OUT. IT IS VERY DIFFICULT TO MOVE IN THOSE AREAS. FOR THE TIME BEING, PLEASE STANDBY, AND WHEN THE SITUATION IS UNDER CONTROL, THEN YOU WILL BE ABLE TO GO HOME. FOR THE TIME BEING, THE SITUATION IS VERY DIFFICULT, AS THE EXPLOSIONS ARE VERY STRONG. THE MACHINEGUN FIRE IS VERY HEAVY.

DEV-MUC3-0674 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [RENE HURTADO] [TEXT] AN ATTACK AGAINST THE NATIONAL POLICE AT CUSCATANCINGO BEGAN APPROXIMATELY 15-20 MINUTES AGO. THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] URBAN COMMANDO GROUPS ATTACKED THE MILITARY GARRISON IN THE AREA. THERE ARE NO REPORTS OF ANY CASUALTIES YET. THE BOMB EXPLOSIONS AND GUNFIRE THAT ARE BEING HEARD THROUGHOUT THE CITY OF SAN SALVADOR CONTINUE TO THIS MOMENT. WE CAN HEAR THEM IN THE SOUTHERN AREA. FMLN URBAN COMMANDO GROUPS ARE ENGAGED IN HEAVY COMBAT WITH THE NATIONAL POLICE MEMBERS AT CUSCATANCINGO.

THE SALVADORAN RED CROSS WILL ISSUE AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE SHORTLY. IT HAS BEEN CONFIRMED WHAT OUR FELLOW WORKER, FRANCISCO RODRIGUEZ, SAID, THERE ARE NO CASUALTIES. HOWEVER, VEHICLE NO 85 OF THE SALVADORAN RED CROSS WAS SET ON FIRE WHEN SOMEONE HURLED A FIREBOMB AT IT. THE UNIT BURNED DOWN COMPLETELY, NEAR THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR IN THE AREA OF ZACAMIL.

SOMEONE SHOT AT THE TIRES OF RED CROSS UNIT NO 93, AND THE DRIVER LOST CONTROL OF THE VEHICLE AND CRASHED AGAINST A TREE. NO CASUALTIES REPORTED THERE EITHER. A SALVADORAN RED CROSS SOURCE ALSO TOLD US THAT A VEHICLE IS IN THE VICINITY OF THE ASTOR MOVIE, WHERE APPARENTLY FOUR PEOPLE HAVE BULLET WOUNDS AS A RESULT OF THE CLASHES THAT ARE TAKING PLACE IN THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE CITY.

FMLN URBAN COMMAND GROUPS HAVE DEPLOYED UNITS THAT HAVE BEEN LAUNCHING ATTACKS SINCE EARLY THIS EVENING. THE ATTACKS BEGAN WITH THIS MORNING'S ATTACK ON THE NATIONAL GUARD. WE WERE ALSO TOLD THERE MIGHT BE MANY PEOPLE WOUNDED OR DEAD FROM THESE ATTACKS BY THE FMLN URBAN COMMANDO GROUPS ON VARIOUS MILITARY POSITIONS.

THE SITUATION IN THE AREA OF ZACAMIL NEAR THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY IS VERY CRITICAL. WE ADVISE OUR LISTENERS TO AVOID THE AREA AND TRY TO FIND OTHER ROUTES TO ENTER LIBERTAD NEIGHBORHOOD AND OTHER SECTORS CLOSE TO THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. BETTER YET, PLEASE WAIT, AS THE SITUATION IS VERY COMPLICATED.

WE HAVE ALSO BEEN TOLD THAT THE CIVIL DEFENSE COMMAND IN EL PLAN DEL PITO HAS NOT BEEN ATTACKED. HOWEVER, THERE WAS A CLASH BETWEEN THE TREASURY POLICE AND FMLN URBAN GUERRILLAS WHO WERE WEARING MASKS. THE FMLN GUERRILLAS SIMULTANEOUSLY AMBUSHED SOME MEMBERS OF THE TREASURY POLICE IN THE UNICENTRO AREA.

DEV-MUC3-0675 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] TWO HOURS AFTER THE LAUNCHING OF A GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE AGAINST MILITARY POSITIONS, THE SOUND OF MACHINEGUNS AND EXPLOSIVE DEVICES IS STILL BEING HEARD IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL.

THE OFFENSIVE, WHICH BEGAN AT 2000 (0200 GMT), ALSO INCLUDES MILITARY POSITIONS IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF USULUTAN AND SAN MIGUEL, IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, ACCORDING TO REPORTS.

MILITARY SOURCES HAVE CONFIRMED THE SIMULTANEOUS ATTACKS IN SAN SALVADOR AND EYEWITNESSES HAVE REPORTED CLASHES IN RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS AND TOWNS OUTSIDE THE CAPITAL SUCH AS AYUTUXTEPEQUE, CIUDAD DELGADO, SAN RAMON, MEJICANOS, AND SOYAPANGO.

LIKEWISE, IT WAS REPORTED THAT THE ATTACKS WERE INTENSIFIED IN VARIOUS NEIGHBORHOODS, SUCH AS CIUDAD MERLIOT, IN WESTERN SAN SALVADOR.

LOCAL RADIO STATIONS ANNOUNCED A NATIONAL RADIO NETWORK, WHILE ARMY SPOKESMEN, WHICH HAVE YET TO GIVE A REPORT ON THE OFFENSIVE, ASKED THE PEOPLE TO REMAIN HOME AND THOSE WHO ARE AWAY FROM THEIR HOMES, TO STAY WHERE THEY ARE RIGHT NOW.

ACCORDING TO THE ARMED FORCES, THE SITUATION IS "UNDER CONTROL" AND "PEOPLE MUST REMAIN CALM."

RADIO STATIONS HAVE JOINED A NATIONAL NETWORK AND ARE ONLY TRANSMITTING MUSIC, WHICH IS INTERRUPTED TO BROADCAST REPORTS ON THE MILITARY SITUATION.

TWO RED CROSS AMBULANCES WERE DESTROYED AFTER BEING SHOT AT.

HELICOPTERS WERE HEARD FLYING OVER THE CAPITAL, WHICH IN CERTAIN AREAS, SUCH AS CIUDAD MERLIOT, ARE CARRYING OUT INTENSE BOMBINGS AGAINST POSITIONS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GUERRILLAS.